<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>344</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES, IN SYDNEY 4 P.M. JULY, 12TH, 1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000344_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS CONFEliNCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE RT. HON. R. 3. MENZIES, IN SYDNEY 4 P. M.<br />
JULY. 12TH. 1961<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think it might perhaps be a good idea you have<br />
all had the communique, or your principals have if I<br />
just said something about the background of this matter;<br />
in fact, if it does not sound too tedious, something<br />
about the history of the matter, because it is some<br />
years now since the Common Market was established in<br />
Europe by the six powers, that is to say, Germany, France,<br />
Italy and the Benelux powers we sometimes call it the<br />
Treaty of Rome. But one of the essential elements in it<br />
is that over a period of years they are aimed at internal<br />
free trade and a common external customs tariff.<br />
When the Common Market was established, when the<br />
negotiations were in hand, Great Britain did not decide<br />
to go in; she had remained out, as a matter of judgment<br />
Since then she has established a European Free Trade<br />
Association which includes six other European countries,<br />
including the Scandinavian countries. Now, she has not<br />
decided that was made clear to us by Mr. Sandys she<br />
has not decided to , o in or to negotiate her way in, but<br />
she has been rethinking the matter; and a decision as to<br />
whether they should negotiate to go in will be taken one<br />
way or the other after Mr. Sandys returns to London, and<br />
after other Ministers who have been visiting other<br />
Commonwealth countries have returned to London.<br />
So the whole thing is quite tentative at the present<br />
time. And I think it is proper to say, because there is<br />
a little misunderstanding about it, that Mr. Sandys did<br />
not come out to ask us to say " Yes" to go into the Common<br />
Market, or to approve of Great Britain negotiating to go<br />
into the Common Market, because Great Britain herself has<br />
not yet taken a decision. What he was really doing was<br />
informing us of the various considerntions that were<br />
operating in the minds of the British Government. And we<br />
welcomed this because although consultation in principle<br />
has been accepted now for the last two or three years,<br />
this was in fact the first occasion when we have had any<br />
close ministerial discussion about the matter in principl<br />
And we therefore welcomed his visit and we enjoyed it.<br />
That would explain to you why, in the course of the<br />
communique we have said " This is a matter for Great<br />
Britain to decide", which it clearly is. It is Great<br />
Britain that may or may not go into the Common Markot;<br />
it is not Australia or New Zealand. Therefore a<br />
decision for Great Britain. That being so we have no<br />
status to object or to do anything else about it except<br />
to exchange our ideas and do what we can to protect our<br />
own interests. And a good deal of our discussion took<br />
place in relation to the w. rays and means of protecting our<br />
own interests should the United Kingdom decide to<br />
negotiate for entry to the Conmon Market.<br />
The reason for that is very clear, of course.<br />
Suppose Great Britain . rent into the Common Market<br />
unconditionally I mean on exactly the sane footing as<br />
Germany or France or Italy or the rest then, in due<br />
course, perhaps over a period of seven or eijht years,<br />
there should be internal free trade. And if Great Britain<br />
went in, it is reasonable to assuno some of the<br />
Scandinavian countries : uald go in, including for<br />
example, Denmark. And if Great Britain went in<br />
unconditionally and I repeat, that is to say on the<br />
same footing as the others then Danish butter would </p>
<p>find free entry into the United Kingdom, but Australian<br />
butter and Now Zealand butter would be net by the common<br />
tariff barrier and would throfore pay duty, which would<br />
seen to us to be rather an unhappy result for an industry<br />
which is substantial in Australia but probably vital<br />
in Now Zealand as an export industry.<br />
And in the same way wheat from France, France being<br />
a great wheat producer, woud move into England duty<br />
free while wheat from Australia would lose its present<br />
advantage of going in without duty.<br />
Dried fruits very important in various areas of<br />
Australia would lose their preferences, because they<br />
would be all subject to the common tariff barrier. But<br />
dried fruits from say Greece Greece having already<br />
decided to be an associate member of the Common Market<br />
would move in duty free.<br />
These of course, are tremendously grave matters for<br />
us, not natters to be disposed of merely in a sentimental<br />
way. They have very grave implications for our own<br />
business. And one of the things that we set out to do<br />
was to establish that these particular interests were not<br />
to be overlooked in any negotiations. That is why you<br />
will have noticed in the course of the communique that<br />
in any such negotiations various Australian export<br />
industries would be involved and Australia should be in a<br />
position to negotiate direct on Australia's ochalf when<br />
dutails and arrangements affecting items of Australian<br />
trade wore being discussed.<br />
dhat that means is that we did not feel that the<br />
case for our export primary industries could be put by<br />
anybody as well as by Australia, because we are familiar<br />
with the problem. Therefore it was not enoughi to be<br />
consulted in the distance; it was essential thrt in case<br />
the British Governiont decided to ne3otiate rnd I<br />
repeat it has not yet decided in case it decided to<br />
negotiate, then we would be, so to speak, in the room, and<br />
taking a hand in the discussion when wheat woul. be<br />
debated, or dried fruit, or butter, or whatever these<br />
corumodities might be.<br />
Of course the United Kingdom cannot guarantee that<br />
that would be so because if it decides to negotiate it<br />
will negotiate with the six nations of the Common Market<br />
as a group, and if they say " No, nobody else is going to<br />
be in the actual n. eootiation", then that, no doubt, will<br />
be conclusive. But I am sure that so far as Great<br />
Britain is concerned, if it does decide to negotiate, it<br />
will do all it can to secure our presence and our<br />
participation when those particular matters are under<br />
consideration. That, I think, will explain why it is that we have<br />
observed a fairly cautious position in these discussions,<br />
not making ourselves a party to a decision it is not<br />
our decision to make but doing all that we can to<br />
protect our own loeitimate interests should the decision<br />
be taken. And that, I an sure, is what the people of<br />
Australia would expect us to do.<br />
I do n-t think there is any trouble about that, so<br />
far as our friends in the United Kingdom are concerned.<br />
I think that represented in the long run a corinon and<br />
cheerfully accepted view of the position. </p>
<p>But there is one matter, difference of opinion<br />
that enmrges that I would like to say sorething about,<br />
and that is the difference on the political implications.<br />
The Treaty of Rome is, in its torns, an economic treaty.<br />
It covers a variety of matters. I have mentioned two of<br />
the great ones, internal free trade and common external<br />
tariff. It also provides for machinery for common<br />
working standards, for social services. It really covers<br />
a groat deal of the economic field in these countries;<br />
and, of course, if Great Britain becomes a eomber it will<br />
correspondingly cover a great deal of the same field in<br />
Great Britain.<br />
de think, and indeed we think that the Coimon Market<br />
countries think, that the political implications of this<br />
are very great. Indeed I think it is one of the proper<br />
objects of the exercise. They did not engage in the<br />
Treatu yf Rome just because of tariffs and trade;<br />
but they were contenplating that as<br />
time went on because of all this common ground, they<br />
would become more and more of a political unity, not<br />
necessarily one nation, not necessarily a fodeortion in<br />
the sense that we understand it, but sonmthing of what I<br />
will call broadly, a political unity, a get together<br />
politically, with a growing tendency to have cormnon<br />
policies, to thrash then out. So that in the result you<br />
would have these European nations together constituting<br />
more people than the United States of JAmrica and<br />
therefore representing what might loosely be described as<br />
a third power in the world.<br />
That is a view strongly held by a number of<br />
European statesmen. I offer no cormxent on it. But we<br />
think that the political tendencies in the Conuon Market<br />
must be in that direction. How far it will go is<br />
anybody's guess.<br />
And under those circumstancos we simply observe in<br />
point of fact, that we do not think the position as<br />
between Great Britain and the other Conmonwealth<br />
countries in the political field remains unaltered. It<br />
is very difficult for no to believe that Great Britain,<br />
intimately involved in European politics, for the first<br />
time this is not the old 19th century balance of power<br />
business it is very hard to believe that her position<br />
in relation to the Commonwalth countries, when we meet<br />
at Prime Ministers' Conferences, would remain so<br />
individual and detached as it is today.<br />
Now I am not saying that is good, bad or<br />
indifferent; neither my colleaguesnor I sit in judjient<br />
on that matter. But we record our view that the<br />
Commonwealth will not quite be the sane. Mr. Sandys<br />
felt, and no do. ubt with groat conviction, that none of<br />
these things would aff-ct the Conmonwealth relationship.<br />
Well, we think it will.<br />
Whether that is a good thing or a bad thing depends<br />
on a choice th: at it is no) t for us to make the choice<br />
between Great Britain effectively participating in a<br />
powerful European group of nations in the international<br />
political field, but with a looser association with the<br />
Comonwealth, or a Great 3Britain refraining from the<br />
European Association and ul intaining her full contact<br />
with the Commonwalth. </p>
<p>I see, and my colleagues see, great nerit,<br />
politically, in a European association. We hardly need<br />
to be persuaded that it has ; reat importance. But we<br />
simply recird our view and we are bound to record that<br />
view that this will lead to a loosening of the Conronwealth<br />
relations. That nay be a price worth paying for<br />
the European association; I an not endeavouring to sit<br />
in judjnent on that. Indeed, only tine will provide an<br />
answer to it.<br />
So that the difference is a difference of opinion;<br />
it does not represent any vital matter. Indeed, it is<br />
very agreeable to me that in a natter in which Great<br />
Britain has tremendous interest some of her people, at<br />
any rate -without attributing a judl4ent to their Cabinetthought<br />
that for Great Britain to be in the Cornon Market<br />
representing an enlarged hone market of about 250 million<br />
people, would greatly increase her copetitive position,<br />
her competitive capacity in the world. That is a very<br />
le,: itimate argument. Ther-are, of course, arguments<br />
the other way, that British industry will be subject<br />
before long, to the full blast of continental competition<br />
in Great Britain itself. And I an relieved to know that<br />
I certainly do not have to decide that matter.<br />
But allowing for all these things, the remarkable<br />
thing about the discussion and about the corm. unique is<br />
not that it exhibits so many differences but that it<br />
exhibits so few. The one difference that I have<br />
referred to is the difference of opinion. And that is,<br />
of course, a matter of historic judgiont. We are all<br />
entitled to our own views on that. I used to think I<br />
knew a lot about the Commonwealth I an not so sure now.<br />
But all that is a matter of judgment. As for the rust,<br />
it has been agreed by then that so far as they can bring<br />
it about we will have every opportunity to defend these<br />
interests of ours if they Jecide to go into the<br />
negotiation. It has been a very interesting experienco. We have<br />
had close debates, as you night have gathered, not from<br />
the speculative stories that appear, but from the sheer<br />
amount of time that we have occupied in the course of<br />
them. Would anybody like to put a question ' o me? I<br />
am sorry to have spoken so long.<br />
QUESTION: Was there any indication of what the time-table<br />
night be, the decision-making process?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think only in this sense, that the six countries<br />
of the Cormon Market have not yet net to discuss<br />
agricultural policy and they are liable to * lo that<br />
before the end of the year. A'nd I think tihre is a<br />
German election in the next two or three months. If<br />
negotiations were to be engaged in it r: ight be more<br />
useful to engage in then before the aricultural policy<br />
talks, while the whole thing is fluid. That is the one<br />
thing that suggests that there will not be too much<br />
delay before a decision is taken.<br />
QUESTION: Can you tell us what present nati: ns in the Group,<br />
if any, entered on a conditional basis?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The original six cmebers are all in under the pure<br />
terns of the Treaty of Rome. There are two countries<br />
that have either acceded or are about to, not as full<br />
members but as associate members Greece and Turkey<br />
and if they do, they will come in on conditions I do<br />
Y </p>
<p>not carry then in nind but they will be allowed to cone<br />
in as associate ro. mbors because they are not highly<br />
industrialised countries. But there is no possibility<br />
of Great Britain coning in as an associate reomber<br />
because she is a very highly industrialised country.<br />
Therefore whatever conditions she might establish will<br />
have to be established by way of derogation fron the<br />
Treaty of Rome and securing the full agreement of the<br />
other six nations.<br />
QUESTION: What would you consider, yourself, to be the<br />
biggest danger to Australia by Great Britain joining the<br />
Common Market? Would it be a weakening of political<br />
ties with Great Britain, or just hardship?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think you have oversimplified that question.) uare<br />
speaking of joining the Ccnmon Market without conditions?<br />
PRESSMAN: Yes.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: If she joined the Conmon Market without conditions<br />
that would represent a tremendous blow to our export<br />
trade running into millions of pounds. It would<br />
represent for Now Zealand I do not want to speak for<br />
them here an almost fatal blow having regard to the<br />
size of the dairy product industry throughout the<br />
country. But whether it would mean the destruction of<br />
this trade or the substantial nodification of it there<br />
c. n be no doubt it would impose a great hardship before<br />
very long on half a dozen of our priary industries of<br />
some significance. That is assuming they went in<br />
unconditionally. But I do not think they will o3 in<br />
unconditionally. I think Great Britain is determined<br />
to do overything she can to get conditions which will<br />
give, at any rate, some measure of protection to the<br />
ComLonwealth trade. It may not be 100 percent; but some<br />
substantial measure. She has made that clear to us.<br />
But she will then, of course, have an awkward docision<br />
to make, because if, having gone into negotiations she<br />
finds there is nothing doing, that it has to be<br />
unconditional, then she nay feel compelled to withdraw<br />
from the negotiations and abandon the whole thing, give<br />
up what she otherwise feels to be economic advantages; or<br />
alternatively, cone to the grin choice about our own<br />
Cormonwealth trade. But we will not anticipate that yet.<br />
QUESTION: You have explained that the A'ustralian Cabinet did<br />
not think the case of Australian exports could be put by<br />
anybody as well as ourselves. I wonder whether that<br />
implies the British Government felt it would like to put<br />
the case of our exports on our behalf?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No it does not imply that. The nmoment we raised<br />
this matter they areeod at once that after all our own<br />
people, whose business it is, whose interest it is,<br />
naturally can put that case in the most c. mplete way.<br />
There was no suggestion they wanted to put it on our<br />
behalf.<br />
QUESTION: Do you think there is a genuine risk to the present<br />
political structure of the Coruaonwealth if Britain were<br />
to join the Common Market unconditionally?<br />
PRIME MINISTERI Yes, that is what we have s. id. This is not a risk<br />
of break-up. But what we say is that it would represent<br />
in our opinion in due course, a real modification in the<br />
present Cornonwealth relations. </p>
<p>QUESTION: What major effects do you think there would be on<br />
the political economy?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I would not guess. All I say is there would be some.<br />
QUESTION: Does the Australian Government intend to apply for<br />
membership of the Common Market?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think I an in enough trouble now with the<br />
Australian manufacturers, but if you are going to suggest<br />
Australia should get into a common free trade area I will<br />
have to take to the bush.<br />
QUESTION: You talk about the fact that some people in the<br />
United Kingdom Cabinet look to their market for their<br />
market for their produce and you suggested that there<br />
mig. ht equally be the possibility of greater cnopetition<br />
if the United Kingdom... Do you find any difforence betwea<br />
the view that our own Government took about advantages<br />
and disadvantages with the United Kingdom Government<br />
econor. ically within the Common Market and what they were<br />
thinking?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I do not think we were thinking along identical<br />
lines, no. It is very hard to judge. We are dealing<br />
with one Minister, although he is a very distinguished<br />
visitor, a distinguished Minister. He, I think, was<br />
* I hope I can say this without putting things into his<br />
mouth pretty conscious of the economic advantages; we<br />
on the other hand tended to think they night be overestimated<br />
and the econorc dadvantages might turn out to<br />
be rather greater. But we are not judging that from<br />
this distance. They are pretty old, as a country; I<br />
think that we will leave that decision to then.<br />
QUESTION: Australia has insisted on the right to negotiate<br />
direct with Common Market countries if Britain j; ins.<br />
What form will those ne . otiations take and what would be<br />
their objective?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I an sorry, I thought I had explained that. Before<br />
Britain decides to enter the Co. mmon Market she will<br />
negotiate. Thus there are two decisions to be made.<br />
First, a decision to negotiate. W4hen she joos in to<br />
noeotiation one of the things she will rant to discover<br />
is what terms and conditions can be got in relation to<br />
Comm: onwealth trade, the existing pattern of Co= nnonwealth<br />
trade, and preferences.<br />
It is at that stage when these matters are being<br />
discussed that we would wish to be present to defend our<br />
own interests or present our own interests. Whether we<br />
can be, or not, will depend upon Great Britain,<br />
If, when the negotiations are over, the osition is<br />
such that Great Britain has to reconsider the : whole<br />
matter she will then decide whether or not to go into the<br />
Common Market on such terms as nay have boon arranged in<br />
the noeotiation, or unconditionally, if no terms have<br />
been arranged. That will be a major decision she will<br />
have to take and she will take that after the stage of<br />
no otiation has been concluded. And I dare say at the<br />
time I am sure at that time when all the negotiations<br />
are over I do not imagine for one monent that she<br />
would arrive at that great crucial decision without some<br />
form of consultation with the Cornonwealth, either<br />
through a top level conference or otherwise. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Having in nind the economic and political facts of<br />
life in Europe do you entertain any real hope that we can<br />
arrive at conditions that will be acceptable to Australia?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I be to be excused from answering that question. I<br />
feel all they want is the best chance they can get if<br />
they decide to noctiate.<br />
QUESTION: Whatever Britain does about the Cornnon Market do you<br />
feel Australians will have to depend more on Asia in the<br />
future for markets than Europe?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think I would prefer to see this present exercise<br />
through before raising ny sights too high.<br />
QUESTION: The Australian Government has said that it is not<br />
entitled to raise any objections to the opening of<br />
negotiations but it does not approve of the opening of<br />
negotiations.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Do not twist it in that way. What I said was we<br />
were not entitled to object because this was a matter<br />
for the decision of the United Kingdom, not for us; that<br />
* this was not to be interpreted as an approval. That is<br />
a different natter.<br />
QUESTION: Sone people wonder why we could not approve of the<br />
mere opening of nojotiations as distinct from deciding,<br />
Ssince having detormined on the course negotiations w-uld<br />
take the opening of it had to be rather explicitly said<br />
to be not approved, by the phrasing of the connunique.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have already given ny reasons for that. I would<br />
not have thou.: ht there was ruch nysteiy about it. I an<br />
not in the habit of objecting to something that is not<br />
within my jurisdiction.<br />
QUESTION: Having in nind the views stated about the effect on<br />
Connonwealth trade do you think the effects to Australia<br />
would be greater politically or econonically?<br />
PRIME MINISTE: Both, if the contingency occurred. But I still say<br />
that I do not think it will.<br />
QUESTION: You said if Britain joined unconditionally it wuld<br />
be a trenendous blow. The figure of œ 170n. has already<br />
been quoted. Does the Governnont agree that that is the<br />
maximun?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Do not ask nm about the figuros. My colleague Mr.<br />
McEwen, has a press talk arranged on this matter ana will<br />
be able to give precise figures in relation to precise<br />
industries, because they were all to be under analysis.<br />
I do not carry those in ny nind. But I know it is very<br />
substantial and I know that overall that total has been<br />
referred to.<br />
QUESTION: Will you be puttin; in train any feelers to European<br />
countries as to whether they would take Austialian products?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We will not feel inhibited fron doing wthat we would<br />
normally do. The Trade Department normally has a few<br />
discussions going on with various countries either to<br />
renew trade treaties or something of that kind. I would<br />
not regard the Department of Trade as being prohibited by<br />
these discussions from following the course they would<br />
otherwise follow on these natters.<br />
CANBERRA, 13th July, 1961. </p>
<p>PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES, IN SYDNEY 4 P. M.<br />
JULY, 12TH, 1961<br />
PRIME MINISTEi: I think it might perhaps be a good idea you have<br />
all had the communique, or your principals have if I<br />
just said something about the background of this matter;<br />
in fact, if it does not sound too tedious, something<br />
about the history of the matter, because it is some<br />
years now since the Common Market was established in<br />
Europe by the six powers, that is to say, Germany, France,<br />
Italy and the Benelux powers we sometimes call it the<br />
Treaty of Rome. But one of the essential elements in it<br />
is that over a period of years they are aimed at internal<br />
free trade and a common external customs tariff.<br />
When the Common Market was established, when the<br />
negotiations were in hand, Great Britain did not decide<br />
to go in; she had remained out, as a matter of judgment<br />
Since then she has established a European Free Trade<br />
Association which includes six other European countries,<br />
including the Scandinavian countries. Now, she has not<br />
decided that was made clear to us by Mr. Sandys she<br />
has not decided to -o in or to negotiate her way in, but<br />
she has been rethinking the matter; and a decision as to<br />
whether they should negotiate to go in will be taken one<br />
way or the other after Mr. Sandys returns to London, and<br />
after other Ministers who have been visiting other<br />
Commonwealth countries have returned to London.<br />
So the whole thing is quite tentative at the present<br />
time. And I think it is proper to say, because there is<br />
a little misunderstanding about it that Mr. Sandys did<br />
not come out to ask us to say " Yes? to go into the Common<br />
Market, or to approve of Great Britain negotiating to go<br />
into the Common Market, because Great Britain herself has<br />
not yet taken a decision. What he was really doing was<br />
informing us of the various considerations that were<br />
operating in the minds of the British Government. And we<br />
welcomed this because although consultation in principle<br />
has been accepted now for the last two or three years,<br />
this was in fact the first occasion when we have had any<br />
close ministerial discussion about the matter in principb.<br />
And we therefore welcomed his visit and we enjoyed it.<br />
That would explain to you why, in the course of the<br />
communique we have said " This is a matter for Great<br />
Britain to decide", which it clearly is. It is Great<br />
Britain that may or may not go into the Common M4crkot;<br />
it is not Australia or New Zealand. Therefore a<br />
decision for Great Britain. That being so we have no<br />
status to object or to do anything else about it except<br />
to exchange our ideas and do what we can to protect our<br />
own interests. And a good deal of our discussion took<br />
place in relation to the . rays and means of protecting our<br />
own interests should the United Kingdom decide to<br />
negotiate for entry to the Cormmon Market.<br />
The reason for that is very clear, of course.<br />
Suppose Great Britain . rent into the Cormmon Market<br />
unconditionally I mean on exactly the :; ame footing as<br />
Germany or France or Italy or the rest then, in due<br />
course, perhaps over a period of seven or eijht years,<br />
there should be internal free trade. And if Groat Britain<br />
wont in, it is reasonable to assume sone of the<br />
Scandinavian countries w: ould go in, including for<br />
example, Denmark. And if Great Britain wen in<br />
unconditionally and I repeat, that is to say on the<br />
same footing as the others then Danish butter would </p>
<p>find free entry into the United Kingdom, but Australian<br />
butter and Now Zealand butter would be met by the common<br />
tariff barrier and would threfore pay duty, which would<br />
seem to us to be rather an unhappy result for an industry<br />
which is substantial in Australia but probably vital<br />
in New Zealand as an export industry.<br />
And in the same way wheat from France, France being<br />
a groat wheat producer, wou. d move into England duty<br />
free while wheat from Australia would lose its present<br />
advantage of going in without duty.<br />
Dried fruits very important in various areas of<br />
Australia would lose their preferences, because they<br />
would be all subject to the common tariff barrier. But<br />
dried fruits from say Greece Greece having already<br />
decided to be an associate member of the Common Market<br />
would move in duty free.<br />
These of course, are tremendously grave matters for<br />
us, not natters to be disposed of merely in a sentimental<br />
way. They have very grave implications for our own<br />
business. And one of the things that we set out to do<br />
was to establish that these particular interests were not<br />
to be overlooked in any negotiations. That is why you<br />
will have noticed in the course of the commuunique that<br />
in any such negotiations various Australian axport<br />
industries would be involved and Australia should be in a<br />
position to negotiate direct on Australia's oehalf when<br />
datails and arrangements affecting items of Australian<br />
trade were being discussed.<br />
dhat that means is that we did not feel that the<br />
case for our export primary industries could be put by<br />
anybody as well as by Australia, because we are familiar<br />
with the problem. Therefore it was not enough to be<br />
consulted in the distance; it was essential thi. t in case<br />
the British Government decided to negotiate and I<br />
repeat it has not yet decided in case it decided to<br />
negotiate, then we would be, so to speak, in the room, and<br />
taking a hand in the discussion when wheat wouli be<br />
debated, or dried fruit, or butter, or whatever these<br />
comrtodities might be.<br />
Of course the United Kingdom cannot guarantee that<br />
that would be so because if it decides to neootiate it<br />
will negotiate with the six nations of the Common Market<br />
as a group, and if they say " No, nobody else is going to<br />
be in the actual negotiation", then that, no doubt, will<br />
be conclusive. But I am sure that so far as Great<br />
Britain is concerned, if it does decide to negotiate, it<br />
will do all it can to secure our presence and our<br />
participation when those particular matters are under<br />
consideration. That, I think, will explain why it is that we have<br />
observed a fairly cautious position in those discussions,<br />
not making ourselves a party to a decision it is not<br />
our decision to make but doing all that we can to<br />
protect our own legitimate interests should the decision<br />
be taken. And that, I am sure, is what the people of<br />
Australia would expect us to do.<br />
I do njt think there is any trouble about that, so<br />
far as our friends in the United Kingdom are concerned.<br />
I think that represented in the long run a common and<br />
cheerfully accepted view of the position. </p>
<p>But there is one matter, a difference of opinion<br />
that enmrges, that I would like to say something abou,<br />
and that is the difference on the political implications.<br />
The Treaty of Rome is, in its torms, an economic treaty.<br />
It covers a variety of natters. I have mentioned two of<br />
the great ones, internal free trade and common external<br />
trriff. It also provides for machinery for common<br />
working standards, for social services. It really covers<br />
a groat deal of the econonic field in these countries;<br />
and, of course, if Great Britain becomes a nomber it will<br />
correspondingly cover a great deal of the same field in<br />
Great Britain.<br />
ve think, and indeed we think that the Connon Market<br />
countries think, that the political implications of this<br />
are very great. Indeed I think it is one of the proper<br />
objects of the exercise. They did not engage in the<br />
Treatu yf Rone just because of tariffs and trade;<br />
but they were contemplating that as<br />
time went on because of all this comnon ground, they<br />
would become more and more of a political unity, not<br />
necessarily one nation, not necessarily a federation in<br />
the sense that we understand it, but sonething of what I<br />
will call broadly, a political unity, a get together<br />
politically, with a growing tendency to have cornon<br />
policies, to thrash then out. So that in the result you<br />
would have these European nations togethor constituting<br />
more people than the United States of A( orica and<br />
therefore representing what night loosely be described as<br />
a third power in the world.<br />
That is a view strongly held by a nunber of<br />
European statesmen. I offer no cor. mcnt on it. But we<br />
think that the political tendencies in the Connon Market<br />
must be in that diroetion. How far it will go is<br />
anybody's guess.<br />
And under those circumstancos we sirply observe in<br />
point of fact, that we do not think the position as<br />
between Great Britain and the other Connionwealth<br />
countries in the political field remains unaltered. It<br />
is very difficult f-r no to believe that Great Britain,<br />
intimately involved in European politics, for the first<br />
tine this is not the old 19th century balance of power<br />
business it is very hard tj believe that her position<br />
in relation to the Connonwalth countries, when we neet<br />
at Prime Ministers' Conferences, would rem. ain so<br />
individual and detached as it is today.<br />
Now I an not saying that is good, bad or<br />
indifferont; neither ny colleaguesnor I sit in judjnent<br />
on that matter. But we record our view that the<br />
Commonwealth will not quite be the sane. Mr. Sandys<br />
felt, and no doubt with groat conviction that none of<br />
these things would affect the Comnonwealth relationship.<br />
Well, we think it will.<br />
Whether that is a good thing or a bad thing depends<br />
on a choice that it is n. t for us to make the choice<br />
between Great Britain effJectively participating in a<br />
powerful European group of nations in the international<br />
political field, but with a looser association with the<br />
C: o onweoalth, or a Gre. t Britain refraining fron the<br />
European Association and maintaining her full contact<br />
with the Crnononwealth. </p>
<p>I see, and my colleagues see, great merit,<br />
politically, in a European association. * Ve hardly need<br />
to be persuaded that it has rreat importance. But we<br />
simply record our view and we are bound to record that<br />
view that this will lead to a loosening of the Commonwealth<br />
relations. That nay be a price worth paying for<br />
the European association; I an not endeavouring to sit<br />
in judjgent on that. Indeed, only tine will provide an<br />
answer to it.<br />
So that the difference is a difference of opinion;<br />
it does not represent any vital natter. Indeed, it is<br />
very agreeable to ne that in a natter in which Great<br />
Britain has troe. ondous interest some of her people, at<br />
any rate without attributing a jud. pont to their Cabinctthought<br />
that for Great Britain to be in the Connon Market<br />
representing an enlarged home market of about 250 million<br />
people, would greatly increase her competitive position,<br />
her competitive capacity in the world. That is a very<br />
legitimate argument. There. are, of course, arguments<br />
the other way, that British industry will be subject<br />
before long, to the full blast of continental competition<br />
in Great Britain itself. And I an relieved to know that<br />
I certainly do not have to decide that matter.<br />
But allowing for all those things, the remarkable<br />
thing about the discussion and about the cor. m-unique is<br />
not that it exhibits so many differences but that it<br />
exhibits so few. The one difference that I have<br />
referred to is the difference of opinion. And that is,<br />
of course, a matter of historic jud.. iont. We are all<br />
entitled to our own views on that. I used to think I<br />
knew a lot about the Commonwealth I an not so sure now.<br />
But all that is a matter of judj ent. As for the rest,<br />
it has been agreod by them that so far as they can bring<br />
it about we will have every opportunity to defend these<br />
interests of ours if they decide to go into the<br />
negotiation. It has been a very intoresting experience. iWe have<br />
had close debates, as you might have gathered, not from<br />
the speculative stories that appear, but from the sheer<br />
amount of time that we have occupied in the course of<br />
them. Would anybody like to put a question ' o mn? I<br />
am sorry to have spoken so long.<br />
QUESTION: Was there any indication of what the time-table<br />
night be, the decision-naking process?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think only in this sense, that the six countries<br />
of the Cormon Market have not yet met to discuss<br />
agricultural policy and they are liable to Io that<br />
before the end of the year. And I think there is a<br />
German election in the next two or three months. If<br />
nugotiations were to be engaged in it might be more<br />
useful to engage in them before the aricultural policy<br />
talks, while the whole thing is fluid. That is the one<br />
thing that suggests that there will not be too much<br />
delay before a decision is taken.<br />
QUESTION: Can you tell us what present nations in the Group,<br />
if any, entered on a conditional basis?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The original six members are all in under the pure<br />
terns of the Treaty of Rome. There are two countries<br />
that have either acceded or are about to, not as full<br />
members but as associate members Greece and Turkey<br />
and if they do, they will come in on conditions I do </p>
<p>not carry them in nind but they will be allowed to cone<br />
in as associate members because they are not highly<br />
industrialisod countries. But there is no possibility<br />
of Great Britain coning in as an associate aomber<br />
because she is a very highly industrialised country.<br />
Therefore whatever conditions she might establish will<br />
have to be established by way of derogation from the<br />
Treaty of Rome and securing the full agreement of the<br />
other six nations.<br />
QUESTION: What would you consider, yourself, to be the<br />
biggest danger to Australia by Great Britain joining the<br />
Common Market? Would it be a weakening of political<br />
ties with Great Britain, or just hardship?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think you have oversimplified that question. ouare<br />
speaking of joining the Ccmron Market without conditions?<br />
PRESSMAN: Yes.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: If she joined the Corlnon Market without conditions<br />
that would represent a tremendous blow to our export<br />
trade running into millions of pounds. It would<br />
represent for New Zealand I do not want to speak for<br />
them here an almost fatal blow having regard to the<br />
size of the dairy product industry throughout the<br />
country. But whether it would mean the destruction of<br />
this trade or the substantial modification of it there<br />
cp. n be no doubt it would impose a great hardship before<br />
very long on half a dozen of our primary industries of<br />
some significance. That is assuming they went in<br />
unconditionally. But I do not think they will go in<br />
unconditionally. I think Great Britain is determined<br />
to do everything she can to get conditions which will<br />
give, at any rate, sone measure of protection to the<br />
Commonwealth trade. It may not be 100 percent; but some<br />
substantial measure. She has made that clear to us.<br />
But she will then, of course, have an awkward decision<br />
to make, because if, having gone into negotiations she<br />
finds there is nothing doing, that it has to be<br />
unconditional, then she may feel compelled to withdraw<br />
from the no tiations and abandon the whole thing, give<br />
up what she otherwise feels to be economic advantages; or<br />
alternatively, cone to the grin choice about our own<br />
Conmonwealth trade. But we will not anticipate that yet.<br />
QUESTION: You have explained that the Australian Cabinet did<br />
not think the case of Australian exports could be put by<br />
anybody as well as ourselves. I wonder whether that<br />
implies the British Govecrnment felt it would like to put<br />
the case of our exports on our behalf?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, it does not imply that. The moment we raised<br />
this matter they agreed at once that after all our own<br />
people, whose business it is, whose interest it is,<br />
naturally can put that case in the most c) i: pletc way.<br />
There was no suggestion they wanted to put it on our<br />
behalf.<br />
QUESTION: Do you think there is a genuine risk to the present<br />
political structure of the Cor-u-nonwealth if Britain were<br />
to join the Common Market unconditionally?<br />
PRIME MINISTERi Yes, that is what wo have said. This is not a risk<br />
of break-up. But what we say is that it would represent<br />
in our opinion in due course, a real nodification in the<br />
present Corronwealth relations. </p>
<p>QUESTION: What major effects do you think there would be on<br />
the political econony?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I would not guess. All I say is there would be some.<br />
QUESTION: Does the Australian Government intend to apply for<br />
membership of the Comnon Market?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think I an in enough trouble now with the<br />
Australian manufacturers, but if you are going to suggest<br />
Australia should get into a cormon free trade area I will<br />
have to take to the bush.<br />
QUESTION: You talk about the fact that sone people in the<br />
United Kingdom Cabinet look to their market for their<br />
market for their produce and you suggested that there<br />
night equally be the possibility of greater cnlpetition<br />
if the United Kingdom.. Do you find any difforence betwem<br />
the view that our own Governrent took about advantages<br />
and disadvantages with the United Kingdom Government<br />
economically within the Conmon Market and what they were<br />
thinking?<br />
* PRIME MINISTER: I do not think we were thinking along identical<br />
lines, no. It is very hard to judge. We are dealing<br />
with one Minister, although he is a very distinguished<br />
visitor, a distinguished Minister. He, I think, was<br />
I hope I can say this without putting things into his<br />
mouth pretty conscious of the economic advantages; we<br />
on the other hand tended to think they might be overestimated<br />
and the econonrdc dvantages might turn out to<br />
be rather greater. But we are not judging that from<br />
this distance. They are pretty old, as a country; I<br />
think that we will leave that decision to then.<br />
QUESTION: Australia has insisted on the right to negotiate<br />
direct with Conrmon Market countries if Britain joins.<br />
What form will those ne ; otiations take and what would be<br />
their objective?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I am sorry, I thought I had explained that. Before<br />
Britain decides to enter the Common Market she will<br />
neootiate. Thus there are two decisions to be made.<br />
First, a decision to negotiate. LJhen she _ oes in to<br />
neootiation one of the things she will rant to discover<br />
is what terms and conditions can be got in relation to<br />
Commonwealth trade, the existing patteon of Commonwealth<br />
trade, and preferences.<br />
It is at that stage when these matters are being<br />
discussed that we would wish to be present to defend our<br />
owm interestsor prosent our own interests. Whcther we<br />
can be, or not, will depend upon Great Britaino<br />
If, when the negotiations are over, the -sition is<br />
such that Great Britain has to reconsider the whole<br />
matter she will then decide whether or not to go into the<br />
Common Market on such terns as may have been arranged in<br />
the negotiation, or unconditionally, if no torms have<br />
been arranged. That will be a major decision she will<br />
have to take and she will take that after the stage of<br />
negotiation has been concluded. And I dare say at the<br />
time I am sure at that time when all the negotiations<br />
are over I do not imagine for one morent that she<br />
would arrive at that great crucial decision without some<br />
form of consultation with the Commonwealth, either<br />
through a top level conference or otherwise. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Having in nind the economic and political facts of<br />
life in Europe do you entertain any real hope that we can<br />
arrive at condi'tions that will be acceptable to Australia?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I boeg to be excused from answering that question. I<br />
feel all they want is the best chance they can get if<br />
they decide to negotiate.<br />
QUESTION: Whatever Britain does about the Cor. non Market do you<br />
feel Australians will have to depend more on Asia in the<br />
future for markets than Europe?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think I would prefer to see this present exorcise<br />
through before raising ry sights too high.<br />
QUESTION: The Australian Government has said that it is not<br />
entitled to raise any objections to the opening of<br />
negotiations but it does not approve of the opening of<br />
negotiations.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Do not twist it in that way. What I said was we<br />
were not entitled to object because this was a matter<br />
for the decision of the United Kingdom, not for us; that<br />
this was not to be interpreted as an approval. That is<br />
a different matter.<br />
QUESTION: Sone people wonder why we could not approve of the<br />
mere opening of njotiations as distinct fron deciding,<br />
since having determined on the course negotiations would<br />
take the opening of it had to be rather explicitly said<br />
to be not approved, by the phrasing of the cormunique.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have already given ny reasons for that. I would<br />
not have thought there was much nystery about it. I am<br />
not in the habit of objecting to sonething that is not<br />
within my jurisdiction.<br />
QUESTION: Having in nind the views stated about the effect on<br />
Cornonwealth trade do you think the effects to Australia<br />
would be greater politically or econonically?<br />
PRIME MINISTEiR: Both, if the contingency occurred. But I still say<br />
that I do not think it will.<br />
QUESTION: You said if Britain joined unconditionally it wuld<br />
be a tremendous blow. The figure of œ 170m. has already<br />
been quoted. Does the Governnent agree that that is the<br />
naximun?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Do not ask me about the figures. My colleague Mr.<br />
McEwen, has a press talk arranged on this natter and will<br />
be able to give precise figures in relation to precise<br />
industries, because they were all to be under analysis.<br />
I do not carry those in ny nind. But I know it is very<br />
substantial and I know that overall that total has been<br />
referred to.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTE<br />
CANBERR, Will you be putting in train any feelers ' o European<br />
countries as to whether they would take Austialian products?<br />
ER: We will not fool inhibited fron doing what we would<br />
normally do. The Trade Department normally has a few<br />
discussions going on with various countries either to<br />
renew trade treaties or something of that kind. I would<br />
not regard the Department of Trade as being prohibited by<br />
these discussions from following the course they would<br />
otherwise follow on these matters.<br />
13th July, 1961. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
