<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2886</transcript-id>
    <title>ABORIGINALS AND SOCIETY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, CIRCULATED TO A CONFERENCE OF COMMONWEALTH AND STATE MINISTERS CONCERNED WITH ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS IN ADELAIDE, FRIDAY 6 APRIL 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/04/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002886.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT NO. 74<br />
6 April 1973<br />
ABORIGINALS AND~ SOCIETY<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the<br />
Hon. E. G. Whitlam, M. P.,<br />
circulated to a conference of Commonwealth and State<br />
Ministers concerned with Aboriginal Affairs in Adelaide,<br />
Friday, 6 April, 1973<br />
The referendum of 1967, by an overwhelming majority, gave to<br />
the Commonwealth concurrent powers with the States in respect of<br />
Aboriginals. The constitution provides that in matters where concurrent<br />
powers are held Commonwealth legislation will prevail. It is my<br />
Government's belief that Aboriginal Affairs is a matter of national concern,<br />
requires the exercise of the fullest range of legislative, executive<br />
and financial powers, and represents in the eyes of the world a test of<br />
the integrity and humanity of the whole people of Australia. My<br />
Government intends therefore to assume full responsibility for policy<br />
ana finance in respect of Aboriginal Affairs and will take any necessary<br />
legislative action to this end.<br />
At the same time, my Government is convinced that, in<br />
formulating and giving effect to its responsibility, it must draw upon<br />
the knowledge, experience and services of all sections of Government.<br />
It will not therefore aim to establish an omnibus Commonwealth Department<br />
of Aboriginal Affairs. It will instead seek to devolve upon a wide<br />
range of Commonwealth, State and local authorities, as well as upon<br />
organisations of Aboriginals themselves, responsibility for carrying<br />
out the policies decided upon by my Government. These authorities<br />
would be responsible for Aboriginals in the same matters and in the same<br />
way as they now are functionally responsible for the community generally.<br />
We have already taken some steps towards a rationalisation of<br />
our own administration of Aboriginal Affairs in the Northern Territory<br />
by combining the former Office of Aboriginal Affairs and Welfare ' Division<br />
of the Northern Territory Administration and by transferring responsibility<br />
for Aboriginal health and education to the Ministers for health and education.<br />
Further transfers of functional responsibilities will be arranged. I<br />
believe that we have already made significant progress in rationalisin~ g<br />
the administrative structure and welding into a single unit those<br />
responsible for t he initiation of planning and policy proposals.<br />
In matters of State constitutional responsibility such as health,<br />
education and so on, my Government will be seeking the help of all State<br />
Ministers and their Departments both in assisting the Commonwealth Minister<br />
and Department of Aboriginal Affairs to formulate appropriate policies<br />
and in giving effect to them within their State jurisdiction. I hope<br />
that Ministers will collaborate with us in the next few months to enable<br />
their officials to confer with ours to work out the most effective<br />
means of putting this plan into operation. c.* o/ </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The basic object 9f my Government's policy is to restore to the<br />
Aboriginal people of Australia their lost power of self-determination<br />
in economic, social and political affairs. The Minister for Aboriginal<br />
Affairs, Mr. Bryant, will be introducing into Parliament, I hope during<br />
the budget session, legislation to enable Aboriginal groups and<br />
communities to incorporate for the conduct of their own affairs. We see<br />
these incorporated societies, set up for purposes chosen by their<br />
Aboriginal members, determining their own decision-making processes,<br />
choosing their own leaders and executives in ways they will themselves<br />
decide, as the primary instruments of Aboriginal authority at the local<br />
and community level.<br />
The Government will also set up, on the advice of Aboriginals,<br />
procedures for the election of freely-chosen Aboriginal representatives<br />
from the various regions of Aboriginal population to form a consultative<br />
council with which the Government will confer on matters affecting<br />
Aboriginals. Mr. Bryant has already convened initial meetings towards<br />
the establishment of this body.<br />
Traditional Aboriginal societies have had close associations with<br />
specific areas of land, and there are many Aboriginal communities which<br />
have maintained that association substantially unbroken. In respect of<br />
land reserved for Aboriginal use and benefit it is the firm policy of the<br />
Government to vest such lands in the Aboriginals, as far as practicable<br />
in ways which accord with traditional Aboriginal law and practice. Mr.<br />
Justice E. A. Woodward has been commissioned to confer with Aboriginal<br />
communities concerned and to advise the legislative and administrative<br />
actions required. His enquiry will also, of course, extend to land<br />
outside reserves0 The Government will await wit# interest his<br />
recommendations in respect of those situations where traditional association<br />
can be established for such land outside reserves,.<br />
In the meantime, my Government plans, as opportunity offers, to<br />
purchase or acquire land which it will vest in the resident Aboriginal<br />
communities and you will be aware that it has undertaken to provide<br />
million per year for the next 10 years for this purpose0 In this way my<br />
Government hopes to restore as far as possible the traditional association<br />
of Aboriginal communities with their land and also provide them with a base<br />
for their economic and social development.<br />
This policy of re-establishing the traditional association of<br />
Aboriginal communities with the land is linked with support for the<br />
preservation and development of Aboriginal languages and culture generally.<br />
A start has already been made in ' basing education of Aborigines on<br />
literacy first in their own tribal tongue0 Increasing support will be<br />
given to the Aboriginal arts and Aboriginals will be helped where they<br />
wish to do so to maintain the active ceremonial life on which these arts<br />
were traditionally based.<br />
An opportunity for self-determination and independent action<br />
would serve little purpose if Aboriginals continued to be economically<br />
and socially deprived. The Government therefore plans to help them as<br />
individuals, groups or communities, in crafts, trades and professions<br />
and as business enterpreneurs. To this end programs of socially valuable<br />
special work projects, vocational training and grants and loans in support<br />
of enterprises, will be actively promoted. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
More generally, my Government is anxious that 200 years of<br />
despoliation, injustice and discrimination have seriously damaged and<br />
demoralised the once proud Aboriginal people. The Government, on behalf<br />
of the Australian people, accepts responsibility for their active and<br />
progressive rehabilitation.<br />
We will legislate to outlaw all forms of discrimination and will<br />
allocate greatly increased resources to overcome the handicaps under which<br />
Aboriginals now labour and to improve their health and capacity generally.<br />
We will not rest until they have taken up, as a distinctive and honoured<br />
component in the Australian society, the position to which their rights<br />
as the first Australians entitle them, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
