<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2802</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER WELCOMES AGREEMENT WITH INDONESIA ON PAPUA NEW GUINEA BOUNDARIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002802.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 29 26 January 1973<br />
PRBiE MINISTER WEODMES AGRE34ENT WITH INDONESIA<br />
ON PAPUA NEW GUINEA BOUNDARIES<br />
The Prime Inister and Minister for Foreign Affairs,<br />
Mr Whitlam, welcomed in Perth today the fact that an agreement has<br />
been drawn up and initialled in Canberra providing for the establishment<br />
of permanent and enduring boundaries between Indonesia and Papua New<br />
Guinea. This followed negotiations in Canberra between an Indonesian<br />
and Australian delegation from 22 January to 26 January.<br />
The negotiations, which dealt with the land boundary between<br />
Papua New Guinea and Indonesia and the territorial sea and seabed<br />
boundary with Indonesia immediately south of Papua New Guinea, were a<br />
continuation of discussions held in Jakarta in October 1972.<br />
The Indonesian Ambassador to Australia, Mr Suyitno Sukirno,<br />
was leader of the Indonesian delegation and Professor Mochtar<br />
Kusumaatmadja, deputy leader. The Solicitor-General, Mr R. J. ELlicott,<br />
was leader of the Australian delegation, which included officials<br />
of the Papua New Guinea Government.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that he was delighted that all matters under<br />
review had been amicably resolved. The Government of Papua New Guinea<br />
had concurred in the initialling of the Agreement which would now<br />
be submitted to the House of Assembly for approval. </p>
<p>Both delegations had welcomed the Agreement as a tribute to<br />
the spirit of reason and good neighbourliness which had marked the<br />
negotiations. The Agreement, when ratified, would conclude the delimitation<br />
of land, territorial sea and seabed boundaries between Indonesia on the<br />
one hand, and Australia and Papua New Guinea on the other.<br />
Mr Whitlam added: " It is also a most important Agreement in<br />
the context of future relations between Indonesia and an independent<br />
Papua New Guinea." </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
