<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21432</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview, Sydney  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/08/2004</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, on the Free Trade Agreement, the Opposition is saying it might have an answer next week.  What do you say to that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well they've had five months and we now know that the Senate inquiry was a complete political alibi because the Labor Senators won't express an opinion until they get their riding instructions from Caucus.  Now this is a total shambles.  This is the country's future we're talking about and I want the Labor Party to support the Free Trade Agreement because without their support it won't go through, and they've had five months to make up their mind and I just ask Mr Latham to show leadership and strength and tell his party, as the Labor Premiers have said, that it's in Australia's interest that this Agreement go through.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you expect Mr Latham to support the Free Trade Agreement?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't know.  I mean it is very confusing.  I know where I stand.  I've known where I've stood on this issue for months, and so do the Labor Premiers.  I mean I have bipartisan support on this, but it's from the State Labor Premiers, not from the Federal Opposition Leader.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>(inaudible) doesn't support the Free Trade Agreement, how important an element will that be in your decision on the timing for the federal election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>This is above and beyond any short term political considerations.  This is about Australia's future.  And I'm just asking Mr Latham to call it for Australia, not for the Labor Party.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So do you agree then, if it's so important, there's no rush, that the Labor Party should take its time?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The Labor Party has had all the time in the world.  They've had five months.  They know, we all know that the terms of the Agreement can't and won't change.  They've had plenty of time to make up their minds.  They hid behind this alibi of a Senate inquiry, but it's now been revealed there's a... as a phoney excuse, an alibi.  The Caucus is waiting on the Committee, the Committee is now waiting on the Caucus.  I mean it is a shambles.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, Kim Beazley is talking about a new battalion for the Army.  Do you think that's a good idea?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well he was talking about that yesterday, but this morning when he was asked about it, he ran 100 miles an hour from it.  I don't know what he's talking about.  I watched his interview with interest, and I was no wiser at the end because he apparently briefed some newspapers about a new battalion but when he was put on the spot, he said oh well I'll be making a speech in a couple of weeks time.  Well I'm sure we'll watch that speech with interest.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What about his defence policy though?</p>
<p>   PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I beg your pardon?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What about their defence policy?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well their defence policy is confused.  They have a confused policy on Iraq and now they are further confusing us.  I thought Mr Beazley was going to bring strength and purpose and clarity to Labor's defence policy.  Judging by this battalion exercise, he's brought confusion.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you believe there is a need for another battalion Mr Howard?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think the arrangements we have at the present time are working very effectively.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you believe we have stronger... our ties with south-east Asia are strong enough to deal with terrorism in the region?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well they're very strong, they're very strong.  In fact one of the things that's happened is that the links between the police and the intelligence services have been strengthened over the last couple of years.  We would never have seen such a terrific operation by the Indonesian Police in catching the Bali attackers if it hadn't been for the close cooperation between the Australian Police and the Indonesian Police.  This suggestion that we're not close to the security services and the police in south-east Asia is completely wrong.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think that the Philippines Government has been aggressive enough pursuing Abu Sayyaf and the other terrorist groups?</p>
<p>   PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I think everybody has to be aggressive.  I'm not going to get into some kind of marking of individual countries.  I'm not... I may be on school premises, but I'm not going to get into that exercise.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, at least 10 people have been identified by ASIO as going through terrorist camps (inaudible) September 11 obviously, and (inaudible) able to be tried under new legislation.  Should the Australian people be concerned?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look everybody should be concerned about the potential of terrorist activity in our region.  Australia is not as vulnerable as other countries, but we're all more vulnerable now than we used to be.  But I'm not going to comment on particular activities of ASIO and I think you know the reason why.  Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
