<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3547</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL ADVISORY COUNCIL ON REHABILITATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003547.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
,,, AUSTKAU( A<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 416<br />
December 1974<br />
NATIONAL ADVISORY COUNCIL ON REHABILITATION<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, said today that a<br />
National Advisory Council on Rehabilitation was being<br />
established to advise the Government on all aspects of its<br />
policies affecting the rehabilitation of the injured and<br />
the handicapped. The Chairman will be Mr Justice C. L. D. Meares,<br />
of the Supreme Court of New South Wales, and the Chairman<br />
of the New South Wales Law Reform Commission.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that the Government had been very<br />
fortunate in securing Mr Justice Meares' services. With<br />
Sir Owen Woodhouse, he had formed the Committee of Inquiry<br />
into Compensation and Rehabilitation in Australia. The<br />
Committee's Report was presented earlier this year, and the<br />
National Compensation Bill, which was currently before the<br />
Parliament, was one substantial result of it.<br />
The Government would be looking to the Council for<br />
advice on implementing the rehabilitation aspects of the<br />
Woodhouse Report, the Prime Minister added. The Committee<br />
of Inquiry said in that section of itp Report dealing with<br />
rehabilitation that " in the past, the handicapped have been<br />
neglected and often isolated. Society has paid far too little<br />
attention to their needs". Mr Whitlam said that with the<br />
Council's help, the Government would ensure that the<br />
handicapped would receive all the assistance and protection<br />
which could reasonably be provided, so that they could find<br />
a worthwhile place in society.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the Council would be<br />
responsible to the Special Minister of State, Mr Bowen.<br />
The other members would be announced following discussions<br />
with Mr Justice Meares.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
