<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3080</transcript-id>
    <title>GRANT TO THE N.S.W. ART GALLERY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/11/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003080.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 6. OOPM FRIDAY 23 NOVEMBER 1973:<br />
PRIME MINISTER Press Statement No. 149<br />
23 November 1973<br />
GRANT TO THE N. S. W. ART GALLERY<br />
The Prime Minister today-announced that he had approved<br />
a grant of $ 20,000 to the Art Gallery of New South Wales to<br />
help clear its outstanding debt of $ 75,000 on the purchase of<br />
the self-portrait by Pierre Bonnard.<br />
The grant is conditional on the Government of New<br />
South Wales providing the remaining $ 55,000.<br />
The grant was recommended by the Visual Arts Board of<br />
the Australian Council for the Arts. The Chairman of the Board,<br />
Mr. John Baily, said that the grant was in about the same<br />
proportion to the total purchase price as the $ 50,000 granted<br />
recently to the National Gallery of Victoria towards the purchase<br />
of the painting " Val d'Aosta" by J. M. W. Turner.<br />
The Prime Minister also announced approval for a shceme<br />
to support living Australian artists by subsidising the purchase<br />
of their work on a dollar-for-dollar basis.<br />
In announcing the scheme, the Prime Minister said it was<br />
designed to encourage Australian art galleries to acquire<br />
contemporary works, and to directly benefit practising artists.<br />
The subsidy scheme, which would operate through the Visual<br />
Arts Board, would be available to all public galleries and collections.<br />
Dollar-for-dollar grants would be given only for the purchase of<br />
works directly from the artist or from his nominated agent.<br />
It would not apply to works bought at auction or by resale,<br />
where there was no benefit to the artist.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said that the scheme would provide a needed stimulus<br />
to the purchase and display of contemporary works, on which relatively<br />
little is spent at present. Public galleries and collections enjoying<br />
this form of assistance will need to satisfy the Board of wide access<br />
to their collections and of their professional competence in the<br />
selection of works.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
