<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>926</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF NEW CLINICAL SCHOOL BUILDINGS, ST VINCENTS&#039;S HOSPITAL, SYDNEY - 3RD MARY 1964 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/05/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000926.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF NEWT CLINICAL SCHOOL BUJILDINGS<br />
ST. VINCENT'S HOSPITAL, SYDNEY<br />
3RD MAY, 1964+<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Mengies<br />
Mr. Chairman, Your Eminence, Mr. Sheahan, Mother Rectress and<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen My simple function this afternoon is to declare<br />
the Clincical School and the Students' Residence open. If<br />
somebody will be good enough to remind me at the right time,<br />
I will do that. In the meantime, I take leave to tell you, as you<br />
have already discovered, that here is a sort of port of last<br />
call. Whenever an occasion of this kind happens and I look at<br />
my State colleagues even a good friend of mine like Mr.<br />
Sheahan, I know that before he finishes, he will lay a little<br />
hand on me ( Laughter) and throw out a broad hint about something,<br />
I don't mind that from another politician, but if I may say so,<br />
with all the truculence of a Presbyterian ( Laughter), I take<br />
great exception to being nudged by the Cardinal ( Laughter)<br />
( Applause), because when we went through the students' residence,<br />
I may have imagined it, but I felt quite certain that he gave<br />
me a quick dig in the ribs. ( Laughter) And under these circumstances,<br />
I think that I really ought to say a few words in my<br />
own defence, unaccustomed as I am to that kind of exercise.<br />
( Laughter) It is quite true, as you have been told, that I have<br />
been fortunate enough to have more than a little to do with the<br />
entry of the Commonwealth into tertiary education, with the<br />
Murray Committee and the adoption of the Murray Report and then<br />
the creation of the Universities Commission, and those things<br />
undoubtedly though they have produced occasional discomfort<br />
for the Treasury have been a great opportunity for new life<br />
to the universities of Australia and for that I am thankful,<br />
but you know, it wasn't until after that had beon done that I<br />
was approached by various people and invited to consider whether<br />
the teaching hospitals ought to be put on some footing which<br />
would approximhate them to the universities proper. So in order<br />
to secure a completely unbiased report, I added to the Universities<br />
Commission a well.-known professor of medicine; that is<br />
a very good way of seeing that nothing is overlooked. And in<br />
the result, we decided two things: First that we would include<br />
teaching hospitals who were, in the view of the Advisory Committee,<br />
doing work that could be properly be described as university<br />
work, that we would include them in the recommendation for grants<br />
to be made by the Commission. Now that was a very great step<br />
forward in the teaching hospitals.<br />
In the second place, we decided we would, pending<br />
a rather fuller examination of running costs because it is not<br />
easy to segregate the normal costs of running a hospital from<br />
the special costs attaching to tuition of a clinical kind<br />
pending the conclusion of that matter we would make contributions<br />
for the capital expenditure of ieaching hospitals. Now<br />
that is a comparatively recent matter. I expect that before this<br />
year is out, we will have received and acted upon the report on<br />
the recurring expenditure side. I say that because my friend,<br />
Mr. Sheahan, was getting in a bit early on this, as if we hadn't<br />
thought of it. I expect before the year is out, that this will<br />
have borne fruit. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
But in the meantime, I tell you, I had a bit of<br />
pleasure in walking through this clinical school this afternoon<br />
because it is literally one of the first fruits of that new policy<br />
and I am delighted and I hope that it will be followed by many<br />
other hospitals in many other places.<br />
I suppose I don't know, but I suppose that centuries<br />
ago you didn't need to know much to be a doctor. Judging by some<br />
of the seventeenth and eighteenth century works that I have read<br />
in my time, you needed to have some of the faculties of a butcher<br />
and your patients needed to have endurance far beyond that of Job.<br />
But in the last hundred years, what miracles we have seen, haven't<br />
we? The great miracles in surgery, the great revolution in<br />
medicine which converted it from a ways and means of sedation for<br />
the patient while nature did the work to this positive antibiotic<br />
approach to the cure of disease these have been marvellous<br />
changes, and not one of themn has been made by Act of Parliament.<br />
( Laughter) We want to remember this. We are a little bit given in<br />
Australia to thinking that if only politicians were all sensible<br />
meaning by that if they all agreed with all of us everything<br />
would be solved, which is of course untrue. None of these changes<br />
that I have referred to were made by Acts of Parliament. How<br />
could they be? They were brought about by devoted men and women<br />
of immense skill going in for research, tackling problems, incurring<br />
risks, making revolutionary changes.<br />
Who would dare to compare the hospital of today with<br />
what hospitals must have been before my time a hundred years ago,<br />
U I said " before my time" because I sometimes feel I am getting<br />
near that point ( Laughter) though, of course, I am encouraged by<br />
the example of Mr. Chancellor, whom I always refer to both<br />
publicly and privately as Peter Pan. ( Laughter) ( Applause) This<br />
is all a magnificent pieco of hum-on endeavour. The complexity<br />
of today far exceeds the complexity of the past.<br />
People don't always perhaps realise it but the work<br />
of a Prime Minister, particulairly in a Federal community, today is<br />
three times as complex as it was when I first became Prime Minister,<br />
and ten times as great as it was for a Prime Minister in the middle<br />
of the nineteenth century in Great Britain. The world, as it<br />
grows smaller, becomes more complex, the whole body of knowledge<br />
in science, in any profession, and above all, in medicine and in<br />
surgery, keeps crowding in. There are more things to be learned,<br />
and the more things there are to be learned, the greater must be<br />
0 the facilities for teaching them and for studying them and the<br />
result is that today's hospital, particularly a teaching hospital,<br />
has a complexity of responsibility, very good for the human race,<br />
of immense benefit to mankind but it can't be done cheaply.<br />
It can't be done without consiantly keeping up to date, it can't<br />
be done without being able to call on the skill of the right<br />
kind of people. Now, Sir Douglas Miller who has spoken to you today is<br />
at shining example of what can be done by a man of great skill<br />
and of great devotion. ( Applouse) I have read in the documents<br />
that were given to me in view of today not for the first time<br />
some account of the honorary medical staff, people who with little,<br />
or for the most part, no remuneration, have used their time and<br />
their talent and their enthusiasm in order to train other people,<br />
in order to help ether people. You know, that's a marvellous<br />
thing; I hope that spirit will never die, I hope we won't become<br />
so highly organised someday in Australia that everybody does what<br />
he is paid to do and no more and that we pay for everything and<br />
9 / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
that we expect to get everything. The world is moving not by<br />
people with that attitude of mind but as result of people of<br />
energy and enthusiasm and imagination who never thought for one<br />
moment that it was someone else's responsibi-Lity to do what<br />
they themselves could do. This is, I think, one of the glories<br />
of the medical profession.<br />
There was a time when I was at the Bar, when I used<br />
to cross-examine medical men quite freely. As a rule, they were<br />
very poor witnesses. ( Laughter) Anyhow, there used to be a lot<br />
of cross-examination going on, and once or twice, because I had<br />
performed some exercise of logic, in which I had outwitted the<br />
medical witness, I used to think to myself, " You know, those<br />
doctors, Put a query against I have long<br />
since got over that childish illusion. I have the most<br />
tremendous respect, and so have you for the medical profession<br />
and I will continue to respect it, so long as it produces, and<br />
it has so far, such marvellous examples of fidelity to ideals,<br />
of energy, of cdication to the task in hand. This, I think, is<br />
one of the things that will be learned in the clinical school.<br />
I had a look at the motto of the institution today<br />
on the front of the cover of the programme. If I may, I would<br />
just like to emphasise, Your Eminence, one word in it, though<br />
this may sound painfully like a sermon " caritas" yes,<br />
charity. I prefer, myself, rather to say " the love of Christ<br />
urges us on." Urges there is an urgency about it.,<br />
The word " urge" is of tremendous importance. Wie must all have<br />
a sense or urgency about the things that we hove to do because<br />
we don't know what tomorrow will bring forth. Urgency is it.<br />
Urgency is in the mind and spirit of the groeat medical worker<br />
as he tackles his problems, isn't it? " This is not something I<br />
can put off for a month or a week or a year; this is the job.<br />
Look at this pationt. Look at this problem" and he is urged on,<br />
he is driven on by these feelings that he has in his heart and<br />
in his mind. This is a wonderful spirit. Wonderful spirit.<br />
All I can say is that I hope that out of this clinical school,<br />
there will come not only medical men of wonderful skill and<br />
medical women. I hope that not only will it produce good doctors,<br />
talented doctors but that it will produce generation after<br />
generation of what I choose to call the Millers of this world,<br />
the enthusiasts, the people who will have a sense of urgency and<br />
who will never relapse into doing their bare duty or observing<br />
the barren rules of routine.<br />
And therefore I am delighted to be here, honoured to<br />
be here. I have made a mental note of what His Eminence, the<br />
Cardinal, said. All I can tell him is that I will take an<br />
opportunity of trying to pass the buck to somebody else ( Laughterl<br />
always reserving the simple truth that I am a port of last<br />
resort, for the time it reaches me there is nobody to whom I can<br />
pass it. But you nay be assured at all times of my own understanding<br />
of the problem and my own simple pleasure at having<br />
been able to take a small part in solving, or helping to solve,<br />
some of these problems in the modern educational world.<br />
And so on this happy day when the heavens have been<br />
smiling on us, I would take liberty huxzibly myself to smile on<br />
you and say that I am. d'e lighted to be here, and remembering with<br />
magnificent accuracy what I an here for I now declare the<br />
Clincial School and the Students' Building open, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
