<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6588</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/02/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006588.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
*. 1xSEoflC~ . J~ b2J*. , t~ t . Z50. SS.. Z-S ~ C4t.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 13 February 1985<br />
The Federal Government's substantial package of offers to the<br />
New South Wales medical profession to end the long-running<br />
doctors' dispute will remain open.<br />
If the leaders of the dispute advise their members to return<br />
to work, the Federal and New South Wales Governments will<br />
immediately undertake direct negotiations on the details and<br />
implementation of the offer.<br />
The Government has sought to meet all the reasonable concerns<br />
of the profession with constructive and specific undertakings,<br />
conditional only upon the Australian Medical Association<br />
advising doctors to resume normal duties.<br />
Both Governments have undertaken exhaustive and objective<br />
discussions with the medical profession in order to settle the<br />
dispute. All we have asked in return is that they recommend a return to<br />
work and get back to the sadly neglected business of caring<br />
for their patients.<br />
Those specific undertakings and commitments made by myself and<br />
the New South Wales Premier remain open.<br />
I strongly urge the medical profession to accept the offer,<br />
return to normal duties, and allow the Government peace offer<br />
to be implemented. There cannot be any implementation of the<br />
Government offers and there cannot be any negotiations on the<br />
finer details of proposals until there has been a call for a<br />
return to work.<br />
If the doctors decide to go through with their resignations and<br />
desert their patients, then they must expect the Government to<br />
take decisive action to maintain public hospitals for the people<br />
of New South Wales.<br />
Neither the Federal nor New South Wales Governments can tolerate<br />
for much longer the current situation of the NSW doctors holding<br />
the public to ransom.<br />
I hope that good sense will prevail and the doctors will realise<br />
that only through a negotiated settlement can we serve the best<br />
interests of everyone concerned and most importantly the patients.<br />
If the resigned doctors do walk out of the public hospital system,<br />
then my Government stands ready to support the New South Wales<br />
Government to ensure the maintenance of those hospital services. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
