<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>561</transcript-id>
    <title>P.M.NO. 53/1962  VISIT OF KING AND QUEEN OF THAILAND STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000561.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO PM J0 1J i2<br />
FOR PUBLICATION MORNING PAP-RS MO-DAY 2 RD JJLY<br />
VISIT OF KING AND QUEAN OF THAILAND<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister te Rt_ ont RG. Menzies<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr, R. G. Menzies, toda;<br />
annomced the itinerary for the visit to Australia next<br />
month of Their Majesties The King and Queen of Thailand.<br />
This had been settled following discussions in Bangkok<br />
recently by Mr, J. H. Scholtens of the Prime Minister's<br />
Department, who is -he Director of the visit.<br />
Mro Menzies said that Their Majesties would<br />
arrive in Canberra by air from New Zealand on Sunday,<br />
August 26, and would leave Perth for Bangkok on Wednesday,<br />
September 12. They would visit all State capitals, the<br />
dates being as follows: Canberra August 26-29<br />
Sydney August 29-31; Brisbane August 31-September 2;<br />
Melbourne September 2-5; Hobart September 5-7;<br />
Adelaide ( including visit to Woomora by His Majesty The<br />
King) September 7-10, Perth September 10-12.<br />
Throughout their 18-day visit, Their Majesties<br />
would be Government guests and would stay at Government<br />
Houses. The Official Suite would consist of 13 persons,<br />
Their Majesties would also have a personal staff with them.<br />
The King of Thailand would be the first reigning monarch of<br />
a foreign country to visit Australia. Their Majesties had<br />
been looking forward to this visit for some time and would<br />
like to meet as many Australians as possible at functions<br />
and at worko<br />
Mr. Menzies also announced details of the Canberra programme<br />
for the visit ( see attachment),<br />
CANBERRA, July, 1962. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
