<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7513</transcript-id>
    <title>SPECIAL PREMIERS&#039; CONFERENCE ON HOUSING 3 MARCH 1989 JOINT STATEMENT OF OUTCOME</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007513.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPECIAL PREMIERS' CONFERENCE ON HOUSING 3 MARCH 1989<br />
JOINT STATEMENT OF OUTCOME<br />
At the Special Premiers' Conference today, all Premiers, the<br />
Chief Minister of the Northern Territory and the<br />
Commonwealth agreed to co-operate in addressing the problems<br />
confronting the housing industry, particularly the supply of<br />
suitable land.<br />
At the Conference, the Commonwealth put forward a major<br />
program of land releases for housing development, amounting<br />
to around 27,000 blocks over the next five years. This is<br />
equivalent to around 15 new suburbs. A further 30,900<br />
blocks will be released in the following five to 10 years.<br />
The Premiers and the Chief Minister responded favourably to<br />
this initiative, and raised some additional issues. These<br />
included difficulties faced by States in providing<br />
infrastructure for new developments in fringe areas and for<br />
higher density developments in some urban areas. New South<br />
Wales and Victoria also raised the issue of the hand back of<br />
surplus Defence Housing for use as public housing.<br />
In the context of decisions to release further land for<br />
housing, concern was expressed by Premiers about the need to<br />
provide housing related infrastructure, and the financial<br />
limitations on them to do this. It was agreed that Premiers<br />
would consider and put forward specific proposals and that<br />
the Commonwealth would give serious consideration to them in<br />
the Premiers, Conference and Loan Council meetings later<br />
this year.<br />
Following consideration of these issues, it was agreed that<br />
there would be bilateral discussions with States on<br />
Commonwealth-owned land identified by the Commonwealth as<br />
available and suitable for housing development. The<br />
Commonwealth also undertook to examine whether other<br />
Commonwealth land identified by the States as suitable for<br />
housing development could also be made available. The<br />
Commonwealth agreed to examine joint-venture arrangements,<br />
as put forward by New South Wales, for developing and<br />
marketing Commonwealth land for housing. Under these<br />
arrangements the Commonwealth would receive no proceeds from<br />
the land until final sales were made.<br />
Concerning Defence Housing, the Commonwealth notes that the<br />
renegotiation of the Commonwealth State Housing Agreement<br />
( Service Personnel) is due to be completed very shortly.<br />
The Commonwealth undertook to have bilateral discussions<br />
with those States seeking them in its consideration of new<br />
arrangements in the next few weeks. </p>
<p>Some less populous States suggested consideration be given<br />
to ways of encouraging more migrants to settle in those<br />
States, rather than in the more heavily populated centres.<br />
The Commonwealth noted that immigration policy had been<br />
changed recently and now includes bonus points if sponsors<br />
live in State nominated areas. The effectiveness of this<br />
new selection system will be kept under review.<br />
The Conference noted that Rental Property Trusts of the kind<br />
promoted by New South Wales can make a significant<br />
contribution to the supply of low cost rental housing. The<br />
Commonwealth agreed to discuss with New South Wales the<br />
marketability of its Trusts, with a view to examining<br />
whether they are taking full advantage of current taxation<br />
provisions. The Commonwealth has also developed a package of measures<br />
directed at problems of land supply, building regulation,<br />
land regulation and local government approval processes.<br />
The program will include initiatives to respond to growing<br />
demand for higher density developments. The States and the<br />
Northern Territory have indicated they are happy to assist<br />
in implementing and funding aspects of this package. It was<br />
also agreed that Local Government be invited to contribute<br />
to this program.<br />
The package of measures includes a three year program of<br />
work to redress inadequacies in the availability of data on<br />
land supply and the composition of demand to be undertaken<br />
in conjunction with the Indicative Planning Council for the<br />
Housing Industry. The States and the Northern Territory<br />
have agreed to participate in this program.<br />
The States and the Northern Territory have also agreed to<br />
participate in a joint program under which financial and<br />
technical assistance will be provided over the next three<br />
years to Local Government to review the technical content of<br />
residential land development regulations.<br />
The Commonwealth has also announced a program to promote<br />
demonstration studies, co-operation, research and<br />
information dissemination, designed to stimulate improvement<br />
in the administrative aspects of approval processes at the<br />
Local Government level.<br />
The Conference also endorsed the setting up of an expert<br />
task force drawn from Commonwealth, State and Local<br />
Government, the design professions and building industry, to<br />
examine the scope for significant reforms of technical<br />
regulation of building codes and standards.<br />
Resources will be devoted to create the capacity for the<br />
analysis and development of policy in relation to housing<br />
supply within the Department of Industry, Technology and<br />
Commerce. </p>
<p>This package of measures will cost around $ 9m over three<br />
years. The Commonwealth Minister for Industry, Technology<br />
and Commerce, Senator Button, will issue a press release<br />
providing more detail.<br />
The Conference reviewed and warmly supported the performance<br />
of the Joint Venture for more Affordable Housing, also known<br />
as " Green Street". This program, which is jointly supported<br />
by the Commonwealth State and Local Governments, as well as<br />
the industry, has been particularly effective at<br />
demonstrating a wider range of housing choices and the use<br />
of more innovative building and land development techniques.<br />
The project has achieved savings of up to 24 per cent on<br />
house and land development. The Commonwealth will be<br />
working with the States to expand awareness of the Green<br />
Street concept.<br />
The Conference also agreed that early consideration would be<br />
given to a joint Commonwealth-State demonstration program of<br />
higher quality, medium density housing in the inner cities,<br />
particularly older industrial and commercial areas.<br />
The supply of skilled labour to the housing industry is<br />
another significant constraint. Accordingly, the<br />
Commonwealth concluded arrangements with the New South Wales<br />
division of the Housing Industry Association on 30 January<br />
1989 which provided for immigration of a maximum of 225<br />
workers in the building trades in the period to 30 June<br />
1990, in return for an increased apprenticeship training<br />
commitment. Further consultation with the Government,<br />
industry groups, the ACTU and building unions, with a view<br />
to developing a national arrangement for the building and<br />
construction industry began in February 1989.<br />
Concerns were raised about the effectiveness of the First<br />
Home Owners Scheme. It was agreed that the Commonwealth<br />
would give serious consideration to proposals from these<br />
States on the future direction of this Scheme.<br />
At the Conference today, the States and the Northern<br />
Territory undertook to review legislation and regulations<br />
under their control, with a view to improving their systems<br />
of land supply and use.<br />
In this regard, the Conference welcomed the initiatives<br />
recently taken by the Government of New South Wales to<br />
increase substantially the turn-off of serviced land and<br />
introduce appeal rights against Local Government decisions<br />
on zonings for medium density housing.<br />
The Conference recognised that there is no " quick fix" to<br />
the problems confronting the housing industry at present.<br />
However, the constructive and co-operative approach of all<br />
participants at today's Conference, which all have agreed to<br />
continue into the future, has laid the groundwork for<br />
substantial relief to the supply-side constraints affecting<br />
the industry. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
