<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11003</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 RADIO INTERVIEW WITH HOWARD SATTLER (6PR)</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Good morning Prime Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning, how are you?</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Thanks for joining us. All right, the unemployment figures are just</p>
<p> out and despite the predictions unemployment is down by .1 of one</p>
<p> per cent which when you talk about it that way doesn't sound</p>
<p> much but what does it all mean?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, they are great figures. I am getting a bit of an echo, incidentally,</p>
<p> so your technician should try and fix it up. The unemployment rate</p>
<p> is down to 7.4 per cent. There's been a rise of 33,000 in the</p>
<p> jobs created in February. Youth unemployment is down to 23.5 per cent</p>
<p> and that is the lowest since September of 1991. We have seen about</p>
<p> 80,000 jobs created over the summer period and a total of 406,000</p>
<p> jobs created in the three years that the Coalition has been in Government.</p>
<p>Now, these are tremendous figures but we still have a long way to</p>
<p> go. And I appeal to those in the Senate who blocked our Youth Wage</p>
<p> Bill to think of the damage they are doing to the job prospects of</p>
<p> the young people who are still out of work. We could have this unemployment</p>
<p> rate going down even further in the years ahead if we do more to encourage</p>
<p> employers to take on young people. And on two occasions in the last</p>
<p> few weeks in relation to Youth Wage Bill and the unfair dismissal</p>
<p> regulation, the Senate has struck down measures that this Government</p>
<p> designed to give young people a better chance. And I just say to those</p>
<p> people in the Senate again, whether they are Labor, Democrat or Independent,</p>
<p> think of what you are doing, think of the opportunity the buoyant</p>
<p> economy presents to really break the back of unemployment in this</p>
<p> country.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>[sound problems]</p>
<p>I was just saying, are you planning to re-present that Bill now? I</p>
<p> mean, you are saying that you're appealing to them but they have</p>
<p> already knocked it back haven't they?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, of course we are going to re-present that Bill. We will re-present</p>
<p> it again in three months time  I am still getting that echo</p>
<p> incidentally  we'll re-present that in three months time.</p>
<p> But I am using the opportunity of these really very good figures against</p>
<p> the background of a very strong economy to just appeal directly to</p>
<p> the Labor Party and the Democrats and the Independents in the Senate</p>
<p> to think of what their political gains are doing to the job prospects</p>
<p> of young Australians. I mean, unemployment is still too high. Although</p>
<p> it's a lot better than what it was it could be a lot better still</p>
<p> if we as a community were prepared to take the measures to improve</p>
<p> prospects for people. And there are a lot of things we have got to</p>
<p> do. Two of those things are to remove the threat of unfair dismissal</p>
<p> legislation from small business, and we have tried to do that and</p>
<p> we have been frustrated at every turn. And the other, of course, is</p>
<p> the youth wage measure. Now, on two occasions now the Labor Party</p>
<p> and the Democrats have voted against those measures. And I am just</p>
<p> saying to the leaders of those two parties, think of what you are</p>
<p> doing to the employment prospects of young Australians.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>[commercial break  sound problems]</p>
<p>I understand the Defence Minister, John Moore, is going to make a</p>
<p> statement to the House this afternoon. Does that have anything to</p>
<p> do with Australians going to East Timor?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, it doesn't. He will be reporting on progress being made with</p>
<p> the defence reform programme that we announced when we came to Government</p>
<p> in our first term. That's what it's about.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>All right. What are the prospects of Australians going to East Timor</p>
<p> in the near future?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we hope that the need for a peacekeeping force will not arise.</p>
<p> We hope that arrangements are worked out between the East Timorese</p>
<p> and the Indonesians for either autonomy followed by independence,</p>
<p> or independence after a reasonable transition period that won't</p>
<p> involve any peacekeeping force. So any talk about committing Australians</p>
<p> in a peacekeeping role at this stage is quite premature.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Okay. But if East Timorese continue to be threatened or people are</p>
<p> continuing to die up there at the hands of para-military groups we</p>
<p> can't just sit back surely?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Howard, I am very careful what I say on this issue because it's</p>
<p> a very important and sensitive one. We want peace. We want the East</p>
<p> Timorese people to be allowed to determine their own future. We believe</p>
<p> that if that future could involve with their consent a period of autonomy</p>
<p> inside Indonesia that would be better for all concerned. In the end</p>
<p> they should be able to determine matters for themselves. And the stance</p>
<p> I took and the Government took before Christmas was very material</p>
<p> in bringing about a change of heart on the part of the Indonesian</p>
<p> Government.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Now, you have mentioned what's happened in the Senate with the</p>
<p> youth wages legislation. What have you done to upset Senator Brian</p>
<p> Harradine who seems to have extraordinary power in this country and</p>
<p> is that going to threaten your tax reform package as it torpedoed</p>
<p> the youth wages policy?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Howard, Senator Harradine always makes a judgement on the merits</p>
<p> of each individual piece of legislation as he sees it. I never take</p>
<p> Senator Harradine for granted.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Well, you can't can you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. Well, I don't but I have never tried to and he is not a person</p>
<p> who believes in cross-trading on issues. He has very strong, what</p>
<p> I would call, traditional Labor views on industrial relations matters.</p>
<p> Remember Brian Harradine was originally a member of the Australian</p>
<p> Labor Party. He was a trade union official. He has very traditional</p>
<p> views on industrial relations matters. He believes very strongly in</p>
<p> a more centralised involved system on the part of the Industrial Relations</p>
<p> Commission. I understand that, I don't agree with him. I disagree</p>
<p> with him quite fundamentally on those matters but I respect the strength</p>
<p> with which he holds those views and they are as I say, essentially</p>
<p> traditional Labor views.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Okay. But is he now irrelevant to this argument given the switch in</p>
<p> policy, or tactics by the Labor Party saying now they probably won't</p>
<p> block your tax reform package and they think that that will now be</p>
<p> a political plus for them at the next election because they think</p>
<p> the GST will be horrendous?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I haven't heard or read that the Labor Party is going to</p>
<p> vote in favour of the GST package. What I read in the Australian this</p>
<p> morning is that the Labor Party won't try and stop a vote being</p>
<p> taken before the 30th of June. Brian Harradine and Mal</p>
<p> Colston are still quite critical to the outcome of the tax plan because</p>
<p> they hold the balance of power until the 30th of June.</p>
<p> After the 30th of June that changes. Senator Colston will</p>
<p> no longer be in the Senate and the Democrats will have more Senators</p>
<p> and the Democrats will hold the balance of power. So nothing has changed</p>
<p> as I understand it in relation to the Labor Party's attitude</p>
<p> on the substance of our tax plan. All I read is that they will not</p>
<p> try and stop a vote being taken by the 30th of June. And</p>
<p> neither they should. I mean after all we did win an election on this</p>
<p> issue. We did lay ourselves bare policy wise. We provided the Australian</p>
<p> people with a full explanation of what we wanted to do and we won</p>
<p> the election. No Government in history has gone to the Australian</p>
<p> people with a more detailed reform plan on such a central issue of</p>
<p> policy as we did last year.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Yeah, except the Senators who were voted in are not the ones who are</p>
<p> there now. They're the ones who will take their place after June</p>
<p> 30.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But Howard, look, this is an endless argument I know. But aren't</p>
<p> elections about parties offering plans for the future and the Australian</p>
<p> people deciding who should be allowed to implement their plans?</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Sure. But also don't you think we should have a system where</p>
<p> whoever is elected, say from October the 3rd, the next</p>
<p> time whatever House sits they're the representatives of the people.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that would involve a Constitutional change.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>I know that.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, well look, we didn't have a referendum on it. I mean I</p>
<p> can only deal with the system that I inherited. And I mean in a sense</p>
<p> it's a futile debate at this stage as to whether our system might</p>
<p> be different or better or changed. I've got to deal with the</p>
<p> system that the Australian people [inaudible] have decided I've</p>
<p> got to deal with. And under that system I put a plan to the Australian</p>
<p> people and the Australian people returned me as Prime Minister. And</p>
<p> what I'm saying is that I think my Government should be allowed</p>
<p> to implement that plan.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Okay. But have you got a better chance now of getting your tax reform</p>
<p> bills through the Upper House before June the 30th or will</p>
<p> you have just as much a chance after June the 30th?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well our prospects after the June the 30th as I read it</p>
<p> at the moment are far less because the Democrats will hold the balance</p>
<p> of power and the Democrats have declared that they won't accept</p>
<p> the plan in its present form, despite the judgement of the Australian</p>
<p> people. So as things stand at the moment it is clearly in the interests</p>
<p> of the plan getting through that we have a vote before the 30th</p>
<p> of June.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>So what are you going to do to get Senator Harradine on side? Are</p>
<p> you going to ban Lolita? Is that what you're going to do?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'll come to that in a minute. The last thing I'm going</p>
<p> to do is to engage in some kind of public discussion about any discussions</p>
<p> I might have with him. I respect him. I've got a lot of regards</p>
<p> for his views. I don't agree with a lot of them and he doesn't</p>
<p> agree with a lot of mine. But that doesn't stop us respecting</p>
<p> each other as public figures. If I have anything to say to Brian Harradine</p>
<p> about taxation or any other matter I'll say it to him first in</p>
<p> private.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>But you will be speaking with him about it personally?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I always talk to him about a whole range of matters. We are in fairly</p>
<p> regular contact.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>All right. Can I talk to you about drugs?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Isn't the Government, or hasn't the Government been a bit</p>
<p> hypocritical on this? You're now committing a lot of effort to</p>
<p> it, and money. Yours is the same Government that reduced the funding</p>
<p> for our federal police who are really on the front line. They're</p>
<p> at the border of trying to stop drugs getting into this country.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Howard, the resources that are now available are the greatest the</p>
<p> federal police have ever had to fight drugs.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Really?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes. We have strike teams available. Two strike teams now in Western</p>
<p> Australia. We have additional resources and the commissioner of the</p>
<p> federal police told me himself about two weeks ago that some of the</p>
<p> drug hauls that have been in the news recently are a direct result</p>
<p> of the additional resources that have been provided.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>And will there be more?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I will be saying something further about drugs in the lead up to,</p>
<p> and at the Premiers' Conference on the 9th of April.</p>
<p> We'll be putting some more proposals to the Premiers. I want</p>
<p> to work with Richard Court. I want to work with all of the Premiers</p>
<p> and Chief Ministers in order to make further inroads on the drug problem</p>
<p> in this country. I don't pretend for a moment that I have all</p>
<p> of the solutions and I don't pretend that it is easy. And I'm</p>
<p> going to keep trying and I want to work. And you've got to tackle</p>
<p> it through law enforcement. That's customs and police. You've</p>
<p> got to have educational programmes to discourage young people from</p>
<p> starting drugs in the first place. And you've got to have treatment</p>
<p> available for people who want to break the drug habit. I don't</p>
<p> think in the past we've had enough emphasis on treatment and</p>
<p> I'm very keen that there be a greater emphasis at both a State</p>
<p> level where normally these facilities would have been provided, or</p>
<p> should be provided, and with some additional involvement by the Federal</p>
<p> Government. And the tough on drugs' strategy which is providing</p>
<p> about $290 million over four years includes support for those three</p>
<p> elements. It's wrong to see it just in terms of resources you</p>
<p> put into police, although that is a very important element.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>All right. Isn't this also an international issue. You've</p>
<p> got a United Nations that sends peace keeping forces, including Australians,</p>
<p> all over the world to try and stop dictators and people like that.</p>
<p> Isn't this an international issue which almost sort of requires</p>
<p> a war on drugs? I mean shouldn't they be sending in sort of UN</p>
<p> forces into places where they're growing all this stuff?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it is an international problem and there have been some very</p>
<p> good developments in that area. Only last week when Madeline Albright</p>
<p> was in Thailand she visited an area where there had been a planting</p>
<p> programme to replace, I think, poppies with another substance which</p>
<p> would deliver the same earnings to the local community. And this transfer</p>
<p> of investment was very widely welcomed in the community and we would</p>
<p> obviously like to see that kind of approach applied in what used to</p>
<p> be called Burma - now called Myanmar - which is one of the major sources</p>
<p> of drugs in the area.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>I mean do we give aid to that place?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Myanmar? We certainly wouldn't be giving any aid at all that</p>
<p> gets to drugs. I don't think we give anything other than bare</p>
<p> humanitarian aid to Burma, if anything.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>The point I'm making is....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I understand your point but I think I can assure your listeners</p>
<p> that none of our dollars would give any kind of succour or substance</p>
<p> to people involved in the drug traffic. I can absolutely assure you</p>
<p> of that.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Yeah, all right. Now just to wind up to....so let's talk about</p>
<p> Lolita, the movie. That was brought up at your meeting, your Coalition</p>
<p> meeting the other day. Are you just going to handball it back to the</p>
<p> public and say: well if you've got a problem with it complain</p>
<p> to the censor, appeal about it or what?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well what's going to happen is that some of my colleagues are</p>
<p> going to lodge an appeal. There's a procedure under the censorship</p>
<p> rules which provide that if people are unhappy with the initial decision</p>
<p> of the censor then they can ask that that decision be reviewed by</p>
<p> a review tribunal. Now that is the correct thing to do. I haven't</p>
<p> seen it. I therefore can't make a personal judgement.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>You're going to be seeing it aren't you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I've read in the papers there's going to be some viewing</p>
<p> of it. Well, I mean, I've got, you know, many things to do.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>I don't think Lolita's at the top of the tray.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, no. But I have to say to you that there are a lot of my colleagues</p>
<p> who raised this issue and I said that given the concern right across</p>
<p> the spectrum, and presumably reflecting public concern, that I said</p>
<p> I would have a look at it in the sense of seeing what would be the</p>
<p> appropriate response for people who are concerned. Now the appropriate</p>
<p> response is what I've described. And I think that is correct.</p>
<p> It's a procedure laid down. And everybody's entitled to</p>
<p> have a view on matters relating to public taste and public standards.</p>
<p> This idea that it's just a monopoly of, quote, "experts"</p>
<p> is never right.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Okay. Just to reiterate on East Timor. We don't have any peacekeeping</p>
<p> forces on standby here at the moment? Is that right? Yes or no.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you wouldn't expect any self-respecting government to be</p>
<p> other than ready for any contingency that might arise in the future.</p>
<p> But if you're asking me, and please, it's a very important</p>
<p> issue, if you're asking me are we contemplating sending any troops</p>
<p> to East Timor at the present time the answer to that is no. If you're</p>
<p> asking me if any contingency in our region arose in the future would</p>
<p> we be able to respond to it, or are we making preparations to be able</p>
<p> to respond to it, well obviously the answer to that is yes. And that</p>
<p> is what any responsible government would do. But this afternoon's</p>
<p> statement is very much about reporting on the progress of the Defence</p>
<p> Review Programme and how that has enabled us to do things that we</p>
<p> wouldn't otherwise have been able to do. You've got to remember</p>
<p> that defence has been the only area of Government expenditure completely</p>
<p> quarantined from budget cuts over the last three years.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Yeah, and so it should be too.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Indeed, so it should be.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Thank you for joining us on the programme. We'll talk regularly</p>
<p> during 1999. I'm sorry about the glitch at the start.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, and glitchless in future. Okay.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>It will be indeed. See you later.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Bye.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
