<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18305</transcript-id>
    <title>2011 Prime Minister&#039;s Australian Exporter of the Year announced</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard has named engineering firm Sedgman Limited as the 2011 Australian Exporter of the Year, praising its commitment to innovation and sustainability.</p>
<p>Sedgman designs, builds and operates coal and metal processing facilities in Asia, the Americas and Africa, as well as Australia.</p>
<p>It specialises in cleaning coal and has helped implement ecologically sustainable initiatives in many developing countries.</p>
<p>Last year, the Queensland company doubled its export earnings, undertaking projects in more than 20 countries including Mongolia, Mozambique, Botswana and Laos.</p>
<p>Sedgman's designs integrate various Australian-developed technologies, helping keep Australian expertise at the forefront of coal processing globally. </p>
<p>The Prime Minister congratulated Sedgman on its achievements, which exemplify the skill and professionalism of Australian exporters and their importance to the national economy.</p>
<p>The Australian Export Awards is one of the country's longest-running and most prestigious business award programs.</p>
<p>It honours the achievements of Australian exporters and celebrates their contribution to national prosperity. </p>
<p>The Prime Minister's Australian Exporter of the Year is selected from the winners of 12 national categories. Sedgman was also the winner of the Minerals and Energy Award. </p>
<p>The 49th Australian Export Awards ceremony was hosted in Brisbane tonight by Trade Minister Craig Emerson, and co-presented by the Australian Trade Commission and Australian Chamber of Commerce and Industry. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
