<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23447</transcript-id>
    <title>Call for volunteers for G20 Leaders Summit</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/04/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Commonwealth and Queensland Governments are calling for volunteers to help showcase Australia to the world during the G20 Leaders Summit in Brisbane in November.</p>
<p>World class events such as the Sydney Olympics, Brisbane and Melbourne Commonwealth Games and the World Expo in 1988 have demonstrated the importance of volunteers to the success of large scale events of international importance.</p>
<p>The Queensland and Federal Governments will team up with Volunteering Queensland to recruit up to 700 volunteers to help deliver a memorable and successful G20 Leaders Summit in Brisbane.</p>
<p>This is the most significant meeting of world leaders Australia has ever hosted.</p>
<p>We want the world to see us at our best, our most professional and our most welcoming and we want delegates to take that experience of Australia and Queensland back home with them as evidence of Australia being very much open for business.</p>
<p>We’re looking for enthusiastic and committed men and women to be the friendly faces of the G20 Summit.</p>
<p>Volunteer roles will include transport information and facilitation, assistance at hotel information desks, media assistance and workforce and accreditation assistance.</p>
<p>Full training will be provided to all volunteers.</p>
<p>Volunteering is a chance for Australians – and particularly Queenslanders – to become involved in the G20.</p>
<p>For the city of Brisbane, it’s an opportunity to hone its reputation for delivering some of the biggest and most important events on the international stage.</p>
<p>To apply to become a volunteer, go to the G20 website at <a href="http://www.g20.org">www.g20.org</a></p>
<p>27 April 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
