<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>557</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF TELEVISION INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES ON WIN CHANNEL 4, WOLLONGONG, ON 12TH JULY 1962 - INTERVIEWER MR MAX AMBROSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000557_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I, w~ wrII WI D1 A~ VMftrf ILT. E.. I<br />
WA III 7W 1 WW<br />
P t Ib0 I7ma"<br />
QUESTION MR. MUZINS Q0 A* t Mr. Prim Minister, I merstand this afteroom<br />
y haVe bad the rAwpioS m of<br />
t: great indus t gilrowth I&amp; the d of<br />
3IpsoniVg* Vould you be so kind Sir as to<br />
give as your impressions of bowtls ass in<br />
with your Oovumnt's peloy of growtk and<br />
prespority?<br />
S Veil IW've seem a little set as os as I<br />
al&amp; have like to have sem. I are of<br />
sourse, been here betf ht the<br />
mm her*-: I think is PheasaRm l, imt eary I&amp;<br />
irm sax steel and OWLq and of ' se with the<br />
œ eWlejvopmnt of the eawi pet, the expot<br />
ofi but aLA@ of m s 7@ U? Qiit tIuInYrmV<br />
In" utres dam on this sernst. Ifi ps i ncf.<br />
And what I libe about It is that at a tiwbefn<br />
peat stability ha been avUvved at so cheap<br />
In the eonsoe prios Iaiz for eighteeemn th,<br />
a sonsLdersbl degree of mmetary stabiity In<br />
Australla the produetion and export of seal<br />
and of irsa and steel don here have rises<br />
alInt fabdIOUle&amp; a. This 4amestrates somethiag<br />
that I as aftrquetly eig that stability is<br />
the 6endition of v t and not the onew of<br />
povth. In other wts a that stablity is<br />
not eta patisa but S is the sendition an whisb<br />
trimr pevth depadq, and bre you have i ome<br />
distriot, with Its matiplislty of sotivitios,<br />
the most perfect example of this that I could<br />
think of*<br />
Nw, Siz, am faist of our area Is the 4*' ing<br />
in&amp; 1$ tz7 frthu d" SkOo MU fvQM~ lC<br />
Thi brinstyio the * ea Gf emo riar t<br />
&amp; vjvwvwwD s ut7 IntQ th eiPi~ r Commm maximt e<br />
WOU yoa asr to sy ~ Fieors t thi sabjeet,<br />
Wellgs, fQubit. r iefly,, becaue I is't need<br />
to ymrit vould take aa h to explain the<br />
variosaspests, of the Cemma xrket. jat I<br />
do't tb Pee3e UNd to be or-eroxitd about<br />
this matt'. w T'dairyiag imdustry is a m7r<br />
iportant am In aradli me Gmrmrnat<br />
Would I of allIg it to be hatally afr~ d<br />
kwvi amwi we Iare of oe battlin her<br />
tkz kth vited RiaM vernment<br />
ofe tir entvr Into the Csin NZRt<br />
vhio will give sa stabili and piespeat to<br />
the 46137U industRY. I an t desp" al of that*<br />
I think te rm ot of tUs Vaited LIXaUMA is<br />
workiag W4rd on it wo itimly re veeking<br />
hax4 it has a ed adea or am tmn..<br />
We ar determinde m Pt best ao that am<br />
be put ad nobdy kkb entbslw. t the SIx<br />
eanMeamtries will aesept 6d0itiens that<br />
M bio Great Writala to p in without<br />
dargig the dairYing instrY In lAmstrala or<br />
* e00000.1/ 2<br />
v 71 li iip-r~~ Um~ g fn </p>
<p>the . n laIndustry in Smt Zealand vhiebt of<br />
SOON, it~~ z1 1a" stat to thet . uWAtry.<br />
But I an nt UM~ the ssimIsts a this mttes.<br />
d4oa uit believe treat Britain voulA V ina on<br />
toru mtj a* vut'bo. ns MA I a pesftstl<br />
cor~ a,= ta mT-Autiinl1* 3 Gsvpeaiot v@ 4A beZ-Ym"<br />
M# 7y to 4. fthd Its am-m lftus tries mine<br />
swtaiul will be am " T I as tar as ~ she<br />
eZ marhets, in ownse llasow" market $ be<br />
Wrest rit" ai am ame9.<br />
Qq sm.# Sir, y"' ve just meatime * thw marbats.<br />
The 4001 a~ tw isam whisk atroots us v~<br />
Ueatlin this W mcgmatlSUrM Sr<br />
tima this arml SWr<br />
A* I do amess m seset Zm k,~ l I<br />
sa 14k ba* to atun Js beiu bakat<br />
Offt ve in emA fW a yewar two tboeaft#<br />
vhs. t Seal fents he" was so low that vswe e<br />
lapettimg = 7a. it## " I&amp; r I* bellow= vwset<br />
impstig sal tfan South Aftles end Inia am<br />
v~ m lakrates a It basins. there Vag<br />
inth sewa tret and*<br />
toftr, ve are expig Jarl; emyPr4. i<br />
all we vast ft ou anyapoos, beteetlg<br />
Do has, tkhoe is this sm at sl. 2a<br />
apatas " tts being W1t teaistamom<br />
Gladstone I&amp; QN6essam4, we amc really &amp; Fewl~ p<br />
wsmzkable el for expert of 040l toth w<br />
last* And this of ovam zet el use" a gnat<br />
deal fb the s0u Ifa n In~ st bat It memos a<br />
seasidtaMe thiag fmt ow belamm atf<br />
It wAIles o-Ii# pass a ll fer1ma<br />
a great fwture fw St.<br />
Q. en aml S3iWr , ei the ai2.4isp~ taaPt Prim<br />
Daito In 1= Septomber,<br />
ou Siaw us a * liot out] UuI of whet yw<br />
0omai will be In the next spLe of vedcs?<br />
A. V. 11, I merwer appear to be vItaut ame essapatiem.<br />
You know whom I got bask ftsm a WeottT OtS<br />
Seri" s .1 4s alsownea whe a forU'taik<br />
ap I ftm mlsolf pivaged Into camt meetlags<br />
and ito the Lems Caeni amd the prmies'<br />
Cariee ana ims them, I hewo beeo tyngt<br />
onak vp a fem arrowrs of work ad meIt msa<br />
mering th ( biuet mets to Lisaste s,<br />
the pet PRO&amp; lM ef the ma~ t fler 12/ 3a<br />
I oqotto be heavily laws" Ina that forat<br />
least three das tbonafter, As a matter of that*<br />
botbwe thoubb es som e of the papers A" eben<br />
seaut to ms Wbe I m using temiohta<br />
I will be &amp; I ag a P" e doal of Weft on the ft<br />
you sma say bre" do% Ohat et taskt ins July<br />
is to w~ e" a smapt and, ofr., . VWybe<br />
who im ss t hae to peaethe Umutato<br />
do It am eml the peo who kev~ do it a" e<br />
tfIamlw with the faeftS This is mi&amp; to be a<br />
puetJ dfftl t am* AWisyhow, w it. Them<br />
c liim mieets, as fto~* a Augat 7t fr<br />
the ftipt Seetie m A then, at the and of Aufast </p>
<p>baVi ma lit with the Oppositica, the Nov" s will<br />
&amp; QeMI ? w a menth and awe o~ f us~ will lp offtthe<br />
Ptie Mniser 00f~ eceIn Septesber on the C sM<br />
Kaikets, We vo't so Just as if ve m wzwoit or the<br />
egsuhell you kw becuse durin Augst wewl " ev<br />
a ret alof Ud.;.. ts.. fro ee Witain MWi<br />
ftie. ftepe about the leak of Its whiat soniditions night<br />
be agreed Upn what tentative ilpwsat mbet<br />
made what Is going to happen todre frI Caned<br />
X1 and batter and meat and womat and sugor and so<br />
final fW* bet Inn : 06slsfru W illb<br />
able to disouss It Ad deide what attitude ve a" e<br />
ping to adopt on these mtters when the PntUw Ministers<br />
inevt. NMI tha mest anSeptsbe 1t in LGG01<br />
I an perhops releasy' asaing, tkat I Will be there.,<br />
I don't kw beSaUSO It there's time in vbich a<br />
T" ent with a majrty of me ean be kidiad out,<br />
It Is Ixt the Bapt SeoIs and therefae I may be<br />
aae " 4 "-pttmist. I sm talking about what I am.<br />
vftg doam what I en ping to says Ato anybowt<br />
ot~ thin being equal, witha&amp; l ittle bit of ludkas<br />
~ they said in the somie ope I'll be tbeanor<br />
that tieW , my Miisters, ; atlisaawly Hz&amp;. ) IjicTh<br />
finister ) wT~ usbde axA 316. hlt, the Treasurer will<br />
hew* been able to diamass what Wesaen and whed our<br />
Attitue ought to be* go the" will be no lack or<br />
aillVel find ow~ time for " creation between these<br />
De you knw that you are about to betvay xy Wiltky<br />
semet? IFor a long time th JZsag pe autbarities<br />
I* Sydney'ksV been trying, to et maose<br />
Leagn matebe I'm a UmIbman follow -you kne<br />
Ausral ln SLthis Vas what I played who&amp; I e<br />
and And nv, theyve, gt ms Ila<br />
* oein to be preent on Satoday aftemmoos at the<br />
inMte reTsetsdt Mbeaetmohu seaqn dsa ltohfo usto urIs e., ptIh'elrl tbhe attr sAnduusltralia<br />
lost the first t" o Test Mai lov'e been mob pleased<br />
to dissav wm b e" e that you've beaten the finglisb<br />
teen. Everybd has bees talking about it. I read<br />
about It in tepapers. I thisk it Is magpiftenat,<br />
And If this bus a stimulating effet a golvanisiag<br />
efteet, em the AuxtrmlIan teem on ada7i. 7I'l ame<br />
a J* 1, y good matebe eve tbousk I an bomA to admit to<br />
you the a" e noWs aspoelts of It that I won't = WkrstaM.<br />
Q. Sows timelly Sir sould we have a ftw words tes you an<br />
the frnthamlng joyal Towr next year?<br />
A* Vell, ve are all looking fomrwid to it. I discussed<br />
this first with the vases a year ago -awe than a<br />
year a .1 I am assure you shels von#, ve7 b<br />
on out aid sIs ftinse Philip One point to<br />
be remebered,, Is that we ean't cmaslh tim the<br />
QNeen a1teo hae a sort or pqphiml towr -yo<br />
knew what I seen -evriag a arg arem of amuntvy<br />
in ssh States, with em town saying., OWelly she didn't<br />
sume har~ e lA&amp; time, she ought to e6here this time.,<br />
The whole advantage that I en trying to got, ad that<br />
the Qmeen would lile, would be for bar to v1i sState<br />
004,0404100 </p>
<p>kV State, to attend oe partim~ laa matter Mtato<br />
of ñ mpwlanoo; maybe in M States so e nt<br />
ei~ tht vould lend itself to Royal at moae<br />
and In anothor sawe other * vet. It Is not to t<br />
thought that tAL Queen is just 4ping en the big<br />
trek &amp; road oaok -tate, bsuse this 1.5137 doe"<br />
be~ em vey tiring ad as I wat to have quite a<br />
few Royal. Visits$ I would like them to be related<br />
to partiougar evonts so that ve, may have no" e<br />
shoter vIsits6 Do you amthe point I sat 9?<br />
go Yeas, Biro<br />
A. And fee long visits, and therohwe am People, will<br />
need to be very umdestaning about that., ht I<br />
ea assuret you that the Quesa is tmozdously keen.<br />
on this visit*<br />
Q* So, Sir, we amy assme that in the fortheoming Royal<br />
Tour the aoect will be, to a not marked dopes an<br />
infomality?<br />
A* Oh. yes. Partle3awa a ets out out a good doel of<br />
the fbrmality, cat out a good deal of what I * all<br />
the bnoirtic hbsiness of wreeiving addresses and<br />
answering thanto We are, locki for a visIt. that<br />
will. leave the quen, with apweeble umeories of<br />
sa* vivid event am Plaose or thins that she saw.<br />
This Is the advanta go. I woud likce to think that<br />
I&amp; two or throe, yea" s" time, she would look back an<br />
the visit and say* Oh, yes I remember what I sam<br />
In sook and seek a StULt. It was splenid. I<br />
rmember vhat happoned. Isted of tryins to remomber<br />
a Series of 26GatM vIsit4. I Me fte You Will<br />
understand that and I = e tkat the people of<br />
Anstnaha will undestand. if we are ping to<br />
beoms elosorr t or nen14 derstand her betteut<br />
as I think do Awsal, thnwe must understand<br />
that sh. is a wars a being of groat intellffaee<br />
fins memown who likes to se things that she,<br />
remmbe : 2take away the away of the peepA1 of<br />
hew own allegiamme vw she has soew In Australia<br />
and vhs have regeived twa' with approval and varmth.<br />
Q&amp; airv ve thank yea vwry muck for Youm omento this<br />
evening azA In Wating aqwe tiust that you enJcW<br />
yourself very mobk over theeoked In Sydney.<br />
A* Thank you*<br />
Goodnight Sir. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
