<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA SPEECH BY RT. HON. R.G. MEZIES, K.C. M.P ON EDUCATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/07/1945</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000019_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
SPEECH BY<br />
RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES, M. P.,<br />
ON<br />
EDUCATION.<br />
[ From the " Parliamentary Debates," 26th July, 1945.]<br />
Mr. MENZIES ( Kooyong-Leader of<br />
the Opposition) | 11.55].-I mInove-<br />
That iii the opinialn ( if this House-<br />
A revised amd extentled educational<br />
-ystcin is of priine iimportalnce ill<br />
pot-xxwtar aeclltrctioi<br />
In palt icohr, a ttcatii i Ieeds to be<br />
dlitected to illncreased facilitie for<br />
-ccuatlari. r urla, techinical aaad<br />
univercizty training, special adult<br />
ed ucatiot. and the problem oul the<br />
quialiicatiuit, ttu and remInlJeration<br />
of teachers;<br />
IFiective reforata mailay ivolxe -ualj-<br />
-tanitial Comoaxx ealth financial<br />
aid and if tlhi sliould pro'e aiecs-<br />
-cry3 bsuCIh aid should be granited:<br />
lit older ti, prvide it baii for satell<br />
retforut the Colllltotealth sli otild<br />
. et up in co-operation with the<br />
States a qualified conmtission, illlaldin<br />
noC expert or epI) Crt fn0111<br />
ox ersa sj to report ii put tle exiting<br />
edNcational facilitie, ill Aii<br />
tralia. to aaakle recoiini eaIdatioi t<br />
for tlheir extensiotI iaud/ or itlltllel-<br />
ICllnt, and to recoamend Ioxx. t'<br />
xwhat extent, oil what terlls, aid<br />
filr xwat 1ptrpowes, Coianall aealth<br />
aitl should he aiven.<br />
' That this House assu res the Governintent<br />
of it' saapport ill tile aitryilar ouit of the<br />
.1 o\ x reotailcudations.<br />
lit sub . itting this notioa which, Un-<br />
Kquestionably, dleakl with a tatter of farreaching<br />
importance. I make it quite<br />
cloar at tihe outset that I int not raising<br />
it in ' i coontroverzial spirit. Tlhis<br />
problet is one on which I believe there<br />
will be a wide conunity of feeling on<br />
lbotih side of the chamnber. In particulur.<br />
T saY to the Minister for Post-wir<br />
5517. Reconstructioti ( 1Mr. Dedman) that L<br />
raise this matter inll no spirit of criticisrt<br />
of hiniself, because ii believe that he<br />
has done notable work in the provision<br />
of educational facilities during his teria<br />
of office; and I congratulate hint uponii<br />
tit fact. I congratulate him, in particular,<br />
upon recent announcements that<br />
have been made. I had prepared nay<br />
* spech on this mruatter before thos2<br />
announcements were made, and, indeed,<br />
my motion has already been postponed<br />
twice. Therefore, I propose to say what<br />
I had intended to say, unmodified by<br />
recent announlcements which, however, to<br />
some degree, bear upon the matter that<br />
I am debating.<br />
It is not my purpose to endeavour to<br />
set out a progranume of educational<br />
reforni. That can he done only by those<br />
whose minds have been informed by<br />
prolonged inquiry and roteflection. I ant<br />
not addressing mysclf to this matter in<br />
any sense as a pretended expert. My<br />
primary purpose is to direct the attention<br />
of the Parliament and the nation<br />
to the vital importance in post-war reconstruction<br />
of a revised and extended<br />
educational systeia in our country, and<br />
to suggest to the Government that a<br />
commission aliould be set up in cooperation<br />
with the States in order to mali<br />
out a plan for such reform. A good<br />
education, nlthrugh it is not by any<br />
ineaiis indispeintable to worldly success,<br />
i or should he, I believe, one of the<br />
Iansic eleiiients in tlhe establishment of ait </p>
<p>(' itizenl inl life. Trhis does tnot uican that<br />
everybodyv can t'eoeive ustfully a highe2r<br />
education as we so describc it. It does<br />
not ntean that the educationi of ever y<br />
citizen is to follow exactly tie same lines<br />
ais if all citizens were destined for exactlytile<br />
iamie career. It doe-s not niteati tht<br />
education i t.: t be so dev-ised a s to<br />
dlevelop) identical focaul ties inl every*<br />
itumani being, whom i t touches. Th1
whole problem is olie of in unite variety.<br />
B~ ut our-experienice, particularly lin thle<br />
le st few Years, has sliowti that we cannot<br />
combine p'ogne's with sect'itv uttles<br />
the general level of the Iraomed capacity<br />
of out-peop~ le ii vei'v hiig'i mldc. l. LelI<br />
ite cite solm':' exalitlles-fit'st, that<br />
of tural education. ITn ruiral 1) 10( 1 ction<br />
aric passing-, it' we Itave not alIready<br />
passed, out of the, erIa lit whticht ott11V<br />
tertaitill c lineQ Of l) ri(, L! eetionl needed<br />
to be eng'a g ed in1, IFoi' \\-citiel I tete<br />
wal a rerisottable a. siiLraiue'-of a wkorl<br />
t'kec f. lThep eriod has be-ci desecribed<br />
hy sonmc experts as thle pm-iod of exploit: 1-<br />
tiott. * We arc p) assing out Uf that. We<br />
a1m-e cteting-the petiod wh'len thlet e<br />
ho( HILii 1m1r0e0 difflcultv ili 0hbta itingi<br />
iiarleets. I ait, now takitiig the lung,-view.<br />
We arie pit-sing inito the 1 criol wh-] enl we<br />
ust dhirect orlv5to 11111: h muore intenlsi<br />
ye ulse of out'. soil, with iitch. more<br />
s! c icitifiloio'dge of its t reatmtent and<br />
po-s] bihi ties anid with miiuch. grecIa ter<br />
VZOtiety oif pi-oduction If out' tuLral<br />
in~ dulstries are nlot to e-Aiov a ht'i( cf<br />
period of high prospertiy while the<br />
World is goiln through the iconzlritetioti<br />
ixiod, followed by a lrinkage<br />
in thle period of fleice collt-<br />
1-tition that will then pruwbibl * y ensuei, it<br />
Seelis cleai' that wve must inicrease out',<br />
itficietiiiaiid ' got our-costi ( 101' it. That<br />
v-. il I iivol ye, I believe, at least two thli-<br />
. itvill involve a large dievelopmletlt of<br />
s4cicittific research inl its relation to the<br />
, i-altiltural anld pastor'al iinduisrme. I t<br />
% ill itta'olve S. ceriouls a ttctitlin to thle ptallit<br />
Of. 1tot tlteo-i'eie tt'ainlitt, hot<br />
CiLtiltifii' tt'Niliitg f'ot' th otttal wot'k of<br />
the faimer. Inl regard to scientific<br />
trininthg foi' tie atait oil the I'mncl. it has<br />
seemed to me for' a long timec anl anotmaly<br />
ha.: t lin a couittry. so larztily ilepetident<br />
1,1. it" tt'ic. pt'spct'tty alni pt'od ntion'<br />
fliOUL thle Soil, SuIch mll to facilities<br />
Iiuld exist inl telatioit to agt'icttlttit'll. ucllcge and that miost of the existing<br />
c'licgs-and I have had a clo. se look at<br />
a e-should be so obviously starved of<br />
plant. equipment, staff anid buildings. It'<br />
otir attitude is to 1) 0 that rural procluctionl<br />
is a incere matter of Practical Cet'eien<br />
cc Aarr ) lIimited to thle locality ill<br />
which It is acquired, and thtat a sound<br />
pr-elimt mary mental trainii'm, is not<br />
nerededl. we shall tall vecry rapidly behind~<br />
tlhe otl, i-competitor countries. Onl these<br />
niatteirS, I should like to mention wvithout<br />
-i icu-sing it further the position of agien<br />
Itural anad other technical experts ii<br />
Tli., S ( Olitr-Y, ofteni underpa id anid over'-<br />
o orked, who are thle advcisers of the tnan<br />
cii the land. They have given aiid arc.<br />
-virtg notable service.<br />
Let aMe T fromn that to tile problelii<br />
of un i veisitY education 10 which the Mint-<br />
). iei' has directedl is attention, as I have<br />
saod u sefully. It i: quiite, clear that<br />
Il: C, 1( %% ill be a bia. increasec of ou1. t' niver-<br />
I I opulations. Inl Australia for every)<br />
( Itie pcrsoti ill 10,000 % 1lto attends n<br />
ill-cems dv. inl Atticrica there are fivi<br />
or ix. I Ihav 11no li b t t I at<br />
Ii undr1d i f I 01t tiltosa MIS Of InIcI<br />
collia tag ouit of the armed Seivice.-, will<br />
dh ; iro to lake Lup some formu Of Linliver'si* ty<br />
man ng } o r one( reaili andI a nother,<br />
I foie--ee a very large increase of the<br />
unk-ersity p~ opulation. That may men a,<br />
erlia ps it already doc., menut, crowded<br />
classroomns and inadequate staffs inl mail.<br />
ut vcrsitics, if ntot all; and crow -ded classroiumS<br />
anld inadequate staffs will mcivitablv<br />
mean falling standards, which we<br />
do not wvant inl out' itiliversitx traiing. i<br />
' 1licrefumo it max' well h c, fear--]*<br />
offer no, dogmatic viewv about it-tha t<br />
tla' tim~ e has comle for its to conisider<br />
ljo t I c packing of itio t and mtore<br />
Sde inito al read y crowded inistitu-<br />
Ionns. but tihe establishment of new\ A uniiveritme-.<br />
Lest I should be isuni~ lderstood,<br />
I1a at onIce that I ant1 not adVOCatingZ<br />
ii; all rovinicial lilt iversi ties that would<br />
eg;: i'd ed as sucotid-ra te. -The.\ would<br />
itot a real ser-vice to edinci tionl ill<br />
A ii'ttht Ihiat nut a criticimi of<br />
t he provinicial untiversities. 1 believe inl<br />
them. But it i~ s a criticism of any idea<br />
tfat we stould establish small univeisitics,<br />
thatI, iti the liature of things, are,<br />
r, 11Cgar14de as second-rate. If a new iniii<br />
to be createdI, it shouild be </p>
<p>created on a first-cla.: s scalk with suchl<br />
financial foundation as will enable it to<br />
nilract the highe. t talent to the teaching<br />
staffs and make the degrees granted<br />
in its faculties recognized and reputable.<br />
Most people familiar with the work of<br />
! inive'rsity staffs will, I think, be disposed<br />
to agree with me that the sheer pressure<br />
of ordinary teaching work in large classes<br />
is nargely excluding them from the work<br />
of i
l sShhovu ld be associated. The research<br />
pee' of university work needs to be<br />
brought into the very forefront of our<br />
-licnetional thinking.<br />
Then. hurrying on. liecause I can do<br />
n. more than make a brief conspectus of<br />
tl: ip! r oblem, let me say a word about<br />
I he problem of adult education. It i. s<br />
one of the real tragedies of our society<br />
Ihat there are so many boys and girls<br />
wvho leave school at fourteen or fiftI.<br />
en years, or whatever the age may<br />
be, rather glad to do so, lured by<br />
lie prospect of some immediate job,<br />
-nieii ilmmnediate wage, or perhaps<br />
driven to it by some family circunmtlance<br />
at home. When they have<br />
heen at school they have not felt much<br />
like learning things. They have been<br />
going through the time of life when<br />
school seems an unnecessary evil. They<br />
leave instructed only in the most elenIentarv<br />
fashion. Yet the same young<br />
men and women, five years later, at<br />
nineteen or twenty, may have developed<br />
a burning desire for knowledge.<br />
If a community has within its boundarifes<br />
( ven a few thousand people burning for<br />
knowledge and deprived of the opportunity<br />
to get it because they have<br />
passed into normal unskilled ways<br />
of earning their living, that coiOmunity<br />
is immeasurably the poorer.<br />
The problem of adult education is<br />
not a problem of offering people a few<br />
university extension lectures or even<br />
the Workers Educational Associations.<br />
Excellent as they are they are not a<br />
real substitute. The point is that the<br />
community has to tackle the problem<br />
of the boy of fourteen years, who<br />
left school not thinking he needed<br />
learning, growing into the young man<br />
of nineteen burning for it. What<br />
are we to do with him? There we<br />
have a problem that we have to tackle with everything we have. It is a problem<br />
that caunot be effectively tackled unless<br />
he is given some reasonably continuous<br />
means of acquiring knowledge. That will<br />
east burdens upon his employers and<br />
burdens upon the community. We must<br />
Ibe prepared to accept those burdens if<br />
we are to have any real system of adult<br />
education, because no man can be more<br />
frustrated as a citizen than the man who<br />
wants but cannot get the necessary training,<br />
whether of the mind or of the hand.<br />
If he can get it, we shall receive enormous<br />
dividends in terms of citizenship<br />
and everything that matters.<br />
S01om1 honorable members-indeed, I<br />
hope, many honorable members-will<br />
have. read two books written and published<br />
comparatively recently by Sir<br />
Richard Livingstone-books which, I<br />
believe, will have a profound effect upon<br />
educational reform all over the Englishspeaking<br />
world. One is entitled The<br />
Future of Education, and the other is<br />
called Education for a World Adrift.<br />
They contain a most acute analysis of<br />
many problems, and, in particular, this<br />
problem of adult education. In his book,<br />
Future of Education, ' Sir Richard<br />
gives a very interesting description of the<br />
people's high schools in Denmark. All<br />
the students are over the age of eighteen<br />
years, and only 25 per cent. of them have<br />
lihd any more than an elementary education,<br />
so that 75 per cent. of them have<br />
had the hiatus, to which I referred, between<br />
the normal school-leaving age and<br />
the age of eighteen at which they enter<br />
the high schools. After they left school,<br />
they spent the intervening years in farming.<br />
and general work in the cities.<br />
Mr. CHAMBEsRS.-What is the schoolb<br />
lring age in Denmark?<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-Speaking subject to<br />
, orrection, I think that it is fifteen years.<br />
Without going into detail on that matter,<br />
I should like to read a passage from Sir<br />
Richard's book. It is an observation by<br />
Grundtvig, who was one of the founders<br />
of the People's High ' School movement in<br />
Denmark. It strikes me as being a most<br />
, rresting observation-<br />
Experience proves that the same amount of<br />
information which it takes the half-grown<br />
youth, dozing on the school forms, three to<br />
five years to learn can be acquired by adults<br />
who are keen on learning and who have done<br />
practical work, in the space of three to five<br />
months. </p>
<p>I di-coiuti liat. I believe that it is an<br />
c: Xaggeration. Mr. SCULLIX.-It is rather optimistic.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I entirely agree;<br />
but, at the same time, allowing for exagi-(<br />
ration, it embodies what is to me a<br />
,*-imulating and optimistic idea. I beic-<br />
ve that we should encourage it.<br />
L,: t us have a look at the problems<br />
i' technical education. We have learned<br />
several lessons from the last depression,<br />
but one of them, perhaps, deserves more<br />
tlhn we have given to it. In a<br />
, cricd of business recession, the first<br />
uiffertir is the unskilled man and his<br />
fa: ily. That alone would constitute a<br />
:: V. oerful reason for the active forwardinu<br />
orfte chnical training. But, of course,<br />
we must add to that the basic truth that<br />
rise in the material standard of living<br />
depend upon more and cheaper<br />
production, and that in cheapness of<br />
production, the effective work done per<br />
man-that is to say, the real skill of the<br />
man-is of far greater importance iand<br />
! h: ould attract far more of our attention<br />
lI: tn the amount of money that is paid<br />
him. In other words, high wages and<br />
L. rsekaitl l and efficiency are natural<br />
a tnIers. If we are to match the<br />
rvst of the world in production and<br />
:: ke our products available to the imasz<br />
it our people at prices which they<br />
a:: n afford to pay, we must begin,<br />
nmt to follow the world, but to lead it<br />
i: i technical skill.<br />
I should like to say now a few words<br />
;: b( ot prc-school education. In the past<br />
w-2 have tended to assume that a child of<br />
p: cr-schcol age presents no problem, extc:<br />
pt the family problem. In the normal<br />
c ur.. e a child, on attaining the age of<br />
fivr yars or whatever it may be, goes to<br />
c . hicoblu; t in those precious years up to<br />
fi c, wel have as a conmunity. broadly<br />
si: akin,, said that it is purelxy a matter<br />
o' family responsibility. It is becoming<br />
ir: c: reasiii! y clear that one of the acutest<br />
iir:) ilemnis of the wife and mother after<br />
: 1 \ wha r will be the problem of getting<br />
hcli in her own home. In these circumnwe<br />
: must jn. st face up to the fact<br />
tlat th! eru'. ill be far too many neglected<br />
chilldron of pre-school years, unless we<br />
:' rcoigize that the community's educa-<br />
I: inl iuicn commence before the normal<br />
s: io lif begins. A great deal of valuable work has been done in the<br />
kindergarten field, but at the best, it is<br />
too dependent on voluntary activities,<br />
and on the zeal and enthusiasm of a comparatively<br />
few people. Last year, the<br />
British Parliament passed the Education<br />
Act-an act which has provoked a great<br />
deal of favorable attention, and which<br />
was based upon a White Paper published<br />
ii: that country. Section 8 provides for<br />
I system of nursery schools for children<br />
undero five years of age. I cannot go into<br />
thii. matter in detail; honorable members<br />
will realize that all I am endeavouring<br />
to do is to assist a general consideration<br />
of this problem by putting such<br />
thoughts as I have in my own mind<br />
Ibefore my colleagues in this Parliament.<br />
Tlhe broad problem, of which . ill these<br />
matters that I have mentioned are merely<br />
a; pects, i. s the problem of education for<br />
citizenship. I did not mention it -first,<br />
beeau-e I regard all the other things with<br />
which I have been dealing as leading up<br />
to it. The greatest failure in the world<br />
in my lifetime, and I amn sure that honorable<br />
melmbers will agree with me, has not<br />
hCen tlie failure in technical capacity or<br />
manual capacity half as much as it has<br />
been the failure of the human spirit.<br />
War after war is the result of a failure<br />
of the human spirit, not of some superficial<br />
elements but of the fatal inability<br />
of man to adjust himself to other men in<br />
a social world. With all our scientific<br />
development of this century, it still<br />
remains true that " the proper study of<br />
mankind is man", and that the real<br />
peace-maker is human understanding.<br />
The closer the countries of the world<br />
have come to each other in point of time,<br />
the more they have tended, unhappily,<br />
to develop a narrow. spirit of self-suffiicency.<br />
The more absorbed the people<br />
become in the technique of material living.<br />
the more they have neglected their<br />
social responsibilities, and the more, unlhappily,<br />
they have neglected the problems<br />
of popular self-government. It is well<br />
to, reni'mber that for years, the greatest<br />
ditt. ger to democracy has been, not so<br />
much a danger from without, as a danger<br />
from within.<br />
My own view is that there are two<br />
reasons for thi. s decline-there may be<br />
scores of others-but these two deserve<br />
particular mention. The first is the in-</p>
<p>it.' 1 .4i gIdlX pilga 1 an1 . Iiua trrial istie<br />
tui tIV of our education. I have no0 lesit:"<br />
tiou in saying, and I have said it miany'<br />
times before in the course of my life, that<br />
.1 1W( if-vv that religion gives to people a<br />
ll~ iltrvs~ tandilig of their obliaions<br />
and that is something which the<br />
World . sadly needs at the present time.<br />
For nny years we have hid in Australia<br />
thuc aclk antage of a systeml of Church<br />
hokof all denominationi, based upon<br />
the belief that education should always<br />
coniducted againist a religious backigi'illud.<br />
iPiit our1 State schlools are, by<br />
matutto, pu1relY secular illi their teaching.<br />
What the answer may be to that piobloni,<br />
I ( 10 110t iiiudertake to sa y, because that<br />
is a n : 1tier which calls for con, idcration<br />
by a comnin ission. But I should like<br />
g1aull to d othle attention of honorable<br />
ineil' rVi toi i lie Jritish Ediieition Act of<br />
1044. Section i imlposes. onl local educai('<br />
1i nltlliti('' a du1ty to conltribute towvai<br />
rIe rHit spiritual, moral, mental and<br />
physical di volopment of tile community<br />
[[ m1; at is a -fine charter for eduncation.<br />
Section 25 provides that the s~ chool day<br />
in eonntv scehool nall voluntary<br />
s(. 11001 JlmalI beg-ini with Collective worship<br />
onl the part of all pupils in attendlance<br />
athe scehool, with a proviso excusing a<br />
pupi I rol reCligiouIs worshlip Or ICl igiou1S<br />
ilst riletion 11po01 his pa rents' request.<br />
Section 26 provides for religious instruction<br />
iii accordanice with anl mgreed<br />
ylaus, but it shiall not include any<br />
( I techism or fornmulanly disztinct to anyv<br />
I., l ig s ( lenomn ila tion. Tis mat tel<br />
( ite of vast importance. Nobody canl<br />
'. lppose that are educating our childrn.<br />
except for disaster, by turning themn<br />
( lit ( If purely secular establishments at<br />
the a~ ge of fourteen, fifteen or sixteen<br />
y-a rs, m erel iy educated to a point at<br />
wih thy think that there is niothiing<br />
h ft for them to learn, aggressively coniu<br />
of wAN-it thley suppose to be their<br />
rights, ndi oblivious of that penietrating<br />
f(/-ling-of moral obligation to othecrs,<br />
Which alone en a make a community of<br />
alen sucessfutl. That is the first reason,<br />
I believe, for the decline to which I have<br />
referred. The second particular reason<br />
i the unthinking contempt which has<br />
faillen upon what people are pleased to<br />
call1 useless. learning The old classic.<br />
al eonception of education has declined if" disfIX yu . Ab parSellts, Nve cAlour.<br />
i'' r nld niorv that our sons and<br />
dnughtt. rs shall be tau ght things at school<br />
l, i ob will enable themn to earn money<br />
if hwey hanve left school, and nothing<br />
'. aiI say plainly that that is<br />
-i pitiful conceptionl of education. Tli<br />
oldI elassical notion of education may<br />
hav i10( its li its. No doubt it did. It<br />
!' Dnnve( d far too miany mnodeirn factors;<br />
hlit the study of humanities ill the Schools<br />
: ilii universi ties can at least develop a<br />
011i-Q of lioportion-the balancing of<br />
; ill cpecial knowledge againist general<br />
I.-tiP. Nv'dge of the vrorld, of the men in it,<br />
r d uof its pruoblcis. Uselesis learning<br />
it lIwi z been described, mnust, I believe,<br />
iomue b~ ack into its own in this world if<br />
noe to lprodutie a really civilized point<br />
I) v Iew%. The first function of education<br />
1to produce A good man and a good<br />
c1tizin1. Its second function is to produce<br />
a -good carpenter or a good lawyer, and<br />
tIn' gool carpenter and good lawyer will<br />
Ii' all the better at their respective crafts<br />
it' hley have becomie aware of the pro-<br />
IleinI of the world, have acquired somec<br />
qumal ity of intellectual criticismn, and havc<br />
developed that compara tive sense which<br />
pirod aces detachment of judgment and<br />
tinmds alw\ ay-s to moderate passion antd<br />
1lutliee. Sir Richard Livingston, the<br />
authority from whomn I have already<br />
quoted, says in his zecond book, Editca-<br />
( loll of a lWor7d Adrift--<br />
Htow can the rpirit of citizeiiiship be created<br />
evliped! Ili\\ tirc good citizens made'!<br />
i j-a it of th1e aieiii and imp ortant<br />
t-iuest imi, where to mecn , vt their vir-tues<br />
1 loii \% lint dleep) soul co areo drawl tile courage'<br />
: iu! l Q-N'iji sl'y ill till airb ~_ lLt oil<br />
1m; 1l WNliei e do tile inhabitant., of, for<br />
oitill Ce, Beritiotids uo r Bow. moinm i of themi<br />
lii iii iiitiileralie s. urrouindings, learn the<br />
lit iv whliclh enabilie them inl peace to be<br />
! o'eiit. k inldlY peole. and ill war cheerfully<br />
tIfallu tiliho rin of thit ir lioiis a l deathi<br />
fro'ill ilit' air I! How alre qull Viils to hei<br />
p re-c rvcd anlid extendted?? Andl oil thie othe r<br />
-hiail Clive tei-omlilAiiii tat sells,<br />
I 111idin i l last's i-ta Ilda rll for iiney,<br />
rolivri n e'very cla ss and rank. par tsa ii-<br />
4p iil ieckie,, statements in pltitics anil<br />
ui~ ilt-ih it. the iiitelleetua~ s betrayal of truth'!<br />
11e 1' 1 pro0i 3Cii'. deerin itill ii 11101-0r<br />
than iniii. sociologieal tiidie. anit very<br />
relevanit to our1 fuiture.<br />
And again-lmgti<br />
Inideed the history of maunkin ngtI<br />
described by a cynic as a series of splendid<br />
Cl tIIditOliS towards tile wrong g-oal or trni'ards </p>
<p>ln '; rl : 1 1. Icle b-mI w I h i ll thI I<br />
cl ' Iderinip C:: cClpt ii iul,-e ci ditectioil,<br />
4 ' 1 rr ecailovntet for iachtiit their<br />
' ni! cxeit the knowledacl of ends worth<br />
( cijevin. We must not forget in our educa-<br />
I . o1 ti:: ieiloiit. a n 5 oCf directon. We lo<br />
forect it. if we aie cite t that our schol<br />
h ioerela impart knowled cc. 4' velop and<br />
Oi-
Iii:-lil ow seie. Tllov p1: ut ilko he placeh<br />
e t4" 1 iti i enrieied bY the right<br />
. i-oni ndul w Iire thie ends of life ar i ' llted.<br />
the same distinguish fed wriiter points<br />
out-It i-pu--l' to : chie e p': c iterial<br />
p: oI-otp-it aitd abolitiion of unetnployiient.<br />
id Yet a civilizatioli of little tal:.<br />
. AI that considera tion leads me, quite<br />
tif8 oall 1nqnu ite logically, to a few<br />
Wiod-cn the qualiflnation, status, and<br />
rtmnoration of teacihers. The task of<br />
ie tenclier is one which brings him for<br />
lnorS every tlday, for many day&gt;, and for<br />
a ItnbtmlI of years, into close coiitact<br />
\ wit h his pupils during their most formae<br />
CalN. it is a task which, if well perfatcid,<br />
cain do more to produce good<br />
citi: zns than all the acts of Parliament<br />
i. tl piaszedl. It appears, therefore, that<br />
if a 1 s'ncular professions, teaching is the<br />
' ie pirofoundly important. The teacher<br />
1oes the work of making men. The<br />
1yiciaii and the surgeon can, at best:<br />
ic! rcir them; the lawyer can, at best,<br />
: Ji! t their differences; and the engineer<br />
, enn. at best, provide them with the means<br />
of physical community association; yet,<br />
el these professions, that of teaching'<br />
i1I' worst paid, and, broadly speaking,<br />
t" in'a the least recognition in a social<br />
1i-cw. As the years have gone by, we<br />
more and more-though per'haps<br />
not et sufficiently-insisted upon high<br />
at'ifications for teachers. The day of<br />
! d 1usher ill some private schools<br />
i! t! ihe time of Dickens, ignoranit, brutal,<br />
a111( uninformned, has gone. We are<br />
insting more and minore upon higher<br />
tcaching qa liflentions. It is relatively<br />
cor mouplace to require the possession of<br />
i1t iversity degree or diploma; yet<br />
i e talc two young men of equal mental<br />
e , patiy1, train one to be a teacher and<br />
tliC other to be a doctor, at the end of<br />
I! h period of training we pay to one<br />
three or four times as much as we pay<br />
to the other. Is it any wonder that<br />
ccacsionally one hears pirents complain<br />
that their children are heing taught by : itll ici w ) hoI i omuewhat " left wing<br />
it his view, who seems to be discontinted<br />
or who is filling their minds with<br />
ideas which appear to their parents<br />
'-athr: disorderly? Of course not.<br />
We must begin to recognize that the<br />
task of the teacher is one which rcquirc. s<br />
lie qualifications that wve demand of<br />
iH: er professions, and merits recognition<br />
whilh is equated to those qualifications.<br />
A community which was aware of the<br />
upreme importance of its educational<br />
stei 1 would insist upon the highest<br />
qiialiflectios for teaching, and would<br />
rouard those qualifications with adequate<br />
inuterantion and proper recognition.<br />
Ottr standards, where thllr exist, seem,<br />
ill too frequently, to he wrong. For<br />
cxatJle, as a Commonwealth, we spend<br />
someting like œ 750,000 a year in<br />
sciontific research; but we are prepared<br />
to spend more than three times that<br />
suint on free medicine, and that, with<br />
' reat respect to the Government, seems to<br />
me to be starting at the wrong end. The<br />
Comnonwealth and States together pay<br />
iii pensions, nearly œ 40,000,000 a year:<br />
tey spend on education only approxiinately<br />
one-third of that sum. What<br />
uZAosfe nv alues does a community possess<br />
lwhich pays three times as much for what<br />
Sw\ ill call-I hope without being mist':<br />
derstocd-social salvage, as it is prepa<br />
red to spend on the most vital work<br />
of social construction? It is not a case<br />
for reducing one, but for increasing the<br />
other. In Australia we spend about<br />
œ 14,000,000 a year on education. The<br />
Coi'unton,' ealth Statistician was good<br />
enough to estimate for me what we<br />
spend on amusements, and the amount<br />
is œ 16,250,000.<br />
Debate interrupted under Standing<br />
Order 119.<br />
Motion ( hbN Mr. DED.\ AN)-i M1 7eaveagreed<br />
to-<br />
Thit , o uitictieo f Standitig Order 119 be<br />
up ' iljed lt woutl ptrevent thie debate being<br />
Conitiited. tr. MENZIES.-I appreciate the<br />
action of the Minister, because I am sure<br />
that honorable members agree that we are<br />
discussing a most important matter. It<br />
i: estimated by the statistician that we<br />
spend in Australia on drink something<br />
like œ 50,000,000 a year, but our expenditure<br />
on education is only œ 14,000,000 a </p>
<p>year. It is not 1my purpome to criticize<br />
any of the items of expenditure to which<br />
I have referred. The coummunity call<br />
nmake up its own mind as to its disbursenienIIt.<br />
in those directions. But I do<br />
citicize our expenllditure oil education. I<br />
bimwn 110 government. Let us criticize<br />
lurselves upon this matter. It is for the<br />
( colon: unity to diecide what it will spend<br />
o( I ( 111rik or alniIuseoent, or, u111b1e1tdte r,<br />
itn ocial services for those who require<br />
tiwni but, if the same courniunity's expadi<br />
ture onil education is so miserable<br />
i: t it i ' uit of pjroportion to its expendiii<br />
other directions, it will give u<br />
a ) ahnr con temiptible place in what we<br />
czl, lroadllY. the civilized world.<br />
Now I 1urn to the position of the Corm-<br />
Mowecalth with regard to educatioi.<br />
There is all agitation inll soine quarters<br />
for the transfer to the Commonwealth of<br />
tl; e colnstitutional power to miake laws<br />
Witt r'spect to education. I do not propose<br />
to di-cuss that, because, iln my view,<br />
rite iprobile is urgent, and it sliould not<br />
e considered i pon the basis of some<br />
Iore or less rei ote constitutional po. ssihili<br />
ty. After all, education was inot ilncluded<br />
manig the subjects referred to the<br />
p( opl itt thtie teent ieferenduim, and<br />
Ai-( rcFon the coiititutioniial a. jeet does<br />
it at aeent arise. There is, however,<br />
it legal l'caron why the Comoniiwealt<br />
ir: ould no( colic to the rescue of the<br />
t: ts oil tite it: tters that 1 a111 discuss-<br />
I Eitlier by appropriations under<br />
t: ti: oii ; I of lthe Constitution, as to<br />
withich I agree that there is some con-<br />
'. lIi onali doubt, or by conditioned<br />
ralit-, to the ttates under section 96,<br />
a oti cii el there is rio coinstitirtionial<br />
th ubt, the (' ornnionwealth could make<br />
: nailable substantiai l . suis ill aid of<br />
t'uicationial reforni and development.<br />
1: K. iiievitale, I think, that that course<br />
-lioold Ut followix, anid, thinking so,<br />
I hwvt'ipt tt fot'nard tihe proposal menliiced<br />
at til ootzet of ily speech. I<br />
bit jeti that the Conilllonwealth will, in<br />
II probabilit*. v be a substantial contribuit.<br />
to cdue tionial reform, and, if so, it<br />
i ilt t ii erests of the Corni 1onwea Ith<br />
to t-iablih fIciltwith, iri collaboration<br />
Sitrlt flit, Sire-, a highly competent cornnine.,<br />
co liis.. ion to investigate the<br />
Prolleri and submit recommendations.<br />
I 1clieve Iitat such a body should be conmpojied of highly qualified persons compe!<br />
ctely detached from party politics, and<br />
reinforced by the inclusion of a member<br />
o: iicemubers familiar iWith developments<br />
abroad. We should not be parochial on<br />
11is itiatter. We have men and women in<br />
this country excellently equipped to sit<br />
on such a body, and I think that we could<br />
steiicure the services of somebody from<br />
CGre a t Brnitain and another from the<br />
United States of Amelrica to reinforce<br />
the committee or commission.<br />
I have said that the Commonwealth<br />
liiust, illn imy opinion, give aid to the<br />
States. Ever since the passage of unifoirmi<br />
taxation laws, the States have not<br />
itter: masters in their own financial house.<br />
Whatevelr State Ministers of Education<br />
iii siy about what they would like to do,<br />
1i1ere is a sharp linlit to their available<br />
V-soure. Yet in more States than one<br />
there is a burning desire to do something<br />
: houit this matter. I should like to say,<br />
it1 tile presence of the honorable member<br />
fir Denison ( Dr. Gahla), that no State<br />
his a better record with regard to educatiioni<br />
than Tasmania. The most dramatic<br />
and interesting educational experiment<br />
a: ide for a long time in Australia has<br />
beenii carried out by the Government of<br />
'[ asllaniia in the establishment of area<br />
5ehoolk. These schools will not only bring<br />
iniirediatc advantages to those who attend<br />
thein, Ibut will also provide a notable<br />
icel of educational research. Unless the<br />
Conirnonwealth, no matter which political<br />
party is in power, can aid the States<br />
financially, only limited objectives will<br />
Ie sought. I have profound distrust of<br />
limlnited objectives on the great and vital<br />
probtrn which we are now considering.<br />
If adequate resources are not available to<br />
the States, they will cut their coats<br />
nccording to their cloth, and that should<br />
niot be allowed to happen. As a nation<br />
We canllllot afford to do anything less than<br />
oui' best in a camupaign the result of<br />
tihich will be to determine whether, in<br />
thie new world, we are to be a nation of<br />
&gt; troiog, self-rcliant, trained and civilized<br />
top! 1. io whether we are to be content<br />
with ecound-rate standards, and moire<br />
A v\ oted t't the pursuits of miaterial<br />
: nlvntaigc ilhan to the achievement of a<br />
gr nuine humane community spirit.<br />
Mr. Fn. acrs.-I formally second the<br />
: iotion.<br />
HBYAU THORIU'FY: L. F. JOHNSTON, COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT ' ItINTErI, CANBERRA. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
