<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>130</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT THE COMMONWEALTH PARLIAMENTARY CONFERENCE, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/10/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000130.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON.<br />R. G. MENZIES AT THE COMM~ lvONWEA~ LTH PARLIAMENTARY<br />CONFERENCE CANBERRA, THURSDAY, 29TH<br />OCT6BER3 1,959<br />Your Grace, my Lords, Your IZxcellencies, Ladies and<br />Gentlemen: My task is a very pleasant one and, you will be<br />relieved to know, a very short one. My task is to propose the<br />health of our visitors, and in doing so I will be supported by<br />Dr. Evatt, representing the Opposition. That simple statement<br />perhaps explains almost all that has to be explained about the<br />Commonwealth Parliamentary Association and about this gathering.<br />qe are speaking now as Australians, completely bipartisan<br />on this occasion, We have no differences when we<br />deal with the Commonwealth Parliamentary Association and its<br />delegates. I have looked round the room and I have seen staunch<br />supporters of mine, hardened tories like myself sitting cheek<br />by jowl with gentlemen. of advanced ideas from Lhe Opposition,<br />giving every possible appearance of being friendly, as indeed<br />they are. That, after all, is the great secret of parliamentary<br />life, and that is perhaps he greatest thing to be learned about<br />S parliamentaSor y tlhiafte , i isnt hea llf ircsotu ntcroimemse nto ldt haotr nIe ww, anted to make<br />that there is something superbly bi-partisan, if I may use that<br />term or non-party, to use a better one, perhaps, about our<br />meetng. The second thing that has been very much in my mind<br />and I am not going to say all that I have in my mind is that I<br />have been instructed that this is only the first of three<br />speeches I shall make to precisely the same audienice on precisely<br />the same topics. So, naturally, I must keep something in<br />reserve. So the second thing, and the last thing, I want to say<br />on this particular occasion, which is a pipe-opener is just to<br />ask one question. This is the Commonwealth Parliamentary Association.<br />What is there that makes us an association? What<br />is it that makes us all feel that we have so-me profoundly great<br />element in common, with all our differences? Some of the oldfo<br />ideas are no longer valid for that purpose, Take the Crown, fo<br />example and its relationship to the people of Australia. We<br />are Her Majesty's subjects, externally and internally. There<br />are other big countries representeO. in the Co-q-. or-' A t h Parlia-<br />S mentary Association who recognise Her Majesty as the Head of the<br />Commonwealth but to whom the Queen is not internally the same<br />constant presence. So there is a difference.<br />There are differences in our law. We all hope and<br />struggle to have the purest of legal administrat~ bn. But every<br />time I begin to persuade myself, with all the natural arrogance<br />of a common lawyer that the Common Law is the secret, I encounter<br />somebody from South Africa who, I find, is a stranger to the<br />Common Law and all messed up with Roman Law, Therefore, I<br />cannot have that as an element of unity.<br />Really, the more you think about it, the :. jreat thing<br />we have in canmon is that we are all Par] liament men and women.<br />v! e know about Parliament, we live in a parliamentary system, We<br />are all of us, or practically all of us, members of some parliament<br />or another, all of them, interestingly enough, modelled on<br />the great model of Westminster, all of them with departures and<br />modifications which depend on local history and local characteristics<br />or the inexorable march of events. But underneath it all<br />we are parliament men. This is our great link,<br />I know of no other body or association in the w'orld in<br />which everybody participating can say: " I am a. man or woman<br />of Parliament. I believe in Parliament. I am part of Parliament,<br />and Parliament is part of This is a unique body,</p>
<p>2.<br />and that is a unique link.<br />Therefore, we in Australia who practise our politics,<br />as Winston Churchill once said, writh a fine Eighteenth Century<br />vigour, are delighted to meet peopleiall of them people of<br />Parliament, some of whom practise politics with more vigour<br />than we do some of w'hom have achieved that state of Nirvana in<br />which cour~ esy prevails always, which we can only envy.<br />Before I propose the toast " Our Guests" I am going to<br />invite my distinguished opponent, the Leader of the Opposition,<br />my bi-partisan friend for this occasion, Dr. Evatt, to support<br />me.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
