<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12748</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP  DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, MELBOURNE     </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/11/2002</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Victorian state election; water policy; economy; Cole Royal Commission; Victorian election; Bali arrest; telecommunications inquiry.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE...........  </p>
<p>JOURNALIST:<br />
Why would Robert Doyle make a better Premier than Steve Bracks?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Because you would have a clearer view of what he stood for, he would be willing to take tough decisions when they were necessary, he would not be pushed around by the unions and therefore he would be more likely to govern in the interest of all Victorians instead of some Victorians.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Mr Howard you';ve been involved in quite a few campaigns, any tips for Mr Doyle?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I wouldn';t be giving any public tips.  They';re always tough.  I mean Mr Doyle is the underdog in this election campaign but the Victorian public is entitled to say why is it being held 12 months ahead of time.  I mean as somebody who operates within three year parliamentary cycles I wouldn';t mind if our terms were four years, and I tell you what if they were I';d go the four years and not go when only three-quarters of my term was up. And when you do that you must arouse suspicions in the minds of the electorate that you want to get in ahead of something and you think things are going to turn against you and I think the Victorian public is entitled to have that suspicion.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
The ALP has announced their water policy today and they';ve called on the Federal Government to match their funding on the Wimmera Mallee pipeline.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well what we are doing on that is committing as we have $3.5 million to design study which the Victorian Government is contributing to as well.  When we know the outcome of the design study we';ll make a decision on the funding. I';d remind Victorian people, particularly those who live in the Mallee, that has an earnest of our commitment to that area relating to water we';ve put $20 million already towards some irrigation or other works in another part of the Mallee.  But we are certainly very interested in the pipeline project but we think the sensible thing to do, seeing that we are dealing with taxpayers' money is to see what the design studies says first and the fact that we';re putting $3.5 million into it means that we';re quite interested in the projects.  We want to see how the design study shapes up.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Do you have any idea of what Steve Bracks might be hiding from by going to an early election?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I don';t think he wasn';t to see the results of the Cole Royal Commission into the building industry, I mean that is obviously going to come out some time in the next few weeks or months, I don';t know exactly when. But it is very odd when you';ve got four years that you go after three, I mean I thought the whole idea of the years was so you could govern longer in the interests of the long term policies decisions that have got to be taken?<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
(inaudible) the Australian economy is going to grow next year, do you think that';s something Steve Bracks'; is worried about in Victoria?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I think it's more local factors, I mean the Federal Government has the dominate influence on the economy, although I do think investors pick and choose between states according to the industrial relations climate and I know from what businessmen say that they';re more concerned about potential industrial relations climate in this state than in other states.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Can you offer what date the Cole Commission report will come out?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don';t know the exact date David, I';m sorry I don';t.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
… rumours that it could leak early, or you may even release it early?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well the release of it will ultimately be determined, the finalisation of it, will be determined by the Royal Commissioner. He submits it and then it';s up to the government to release it. We haven';t got it and I can tell you now I';m not exactly certain what date it will be available to us.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
What are your plans … to be back on the hustings in Victoria?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I will come back again, yes.  This is a very important election for Victorians, Robert has my very strong support and it is going to be very tough for us. We are the underdogs but I do think the Victorian people have been given an unexpectedly early opportunity to make a judgment as to whether they have a Government and a Premier that have the bottle and the commitment to take the more difficult decisions that might be needed to protect the Victorian economy.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
The arrest of the alleged Bali bomb driver – is that a breakthrough or another false claim?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I';m not going to comment on that. I made a rule right at the beginning of this investigation that I would leave comment to the police on operational matters. I don';t think it';s a good idea for Prime Ministers or Premiers to be giving running commentaries on police investigations. I have read the papers. I have spoken to the Federal Police. It';s a matter for the Federal Police when they are ready, and only when they are ready, to have something to say about that. I';m not going to comment.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
[inaudible] happy with the progress of that investigation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I am quite satisfied that not only are the Federal Police - with help from state police forces might I say and for which I thank the various State Governments of Australia - not only are the Federal Police and the police of Australia putting great resources into the investigation, but there is very close cooperation between the Indonesian police and the Australian police. Notwithstanding some of the comments that have been made, the Indonesian police and the Australian police are still cooperating very closely and that is a good thing and that must be very reassuring to the relatives who have lost so much in this terrible event. Thank you.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Mr Howard, [inaudible] Simon Crean [inaudible]<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don';t know. That is a matter for him and a matter for Mr Bracks. I don';t wish to make any gratuitous comment on that. I am here because I';m keen to help Mr Doyle out. Mr Doyle is keen to have me.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Do you think that Federal leaders can play a role in an election that both State leaders are saying will be determined solely on State issues?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look self-evidently if a State leader wants you in an election campaign, you come. It';s as simple as that. Self-evidently, but in the end the election will be determined on State issues. State issues determine State elections and Federal issues determine Federal elections, but it has been my invariable experience in 28 years in Federal politics that if State leaders want Federal leaders in a State election, they invite them and they come.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Mr Howard just on the telecommunications inquiry. Dick Estens has released the report today. Can you put a timeframe now on when Telstra will be sold?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No. What we';re going to do is look at the report and then give some indication as to whether it meets our stipulation that conditions in the bush had to be up to scratch before we went any further and if they';re not up to scratch now, what extra is needed to get them up to scratch arising out of the Estens report. And when we';ve made that assessment we will give some indication of future action. But that will be soon that we will give indication but we want a few days to have a look at the report.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
[inaudible] up to scratch?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well have a look at Estens. I mean the whole purpose of Estens was to benchmark, was to assess what had happened. And it';s pretty clear on my preliminary assessment that Estens has said that there has been enormous progress made over the past few years and I think that is very encouraging and that is what we want because we want a fair go for people in the bush in telecommunications.<br />
Thank you.<br />
[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
