<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5699</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO ROTARY INTERNATIONAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/11/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005699.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 9.30 AM<br />
FOR MEDIA SATURDAY, 28 NOVEMBER 1.981<br />
ADDRESS TO ROTARY INTERNATIONAL<br />
I. am very pleiased to join you this morning a this Pacific<br />
Conference of Rotary : nternat: Lonal and I would like to weolcom~ e<br />
to Australia -all the visitors, com,-ing from some 24 Pacific<br />
nations, who are attending this Conference.<br />
It is only a few weeks since this building was the scene of<br />
the Common-wealth lieadS o-F Government Meeting, at which I<br />
happened to b-e in the chair, and I must say, Mr Chairman,<br />
that in makinc the jour-ney here this mornitng, I experienced<br />
a considerable decroe of relaxation through knowiJng that the<br />
respons iblizY, of chairino this meeting was going to rest on<br />
your shoulcerrs rather th'-an mine. A number of the countries<br />
represent. ed at ithi -m-eeting were a--lso particioants in the<br />
recent CorTonwealth meeting, and I hope that your meeting will<br />
be as productive in terms of its objectives as was that<br />
earlier meetina.<br />
The theme of your Conference, " The Ihiture of the Paci fic"<br />
reminds me of thnat oft-re-Leated remrark that the Mditerranean<br />
is the ocean of the, past, the Atla-ntic is the ocean of the<br />
present, an--th-Pacific is the ocean of the future. It is<br />
not so many yiears since the Pacific ocean seuneda barrier<br />
between countries, but now the position is changing and as<br />
Pierre Trucleau of Canada said recently, " with modern technotocjy,<br />
communications and travel, we feel that th-is Pacific Ocean<br />
joins us raz~ er tin separates us", and howrtoh to speak<br />
of " the vital. sense of -, rowth-and dynamisii w-hich characterises<br />
the countr-ies of the Pacific rim."<br />
There is a large nu-mber of neow, and emerqing, states in the<br />
Pacific hasi~ n, anC" d I belic!% V that with the outstand-ing; cr~ t<br />
rates crcc~ O~:: contiesa ach icvincj -with. incaie-scJ<br />
economic inedprdncand wi the cnincto~ sand<br />
tech-nolocr-I ha\ ve ref:, rrc? to, we: c-an betl. forw,. ard to : losr~<br />
relationships at i7-any . vcsbetweon Paci fic countries. In<br />
term-, Of your ther'-a of the:-future of, Pacific, I like<br />
to take-this orppor12.-ti Ifirst to cosie Australia,'; s trade<br />
with the eeiOPin' cun,). Cs a sub."-ct which has spe cial .12 </p>
<p>2<br />
relevance to the South Pacific, then to discuss Australia's<br />
very important trading partnership wtih Japan, and finally<br />
to comment on independence and political stability, especially<br />
in connection with the South Pacific.<br />
Throughout 1981, Australia has taken every opportunity to<br />
highlight the massive proportions of the problem of world<br />
poverty, and to stress the need for a renewed will, especially<br />
among the developed countries, to do something about it.<br />
As Australia's Foreign Minister, Mr Tony Street, said this<br />
week, Australia's close association with the attempts to get<br />
progress on this front has been recognised by the invitation from<br />
the President of the U. N. General Assembly for Australia to<br />
join a contact group of 22 countries which is seeking agreement._<br />
on the launching of global negotiations.<br />
At the recent Commonwealth meeting also, the heads of government<br />
agreed to make every effort to remove obstacles to an early<br />
start to global negotiations. In addition, the Commonwealth<br />
meeting called for a study of the negotiating process<br />
itself, because it is important that nations should not become<br />
locked into inflexible positions simply because of the way<br />
negotiations are conducted.<br />
As we come closer to the end of this year, I am very conscious<br />
of Pierre Trudeau's comment that " history will judge the year<br />
1981 as a watershed in North-South relations, as the time<br />
when the countries of the world either moved foward... or<br />
when they allowed a momentous opportunity to slip through<br />
their fingers." And if current session of the U. N. General<br />
Assembly can make a decisive contribution to getting global<br />
negotiations started, that will be a significant achievement<br />
in terms of the countries of the world " moving forward together<br />
in a concerted attack on the economic disparities which<br />
plague our global community".<br />
In humanitarian tems, there is an irresistible case for<br />
the most determined efforts to come to grips with the problems<br />
of poverty. But enlightened self-interest also provides the<br />
strongest incentive for co-operation between developed and<br />
developing countries in pursuit of economic taike-off.<br />
Australia is a trading nation, so we are acutely conscious that<br />
the economic success of other countries, especially the<br />
developing countries, is an important factor in our own continuing<br />
prosperity. Growing markets in developing countries are vital<br />
for employment and prosperity in developed countries. Some<br />
of the west's entire trade is with developing countries<br />
and the proportion is even higher in the case of the U. S.,<br />
where the figure is 40% and in the'case of Japan where it is<br />
Between 1973 and 1978, while exports from developed to<br />
developing countries increased at an average annual rate of<br />
over 25%, exports from developing to developed countries<br />
increased only at around 10% per annum. / 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
There is an obvious message in this, for without economic growth<br />
in the developing countries, the developed countries will not<br />
be able to keep up their export growth rates. It needs<br />
to be realised that the growth rates achieved over the last<br />
decade by the so-called newly industrialising countries,<br />
including South Korea, Taiwan, Hong Kong and Singapore,<br />
have helped to limit the severity of the world recession,<br />
and developed countries must reject any temptation to resort<br />
to protectionist measures which deny developing countries<br />
the fruits of their efforts and enterprise.<br />
In fact, it is in the interests of all that further progress<br />
be made in reducing the trade barriers which already exist,<br />
which currently have the greatest impact on the exports of<br />
the developing countries. The recent Tokyo round of<br />
multilateral trade negotiations offered smaller than average<br />
benefits to the industrial exports of developing countries,<br />
and these negotiations made even less progress on non-tariff<br />
barriers and agricultural protection.<br />
The impact of agricultural protectionism on the developing<br />
countries is dramatically illustrated by a joint UNCTAD/ FAO<br />
study in 1972 which estimates that agricultural trade barriers<br />
were costing the developing countries something like $ 34 billion<br />
per year in 1981 values. Even the partial removal of agricultural<br />
protection in industrial countries which has been estimated<br />
to be three times as high as protection on industrial products,<br />
would be a major benefit to the developing countries.<br />
In the context of Australia's progress towards lower protecticn,<br />
I would refer to our new seven-year program in the key area<br />
of textiles, clothing and footwear, which will reduce assistance<br />
over time, which will further increase access to the Australian<br />
market, and which also includes a preference scheme for<br />
developing countries.<br />
I would also refer to the New South Pacific Regional Trade<br />
and Economic Co-operation Agreement under which Australia will<br />
provide preferential non-reciprocal duty free access for the<br />
major export products of South Pacific Forum island states.<br />
Access to the Australian market, particularly-" for the products;<br />
of developing countries, is already relatively high and it is<br />
growing. Between 1972/ 73 and 1979/ 80, while total Australian<br />
imports increased at an average annual rate of just over 21%,<br />
imports from developing countreis increased at a rate of<br />
almost 30%, and from ASEAN countries at about 38%. Two ASEAN<br />
trade fairs have been held to pro. mote ASEAN products in<br />
Australia, and Australia is proposing a third trade fair for<br />
1983.<br />
While access to the markets of developed countries is vital<br />
to developing countries, effective aid is also indispensable<br />
to developing in a number of situtations, and I am very pleased<br />
that Australia's Bu'gt allocation for official development / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
assistance has increased this year by almost 20% to more than<br />
$ 600 million. Our food aid program. has been substantially<br />
expanded and we have established a research centre to mobilise<br />
Australian expertise to address agricultural problems in<br />
developing countries.<br />
We are contributing to the development of new and renewable<br />
sources of energy in developing countries, we have pledged<br />
million to the second account of the common fund to<br />
assist the development, marketing and production of<br />
commodities. And we have committed $ 7.5 million to the<br />
ASEAN-Australia economic co-operation program for 1981/ 82 to<br />
assist in the development of industrial projects.<br />
Within the South Pacific, Australia is increasing regional<br />
co-operation through assisting with sea transport, seabed<br />
research and education and our allocaidons for bilateral<br />
project aid to South Pacific countries have increased from<br />
$ 11 million in 1976/ 77 to $ 43 million this year. Australia's<br />
recognition of the economic and trading problems of the<br />
island states is shared by other Commonwealth nations,<br />
and it was agreed at the Melbourne meeting that measures to<br />
assist the island states to develop resources with their<br />
exclusive economic zones are vital.<br />
In the lives of these island states, the convention on the law<br />
of the sea assumes a dimension which many developed states<br />
cannot easily comprehend, and is a matter of satisfaction for<br />
Australia that after close involvement in seven years of<br />
negotiations, finalisation of this convention is now expected<br />
in 1982. That will be a desirable result, and it creates<br />
the potential for significant economic advancement in many<br />
Pacific countries.<br />
In the wider context,. the proble. ms of world poverty and<br />
development are not ones which can be solved next week or<br />
next year or even in the next decade. But as I have said<br />
on many occasions, unless something is done about building<br />
up the economies and the trade of developing countries, our<br />
children will curse us for our selfishness and our<br />
shortsicjhte'dnss. Let me add that in any consideration of<br />
trade between nations there are a number of age-old lessons<br />
which must never be overlooked, especially at -times when<br />
trading circumstances become difficult. </p>
<p>I would hope that a number of old lessons have been<br />
re-learned following the early 1970s, when the damage caused<br />
by certain stop-start trading policies tended to strike at<br />
the. very heart of stable trade relationships.<br />
It is true that trade between nations can seldom be wholly<br />
predictable, but reliability, especially at the policy level<br />
and a willingness to establish genuinely two-way trading<br />
. relationships, are vital if the best use if to be made of the<br />
productive capacities of nations and of people. I would add that<br />
while stability and reliability are important in all trading<br />
relationships, they are particularly important for developing<br />
economies. I have been speaking of the problems faced by developing countries<br />
and without question, these problems are massive and daunting.<br />
But we also need a sense of perspective, because the economic<br />
success which a number of countries have achieved in recent years<br />
shows that progress can be made and the vision of success should<br />
be kept in mind when people grapple with issues of economic<br />
development.<br />
Let me turn to the second topic I said I would like to discuss<br />
this morning Australia's trading relationship with Japan.<br />
Japan has been Australia's major trading partner since 1971, and<br />
I am confident the partnership is one whi-ch both countries will<br />
continue to value and respect. While Japan is Australia's largest<br />
export market, Australia is certainly one of Japan's fastest<br />
growing export markets. Japan has better access to Australia's<br />
markets than to those of any other industrialised nation and<br />
Australia also welcomes the growth in new Japanese investment,<br />
which has more than trebled, to nearly $ 700 million, in the<br />
three years to 1980/ 81. Japan is Australia's most important<br />
market for exports of minerals and primary products such as coal,<br />
iron ore, wool, sugar, and dairy products, and is a major market<br />
for our wheat and meat.<br />
While Australia ranks fourth among Japan's trading partners Japan<br />
relies on Australia as a major supplier of many commodities, and<br />
the Australian . share of certain key Japanese raw material imports<br />
is very high. For example, in 1981., Australia has been providing<br />
of Japan's imports of coal, and 10% of its iron ore.<br />
Despite the difference in the size of our twoeconomies, our<br />
trade relationship is one of mutual dependence and I believe it is<br />
greatly strengthened as a result of the acceptance by both<br />
countries of the trading principle which I have already referred<br />
to that a satisfactory trading partnership depends on certainty<br />
and stability of trade in both directions. The complementary<br />
nature of our economies and our gcog.: acphical closeness have been<br />
important factors in sustaining a healthy growth in trade at a<br />
time when difficult economic coneditions have limited growth in<br />
other areas of the world. It will be important in the years ihead<br />
to ensure that through close consultation and co-operation we<br />
understand each other's requirements fully. Only in this way<br />
can we maaitain stability and trust in our trading relati. onship,<br />
and take full advantage of the opportunities that make our region<br />
one of the -bright spots on a relatively gloomy world conomic scene-<br />
/ 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
The third topic I wanted to comment on this morning, because<br />
the theme of your conference really does give me a great deal<br />
of leeway, is the wider issue of stability especially in<br />
connection with the South Pacific region. It is remarkable to<br />
realise that it is less than 20 years since everySouth Pacific<br />
state was subject to some form of colonial administration, and it is<br />
a matter for great satisfaction that the political life of the<br />
independent states of the South Pacific since independence has<br />
been one of political stability. But not all Pacific islands<br />
are yet self-governing, and the principles of self-determination<br />
and independence for all Pacific island countries principles<br />
which certainly enjoy Australian support still need to be advanced.<br />
Australia well understands the aspirations of colonial peoples<br />
to be free and self-governing and the delegation from the<br />
South Pacific soon to visit France for discussions on this subject<br />
has the full support of the Australian Government.<br />
The new French Government has shown signs of taking a fresh<br />
approach on the question of decolonisation and I hope that the<br />
delegation's visit will result in movement towards independence<br />
for French territories in the region.<br />
In addition to these considerations, the strategic importance<br />
of the South Pacific has been amply demonstrated in earlier<br />
times and Australia has a direct and immediate interest in<br />
continued stability throughout the decolonisation period and<br />
beyond it.<br />
We in Australia are well aware of the responsibilities which fall<br />
upon us in relation to the South Pacific region, and we are<br />
continuing to take initiatives, as we have done in past years,<br />
to discharge those responsibilities. The regional organisations<br />
which have been established in the South Pacific, especially the<br />
South Pacific For-um, have been particularly successful bodies,<br />
and they will continue to play a significant role.<br />
The regional meetings of the Commonwealth Heads of Government.,<br />
which Australia was instrumental in establishing, also provide<br />
a valuable forum for many South Pacific countries. More recently,,<br />
at the Melbourne meeting of the Commonwealth Heads of Government,<br />
Australia offered to fund appropriate facilities in New York to<br />
en1ble Pacific island states not presently represented at the<br />
Unit: d Nations to maintain representation. All of this should help<br />
to bring about a greater understanding of South Pacific concerns<br />
and issues in the international context, " and also to encourage<br />
the participation by South Pacific countries in discussions of<br />
wider international issues.<br />
Thi.: leads me to a consideration of a rather different kind, for in<br />
talking about the issues of development, trade and stabil. ity, I<br />
have concentrated on Governmental approaches to issues of<br />
inteirnational concern. But Governments do not have a monopoly<br />
on these concerns and there are, at least in the free world,<br />
noI -Governmental bodies which have demonstrated a capacity to make<br />
sigcnificant contributions to certain international issues. / 7 </p>
<p>7-<br />
I have no doubt that the voluntary work of individual, people<br />
in Rotary and other service blubs contributes in A real and<br />
important way to international. understLanding and stLability.<br />
I believe that organisations such as Rotary, which have an<br />
international outlook and traditions ofl service have an important<br />
-role to play in the overall pattern of -international discuss--lon.<br />
I hope that this conference will have made its own contribution<br />
just as I hopa that all the visitors will have had a happy<br />
and rewarding stay in Australia.<br />
I think you for inviting me-here this morning and wish YOU Well<br />
in the remainder of your conference. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
