<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9516</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS, RADIO 2UE, 21 MARCH 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009516.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS, RADIO 2UE, 21 MARCH 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
JL: After that 10 day overseas trip, you leapt right into domestic issues.<br />
Didn't talk once about what was achieved while you were away. What<br />
did you achieve while you were away?<br />
PM: Well, the purpose of the visit was to re-establish Australia's<br />
relationship with the third largest economy in the world, that's<br />
Germany, and also to again try and rebuild further our relationship with<br />
The Netherlands, and to attend the UN Social Summit in Copenhagen.<br />
JL: When you say rebuild with The Netherlands, has there been a problem<br />
with The Netherlands?<br />
PM: Oh no, but again the last Australian Prime Minister to go to The<br />
Netherlands went there in 1975. So that's a long time ago and I think<br />
even though they regard us as people they can rely upon and we the<br />
same with them, there is a point in going and I had a terrific<br />
conversation with the Dutch Prime Minister, and I had a very, very big<br />
meeting and discussion with the German Chancellor.<br />
JL: Okay, are they of equal importance to us, The Netherlands and<br />
Germany?<br />
PM: Europe is the largest economy in the world. The European Union has<br />
a gross product of about 6.6 trillion. The United States is about 4 and I<br />
think Japan is about 3, so it gives you some idea of the size of the<br />
thing, and Germany of course is the largest west European country.<br />
It's now reunited with 80 million people, I mean before that it had<br />
million people.<br />
JL: And they were all sort of around 60 million weren't they England,<br />
France, Germany they were all somewhere around that number<br />
weren't they? </p>
<p>PM: Yes, they have been sitting at around 55-60 million since the war<br />
which has meant there has been a sort of equality between them. But I<br />
think what is happening now, the new dynamic in Europe, is that with<br />
West and East Germany united, at 80 million and with enormous<br />
investment by West Germany in the east, in Eastern Germany, their<br />
national accounts came out the week I was there and they had the<br />
West German economy growing by about 2 per cent and the East<br />
German economy growing by about 10 per cent. I think what all that<br />
means is that Germany is going to be a united stronger state and its<br />
economic performance is going to see it pull away from countries like<br />
France and The Netherlands, particularly France, and I think that<br />
therefore the imperatives of the union, that is tying for instance, let<br />
me just make this point...<br />
JL: Just back to the growth in Germany, you said 10 per cent?<br />
PM: 10 per cent in the east.<br />
JL: Well, if you were running the joint, you would have to lift interest rates<br />
wouldn't you to slow down the growth?<br />
PM: Well, the whole country is running at 2.9 per cent because the east is<br />
still a relatively small part of the German economy but it's going to be,<br />
because it is much the same sort of land area and it's got still a large<br />
population, what's going to happen is Germany is going to continue to<br />
grow quite strongly and modernise via the east and I think that this is<br />
going to put tremendous growth potential into Germany. And the<br />
whole point of the Helmut Kohl-Mitterand discussion of the last ten<br />
years, and the whole point of the post-Second World War<br />
arrangements in Europe with Conrad Adenauer and Schuman and<br />
these people, was to tie Germany into Western Europe because<br />
Berlin, where I went as well, is 40 miles from the Polish border.<br />
Germany sees essentially a relatively invisible border between<br />
Germany and Poland which means the German economy will drift into<br />
Poland.<br />
JL: How many people in Poland, do you know?<br />
PM: I think it is about, from memory, about 40 million. It really means that<br />
we are seeing Germany start to return to where it was before the First<br />
World War, that is it's starting to go east again. So it's got to get a<br />
sheet anchor in western Europe and the sheet anchor is the European<br />
Monetary Union. And it was that that I had quite a long discussion with<br />
the Chancellor about and let me say that means that basically there is<br />
one currency, what they call the EMU, one currency which would be in<br />
France, in Germany, in The Netherlands, in the Benelux countries. In<br />
other words, we would just not have simply a single market in Europe,<br />
but a single currency in western Europe.<br />
JL: How does that affect Australia? </p>
<p>PM: Well, how it affects Australia is two ways. One, that it would mean for<br />
the first time really since the 19th century, welt the first time ever, we<br />
would have a united Europe. Certainly in the West with these key<br />
economies of Germany, France and the Benelux countries. That<br />
means there's a much more stable set of currencies because when<br />
there's a flight out of the American dollar, people buy Deutschmarks.<br />
But Deutschmarks only have the monetary base of one country, that's<br />
Germany. If there's an EMU, there's a bigger monetary base but the<br />
most important point is this John it means that Germany will not, in<br />
that circumstance, find itself drifting east towards Poland and Russia<br />
as was the case in the past. Unless that monetary link comes<br />
together, Germany will simply grow away I think from France and all<br />
the old suspicions start again.<br />
JL Yes, exactly.<br />
PM: So, nobody in Australia should ever think that what happened in<br />
Europe doesn't matter to us. I mean here we are, we are in the Asia-<br />
Pacific, it's nice and peaceful here.<br />
JL That's very important.<br />
PM: You can see what's happening already in Bosnia. I mean look in 1895,<br />
100 years exactly ago, in Europe, the Balkans were a problem then,<br />
they're a problem now. People thought they faced the new century,<br />
the 20th century, with great hope and expectation. I just think that the<br />
Europeans have got to work quite hard now to pull this monetary link<br />
together.<br />
JL What do we do, just keep an eye on it?<br />
PM: Well, let me say, it comes at a time when President Mitterand is retiring<br />
so this great partnership which Chancellor Kohl has had with him is<br />
going to change.<br />
JL There's no love lost between the Germans and the French anyway, is<br />
there?<br />
PM: I think there's a big commitment now, not simply by the Governments,<br />
by the communities to work together. I just don't think they can<br />
countenance ever again the problems of internecine strife between<br />
them, but while ever the Deutschmark puts pressure on other<br />
currencies and we have different rates of growth in Germany, different<br />
rates of workforce growth in those countries, I mean there is a case, I<br />
think, for getting it together. One of the interesting things, John, I'm<br />
sure you may be surprised to know, but you know there's a thing called<br />
the Maastricht Treaty, you know of that?<br />
JL Yes, I'm aware of that.<br />
PM: This has very, very tight disciplines about who can join the European<br />
Monetary Union because the Deutschmark sits, in a sense, and the </p>
<p>Bundesbank sit at the moment on the top of that particular heap and<br />
you've got to be in first rate condition to join. Now at the moment, the<br />
only two countries in the OECD, that's the western world area, who<br />
meet the Maastricht Treaty criteria are Germany and Australia.<br />
JL: Is that right?<br />
PM: Australia is the only other country in the world that could actually join<br />
this year the European Monetary Union on the convergence criteria.<br />
JL: Will Australia do that?<br />
PM: No, well of course we're not in Europe. So we're not joining.<br />
JL: But if you were able to, would there be any advantages in doing so?<br />
PM: Well, for us, no. It's just completely different economies and we're just<br />
too far away. But a key point is on inflation, on productivity, on<br />
Government debt to GDP, on a whole lot of criteria I think we're the<br />
ones who could join with Germany and I think Luxembourg comes in<br />
next year. So, it's a measure of how we're going. The Chancellor, can<br />
I say, was quite surprised at this but I gave him a little note with the<br />
various criteria, he didn't doubt for a moment what I was saying was<br />
right. But it just makes this point, it makes two points: they've got<br />
to get the link together quickly and that political stability, because the<br />
monetary union in Europe is not just a matter about the monetary<br />
system, it's a political imperative, it's not just an academic exercise to<br />
central banks, it's a political imperative to basically tie West Germany<br />
into western Europe as it continues now historically to start to look east<br />
and to works its economy east-ward.<br />
JL: Okay, on the subject of money. The Australian dollar is being sold off<br />
dramatically at the moment against the US dollar. Our dollar, I think, is<br />
6 per cent lower in value now than it was at the start of the year. I<br />
presume you're going to tell me it has got nothing to do with the<br />
concern of the financial world about the size of the current account<br />
deficit?<br />
PM: Well, it's always got some of that in it, but by and large, the currency<br />
has been a commodity driven currency and I think that they look at<br />
what they think was going to happen to commodity prices, basically, I<br />
think that's part of it. But again, I mean these fluctuations come and<br />
go. We have appreciated quite substantially over the last 18 months<br />
and I always believe let the market fix this price. It's the most<br />
important price in the economy, it's the thing that governs our<br />
competitiveness abroad.<br />
JL: If it's 6 per cent lower than it was at the beginning of the year, what is<br />
the reason?<br />
PM: Well, all sorts of reasons I think. Commodity prices, where they see<br />
demand going, an important thing will be the message the Government </p>
<p>sends to the financial markets about the Australian budget, and let me<br />
just make this as clear as I possibly can: we will be introducing a<br />
budget which does all that I believe it should to make a contribution to<br />
public savings by bringing the budget deficit back more quickly.<br />
JL: Are you going to increase tax to do that?<br />
PM: We are in the course of preparing that budget now, it will be<br />
announced in May, and I think markets will be waiting for that to<br />
happen. But I mean John, there have been a lot of shifts in the<br />
currency market lately a lot of skittishness with the collapse of the<br />
Mexican currency and with the upsets in the US dollar market.<br />
JL: OK. Another concern of the money market is that interest rates are<br />
being deliberately held at the current level because of the NSW<br />
election.<br />
PM: Well that is just nonsense that is absolute nonsense, I can assure<br />
you that is absolute nonsense.<br />
JL: So after the forthcoming NSW election you won't back off the shackles,<br />
eh?<br />
PM: No. Monetary policy is set by the Reserve Bank in conjunction with the<br />
Government, and I can assure you I and the Treasurer have had no<br />
such conversations with the central bank to do with the NSW election.<br />
And again, the NSW election is largely being fought out on state<br />
issues.<br />
JL: As it should be.<br />
PM: As it should be, exactly.<br />
JL: Will the spending cuts you announce in the May budget be deep<br />
enough to satisfy those who are yelling loudly for deeper cuts in the<br />
budget deficit?<br />
PM: The problem is not that we need the budget to meet a short-term<br />
demand management task, but rather a medium-term savings task.<br />
That is, what we need to do is see the public sector save some more,<br />
mainly because Australian private savings are lower than they need to<br />
be for the level of Australian investment.<br />
JL: Yeah.<br />
PM: In other words, we want to keep this level of investment up we need<br />
to save more. If private saving is not as strong as it ought to be, then<br />
the Government has got to play another role it wouldn't ordinarily be<br />
expected to play. That is, to actually add more to public savings<br />
themselves. </p>
<p>J L OK, so are you going to add more to public savings by cutting<br />
Government spending further?<br />
PM: We will be cutting government spending, but again, it's all a matter of<br />
degree, remembering John, that this is now the lowest taxed country in<br />
the western world, it has one of the smallest public sectors in the<br />
western world, and that happened because of the cuts in Government<br />
that this Government put into place in the 1980s.<br />
JL Yeah, but there will be more cuts?<br />
PM: There will be more cuts, but there is every year, and we will be seeking<br />
to bring the budget balance back.<br />
JL You see the tax payers get pretty upset understandably when they<br />
realise it costs them more than $ 50 million a year which, in the overall<br />
scheme of things probably isn't a lot of money to pay performance<br />
bonuses to senior Government bureaucrats, and another $ 50 million a<br />
year is needed to compensate bureaucrats for the stress they suffer<br />
doing the job. Now, surely that sort of thing could, and should be,<br />
looked at?<br />
PM: Well, I am not sure where those numbers came from..<br />
JL From your people.<br />
PM: well, there is an enormous..<br />
JL That's $ 100 million we are talking about.<br />
PM: We are talking about a public sector of a couple of hundred thousand<br />
people, so $ 50 million might should a lot but it doesn't go very far<br />
spread across that number of people, but..<br />
JL But if you add a whole bunch of $ 50 million together, it goes a long<br />
way.<br />
PM: the key point is this John we cut Government spending from 30.5% of<br />
GOP down to 23.5% in the 1980s by 7% of Gross Domestic Product.<br />
JL What is it now?<br />
PM: It is about 25.5% 26% but it's heading back to around 24%. In other<br />
words, on a no policy change basis, it is heading back to around 24%<br />
of GDP. Now, that's . now GOP this year that's the total<br />
economy, what we call Gross Domestic Product the total value of our<br />
goods and services is about $ 420 billion, 6% is about $ 24 billion, so<br />
every year, this Government has cut back around $ 24 thousand million<br />
as a result of what we did in the 1980s. That's why Australia that's<br />
one of the reasons why Australia would meet the EU Convergence<br />
criteria. </p>
<p>JL: Yes, but you know as well as I know that it is all about perception, and<br />
million mightn't be a lot here, there or some place else. Another<br />
million even might be important but it is about perception. And if<br />
the people who are going to vote or not vote for you or any political<br />
party, keep hearing and they do hear constantly because we tell them<br />
that $ 50 million a year is paid into performance bonuses over and<br />
above a high salary that those public servants get anyway and another<br />
million goes for stress when there are people listening to us<br />
across Australia now who are pretty stressed trying to pay the<br />
mortgage, the perception of the Government is not really very good.<br />
PM: Well, the federal public service is the largest employee group in the<br />
country and $ 50 million may sound a lot of money but spread across a<br />
very large number of people I don't think it is. The point is, John, there<br />
is no point in you and me trying to work out how we cut government<br />
spending on 2UE. I mean, in the end these are things we have proven<br />
that we can do over a long period of time and that is why Ralph Willis<br />
and Kim Beazley, the Minister for Finance, have been sitting in our<br />
Expenditure Review Committee now for weeks running through these<br />
line items of outlays so as to get it back. But I think the important thing<br />
is that we will produce a Budget which is appropriate to Australia's<br />
economic circumstances and keep this competitiveness rolling.<br />
Let me just make this point again about Australia in Europe. I was able<br />
to go to Europe and say amongst other things, I am walking around<br />
with five per cent economic growth, two and a half per cent inflation,<br />
three and three quarter per cent employment growth and four per cent<br />
productivity growth, I am the only leader of a government in the OECD<br />
area, in the western world area, able to say those things. You know,<br />
three and three quarter per cent, we have had now 590,000 job growth<br />
since the last election, I mean, what happened at the last election<br />
John, essentially the Government was signed up again for three years<br />
to restart growth and get employment going. Now, if you look at the<br />
NSW election John Fahey is running around spending the state<br />
budgetary monies on this project, that project, but essentially it is<br />
coming off the Federal Government's growth policies. In other words,<br />
who has introduced the growth and the wealth and the change in the<br />
last three years? It is has been this Government.<br />
JL: OK, just back to this Budget, talk continues about taxation increases.<br />
One tax being talked about in the NSW election campaign is death<br />
duty or an inheritance tax, long-term goal of the Left wing of your party,<br />
everybody knows, and it was also one of the key recommendations put<br />
to you in the Fitzgerald Report on a national savings strategy. Are you<br />
ruling that out absolutely and totally?<br />
PM: I ruled that out at the last election.<br />
JL: But what about now? </p>
<p>PM: I mean, I made that very clear, but John, these old furphies have been<br />
around for a long time. The biggest taxing outfit around at the moment<br />
is NSW. Did you see that..<br />
JL: Yes, but hang on Prime Minister, you still didn't answer the question,<br />
are you ruling this out totally?<br />
PM: I am. I ruled it out last time, but John, I am not in the business of ruling<br />
in and ruling out taxes on radio.<br />
JL: Well, you did last time.<br />
PM: That was an election campaign.<br />
JL: I see, it is different then?<br />
PM: Well, you can start then on the excises, you know, beer, cigarettes,<br />
liquor, all these sorts of thing, I mean we could be sitting here for half<br />
an hour going through it. Look, the proof of the pudding is this John,<br />
which is the lowest taxed country in the developed world? This is,<br />
Australia, under this Government.<br />
JL: Yes, I am aware of that. But just back to what I said about death duty<br />
or inheritance taxes. When you say you are not in the habit of ruling<br />
things out on radio, you have done it before with me frequently, ruled<br />
things either in or out.<br />
PM: You get up to it, but I don't often come in on it.<br />
JL: Well, you have a few times, but listen I would have thought that this<br />
was the best place of the lot to rule it out when you have got about<br />
million people listening to you.<br />
PM: Well I have just made that one clear. What I suspect you are at is to<br />
go through another heap of them.<br />
JL: No, no, I am simply asking you about the death duty or inheritance tax,<br />
is it ruled out completely? I won't ask another question about that tax.<br />
PM: The answer to that is yes.<br />
JL: OK, so what does Ralph Willis mean when he talks about the need for<br />
action on both sides of the Budget, what does that mean?<br />
PM: That means receipts and outlays.<br />
JL: There is a lot of talk about company tax increases and you have just,<br />
again, cemented the fact firmly in our minds that we are a low taxed<br />
country, does that indicate to us that company tax might rise?<br />
PM: No, it doesn't, and again that is the point I am making, I can't go<br />
through the Budget here on radio. </p>
<p>JL: No, I don't want you to do that.<br />
PM: Well, I think you are trying to, you are getting around to it.<br />
JL: Well, I'll get as close as I can.<br />
PM: Let me just say this, one of these sorts of debates in this country, you<br />
have got Mr Howard running around saying ' oh, I think we ought to<br />
have lower taxation in this country'. He was the highest taxing<br />
Treasurer since the war and revenue to GDP was much higher under<br />
him. We have cut it. And, there you have got his mate in NSW, John<br />
Fahey, who has got the highest State taxes and charges than any<br />
other state in Australia.<br />
JL: Yes, a panel of economists today<br />
PM: I mean they are good.<br />
JL: Yes, well I suppose they are all in the same business. A panel of<br />
economists today are saying Australia can't sustain growth of over<br />
three to three and half per cent because higher rates of growth push<br />
up the rate of imports and imports on consumer products don't help us<br />
to much, we have got to get capital equipment in here. How do we<br />
escape this growth trap. I have been looking at some of the people<br />
who are saying it. Peter Costello is saying it very loudly and<br />
PM: Well, you can just discount anything he says. You wouldn't trust him<br />
with a jam jar full of five cent pieces.<br />
JL: " After 12 years of Keating rhetoric the fact is that everytime growth<br />
picks up it spills over into imports and Australia is faced with another<br />
current account deficit crisis, the current crisis is the third in the last<br />
decade and the second blow-out since the days of the ' banana<br />
republic'." Now, what do you say to Mr Costello?<br />
PM: What I say is this, that what we have to do in this country is to improve<br />
the capital stock. You can't do anything but produce your way out of<br />
your difficulties. Now, what happened in Australia in the 1970s with<br />
double digit inflation and in the earlier part of the 1980s is that the<br />
capital stock, that is the stock of equipment with which we produce our<br />
goods and services, fell into antiquity. We ended up with an industrial<br />
museum here by the early 1980s. John, one of the other things I was<br />
in Germany for was for CeBIT the information technology fair we<br />
had 170 Australian companies with leading edge technology as the<br />
guest country of that great international exhibition. This would have<br />
been inconceivable 10 years ago. We would have had maybe three<br />
companies there. There is now 170 with software, all sorts of niche IT<br />
technology. All this has come from the renewed industrial base of this<br />
country, but it has to be put into place. </p>
<p>Now, Australia does not have a mainframe computer manufacturing<br />
industry. It does not have a mainframe manufactured tool industry and<br />
so whenever we have an investment phase of strength we always see<br />
the current account move out of line. At the moment, I think the<br />
economy is slowing naturally. It is starting to slow down and that is<br />
fine.<br />
JL: If it slows down naturally, does that automatically mean that you won't<br />
increase interest rates?<br />
PM: We have already increased interest rates last year and, I think, at the<br />
right time to slow it so that it becomes sustainable with low inflation.<br />
JL: OK, but if it slows of its own accord, it is unlikely then that interest<br />
rates will rise?<br />
PM: Much more unlikely that interest rates will rise and that is why the<br />
Budget becomes, again, important. In other words, what we want is<br />
the highest rate of growth we can have which is sustainable with low<br />
inflation. What the Liberals would have given us is 1.5 to 2 per cent<br />
growth, like John Howard did through the 1970s. They had one fifth<br />
the level of employment growth that we had. Now, we averaged, I<br />
think, over 4 per cent GDP growth right through the 1980s. They<br />
averaged less than 2 per cent about 1.7 or 1.8 per cent. Anyone can<br />
hold inflation down by squeezing growth and employment out of the<br />
economy, but not anyone can hold inflation down with growth, that is<br />
the hard part.<br />
JL: OK, the Green movement is keeping up its pressure over what it sees<br />
as some sort of back down by you on the woodchip issue. Have you<br />
lost your patience with the sight of these fool protesters deliberately<br />
sabotaging forestry workers who are attempting to earn a living in a<br />
free country?<br />
PM: I think there has to be, as always, a balance in these things, but that<br />
story you are referring to says, you know, the Government has given<br />
up on the processes again. I mean, it is sort of a pro-green anti-forest<br />
story. Then the next story you will see will be a pro-forest anti-green<br />
story. I mean, the problem about The Sydney Morning Herald, it can<br />
never get that nice place in the middle where the Government and the<br />
community must be. That is, how do you have a sustainable forest<br />
products industry while at the same time looking after, as best you can,<br />
these important stands of trees and our national estate. That is the<br />
aim of the game and there is nothing that the Government is going to<br />
be doing that will detract from that.<br />
JL: I think it is a bit unfair to give The Sydney Morning Herald a bake, it<br />
was the ABC news.<br />
PM: It was on the front page. The story is on the front page of The Sydney<br />
Morning Herald saying.. </p>
<p>J L: Probably from the ABC news last night.<br />
PM: No, I don't think so. I think one is from the other and I think it was the<br />
other way around, but basically I mean, it is either all bad news for<br />
greens or it is all bad news for forests. There is nothing inbetween<br />
with them. In fact, what the Government has to do is do what, I think,<br />
most Australians want done and that is to have a sustainable forest<br />
products industry, but at the same time protect those important areas<br />
of native forest and forest with heritage values which are important to<br />
us all.<br />
JL: Are you going to reserve seats in Parliament for Aboriginal people?<br />
PM: That was a recommendation in the Justice Committee Report. That is<br />
something that we have got to think long and hard about. Can I just<br />
say though John, the Government and I think all Australians, including<br />
Aboriginal Australians have two very great victories in the last couple<br />
of weeks. While Mr Howard was in there asking improper questions<br />
under privilege with his mate Mr McLachlan, we had passed the Land<br />
Fund legislation and we had in the High Court the validation of the<br />
Native Title legislation. I mean, two huge landmark social and cultural<br />
changes in this country.<br />
JL: Will that do for a while or are you going to look at the idea of having<br />
reserved seats in Parliament for Aborigines?<br />
PM: We are now looking at the pressing problems of Aboriginal health and<br />
housing.<br />
JL: That's good. I hope you looked past ATSIC.<br />
PM: Well, I am just saying this. Have a look at the substance, I mean, you<br />
see all this crazy elements of the public debate, of people throwing<br />
muck around in the House, in Parliament, just see what the<br />
Government has done seven to zero on Native Title, Land Fund Bill<br />
passed and now we are moving on to Aboriginal health.<br />
JL: OK, we'll keep an eye on the Aboriginal health because, I think, that is<br />
an area that obviously needs great assistance and I don't believe they<br />
are getting the right assistance from ATS IC, but we'll talk about that on<br />
another occasion. Thank you very much, as usual, for your time.<br />
Good to talk to you.<br />
PM: A pleasure. Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
