<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6115</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO THE 1983 ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE NATIONAL FARMERS&#039; FEDERATION, 10AM, TUESDAY 17 MAY 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006115.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A~ Tl T1; 11 ; TE<br />
OAF. L: DR1LHES S ! IBAY7, 1IT; n! E PiI-L lI NI STEPR TO '; iE 1983 ANNUAL CONFEK NC?<br />
OF 1! E N I OAL FAIERS' FEDERATI N' 1, U O A" i, ILESDAYJ<br />
1 MIAY 1933<br />
i AM DELIGHTED TO BE HERE TODAY TO ADDRESS AND OFFICIALLY<br />
OPEN THE 1933 ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE NATIONAL FARMERS'<br />
FEDERATION, I HAVE BEEN IMPRESSED BY THE POSITIVE AND CONSTRUCTIVE<br />
ROLE PLAYED BY THE FEDERATION SINCE ITS FORMATION IN 1979,<br />
THE OBVIOUS SUCCESS OF THE FEDERATION IN ACTING AS THE<br />
RURAL SECTOR'S VOICE, WITH CLARITY AND FORCEFULNESS,<br />
IS CLEAR ENDORSEMENT OF FARM ORGANISATION AMALGAMATION,<br />
BY PUTTING FORWARD ON BEHALF OF THE RURAL SECTOR A WELL<br />
ARGUED POSITION WHICH HAS REGARD TO BROADER NATIONAL<br />
ECONOMIC ISSUES, THE FEDERATION DOES CONSIDERABLE SERVICE<br />
BOTH TO ITS MEMBERS AND THE COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE,<br />
SINCE BECOMING PRIME MINISTER I HAVE GREATLY APPRECIATED<br />
THE GOODWILL EXTENDED TO ME AND MY-GOVERNMENT BY PRIMARY<br />
PRODUCERS AND RURAL ORGANISATIONS. I HAVE RECEIVED<br />
INVITATIONS FROM MANY PARTS OF THE COUNTRY TO ADDRESS<br />
RURAL CONFERENCES AND OPEN AGRICULTURAL SOCIETY SHOWS<br />
AND FIELD DAYS, PRESSURES OF OFFICE WILL UNFORTUNATELY<br />
PREVENT MY ACCEPTING MANY OF THESE KIND INVITATIONS,<br />
HOWEVER, I TRUST MY PRESENCE HERE TODAY WILL UNDERLINE<br />
THE GOVERNMENT'S APPRECIATION OF THE VITAL CONTRIBUTION<br />
THE RURAL COMMUNITY MAKES TO OUR NATIONAL ECONOMY, S, 2/, </p>
<p>11 Nin SEEK iIn[ AaN TH RLS; P: C* AND, SUPPORT<br />
uFTHR .7IAL S ECTOR Ti QOL'C THE APPL ICAVION OF SOUND AND<br />
RATONAL PbL ' 71 BASED ON C( Th7JLTA' ION ANID THEV NATICNAI..<br />
INT EREST,<br />
PRIMARY lND. U HAS A NEW AND ENE9FFTIC M iNICER WIT1 H A<br />
S T ,: ON AG I CULTUPAL EAC KGRc'UND, I UNDERSTAND THAT<br />
joUHN KLR IN HAS AL READY DEVELOPED A CLOSE AND CUjNSTRUCT IvE<br />
AORKIN3 RE. T IONSHIP WITH THF FEDERJ'TICN, WV REFLECTS<br />
I N PARIT % ULAR CONTACT SET WEEN MP KERN AND THE FECRAT ION<br />
07ER fE ; PAOT COUPLE OF YEARS, As A MFieER OF THE<br />
MiNORTANI ECONOMIC AND INDUSTR'; COMMITTEES OF CABINEIT<br />
HE IS ! N A % OOD POSITION TO PRGTECT THE INTERESTS OF THE<br />
RURA. L SETCTOR,<br />
JOHN KERIN WILL BE ADDRESSING YOU TOMORROW, CONSEQUENTLY,<br />
WILL CONFINE MY REMARKS MAINLY TO THE GENERAL DIRECTION<br />
OF THE UOVERNMENT S POLICIES AND ALLOW JOHN TO ADDRESS<br />
SONE MORE SPECIFICALLY RURAL POLICIES,<br />
IN THE RURAL POLICY SPEECH WHICH I DELIVERED IN GRIFFITH<br />
DURING THE FEDERATION ELECTION CAMPAIGN, I MADE AN<br />
UNQUALIFIED CONMITMENT TO MAINTAINING THE VIABILITY<br />
OF AUSTRALIA'S GREAT RURAL SECTOR AND THE PROVINCIAL<br />
INFRASTRUCTURE, I HAVE NO HESITATION IN REAFFIRMING<br />
TH IS COMM ITMENT, i. t 3/ 1 </p>
<p>ALL. AUSTAL: S WERE GREATL'Y LI LVLD ' 4HEN THERE WE? GOOD<br />
RAINS OVER MUCH OF THE COUNTRY OVER ' 11E PAST TWO MONVHS<br />
IF MtORE NORMAL SEASONAL CONDITIONS CON I NUE TiiROUGH INTO<br />
THE SPRING AND BEYOND, FARMERS IN EASTERN AUSTRALIA<br />
WILL BE ABLE TO BEGIN THE LONG PROCESS OF RECOVERY<br />
FROM THE DROUGHT,<br />
THE GOVERNMENT RECOGNISES THE POTENTIAL CONTRIBUTION OF<br />
RURAL RECOVERY TO OVERALL DOMESTIC ECONOMIC RECOVERY,<br />
BUT, OF COURSE, GOOD RAIN ALONE WILL NOT BE SUFFICIENT<br />
TO SUSTAIN RECOVERY,<br />
THE GENERAL STATE OF THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY IS OF THE<br />
UTMOST CONCERN TO FARMERS THERE IS AN OVERRIDING NEED<br />
TO GET INTEREST RATES AND INFLATION DOWN TO MAINTAIN<br />
INTERNATIONAL COMPETITIVENESS OF OUR PRODUCTS, TO EXPAND<br />
OUR MARKETS AND TO GET THE ECONOMY MOVING,<br />
SINCE ASSUMING OFFICE, SOME TWO MONTHS AGO, THE GOVERNMENT<br />
HAS TAKEN A NUMBER OF STEPS TO SET AUSTRALIA ON THE ROAD<br />
TO NATIONAL RECOVERY, NATIONAL RECONCILIATION AND<br />
NATIONAL RECONSTRUCTION.<br />
WE HAVE BEGUN THE PROCESS OF GETTING BUSINESS AND UNIONS<br />
TO UNDERSTAND EACH OTHER BETTER, TO UNDERSTAND EACH<br />
OTHER'S PROBLEMS AND VIEWPOINT, AND TO WORK TOGETHER<br />
TO PROMOTE THEIR MUTUAL INTEREST, AN IMPORTANT<br />
ELEMENT OF THIS APPROACH, WHICH WILL BE PART OF OUR i, </p>
<p>ONGOING TASK OVER THE YEARS O UJM IS TO LND iHE<br />
ARTIFICIAL CONFLICT OF INTEREST LETWEEN CIT' AND COUNTRY,<br />
THERE ARE IN MY OPINION, PAR TOO MANY MISUNDERSTANDINGS<br />
BY CITY PEOPLE OF THE PROBLEMS AND NEEDS OF COUNTRY<br />
PEOPLE, AS A PARTY, AND NOW AS A GOVERNMENT, WE REJECT COMPLETELY<br />
THE CONCEPT OF CONFLICT BETWEEN CITY AND COUNTRY, WE<br />
DEPEND ON EACH OTHER AND WE NEED EACH OTHER,<br />
AT THE OUTSET OUR FIRST MAJOR TASK IS TO CLEAR THE GROUND<br />
SO THAT WE CAN BEGIN TO END DIVISIONS, ACHIEVE SOME<br />
RECOGNITION OF OUR COMMON GOALS AND OBTAIN AN APPRECIATION<br />
OF THE NATURE OF THE TASK WHICH THE NATION HAS BEFORE IT,<br />
THIS HAS INVOLVED A GREAT DEAL OF CONSULTATION AND<br />
INFORMATION-SHARING.<br />
THE NATIONAL ECONOMIC SUMMIT CONFERENCE ITSELF WAS AN<br />
IMPORTANT PART OF THAT PROCESS; AND IT WILL BE A<br />
CONTINUING PROCESS,<br />
THE PART PLAYED AT THE CONFERENCE BY THE NFF WAS MOST<br />
VALUABLE. THE POINTS MADE IN THE FEDERATION'S SUBMISSION<br />
AND IN STATEMENTS MADE BY YOUR PRESIDENT, MICHAEL<br />
DAVIDSON, HAVE BEEN CAREFULLY NOTED, </p>
<p>FARMERS WILL BE REPRESENTED ON THE ECONOMIC PLANNING<br />
ADVISORY COUNCIL, WHICH WILL BE CONTINUING THE WORK<br />
OF THE SUMMIT, THE COUNCIL WILL HAVE AN IMPORTANT<br />
ROLE IN ADVISING ON ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENTS AND<br />
PROVIDING A FORUM FOR COMMUNITY CONSULTATION ON NATIONAL<br />
ECONOtNIC AND SOCIAL STRATEGIES.<br />
THE SU.', MIT LED TO WIDESPREAD UNDERSTANDING OF THE SERIOUSNESS<br />
OF THE PRESENT ECONOMIC CRISIS AND AGREEMENT ON HOW<br />
BEST TO PROCEED FROM HERE, IHE IMPORTANCE OF ACHIEVING<br />
RESTRAINT Itl INCOME CLAIMS BY ALL BUT THE IMPOVERISHED<br />
WAS RECOGNISED, AS WAS THE NEED TO FIGHT INFLATION<br />
AND UNEMPLOYMENT TOGETHER,<br />
WE CAME TO OFFICE WITH THE PLEDGE TO PURSUE EXPANSIONARY<br />
POLICIES WHICH EMPHASISE JOBS, THAT IS STILL OUR AIM,<br />
HOWEVER, WE FOUND ON COMING TO OFFICE THAT THE RECKLESS<br />
FISCAL POLICY OF THE LIBERAL GOVERNMENT IN ITS LAST<br />
YEAR WOULD, UNLESS CORRECTED, LEAD TO A $ 9.6 BILLION<br />
DEFICIT IN 1983/ 84, THIS MEANT THAT THERE WAS A NEED<br />
TO REIN IN THE DEFICIT AT THE SAME TIME AS WE ENCOURAGED<br />
INCREASED ACTIVITY, THIS WAS NECESSARY TO MAINTAIN<br />
INTEREST RATES ON A DOWNWARD PATH AND MAINTAIN ECONOMIC<br />
STABILITY, 6/. </p>
<p>ij, L. i i<br />
CIP E FF1L I I CTE2Iy AONIh HSO<br />
Li: I-SCAL FOG I C O~ CO~ lJlSV IiA 3S~ lN I<br />
-N VE R1E V E1CAOKNEOMIC STAIL TYE,<br />
LAINGS ' Y CUTTING THE PROGIRAMS O O R P E D C SSORS At; D ALSO<br />
I CEE OLR TAX COLLECTIONS. H( E SPEC [ AL CONC EPRN OF Y<br />
GOVFRNM"-;' T ALSO RUIURE US O MAKE R' OtN iOR PROGRAMS TO,<br />
2O: OTE EMPLOYMENT AND TO I NCREASEE EQUITY IN THE wAY THtE<br />
BUD AFE" CGETTS IHL COMMU!; NIT. TY,<br />
IHERE IS NO SUCH THING AS A PAI: LESS EXPENDITURE CUT OR<br />
TAX INCR EAE. THE RESTORATION OF FISCAL RESPONSIBILITY AND<br />
ECONOMIC STAEILiTY REQUJIRES SACRIFCE, Y GVENMENT'S AiM<br />
IS TO ENSURE. THAT T! : ACR fITICL iS BORNE EQUITABLY ACROSS<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN C MUITIYT YTHABLYA NS H AE IN A<br />
RELA 1Y-1FI LY ( GOOD' iPOo ' TO BE A iT,<br />
NE A S A GOVERNMENT WERE NOT PREPARED TO LET THE BUDGET DEFICIT<br />
PREVET US FROM IMPLEMENTING OUR PROGRAMS TO STIMULATE<br />
EM'-PLOYMEINT AND TO PROMICTE EQUITY, To GET AUSTRALIA MOVING WHILE<br />
RESTORI. NG ECONIC STABIL. ITY, THE TREASURER WILL1 BE MAKING A<br />
MAJO STATEMENT ON THE ECONOY ON ' HURSDTAHIYS WEEK<br />
WE ARE NOW EXPECTING REASONABLY STRONG GROWTH NEXT FINANCIAL<br />
YEAR, AS TH-iE POLICIES 1' O BE ANNOIUNCED BY THE TREASURER TAKE<br />
-7 </p>
<p>F ELT THLE R EC 1-N T RE 0: L" J 1 SS S A ND C 0N i~ lER<br />
CONF~~~ I-DEiC AS TH') E? T3T RNTESF ' HE RECENT<br />
~) EALATC~ f-LOW THROUC; H TO NCY&amp; AND INVESTMENT, AND AS<br />
iNFLATION AN-1D IWI EREST RAT ES i' 1DERATE WE EXPECT THEMl TO<br />
UNDER OUR POLICIES,<br />
HE RU: RAL C. OAIM UNITY, LIKE ALL OTH. EP PARTS OF THE AUSTPALIAN<br />
COMNl-' UNiCY, MlUST ACCEPT ITS SHAPE 0CF FISCAL RESTRAINT,<br />
SOME OF THE MEASURES THAT WE WOULD L-IKE TO IMPLEMEliT TO ASIST<br />
THE RURAL SECTOR MUST, I AMl AFRAID, WAIT FOR IMPROVED BUDGETARY<br />
CONDITIONS, BUT THE OTHER SIDE OF THE COIN IS THAT RURAL<br />
COPiljJ-NITIES WILL SHARE, PERHAPS OR THAN OTHiEP[ AUSTRALIANS,<br />
IN THE BENEFITS C. F THE FISCAL RESTRAINT, WHICH WILL TAKE THE<br />
FORM OF MODERATION OF INTEREST RATES AND COST INCREASES.<br />
CAN ASSURE YOU THAT TrHE GOVERNMENT IS POSITIVELY DISPOSED<br />
TOWARDS THE RURAL SECTOR, AND THAT THIS WILL BE REFLECTED IN<br />
THE OVERAL. L M'lIX OF ECONOMIC POLICIES, THE GOVERNMENT IS<br />
COMM ITTED TO PROGRESSIVE LONG-TERM POLICIES DESIGNED TO<br />
ENSURE A STRONG RURAL SECTOR.<br />
THE NIFF HAS ALWAYS ARGUED THAT AUSTRALIAN TRADE POLICIES ARE<br />
CR UCTI TO THE PROSPERITY OF AUSTRALIA'S RURAL INDUSTRIES,<br />
THE FCEDERAT ION IS RIGHT TO DO SO. IT IS RIGHT TO POItIT OUT<br />
THE COST THAT PROTECTION FOR AUSTRALIA'S MANUFACTURING<br />
INDUSTRY IMPOSES ON AUSTRALIAN FARMERS, I HAVE NOTED REPORTS<br />
OF THE FEDERATION'S RECENT REPRESENTATIONS ON STEEL IMPORT<br />
19 ,/ 1 </p>
<p>U IlkS S, l SAY' ThAi SE:~ SO" I" M-ER-r I N iA<br />
SHE SAEEt ' E NO E HLRLN LINEMPL. O'YMENTl AT RECORD LEVLLS,<br />
S 13T T IME TO REDUCI: iMANUFAC'TUJRI NG PROTECT ION. TL IE<br />
L: R FAC y; A D I LIiIM CAIN ASSURE! Jp--YOU THAT AS wEI<br />
, T T IXP T1 R ESO0L VE 11H IS D I LEMA, WE -I'L L B E T AKI1NG YO.<br />
:~ LENATI H2I N 0O ACCOUNT, E DO NOT SEE THE SOLU_ ION TO<br />
AiU TR AL I A'S E COJNONA I C P ROB LEMN! S I N I N CRE As i-I Nj P RO0T ECT I oN,<br />
H E VE DERAT 0; 1IS A LSO R I GHT TOU E I" Pi A S I S IHE I NPOR TANC E<br />
T o AUST2! AL_ A A A WHOLE OF ACCES'S 10 OVERSEAS MARKETS FOR<br />
K: A ' ODUtC-' T3 S L. iK E THE PREVIOIUS GOVERNIM2NT, WE ARE<br />
CONCRNETH * HE RULES OF TjHE I NTERNAT lI ONAL_ TR0ADING<br />
SYS TEM DllS'CRIINAT E ACGA IN ST A I S FRA 1L A AND OTHC EFFIC I ENT<br />
: RODUCERS OF F: OOD. IWILL HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO EXPLORE<br />
TEEISSUES WrITH FRENCH AND AMERICAN LEADERS NEXT MONTH, AND<br />
D W'' ELCOME THE FEDERATION'S ADVICE ON PRIORITIES AND<br />
STRATEGiES ON INTERNATIONAL MARKET ACCESS FOR AUSTRALIAN FOOD.<br />
IKNOW THAT YOU HAVE BEEN ESPECIALLYWWORRIED ABOUT<br />
INDUSTRIAL RLELATIONS IN THE RURAL INDUSTRIES. No ONE IS<br />
MORE A'IAREL THAN AM OF THE SERIOUS IMPACT OF POOR INIDUSTRIAL<br />
* RELATIONS ON THE PRIMARY PRODUCERS OF AUSTRALIA, I HAVE<br />
COMIT T ED IMY GOVERNMENT TO0 INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS POLIC" IES<br />
WH ICH, BELIEVE, WILL VASTLY IMPROVE THE GENERAL INDUSTRIAL<br />
CLIMATE IIN AJSTRALIA, IN PUT7ING THOSE POLICIES INTO EFFECT,,<br />
t. 1 </p>
<p>vE ILL DE PART CiIAARHLEY MIHDFUL OT iNTERESTS OF<br />
PR IMARY PUDUlC LER S<br />
THE P1I ' N ISTER FOR LENPLOYMENT AND I NDUSl1 RI AL RELA TIONS,<br />
RALPH ILLIS) HAS WORKED TIRELESSLY TO RESOLVE THE<br />
JNFORT: JNATE WIDE COMG! 3S DISPUWEi, HAT EFFORT HAS<br />
CONTR* BUTED CONSIDERABLY TO THE PROGRESS THAT HAS BEEN<br />
MADE ON THIS ISSUE.<br />
I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING CLOSELY WITH THE NATIONAL FARMERS<br />
EDERATION. I PESPECT THE FEDERATION'S PROFESSIONAL<br />
APPROACH TO ITS ROLE. THAT PROFESSIONALISM HAS GIVEN THE<br />
" IARi IHG COMMUNI Y A RESPEC 7LD V'( ICE NEAR GOVERNMENT JUST<br />
AS I APPRECIATED fICHAEL DAVIDSON'S HELP AT THE SUMMIT,<br />
LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH THE FEDERATION W; ITHIN AC,<br />
AS WELL AS LESS FORMALLY, OVER THE YEARS AHEAD.<br />
GOOD LUCK WITH THE BUILDING OF NFF HOUSE HERE IN CANBERRA,<br />
I AM TOLD THAT PLANS ARE WELL ADVANCED AND THAT FUND RAISING<br />
IS CLOSE TO THE TARGET EQUITY OF $ 1.5 MILLION PLANNED FOR THE<br />
PROJECT, I HOPE CONSTRUCTION WILL PROCEED SMOOTHLY AND LOOK<br />
FORWARD TO ITS COMPLETION IN I938,<br />
SWOULD LIKE TO WISH EVERYONE ASSOCIATED WITH FARMING GOOD<br />
FORTUNE IN -: THE PERIOD AHEAD. WITH THE BREAK IN THE DROUGHT<br />
AND SIGNS OF IMPROVEMENT IN THE WORLD ECONOMY TOGETHER WITH<br />
APPROPRIATE POLICY RESPONSES WITHIN AUSTRALIA AND CO-OPERATION<br />
ALL AROUND, I AM CONFIDENT WE CAN OVLRCOME THE PROBLEMS WHICH<br />
FACE US,<br />
I DECLARE THIS CONFERENCE OPLN, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
