<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1779</transcript-id>
    <title>HIGGINS BY - ELECTION CAMPAIGN OPENING SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON CAULFIELD TOWN HALL, MELBOURNE 13TH FEBRUARY, 1968</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/02/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001779.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
HIGGINS BY-ELECTION CAMPAIGN<br />
OPENING SPEECH BY THEE PRIME MINISTER, N BR&gt;<br />
JOHN GORTON<br />
Caulfield Town Hall, Melbourne 13TH FEBRUARY, 1968<br />
Mr Ch~ airman, Mr Premier, Wr Anthony, Mr McMahon, Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
I come before you tonight as a candidate for t he seat of.<br />
Higgins, seeking the endorsement of the electors of Higgins, and asking<br />
them to place me In that situation which was previously held by a great<br />
Australian who led this country for two years. This is, in essence, a<br />
by-election, a request to the electors of Higgins in particular that they<br />
should think me worthy, as I hope they will, to fill that place so tragically<br />
vacated by Mr Holt. I would try and fill it as well as he did.<br />
I must say to the electors of Higgins tonight, and to those<br />
people In Australia who may be outside this hall or outside the electorate<br />
tonight, the attitudes which I would adopt, the approaches which my Government<br />
would adopt, towards the future progress of this, our joint country. But<br />
there is something I must say to you at once, and that is that this is not<br />
tonight, this speech, and I think it ought not to be, a policy speech in the<br />
sense that policy speeches are made at general elections. This is no<br />
time at a by-election, being held two-thirds of a way through a financial<br />
year for which a government has budgeted, for which it has struck a rate of<br />
taxation, for which it has assessed expenditure and income, to launch out<br />
into new promises involving new expenditure, and either new rates of<br />
taxation or increases in deficit.<br />
Indeed, I think that a mini-policy at this time could well<br />
be held to be irresponsible. Rather, I think, is this a time to express to<br />
the electorate and to Australia, our approaches to the needs of Australia,<br />
the goals which we will set ourselves to try and attain as and when we can,<br />
the course on which we will seek to steer our country towards the future<br />
years of greatness which lie in store for us.<br />
And so I shall talk to you tonight of the settled policies<br />
which we have adopted and will continue to adopt on defence, on foreign<br />
affairs, on relations with our neighbours, for on these things, indeed, may<br />
depend in the ultimate our capacity eventually, acting as a free people, to<br />
work out our own destiny and to decide what our domestic progress will<br />
indeed be. Having spoken of these th ings, this touchstone which may<br />
decide the future of Australia as an Independent nation, then I shall seek to<br />
put before you certain domestic matters, and the approaches and the emphasis<br />
which we would put on these domestic matters.<br />
First let me talk to you on the question of Defence.<br />
I have said that on our efforts here may well depend our capacity in future<br />
years to decide our own destiny and to run our own affairs. This calls now,<br />
In the state of the world as it is at present, for a significant and an onerous<br />
effort from the Australian people, and an effort which all of us would wish,<br />
were circumstances different, could be put not into an Insurance policy but<br />
into the kind of development for which our effort in defence could do so much. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
However great the effort we make In defence and it is<br />
becoming great In no future that I can foresee can we In Australa rely<br />
on ourselves alone, or remain secure without alliance with some friendly<br />
and significantly powerful ally, having the same approach to life as we<br />
Australians have... ( Interjection " The same old line") and a true old<br />
line and a line on which Australia has depended for more than a century<br />
and a half, from the United Kingdom.<br />
For us, though we can look to, and though I am sure we<br />
would in a crisis be given military assistance in time of need by the United<br />
Kingdom, who for over a century and a half has been our shield and our<br />
buckler, and to whom, if blood be the price of protection Lord God, we<br />
have paid in full, but who has for that period of time protected us, and to<br />
whom we could still look for protection, yet the changing years have<br />
ordained that In the ultimate, the security of this small nation now depends<br />
on its alliance with the United States, and on protection from the United<br />
States. No small nation such as ours can, in the world as it is today, I<br />
suggest to you, iive with happiness and security and safety without<br />
protection of that kind.<br />
This Is a fact which places on us, as I believe, a duty of<br />
being an ally, when we think the United States Is right, in the fullest sense<br />
of the word, of being prepared to contribute, as we have been prepared to<br />
contribute In the past, and not merely to receive and give nothing In return.<br />
That, as a basis for a defence policy for Australia is, I believe, essential<br />
for our future security. That is why the expenditure on defence In this<br />
country has risen until it is this year 118 million, and with commitments<br />
we have already entered Into and which will flow from the commitments<br />
we have already entered into, will in the two years ahead Increase above that<br />
figure. It is not a sum which alone can afford us security but It Is the<br />
smallest sum which, I suggest to you, we can with honour expend, and as<br />
a result of it, expect that protection which may be necessary for our future<br />
progress. ( Interjection " Not for my son, Clive)<br />
Well, I don't know where your son, Olive, is sir, but there<br />
are a number of other sons of a number of other Austraan s in the past, now<br />
and in the future who no doubt would be prepared to back what I have said<br />
for the sake of their country.<br />
That, Mr Chairman, leads me to a discussion on the<br />
position which past governments have taken up and which this government<br />
will sustain on the matter of our involvement In Viet Nam. I believe our<br />
policy In Viet Nam, the policy of the Government, ought to be stated, or<br />
rather, re-stated clearly, and I shall try to do this.<br />
Firstly, we believe that the United States was right, uni er<br />
President Kennedy in the later half of 1961, to accede to the South Vietnamese<br />
request for military assistance to counter a military Incursion from the<br />
North. And we believe the United States Is right, under President Johnson,<br />
to have continued and to continue the courg-efirst mapped by President<br />
Kennedy in this matter. We believe that when the original decision was made armed<br />
attacks were being made on South Viet Nam, and that those attacks were<br />
Instigated, controlled, supplied and maintained by the North Vietnamese o 9 / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
which provided regular troops to assist and command the insurgents. We<br />
believe that in spite of the terrorist activity carried on since that time,<br />
local support has so fallen off In South Viet Nam that more and more North<br />
Vietnamese regular armed troops have been deployed in the South, and that<br />
the fighting has assumed the character of an invasion of South Viet Nam by<br />
the Government of North Viet Nam, just as there was previously an Invasion<br />
of SoUth Korea by the Government of North Korea.<br />
It is true thts is aggression by a communist govenment<br />
seeking to Impose its rule by force, but the prime reason for preventing<br />
It succeeding is not because of its source, not because it stems, as it happens<br />
to In this case, from a communisat country, but because it Is aggression.<br />
That Is the reason for opposing it.<br />
For I believe, and I suggest to all you Australians that<br />
what best promotes our national security and the national security of other<br />
small States, what best guarantees our national survival, along with the<br />
survival of other small powers as truly Independent nations, Is that we<br />
should havo a world in which aggression by one nation or part of one nation<br />
against another is shown to be unsuccessful and does not succeed In whole<br />
or in part. For if it is seen to succeed, then It Is likely as our history<br />
has shown " as the history In tbe lifetimze of inumy people in this hall<br />
has shown -if it Is seen to be successful, then It Is likely to be repeated and<br />
repeated and repeated until eventually it must be stopped at a cost greater in<br />
de~ truction, In pain and in loss of life than would have been required had it<br />
been stopped at its Inception.<br />
That is why Australians fought against the aggressions of<br />
Hitler which succeeded one another until they had to be stopped... ( Cheers)<br />
Sir, If you are prepared to cheer Hitler, I am not, any more than I am<br />
prepared to cheer a communist dictator or any other governing power which<br />
seeks to impose its wish by force upon some other independent nation.<br />
That Is why Australians fought with the United Nations in<br />
Korea against an attack on South Korea by North Korean naked aggression.<br />
That is why Australians opposed the militant expression<br />
of confrontation between Indonese-a and Malaysia, opposed it In conjunction<br />
with the United Kingdom. And that is why we are right, as I believe, to<br />
help our ally, the United States, In South Viet Nam.<br />
We shall continue to take the action we are now taking<br />
for as long it is necessary to help attain the objective of preventing the<br />
success of North Vietnamese aggression. At the same time, we have always<br />
realised that the military effort In Viet Nam, although absolutely necessary,<br />
is only one of the components required In this kind of war.<br />
The other component is the raising of standards of everyday<br />
living in the areas where military forces provide a shield for the civilian<br />
population a shield which can, of course, be pierced but which can prevent<br />
the destruction of what Is sought to be done to raise living standards.<br />
Let me, ladies and gentlemen, at this time, put to you an Illustration of<br />
what I mean by that. I', t one stage, I was in charge of running the Colombo Plan 9 / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
for Australia, and in an attempt to help the people of South Viet Nam, quite<br />
some years ago, we sought to take over we did take over a tract of land<br />
of a kind which was not being used in that country because it was thought that<br />
it could be in no way productive. By the introduction of special kinds of<br />
legumes, of a manurial programme, we were able on that land to grow and to<br />
show surrounding farmers there could be grown pastures on which cattle<br />
could be grazed, and were able to set up a dairy farm at Ben Cat which provided<br />
for the first time in history for the children of Saigorl pasteurised milk groyni<br />
in that experimental farm and sent to the city.<br />
This was an illustration to the people of that region of what<br />
could be done. You can, from your own minds, Imagine what would have<br />
happened there to inlcrease living standards had this been permitted to succeed,<br />
but it was not permitted to succeed. It was not permitted to succeed because;<br />
that farm was attacked, those cattle were slaughtered by the Viet Cong<br />
regulars who did not wish living standards to be increased, because if they<br />
were so increased, then it would show that we were able to provide a better.<br />
standard of life than they themselves could do.<br />
This is why there is a need for this protection of this civil<br />
action. An d that is why from the very beginning, our army In Viet Nam has<br />
been provided with money to carry out its own civil aid programme in the:<br />
villages, to help with the medical treatment of the villagers, to help in the<br />
small matters which mean so much to them the construction of a school.<br />
house, the construction of a small culvert, the construction of a small<br />
infirmary and the provision of village industries. These are the things which<br />
go hand in hand with what we are trying to do, and the things which must.....<br />
dyooue s suagnygbeostdiyn gd itshaagt rtehee? s e Itsh itnhgesr em suosmt en omt buer mduonr e, o f tdhiasta gwree emmuesnt t? n ot sAereek* to<br />
build up the living standards of the villagers and the townsfolk? Because if<br />
you do suggest that, then I can understand why you would oppose the policy<br />
which we adopt. But If you dont, if you believe these should be built up and<br />
should be shielded while they are being built up, then you must support what<br />
we have done. To sum up our policy, Mr Chairman: We believe it right....<br />
( interjections) Oh, yes, I think these policies should be summed up, don't<br />
you? There has been a marked reluctance to sum them up In some quarters<br />
on this matter. We believe It right to maintain the elementary right of the<br />
South Vietnamese people to determine their own future, as they showed in.<br />
recent elections they were capable of doing. We will continue to provide,<br />
as we are providing, significant and effective military assistance to the<br />
allied effort to achieve this aim, and we will provide it for as long as we are<br />
called upon to help achieve this aim.<br />
We will support, as we have supported, the many efforts by<br />
the United States and the United Nations for discussions seeking a negotiat ed<br />
end to the war and a settlement which provides the South Vietnamese with a<br />
just and an enduring peace under which they can determine their own future.<br />
The United States has amply demonstrated Its desire for such discussions,<br />
the United Nations has sought to help the United States to obtain such discussions,<br />
but so far every such proposal has been rejected, whether it came from the<br />
United Nations or the United States, by the North Vietnamese.<br />
But, TMr President, there is one thing we will not do. We will<br />
I </p>
<p>not urge on the United States that there should be discussions designed<br />
solely to negotiate methods of surrendering the South Vietnamese to thie<br />
rule of the North, which Is a course which sometimes seems to be suggested<br />
in this country. Nor will we urge on them that bombing designed to. impede<br />
the flow of men and materials to the South, as distinct from bombing on a<br />
civilian population men and materials travelling down to kill Australian<br />
ca~ d Ameri1can troops -should be ectopped as a condition Imposed by the Viet<br />
Cong for possible talks with no compensating conditions as to holding up the<br />
sending of such men and material.<br />
We will, insofar as we can, continue to seek to Improve the<br />
economic lot and the living conditions of the villagers in the area In which<br />
our troops operate, for we coneider this to be a vital and necessary task and<br />
one which must, as soon as possible, be tackled through out the whole of<br />
South Viet Nam. We will do it by continuing and expanding what we are<br />
already doing.... ( Interjection If you hadn't Interjected you would have heard.<br />
I will repeat It: By providing to the villagers the simple medical treatment<br />
there required, by building school houses in the villages, by fostering<br />
co-operatives In the villages and providing fertilisers so that their crops<br />
can be yi by providing wells for pure water. Not by vast overriding<br />
ioV% 49ab~ n approaches, but by getting down to the grass roots,<br />
as we have been getting down to the grass roots In our area. That, sir, is<br />
how we will do It, and that, sir, Is something I believe the people of South<br />
Viet Nam understand and will appreciate, now want, and will want In the<br />
future. I was seeking to spell out, before I was diverted, a policy<br />
which we are going to implement, and I have sought to spell it out In simple<br />
words, and words which can be understood by all, as I hope they will have<br />
been. But this thing that I am discussing Is one of moment to the present<br />
and to the future of Australia, one of moment to the association between<br />
this nation and the United States, and therefore It is a matter of great public<br />
concern. That Is why I have sought so carefully to try to put before* you,<br />
whether you agree with It or not, what we are doing and what we will continue<br />
to do. I bd ieve that on matters of this moment clear statements of<br />
policy ought to be made.<br />
But I do suggest this. Australians are denied or have so far<br />
been denied any clear statement of policy on this matter by the Opposition.<br />
It is true that last year the Federal Labor Confcrence, by resolution<br />
( Interjection) adopted a policy which you clap which requires that the<br />
United States should cease bombing North Viet Nam e~ n conditionally<br />
( Cheers' Fine, fine, you express your opinion. This is what the Federal<br />
Labor Conference adopted, and no doubt those who applauded agree with it,<br />
as Is your right. They adopted a policy that the United States shctild<br />
recognise the National Liberation Front the Viet Cong as a principal<br />
party to negotiations ( boos... I don't know who you are booing, but I takce<br />
it you are booing the Viet Cong. They adopted a policy that the United<br />
States should transfcrm operations In South Viet Nam Into holding operations,<br />
which means staying where you are and repelling attacks and allowing attacks. to<br />
be concentrated and mounted against you and just pushing them back but not<br />
doing anything to prevent them from materialising, or to move out Into<br />
country surrounded by the enemy.<br />
Now that is the policy that was adopted, I agree, by the<br />
Federal Labor Conference. A further policy adopted was that If the United<br />
States-did not accept this ultimatum on all these three points, then the / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
Australian Government must withdraw Its armied forces' ( Interjections)<br />
which, of course and those of you who clap, if you are Intellectually<br />
honest must admit this means abandoning the expression of the United.<br />
States / Australian alliance In Viet Nam.<br />
Now these were resolutions adopted at the 1967 Conference<br />
of the Australian Labor Party, and the Rules and Standing Orders of that<br />
party state " The Federal Conference shall be the supreme governing<br />
authority of the party.. : XInterjector " Hear, hear")<br />
Well I think there is at least one man in Australia who disagrees with you,<br />
f I heard him properly on<br />
0 and its decision shall be binding upon every member and<br />
every section of the party.<br />
So it would seem, would it not, that this policy of presenting an ultimatum<br />
and withdrawing all Australian troops, if It is not accepted, is the policy<br />
of the Opposition, one would think.<br />
But the present Leader of the Opposition refuses either to<br />
confirm or to deny that this is the policy by which he is bound and which he<br />
and his supporters are bound to carry out, and indeed, has Indicated that<br />
no matter what the Federal Conference says, he is supreme and not bound<br />
by It. I don't know whether that is true or not, but the people of<br />
Australia ought to be told whether it Is true or not, because I think it fair to<br />
say that there is an attempt here to blur the issue, to slither away from<br />
questions and to be evasive. And further, I think it fair to say<br />
( Interjector " Where Is your policy?) Where's my policy? I stated<br />
it in explicit terms we are continuing to do what we have decided to do<br />
because we think It right. Now that is clear, explicit and cannot be<br />
misunderstood. I think It fair to say that if the Leader of the Opposition<br />
is bound by the official policy, as I believe he Is, then carrying out that<br />
policy would severely damage our relations with the United States and would<br />
weaken, If not destroy, that Australian/ United States alliance on which our<br />
future security could so much depend, and which the Opposition policy pays<br />
is so important that they are going to withdraw Australian troops unless<br />
the United States accepts an ultimatum in order to maintain the alliance<br />
they regard as so important.<br />
There is, therefore, I do believe, In the Interests of<br />
proper ly-informed democratic debate, an obligation on the Leader of the<br />
Opposition clearly to state whether he is inund to adhere to official Labor<br />
policy, and whether he will do so, and if not, how he can avoid doing so,<br />
assuming he wishes not to do so. And that ought to be a question which<br />
could be answered In as simple terms as I have spelt out our policy tonight,<br />
and is a question to which the Australian people have a right to an answer,<br />
when forming a judgment, even In H-glns where there is an opponent<br />
adopting some sort of policy I don't know what against the Government.<br />
They ought to know precisely what that policy is if they are to form a<br />
considered judgment in the way a democracy should do so.<br />
Mr Fresident, moving on from that particular matter, I come<br />
to another area which is of great import ance to this nation and to the future / 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
of this nation, and that is the effect of what Is happening now, or what<br />
Will happen in the future, in Malaysia, in Singapore, countries so close to<br />
us; indeed, the closest countries to our shcv., s, I think, except that of our<br />
closest neighbour, Indonesia.<br />
In this field, there are questions of maintaining a military<br />
presence in Malaysia and Singapore, and of assistance in raising the<br />
economic activity and helping the economic progress of that region.<br />
Why? Because we hope that by assisting the economic progress of that<br />
region we will see, and we must see if this assistance Is to be fully<br />
effective, that that assistance leads to an incmiase in the standards of<br />
living of the people In the villages, the hamlets and the towns of those<br />
countries. That is the end result that we are seeking.<br />
On the military side, Great Britain has for long maintained<br />
In Malaysia and Singapore naval, air and ground forces and the bases from.<br />
which they can operate, and has maintained them as a stabilising force'In<br />
that area. They have been Intended to prevent, and they have prevented<br />
with Australian forces participating, local armed insurgency and attack~ s by<br />
one country in the region on any other. And so they were Instrumental<br />
in preventing the communist insurgency Irn Malaysia when it took place,<br />
supported at the time by many of the people who now support the same sort<br />
of insurgency elsewhere, and the Australians helped In that. They were<br />
able, If not to stop it, to discourage it to the extent that It ceased, the<br />
armed expression of confrontation of k1donoin against Malaysia.<br />
Now for some time, It has been planned that these forces<br />
should be run down, and should be withdrawn at the end of 1975, and we<br />
in Australia knew that and planned on that. At that time, it was envisaged<br />
when these plans were made, that British ground troops would have left the<br />
region by the end of 1975 but that there would be still instantly availa1le<br />
and earmarked for the purpose, a British Air and Naval capability able<br />
swiftly to return and to bring back ground troops should a situation require<br />
i t. But more recently, on what I understand are economic<br />
ground, it has been decided that the withdrawal of British Forces will be<br />
completed not by the end of 1975 but by the end of 1971, some four<br />
years earlier. At the same time as this decision was made known, the<br />
swift availability of that naval and air capability which was previously<br />
planned is clouded by doubt, and we do not know what its composition will<br />
be, what its capacity to fill the role previously planned for it will be,<br />
what time will be necessary for it to be available, and whether it would<br />
indeed be available on the decision of the United Kingdom alone.<br />
This has put into this situation entirely new matte is for<br />
discussion which were unknown to us until the recent visit of the British<br />
Cabinet Minister. There has therefore been not merely a quite cons ider able<br />
alteration of the date by which withdrawal Is to be completed but also<br />
what appears to be a significant difference in planning for the situation<br />
which will obtain after withdrawal.<br />
It is clear to everyon e, of course, that Australia and New<br />
Zealand cannot step in and fill the role which Britain has vacated. But the<br />
Prime Minister of Singapore and the Prime Minister of Malaysia have both<br />
indicated a strong desire that there should be some continuing Australian<br />
military presence in the area after 1971. They wish this, they have asked<br />
e a / 8 </p>
<p>8-<br />
for this. They see it as a contribution to stability In their region, and<br />
their wishes must, of course, have great weight with us.<br />
For these reasons, the Minister for External Affairs has<br />
recently been on an exploratory mission to Singapore and Malaysia to discuss<br />
In more detail what those countries are able to do to help thernselvqs, what<br />
contribution they see Australia making, what role they see for a contribution<br />
Australia might make, and matters of that kind. This will be followed by<br />
further technical military discussions and Five Power discussions at a time<br />
to be arranged. Many of the military factors in this matter are as yet unknown.<br />
They are not known clearly enough for final decisions to be taken now, but<br />
it is clear that the rulers of Malaya and Singapore have indicated that they<br />
wish a continuing Australian presence after 1971, and It Is the feeling of my<br />
Government that these wishes having been so expressed, we should seek<br />
as far as possible, according to our own resources, to fall in with them.<br />
We have, of course, provided other aid to these countries.<br />
We have provided already, and earmarked funds already, to provide<br />
million in aid to Malaysia and to Singapore to enable them to help<br />
defend themselves. But still the matter does remain that it will be there<br />
a different situation than that which existed before, that in that situation<br />
we are asked by our neighbours to contribute, and that we must pay attention<br />
to the wishes which our neighbours so put forward.<br />
But it must be made clear, and it has been made clear,<br />
that any Australian military presence In these countries is not in any way<br />
directed against Indonesia, that other great country In our immediate region<br />
and our nearest neighbour. Indeed what we would lik1e to see and what we<br />
would seek to bring about, insofar as in our power lies, is a closer and<br />
closer association of Indonesia, Malaysia, Singapore, Australia and New<br />
Zealand not necessarily militarily, but In the fields of economic,<br />
co-operation, technical assistance and common action on regional grounds.<br />
This is an objective we should like to see attained and which we shall do<br />
all in our power to see attained. ( Sustained applauset<br />
These are two of the important matters facing this piation<br />
In the years ahead, but of course, again outside our borders before I turn<br />
to problems Inside it, are matters not military but matters of helping<br />
insofar as our resources and requirements permit, the world comm~ unity,<br />
and particularly that part of that community which is in our region and<br />
closest to us. That is the provision of economic assistance, of technological<br />
training, of what we can do to help to build the economies of those countries<br />
outside of this. We will this year, as Australians, contribute in foreign<br />
aid, including aid to New Guinea, something like $ 143 million or about<br />
$ 12 per head for each Australian. ( Interjection) Well If you don't think it<br />
is enough, give me another dollar and I will see it goes there.<br />
In the field of helping to develop the trade trade as<br />
distinct from aid of less developed countries, a field which in the long<br />
run can be of more significance and more assistance than mere aid we<br />
have as a country, taken Initiatives through the Department of Trade, and<br />
through Mr McEwen, which have been acknowledged and appreciated<br />
greatly by those less developed countries which seek outlets for their trade<br />
because they wish to help themselves and can only do that in this way. / 9 </p>
<p>9-<br />
We shall continue our efforts, particularly in aid directed<br />
to the countries In our region and to other Asian countries not directly In<br />
the region, for we are not only in, but of, a region where all our neighbours<br />
are Asian neighbours. The aid should be designed, except during disaster,<br />
not for consumption but for capital formation anft the imparting of skills arid'<br />
knowledge and technologies which permit the end benefit of the original aid<br />
provided to be many times multiplied in those countries in which those sk is<br />
and technologies and efforts are expended.<br />
This we must and will contin ue, but here, as In the field Of<br />
Defai ce, we should balance proposals for the growth rate of such expenditur e<br />
with proposals for the growth and development of Australia Itself. What we<br />
are doing, and what we are committed to do in the fields both of Defence-and<br />
of Foreign Aid, is a clear indication that we are no isolationist nation, 4n d<br />
we will not be, that we will not withdraw into ourselves and let Defence ' and<br />
Foreign Aid take care of themselves. But the level of what we are doing,<br />
and the rate of growth of what we are doing in both these fields must be<br />
regarded In the context of our own resources and our own needs, again and<br />
all the time, and the requirement so to grow ourselves that we will be able<br />
In the years ahead to be able to provide more and yet more into our own<br />
protection and into the development and help of the countries so close to us.<br />
I have spent some time on these matters of great Importance<br />
to this nation in Its place In the world. We are, I think, providing all that<br />
a nation of 12 million, a nation with a population not Mch~ i greater than tINt of<br />
Greter New York or Greater London can be expected to provide towards<br />
Defence and towards Foreign A-ssistance.<br />
We will continue to expand what we are doing in these fields,<br />
as indeed we must, but we will test each proposal against the requirements<br />
for the peaceful development of our own nation and the production of<br />
industrial musci s in our own nation to enable it to become great, to do yet<br />
more In the world in which it finds itself.<br />
I turn now to questions which are more domestic. What Is<br />
it don't all answer, please, because I am going to tell you the answer<br />
what is it that Australians throughout this nation would want to see done in<br />
the domestic field. I will tell you what I think it is they would want to see<br />
I believe that what they would want first to see is that there<br />
should be maintained, as has been brilliantly maintained for 18 years for<br />
Australians, the opportunity for full employment of all those who are willing<br />
and able to work for the advancement of their nation. And if I may say so<br />
to somebody from the back who called out something which sounded to me<br />
like " Our Henry", in no State has there been more jobs provided and les s<br />
unemployment than there has over the years been in this State of Victoria.<br />
This, I think, is what Australians would want to see maintained and maintained<br />
with it, I suggest, they would want to see that rates of taxation already<br />
significantly high should not be so increased, that the incentive to work<br />
harder or better or to earn more should be reduced, because not only would<br />
that be bad for the Individual but bad for the nation of which the individual<br />
is a living part. And they would want to see, I suggest, that rates of<br />
inflation were kept to a level where they could be absorbed without d~ s comfort i/ 1c. </p>
<p>ic<br />
and without leading to that kind of bust and lack of employment and industrial<br />
chaos which can occur if they get out of control. These are the frameworks,<br />
I believe, that Australians hawe had and would want to keep, and these are<br />
constricting frameworks.<br />
( Interjection " What about ccwz~ icting profits?")<br />
Do you really want to restrict profits If somebody makes it legitimately?<br />
If somebody invents something which benefits the community in which he<br />
lives? If somebody discovers a better way and a cheaper way of producing<br />
something, and is able to introduce that into a factory and to give to the<br />
people of this country something at a cheaper ; rice while yet he makes<br />
higher profits? Do you want to stop him making profits so that this better<br />
article at a cheaper price is not a vailable? Because that is not Liberal<br />
philosophy. That is the direct antithesis of It. ( Applause)<br />
But this background which I have put to you which It is<br />
essential to keep and which the people of this country would want to keep,<br />
I think is restricting when we consider all the things that need to be done<br />
both by Commonwealth and State and local governments throughout<br />
Australia. There Is a tendency to suggest that the solution to this Is just<br />
to make more money available here, there or the other place, and yet you<br />
know even you who are Interjecting know If you put your mind to it that<br />
this is true If you have your manpower fully employed, and if you have<br />
your materials and resources fully employed, then injecting further amounts<br />
of money does not get more things done, it only gets either a smaller amount<br />
of things done or the same amount of things done at a greater price, unless,<br />
of course, you take action to prevent some field of activity from continuing.<br />
And so these are restricting matters, but within the levels<br />
of those restrictions I should put to you what my Government will seek to do<br />
as and when it can In these fields, and indicate the matters we think of<br />
significance in this all-embracing word " development". I have used this<br />
be fore, of course, " development", and It has been rightly pointed cut that<br />
this Is a word which covers a vast area of Australia's activity. Too often<br />
It Is assumed to be merely that kind of development which takes place In<br />
country areas by the building of dams or the building of beef roads or some<br />
other activity of that kind. Essential as these forms of development are,<br />
they are not the only meaning of development even in that kind of context,<br />
for we have here developing in Australia, cities which are going to be at<br />
least twice as large as they are now, and cities In which the congestion of<br />
traffic Is going to pose really vast economic problems In the future and the<br />
beginning of studies by Commonwealth and State Governments which I would<br />
hope would take place, which I would seek to see did take place, Into this<br />
mater and how it could be overcome, must take Its place with development,<br />
alongside the development of areas outside the ci ties.<br />
This is governmental development, of course, but side by<br />
side with It must go, as we have seen happening lately so much, development<br />
which takes place because of private initiative, because of individual<br />
willingness to risk, because of willingness to go out and seek and find and<br />
develop which we have seen happening, and which Is happening now for the<br />
benefit of all of us throughout the whole of Australia. Again, It is necessary<br />
to see that the public sector of development, necessary though It Is, is not<br />
so expended that no Incentive is left, that no ability Is left In the private<br />
sector to take their share in development which ultimately Is the basis of<br />
a nation's life. But these are material things. These are the developments </p>
<p>11<br />
of industrial muscles as I have said before, and these are not in themselves<br />
enough to make a nation great. But no nation can be great unless It seeks<br />
not only materially to progress but also to take care of the weaker within<br />
it, the aged within it, the ill within it.<br />
Now this, too, must be a goal for any nation seeking to<br />
attain greatness, and this will be the examination of these problems,<br />
one of the first matters to which my Government would direct its attention.<br />
Indeed, it has begun to do so already in the field health, and i-ndeed there<br />
has already been some indication of that in announcements just recently<br />
made. Wle have here, and I expand on this matter only as an<br />
example of the way in which we would approach these problems, we have<br />
here in Australia a health scheme which is good, which is amongst the<br />
best in the world, which permits choice by the patient of the doctor,<br />
which does not ration hospital or other accommodation. But it is a heafth<br />
scheme which still suffers from disabilities. It ic tending to become rather<br />
too dear for many people for them to be enabled -Lo insure themselves for<br />
all the benefits which they should be able to achieve.<br />
And It suffers from the further and I think crippling<br />
disability that It does not cover those who have long-continuing illnesses<br />
br a year or two years or three years, and does not prevent the fear not only<br />
of that illness but the fear of the economic hardship, indeed in some cases<br />
the economic ruin which can flow from such long-contin ued illness. This<br />
will be a first matter to which we shortly will be directing our attention and<br />
which wle will seek, and I believe successfully seek, to overcome.<br />
( Cheers and applause). Mr President, I have sought at this by-election to put befcre<br />
the people of this electorate and those who may be listening in, unequivocally<br />
our approach to the problems of Defence, of our involvement in Viet Nam<br />
and Malaysia, of the course we would seek to follow in Foreign Aid, and I<br />
have Indicated, and only indicated by example what it is we would wish to<br />
see happen at home. I cannot tell you, and no politician of any party standing<br />
here could tell you exactly when and exactly how quickly these goals we've<br />
set before us will be achieved because there are so many unknown factors.<br />
We don't know what those things we produce will be sold for abroad. We<br />
don't know what rate of capital inflow there will be. VWe don't kiow what<br />
is going to happen in many other fields. But we do know this that t! l ase<br />
things, as a government, are cf importance to us, and that we wffIL, i.-ying<br />
attention to the constricting things which I said to you at the beglin:, seek<br />
to overcome them and the first amongst them, areas where there is<br />
injustice I won't say Injustice areas where there Is need, real need<br />
amongst our people. This is not simple, even in the field of health of 1'. r I<br />
have spoken to you it is not simp' e. VWe don't yet know and i. i~ c 11eve<br />
nobody yet knows exactly what area of geriatric treatment ought*. to be<br />
provided in existing-type hospitals, exactly what would happen we sought<br />
more to provide visiting nurd ng assistance for the aged aa eldclerly so<br />
they could stay in their own homes.<br />
All these things are matters which the Department of </p>
<p>12<br />
Health and the Minister for Health has been examining for weeks, and<br />
is examining now and about w hich you will hear from us as soon as may<br />
be. There will always be left areas in which we are not able to<br />
provide what we would wish to provide, and you are not able to get what<br />
you would wish to get. Right now, we are in what I call the tantalising<br />
years. We can see coming into this country 1970, 1971 and thereafter<br />
huge revenues from tae mineral and oil resources, and other resources<br />
which have been discovered and which will by then shed their full benefit<br />
on the people of Auctralia. But they are not here yet; we can see them<br />
coming. Even when they do come, while we will be able to make great<br />
advances, I think it probable, that as has been the case In every nation<br />
throughout history, neither the central Commonwealth Government nor<br />
any State Government will ever have the capacity to do all the things It<br />
would want to do as quickly as it would want to do them and still leave<br />
In the hands of individual citizens that which should be left in their hands.<br />
But we are moving towards it and we will move more rapidly<br />
towards It, and we can see coming up a time when great movement in<br />
that direction can be made.<br />
May I, Mr President, mention one more matter? Somebody<br />
called out about, I thinkc, and that Is the question of education. I mention<br />
it, of course, because it is something with which for some years I have<br />
been personally quite concerned, and a matter for which, should you wish<br />
to do so, I could be properly blamed if you thought it right, or I could be<br />
accepted if you thought it right.<br />
I want to put before you, both as an indication of what has been<br />
done and as an earnest of what could be done in the future because of<br />
what has been done in the past, as an Indication again of the approach of<br />
this Government, what has gone on In this field, a field traditionally<br />
that of the States.<br />
I was first appointed as the Minister Assisting the then Prime<br />
Minister In Education and affairs in the financial -year 1963/ 64. In that<br />
year, we were expending from the Commonwealth $ 57 million. The<br />
next year that went up to $ 94M. In 1965/ 66, it went up to $ 104 million.<br />
About that time, I became a full Minister. In 1966/ 67, it went up to<br />
$ 127 million, and this year, ladles and gentlemen, it has gone up to<br />
$ 175 million. ( Interjection " Not enough"). Of course, someone wiV<br />
" tnot enough", but in four years from $ 57 million to $ 175, with -S3tate<br />
contribution Increasing too, with a doubling of enrolments In univ:; r--il-es,<br />
with the introduction of colleges of advanced education, with the buil-t-n1g<br />
within this electorate in some cases of secondary bvel technical schools<br />
such as the one at Caulfield, these can be seen as monuments, they don't<br />
have to be heard just as words from a platform, they don't have to be just<br />
listened to as monetary figures. They can be seen as monuments throughout<br />
this State and throughiout this nat ion, and I believe that if you w. 1l support<br />
me in Higgins and I have the backing as I have the backing of the Coalition<br />
parties to this Government that there will be throug-. out Austr alia<br />
more and more monuments in more and more fields to the benefit of the<br />
people of Australia, and built by co-operation between the Commonwed th<br />
Government and the various State Governments as we have seen happen </p>
<p>13<br />
in the field of education.<br />
No promises. No specific promises.......<br />
( Interject ion " Why not?"<br />
I have told you why not. But you will be able to judge by what we do<br />
between now and the next elections. You have an indication of our<br />
thinking and of our goals,.<br />
Perhaps there is one specific promise that I can give you.<br />
I will ask from you for all that you can give towards building this State<br />
and this nation, and I will in return pledge to you all that I can give and<br />
my colleagues can give for a joint effort to see that together we can<br />
open the door of the destiny that lies before us. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
