<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1020</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH ON DEFENCE REVIEW MINISTERIAL STATEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/11/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001020_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />SPEECH BY<br />Rt. Hon. SIR ROBERT MENZIES,<br />ON<br />DEFENCE REVIEW<br />MINISTERIAL STATEMENT CAMBERRA<br />[ From the " Parliomentary Debates," 10th November, 1964] LIBRARY<br />4-~<br />Sir ROBERT MENZIES { Kooyong-<br />Prime Minister).-by leave-For some<br />months the Department of Defence and the<br />Service and Supply Departments, in close<br />collaboration with the Chiefs of Staff Committee,<br />have been making a complete reassessment<br />of our defence needs and programme.<br />Their labours have been conducted<br />against the background of affairs overseas,<br />and particularly in and around South East<br />Asia. The Government has exhaustively<br />studied the reports placed before it, and<br />has consulted closely with its professional<br />military advisers. In the result, we have<br />formed certain views about our strategic<br />0 position and about our defence requirements<br />which I will now proceed to state as clearly<br />as I can.<br />I refer, first, to our strategic position.<br />This requires an examination of our position<br />in relation to our neighbours. and our<br />international associates. Since the Second<br />World War and increasingly in the last<br />decade, the struggle against aggressive<br />Communism coupled with other developments<br />in Asia has forced us to recognise<br />that we are in a new situation. General or<br />14661/ 64. global war-that is, unrestricted conflict<br />between the major world powers-has<br />receded in probability because of the<br />deterrent effect of nuclear weapons, and we<br />continue to believe that it is unlikely except<br />as a result of miscalculation. But armed<br />conflicts short of general war could develop<br />at any time in areas of tension throughout<br />the world. Communist powers will continue<br />to press their aims through all the varied<br />cold war techniques of subversion and<br />insurgency and other threats to the<br />integrity of States which they wish to bring<br />under their domination.<br />At present, important questions arise<br />which require frank answers. They will, I<br />regret to say, indicate that there has been<br />a deterioration in our strategic position since<br />the review which I presented to Parliament<br />last year. The range of likely military<br />situations we must be prepared to face has<br />increased as a result of recent Indonesian<br />policies and actions and the growth of<br />Communist influence and armed activity in<br />Laos and South Vietnam. If these countries<br />collapsed, there would be a grave threat<br />to Thailand and the whole of South East</p>
<p>Asia would be put at risk. The effectiveness<br />of the South East Asia Treaty Organisation<br />as a guarantee of mutual security would<br />be seriously jeopardised.<br />In particular, in South Vietnam the continued<br />instability of government has made<br />the task of resistance more difficult and to<br />some extent frustrates the massive efforts of<br />the United States and our own necessarily<br />small contributions. The aggressive attitude<br />of North Vietnam towards South Vietnam<br />is demonstrated by continued political and<br />ideological support given to the military<br />insurgents, and the infiltration of thousands<br />of trained men. There was the Tonkin<br />Gulf attack on United States warships;<br />Communist China has ignored the Nuclear<br />Test Ban Treaty. These are sinister and<br />significant developments.<br />In Malaysia, to which we have given the<br />specific assurances which I announced in<br />this House, Australian troops have for the<br />first time been in combat with Indonesian<br />forces. True, in international opinion,<br />Malaysia has been strengthened by the vote<br />in the Security Council, the meeting of the<br />Commonwealth Prime Ministers in London,<br />and the relative failure of President Sukarno<br />to gather support at the Cairo conference<br />of unaligned nations. But, though it is now<br />clear that, for all practical purposes, no<br />impartial person doubts that Indonesia is<br />carrying on active and entirely unjustified<br />armed aggression against her neighbour,<br />the fact is that Indonesia still goes on her<br />unlawful way, seeking to undermine<br />Malaysian morale, to cause the disintegration<br />of Malaysia, and no doubt to dominate<br />the Borneo territories if and when they can<br />be detached from Malaysia.<br />If Indonesian attacks continue, Malaysia<br />may find it intolerable to confine defensive<br />measures to the guarding of Malaysia's<br />shores and jungles against Indonesian intrusion.<br />These Indonesian attacks may create<br />a real risk of war, a war so hopelessly unprofitable<br />to Indonesia that it is hard to<br />understand how any leader concerned with<br />the well-being of the ordinary men and<br />women of his countr-y could seriously be<br />prepared to provoke it. Indeed we must<br />prepare for all eventualities including the<br />c ontrol and, if necessary, defence of the<br />frontier between West New Guinea and the<br />Territory of Papua and New Guinea. Meanwhile,<br />by his cultivation of the Communist Powers, President Sukarno is exercising an<br />influence in South East Asia which could<br />weaken resistance to Communism.<br />It must be conceded, therefore, that the<br />risks of our situation in this corner of the<br />world have increased. This does not mean<br />that we suffer from fatalism or defeatism;<br />there is not the slightest occasion for either.<br />But it does mean that we must do more, and<br />pay more, as our contribution to our<br />national security. This is, of course, to be<br />done having in mind, and indeed never<br />forgetting, that in the South West Pacific<br />Australia and New Zeal-and have allies, including<br />Great Britain and the United States,<br />who are rich in power and goodwill. Without<br />them, Australia's task in defending so<br />vast a territory with so few people would<br />be a fearful one.<br />But Australian defence cannot be considered<br />in isolation, any more than the forces<br />we possess should be regarded as garrison<br />forces. Placed as we are, our defence, if<br />it is to be successful, must be beyond our<br />shores, and in depth. Hence and<br />A. N. Z. U. S. We are in S. E. A. T. O. not only<br />because we have a goodwill towards the<br />nations concerned and would wish to help<br />to protect them against Communist aggression,<br />but also because the further Cornmunist<br />powers are kept away from us, the<br />more secure we will feel. Thus, in<br />S. E. A. T. O. a high common interest is rendered<br />stronger, not weaker, by the<br />individual national interest each of us has.<br />Again, we are with Malaysia for several<br />good reasons. Malaysia is a well governed<br />and friendly Commonwealth country, and<br />as such is entitled to our support. Malaysia<br />is a non-Communist nation, and is willing<br />at all times to resist the Reds; it is monstrous<br />that she should be the subject of<br />unprovoked aggression from the south. But<br />again, we in Australia also want Malaysia<br />preserved because we want the Communist<br />powers as far away as possible. It should<br />not be forgotten that one of the aims of<br />what Indonesia calls its " confrontation" of<br />Malaysia is the removal of the Commonwealth<br />presence, including the bases. We<br />are advised that so long as the bases are<br />available and Commonwealth forces support<br />Malaysia, there is little prospect of a defeat<br />of Malaysia by Indonesian military action.<br />In short, Malaysia and Australia have a<br />common interest and an individual interest,<br />and they coincide.</p>
<p>In the same way, it is tremendously<br />important for us that Indonesia should not<br />become Communist, but retain its independence<br />under a Government serving only<br />the good of the Indonesian people. It is very<br />much to be feared that if Indonesia provoked<br />a war, the only people in Indonesia<br />who would get advantage from it would be<br />the Communists, ever ready to thrive on<br />disorder and defeat. Thus, Indonesia and<br />Australia have vital interests in common.<br />The recent actions of the Indonesian<br />Government are therefore all the more<br />deplorable. It is a misfortune to have to<br />join in a defence of Malaysia against a<br />nation with which we have no other quarrel,<br />and so much in common. Yet it is a misfortune<br />which we must be prepared to face,<br />to the utmost of our power.<br />Now, this has been a brief account of<br />some of the developments which have led us<br />to the conclusion that there has been, since<br />my revierw of 1963, a deterioration in our<br />strategic position. What new defence provision<br />should be made, in the light of this<br />conclusion? True, we are not and cannot be<br />the sole guarantors of our defence. But<br />we must be able to say with truth that we<br />are making a contribution to it which is<br />commensurate with our capacity and our<br />national self-respect.<br />The 1963 review itself added very considerably<br />to the defence programmes and<br />votes. Since then, substantial additions have<br />been made. It will be of interest if I<br />remind the House that until very recent<br />years our defence vote was, and had been<br />for some time, of the order of œ 200 million<br />a year. The order of financial magnitude<br />involved in our present revierw can be briefly<br />stated at this stage. The review of May 1963<br />Y raised -the programme for 1965-6, 1966-7<br />and 1967-8 by about œ 40 million a year to<br />a total of œ 816 million. In other words<br />before that review only 18 months ago the<br />total figure for these years had been of<br />the order of the œ 700 million and it was<br />raised to œ 816 million. This present review<br />Taises that total to œ 1,220 million, that is,<br />a further increase of œ 404 million. I will<br />return to the figures before I conclude.<br />I now turn to the concrete decisions<br />which have led to these financial conclusions.<br />Because of the central importance<br />of manpower to the whole of our defence<br />preparations I shall deal first with this<br />question. 3 At present the regular forces number just<br />over 52,000 including 22,750 in the Regular<br />Army, 16,600 in the Air Force and 12,900<br />in the Navy. In addition, there are approximately<br />1,000 Pacific Islanders in the Pacific<br />Islands Regiment. In the Citizen Military<br />Forces we have 27,630; in the Citizen<br />Naval Forces 5,115; and in the Citizen Air<br />Forces 868.<br />Over the programme period to mid-1968<br />the Navy and Air Force will require a considerable<br />increase in manpower to correspond<br />with the planned expansion of these<br />forces including the progressive introduction<br />of new equipment. By June 1968, the Navy<br />will have a requirement for approximately<br />16,700 and the Air Force for 21,000 men.<br />The Government and its naval and Air<br />Force advisers are confident that a satisfactory<br />progressive build up of manpower<br />towards these levels can be achieved by<br />existing means of recruitment.<br />The question of Army manpower is more<br />difficult. The numbers are larger; the whole<br />strength and organisation of the Army are<br />involved. We have given close attention<br />to this problem which has before<br />now given rise to great controversy.<br />After an examination of all the factors,<br />and in full consultation with our<br />military advisers, we have reached the conclusion<br />that the Regular Army should be<br />built up as rapidly as possible from the<br />present 22,750 to an effective strength of<br />33,000 men, which means a total force of<br />37,500. A peace-time Army of this size<br />would be adequate to meet our immediately<br />foreseeable operational requirements and<br />form a basis for rapid expansion in war.<br />The training effort required to achieve<br />any reasonably quick build up of a much<br />larger Army than the one we now contemplate<br />would be such that the Regular<br />Army would cease to be an effective fighting<br />force and become for some considerable<br />time simply a training organisation. This has<br />been one of the limiting factors in this. Let<br />me remind honorable members that we have<br />through successive programmes built up the<br />capacity of the Regular Army as an effective<br />and readily available fighting force, and it<br />is essential in present circumstances that this<br />capacity and quality be retained to the greatest<br />possible extent.<br />The Government has given the most<br />careful consideration to the means by which</p>
<p>the Army's manpower requirements may be<br />achieved. It seems clear, on our military<br />advice and our own carefully formed judgment,<br />that we cannot expect by voluntary<br />means to achieve a build up in the Army's<br />strength of the order we require and to the<br />timing which is necessary. We are living'in<br />a period of unsurpassed prosperity and more<br />than full employment; the attractions of<br />civilian employment are very great indeed.<br />The Government has therefore decided<br />that there is no alternative to the introduction<br />of selective compulsory service. We<br />know that this presents difficult personal,<br />social, economic, and perhaps political<br />problems. Our decision has been taken only<br />because of the paramount needs of defence<br />and, in the difficult circumstances I have<br />described, the preservation of our security.<br />May I return at this point to the observations<br />I made earlier in reference to the<br />demands of our deteriorating strategic<br />situation? We expect a continuing requirement<br />to make forces available for cold war<br />and anti-insurgency tasks. We must have<br />forces ready as an immediate contribution<br />should wider hostilities occur. We must at<br />all times retain adequate forces against any<br />more direct threat which might develop to<br />our. own security. Because of our geographic<br />position we have the most compelling<br />reasons to take those steps which will<br />put us in a position to meet these various<br />demands. The necessary units cannot be<br />provided with a lesser effective strength than<br />33,000, yet this number cannot in present<br />circumstances and in proper time be<br />obtained by voluntary means.<br />It follows also that, to enable the Regular<br />Army to achieve the required degree of<br />operational readiness, selective servicemen<br />must serve in regular units on a full time<br />basis. If the scheme is to be effective, those<br />called up must therefore be under an obligation<br />to serve overseas as necessary and must<br />be available to go with the regular unit in<br />which they are serving.<br />In assessing the length, of service<br />required, an average of six months must<br />be allowed for recruit and corps training.<br />Provision must also be made for leave,<br />movement and acclimatisation should the<br />national servicemen be sent to an overseas<br />theatre. In order to permit a period of at<br />least twelve months effective service in a<br />unit a total period of two years full-time duty * is required And this will be the basis<br />of the Government's scheme. This will be<br />followed by a period of three years on the<br />Reserve. Briefly, we have decided that young men<br />will -be required to register in the calendar<br />year in which they reach the age of<br />years. The first actual call-up will take place<br />about the -middle of next year. During the<br />second half of 1965 a total of about 4,200<br />will ' be required. Thereafter there Will be<br />annual call-ups of about 6,900. This will,<br />by December 1966, give an Army of a<br />total strength of about 37,500-this is the<br />Regular Army-which will mean an<br />effective force of 33,000. Detailed consideration<br />is being given to the conditions<br />of service and the question of exemptions<br />and deferments to meert particular circumstances.<br />Civil ' employment rights of -those<br />called up will ' be appropriately protected.<br />I hasten to say that the introduction of<br />selective compulsory service does not in any<br />way detract -from the importance of<br />volunteers for the Regular Army, the<br />Emergency Reserve or the Citizen Military<br />Forces. On the contrary, we would wish<br />the volunteer spirit, which has meant so<br />much to Australia in the past, to continue.<br />Both the Government and the net-ion would<br />urge that as high a percentage as possible<br />of those in our armed services should be<br />those who, of their own choice, and in the<br />spirit of a great natio ' nal tradition, have<br />joined one or other of those Services.<br />Mr. Clyde Camneron.-I know one who<br />dodged it in 1914.<br />Sir ROBERT MENZ~ IES.-You do not.<br />You must not repeat other people's lies.<br />Mr. Clyde Cajneron.-Well, 1915.<br />Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-That is a very<br />bad habit, Clyde, and I advise you against<br />it. Indeed, so far as the Regular Army is<br />concerned, volunteers will continue to be of<br />fundamental importance to the effectiveness<br />of the force. Volunteers on longer terms of<br />engagement will reach the highest standards<br />of training and will give greater flexibility<br />in the organisation and deployment of our<br />forces. A selective service scheme does not<br />give sufficient time to train ' highly qualified<br />specialists and technicians and we must<br />continue to look to volunteers to provide<br />these. The Government has . already</p>
<p>reviewed and improved conditions of service<br />to make a career in the Permanent Forces<br />as attractive as possible. With this in mind<br />and in the light of the strategic situation<br />which I have outlined, we would ask the<br />young men and women of Australia to consider<br />carefully a permanent career in the<br />armed forces.<br />The new Emergency Reserve, for which<br />enrolment will be commencing almost<br />immediately, will provide a ready means of<br />supplementing -field force units, increasing<br />our cold war military capability and providing<br />reinforcements in the initial stages of<br />hostilities. It -has a most important place in<br />the full concept of our defence forces. The<br />role of the Citizen Military Forces-to provide<br />in war or defence emergency the<br />follow-up forces and the expansion of our<br />military effort-remains unchanged, and<br />indeed assumes even greater importance<br />following the passage of the legislation to<br />make these forces available in a defence<br />emergency. I seek the co-operation not only<br />of our young men, but also of their employers<br />and others to ensure that the Citizen<br />Military Forces target of 35,000 is<br />achieved over the period of the new defence<br />programme. The detailed organisation of the Army<br />will ' be further reviewed to provide for an<br />expansion in the field force with particular<br />emphasis on a substantial increase in the<br />combat element and high priority logistic<br />units. Two additional battalions will be<br />raised making a total of six including the<br />two battalions in our first two battle<br />groups and the battalion already deployed<br />in Malaysia. In addition, the organisation<br />will provide adequate backing, not only to<br />. j maintain and support the expanded field<br />force, C. M. F. and cadets, but also to provide<br />a sound basis for further expansion<br />and mobilisation.<br />There is, for a variety of good reasons,<br />some concentration of military provision<br />and organisation in the south-eastern areas<br />of the continent. We feel, however, that,<br />in the overall interests of rapid mobility,<br />this should not be carried too far. We have,<br />therefore, af ter careful consideration,<br />decided that a new battle group will be<br />established in north Queensland, probably<br />in the Townsville area. The Special Air<br />Service Regiment already established at<br />Perth will be more than doubled in size to provide a head-quarters squadron and four<br />squadrons. The Government has decided on<br />a substantial change in the organisation of<br />the Citizen Military Forces designed to<br />create additional battalions, give greater<br />flexibility and increased opportunities for<br />service, particularly in country areas. The<br />target strength for the cadets is being increased<br />from 40,000 to 45,000.<br />In the 1963 defence review, I announced<br />that it was intended to double as soon as<br />possible the strength of the Pacific Islands<br />Regiment, which at that time was of the<br />order of 700, and I also indicated that<br />further developments in relation to the<br />force were under consideration. Recruitment<br />to the P. I. R. has increased steadily, and the<br />target strength we envisaged in our previous<br />plans will be attained earlier than we had<br />expected. In the present strategic situation<br />the Government continues to<br />attach high priority to the strengthening<br />of the P. I. R. The detailed investigations<br />have now been completed,<br />and the Government will proceed with<br />the plan ' to increase the force to three<br />battalions and supporting units with a total<br />strength approaching 3,500 by June 1968.<br />Tenders closing on 30th November this year<br />have been called for necessary Army works<br />for Papua and New Guinea which could<br />cost about œ 12 million. An honorable member<br />opposite asked me today whether there<br />was any difficulty about this, having regard<br />to the fact that it was a Trust Territory.<br />Part of the answer is that there is not.<br />These include additional barrack buildings,<br />workshops and engineering services, and<br />housing for native married members of the<br />force. The -provision of equipment for the Army<br />must match the improvements in the strength<br />and availability of units. In the defence<br />review of May 1963, expenditure on Army<br />equipment was raised from the rate of<br />million Per annumn to the much higher level<br />of œ 17.5 million.<br />. In the light of the deterioration of our<br />strategic Position there is a need to aocelerate<br />the rate of progress towa~ rds achievemenit<br />of the approved objective of providing<br />modern equipment for one division. Provision<br />is also required for the expanded forces<br />in Papua and New Guinea. Provision must<br />be made for the replacement of out-moded.<br />equipment as new items become available</p>
<p>from research and development for introduction<br />into service. Sufficient additional<br />equipment must be provided to ensure that<br />C. M. F. training is realistic and effective.<br />For all these purposes, and in line with<br />the expansion in other elements of our<br />defence preparations, the Government has<br />approved a major acceleration in Army<br />equipment purchases. Expenditure will be<br />increased to œ 20 million in 1965-66-the<br />first year of the new defence programme<br />o œ 25 million in the following year, and<br />to œ 30 million in 1967-68. The equipment<br />to be purchased will include the whole range<br />of moder conventional weapons, ammunition,<br />vehicles, light aircraft, engineering and<br />signals stores and so on. Items of new equipment<br />which the Army is investigating include<br />low level anti-aircraft weapons, air-portable<br />armoured fighting vehicles, new artillery<br />weapons, combat surveillance equipment -and<br />various other items. Emphasis will continue<br />to be placed on air-portable equipment and<br />those items which will improve Army<br />mobility. The general effect of this approval<br />is that as the strength of our forces is built<br />up, the weapons and equipment which they<br />require, and of the most modern types, will<br />be available to them. The increase in the<br />Army strength from under 23,000 to some<br />37,500 by the end of 1966 means that<br />accommodation for an additional 15,000<br />men has to be provided. This is . additional<br />to the large works, programme for the<br />Pacific Islands Regiment which I have<br />already mentioned. This will mean a greatly<br />increased Army works programme which<br />will be carried out with the highest priority.<br />I turn now to our proposals for an expanded<br />Navy and Air Force as part of an<br />overall programme for strengthening the<br />Australian military effort. Before the defence<br />review undertaken by Cabinet last week,<br />the Naval programme provided for a Fleet<br />comprising the following main units: One<br />aircraft carrier, operating anti-submarine<br />helicopters and also fixed wing aircraft for<br />their remaining service life; two Daring<br />class destroyers: three Charles F. Adams<br />destroyers-D. D. G.' s; six type-12 frigates;<br />four Oberon class submarines; six " Ton<br />class minesweepers; one escort maintenance<br />ship-being construdted in Australia; one<br />fast transport; one fleet tanker; and one<br />Battle class destroyer for use as a training<br />ship. This programme involved the construction<br />of ten new ships, including three<br />Charles F. Adams destroyers which<br />rank among the world's finest guided<br />missile ships; four Oberon class submarines;<br />and two type-12 antisubmarine<br />frigates and an escort maintenance<br />ship being constructed in our own<br />shipyards in Australia. These additions in<br />themselves would provide a significant increase<br />in the capability of the R. A. N. to<br />fulfil its increasing operational commitments.<br />Careful consideration has been given to<br />the future of the Fleet Air Arm which is<br />a complex field of defence and could<br />involve very large expenditures. H. M. A. S.<br />" Mellbourne" was converted to the antisubmarine<br />role with the acquisition of 27<br />modern Wessex helicopters in 1963, and a<br />number of Gannet and Sea Venom aircraft<br />were also retained. A number of possibilities<br />as to the continued operation of the<br />Melbourne" have been considered,<br />having regard to the remaining life of the<br />ship, the general cost of naval aviation, and<br />other defence considerations.<br />The Government has now made two<br />important decisions-<br />First, as the Gannet and Sea Venom aircraft<br />are approaching the end of their service<br />life and ' becoming difficult and<br />uneconomical to maintain, it has been<br />decided to replace these aircraft with 14<br />S2E Tracker anti-submarine aircraft. This<br />aircraft, which is in service with the United<br />States Navy-as members of the House<br />who visited recently the U. S. S. " Enterprise"<br />will recall-is a twin piston-engined<br />aircraft with good endurance and well<br />equipped for all-weather operations. The<br />anti-submarine equipment it carries includes<br />the latest electronic devices, and it also has<br />the capacity for carrying a good weapon<br />load. Its inclusion in the Melbourne's"<br />equipment will improve considerably the<br />ship's anti-submarine capability. If I<br />remember accurately, the cost of this item<br />is about œ 16 million or œ 17 million.<br />Secondly, the Government has also<br />approved an extensive modernisation of<br />the " Melbourne" going much beyond that<br />approved in the 1963 review. This<br />modernisation will cost nearly œ 10 million.<br />The main functions in which modernisation<br />is required are the operation of antisubmarine<br />aircraft in all weather by day<br />and night; long range detection and height</p>
<p>finding radar; improved close range air<br />defence by mounting Seacat missile systems;<br />and improved habitability.<br />Those proposals will add substantially to<br />the anti-submarine capability of the Royal<br />Australian Navy. In the 1963 review the<br />Government authorised modernisation of<br />our Daring class destroyers directed mainly<br />towards improving their anti-subm'arine<br />capability. This plan has been reviewed in<br />the light of the Navy's tactical requirements<br />and the needs of our strategic situation.<br />It has now been decided to modernise<br />the Darings by providing them with Ikara,<br />which, as honorable members are already<br />aware, is a guided anti-submarine weapons<br />system developed in our own research and<br />production establishments. The estimated<br />cost of modernising the two Darings is in<br />excess of œ 13 million.<br />With a view to enhancing the Navy's<br />mobility, a fast fleet replenishment ship with<br />some provision for the carrying of oil fuel<br />is to be acquired. It is expected that the<br />ship will come into commission in 1970.<br />The question of local construction-which<br />we would prefer-or purchase from overseas<br />will be determined at a very early<br />date. It has -been decided to add two minesweepers<br />to the present force of six vessels<br />which were obtained in 1962. The<br />additional minesweepers will be introduced<br />into service in 1968.<br />Concurrently with the planning of the<br />expansion of the Pacific Islands Regiment,<br />investigations have been proceeding into the<br />formation of a coastal security force in<br />Papua and New Guinea. It has now been<br />decided that five patrol craft of a type suiti<br />able for local manning and maintenance<br />will be obtained. These will contribute substantially<br />to the general surveillance of the<br />shores and rivers of the Territory. Nine all<br />purpose patrol craft to replace vessels in<br />use by the which are now approaching<br />the end of their useful life, will also be<br />obtained. These vessels will be suited for<br />patrol duties such as those being carried out<br />at the present moment by our minesweepers<br />in Borneo waters.<br />In addition to the above proposals,<br />Cabinet has approved a wide range of naval<br />projects designed to support objectives<br />which have already been approved, including<br />support facilities for the Charles F. Adams destroyers, a missile firing range,<br />development of a submarine base and support<br />facilities and provision for a submarine<br />rescue vessel, replacement of harbour support<br />craft and fleet boats, modernisation of<br />Wessex helicopters, and rehabilitation of<br />Manus Island oil fuel installations.<br />In recent defence programmes, the<br />Government has approved the substantial<br />re-armament of the fighter and strikereconnaissance<br />elements of the R. A. A. F.<br />with modern aircraft of advanced performance.<br />The order which has been<br />placed for 100 Mirage supersonic fighter<br />aircraft will provide for the re-equipment of<br />the four Sabre fighter squadrons. Deliveries<br />of these aircraft from local production to<br />the R. A. A. F. are continuing. The 24 Fl 11A<br />aircraft which have been ordered from the<br />United States will add powerfully to the<br />deterrent and strike capability of the<br />R. A. A. F. The Government is confident that<br />the FIl11A aircraft, which is expected to fly<br />before the end of this year, will amply fulfil<br />its promise as an outstanding military aircraft.<br />In this programme the Government has<br />given particular attention to the transport,<br />maritime and training requirements of the<br />R. A. A. F. and to the continued development<br />of our airfields. The existing squadron of<br />12 Hercules C130A aircraft with which the<br />R. A. A. F. was equipped in 1958 has considerably<br />improved the air strategic mobility<br />of the Australian forces. The development<br />of plans associated with our S. E. A. T. O. and<br />other commitments has, however, shown<br />clearly that our present air strategic movement<br />facilities fall short of those required<br />to meet likely military situations. A study<br />by our professional military advisers on the<br />strategic mobility requirements of the Australian<br />services indicates that in addition to<br />the aircraft which would be provided from<br />civil resources, the services require an<br />additional squadron of medium range transport<br />aircraft. The aircraft selected to meet<br />this requirement is the C130E, a greatly<br />improved version of the C130A at present<br />in service in the R. A. A. F. For operational<br />and maintenance purposes these aircraft are<br />compatible with the C130A. They provide<br />an increased strategic lift capacity and they<br />possess the short field characteristics which<br />enable them to carry out intra-theatre operations<br />as well as inter-theatre tasks. Approval</p>
<p>has been given to acquire 12 C130E aircraft.<br />This will mean an increase in the<br />order of battle of the transport element of<br />the R. A. A. F. from two to three squadrons.<br />The existing squadron of Hercules C130A<br />aircraft will, of course, continue in service,<br />together with the squadron of Caribou aircraft<br />which has recently been acquired. The<br />detachment of Caribou aircraft in South<br />Vietnam has already given notable service<br />in operations against the Communist Vietcong.<br />The maritime element of the Royal Australian<br />Air Force, working closely with the<br />carrier " Melbourne" and with the escorts<br />of the Royal Australian Navy, provides<br />maritime reconnaissance and anti-submarine<br />protection for our forces. At present there<br />are two maritime squadrons in the<br />R. A. A. F. No. 10 Squadron is equipped with<br />Neptune SP2H aircraft embodying modern<br />surface and underwater submarine detection<br />equipment. No. 11 Squadron stationed<br />at Richmond is, however, equipped with an<br />older version of the Neptune aircraft, the<br />P2E, containing submarine detection and<br />tracking equipment, which is now coming<br />to the end of its useful operational life. It<br />is accordingly necessary to re-equip this<br />squadron so that it will be fully effective<br />against modern submarines. It has been<br />decided to re-arm the squadron in 1968<br />with Lockheed Orion aircraft which have<br />outstanding performance in the location<br />and destruction of enemy submarines. The<br />Orion is the best maritime aircraft available<br />in the world today. Ten of these aircraft<br />will be obtained.<br />The current flying training aircraft in<br />the R. A. A. F. are the Winjeel in the basic<br />and the Vampire in the advanced stages.<br />The introduction of high performance aircraft<br />of the Mirage and Fl111A types will<br />require new types of training aircraft and<br />new techniques in training. In major air<br />forces operating supersonic aircraft the use<br />of a jet aircraft from the commencement<br />of training has proved to be necessary to<br />achieve . the required standard quickly. The<br />Government has accordingly approved the<br />purchase of an all-through jet trainer of<br />suitable performance to replace the Winjeel<br />and the Vampire, thereby enabling the<br />training organisation to advance in parallel<br />with the re-equipment of operational squadrons. Seventy-five of the new aircraft<br />will be obtained.<br />At present navigators and signallers of<br />the R. A. A. F. are trained in Dakota aircraft<br />modified in 1952 for this purpose. In a<br />few more years these aircraft will be<br />inadequate to train navigators and signallers,<br />having regard to the latest training<br />techniques, the type of training equipment<br />required and the modern operational aircraft<br />being obtained for the R. A. A. F. The<br />Government has approved the acquisition<br />of eight replacement -trainer aircraft of a<br />suitable type.<br />Experience gained by the members of the<br />R. A. A. F. Mirage instructional team in<br />France, coupled with the experience of<br />other air forces operating supersonic aircraft,<br />indicates that a dual mirage aircraft<br />is necessary ' to provide safe, efficient and<br />fast conversion of both experienced and<br />less experienced pilots. The Government<br />has approved the acquisition of ten dual<br />Mirage aircraft. These will be additional to<br />the 100 operational Mirage aircraft already<br />on order.<br />I have referred already to the additional<br />equipment which we are providing to<br />improve the essential strategic and tactical<br />mobility of our forces. The continued<br />development of airfields to permit the rapid<br />deployment and effective operational use of<br />our forces -both strategically and tactically is<br />a complementary measure to which the<br />Government continues to attach the highest<br />importance. In earlier years we have carried<br />out an extensive programme of airfield<br />works and development in such places as<br />Darwin, Townsville, Amberley and Williamtown.<br />The construction of a second airfield<br />in the Northern Territory at Tindal, which<br />was approved in the last programme, is<br />proceeding satisfactorily and will be completed<br />in 1966. Detailed investigations and<br />technical planning for the new airfield at<br />Boram near Wewak in New Guinea have<br />now been completed and construction will<br />proceed without delay. This airfield will be<br />built to standards which will permit its use<br />by all aircraft now in service or to be<br />acquired by -the R. A. A. F.<br />We have now approved ' the further<br />development of airfields in New Guinea. The</p>
<p>existing airfield at Nadzab will ' be rehabilitated<br />and extended for ferrying purposes to<br />standards permitting its use by Mirage and<br />other aircraft. The airfield at Daru in the<br />south west of Papua-New Guinea will be<br />extended and developed and smaller airstrips<br />between Daru and Boram will be brought<br />to a higher standard. This will add to the<br />flexibility of our forces and improve the<br />effectiveness of the patrols now carried out<br />by the Pacific Islands Regiment. On the<br />mainland the existing airfield at Learmonth,<br />near North West Cape, will be further<br />developed by the provision of taxiways,<br />hard standings and other essential services.<br />Improvements are also to be made to the<br />airfield at Cocos to increase its capability.<br />The Government has previously<br />announced -the acquisition of two new<br />control and reporting units, one of which<br />will -be installed at Williamtown and one at<br />Amberley. Both these equipments will be<br />mobile. Provision is made in ; the new programme<br />for the modernisation of the control<br />and reporting unit already installed at<br />Darwin. Adequate provision will be made<br />for new capital construction and modernisation<br />of existing facilities in. our production<br />and research establishments so that they<br />may continue to meet the demands of our<br />expanded -forces.<br />A major expansion of the nature which I<br />have outlined must inevitably bring a substantial<br />increase in expenditure. Briefly, we<br />estimate that defence votes in the three<br />years of the programme will be: 1965-66,<br />œ 370,000,000; 1966-67, œ E421,700,000; and<br />1967-68, œ 429,100,000. In our defence review of 22nd May<br />1963, we contemplated expenditure allotments<br />as under-1963-64 1964-65 1965-66 1966-67 1967-68<br />Em Lm LM œ m LMr<br />Navy 53.3 54.3 63.3 65.2 59.7<br />Army 77.6 87.5 90.7 94.0 97.2<br />Air 80.1 84.9 87.9 89.1 82.6<br />Supply and 26.5 26.7 27.7 28.7 30.0<br />other Departments -23 7.5 1253.4 269.6 277.0_ 269.5<br />Since May 1963 these allotments have<br />been increased by Cabinet approvals of<br />new projects, of which the main items are:<br />Purchase of 24 Fl111A strike-reconnaissance<br />aircraft; construction of two additional<br />frigates to replace H. M. A. S. Voyager";<br />increased costs for the fleet fitting of Ikara;<br />expansion of the Pacific Islands Regiment<br />in Papua and New Guinea; replacement of<br />V. I. P. aircraft; purchase of seven additional<br />Caribou aircraft; a housing programme;<br />and defence aid for Malaysia. The<br />total estimated cost of these approvtals is<br />œ 1 18 million.<br />In addition to these specific projects,<br />additional costs have also been incurred<br />with the introduction of new Service pay<br />scales, improved conditions of service,<br />basic wage increases and margins adjustments.<br />The ' addition of the expenditure<br />flowing from all these decisions has<br />involved an increase in the planning allotments<br />of ' the May 1963 review to the<br />following-<br />1963-64<br />( Actual) 1964-65<br />( Estimates) 1965-661966-671967-68<br />im Emn Em Em Em<br />Navy 55.6 69.2 80.1 81.3 76.9<br />Army 79.0 94.2 106.5 109.4 111.2<br />Air 89.2 90.0 99.6 108.1 105.3<br />Supply Department 29.3 33.0 34.0 33.2 34.6<br />Defence Department and other charges to the<br />Defence vote 7.4 10.4 10.2 9.0 9.8<br />260.5 296.8 330.4 341.0 337.8<br />14661 / 64.-2</p>
<p>The decisions which<br />announced will increase<br />figures still further to -the I have just<br />these adjusted<br />following-<br />1965-66 1966-67 1967-68<br />œ m œ m œ m<br />Navy 95.2 105.3 98.5<br />Army 118.1 138.0 150.1<br />Air 107.8 130.3 131.5<br />Supply Department 38.4 39.0 39.1<br />Defence Department and<br />other charges to the Defence<br />vote 10.5 9.1 9.9<br />370.0 421.7 429.1<br />These are very great increases. We consider<br />that they are warranted having regard<br />to the situation which we now face.<br />Although decisions which we have now<br />made will mean an increased allocation<br />over the three years commencing 1965-66<br />of some œ 212 million, we are certain that<br />the people of Australia will also recognise<br />the need for us to continue to maintain<br />adequate defence forces capable of meeting<br />the obligations which we have to make<br />a great Australian defence effort, and also<br />those obligations which we have assumed<br />with our allies. No-one can doubt that the<br />increase in defence expenditure arising from<br />the decisions which I have announced, with<br />their added demands for manpower and<br />material resources, will have very significant<br />economic and financial effects.<br />In the present financial year, the direct<br />budgetary effects will be limited. There will be a spurt between now and the end of the<br />financial year in accommodation and other<br />works expenditure necessary to the commencement<br />of the selective service<br />scheme in July. And here and there,<br />there will be a need to make small<br />initial payments this financial year<br />towards new equipment which is the<br />subject of the new three year programme.<br />However, in 1965-66 and later years, the<br />impact will Ibe large. In the first place, it<br />will present a formidable budgetary problem.<br />On top of -that, the additions to expenditure<br />at home will add to the call on the resources<br />of the economy, which are already under<br />some strain, and the additions -to expenditure<br />abroad will increase whatever drawings<br />would otherwise be made on our external<br />reserves. There are thus involved obvious problems<br />for -the national economy. These must and<br />will be faced and solved. All I need say<br />at present is that, as a Government, we have<br />acted under a sense of national duty. We<br />believe that we will have wide public support<br />in whatever tasks may lie ahead. I present<br />the following paper-<br />Defence Review-Ministerial Statement,<br />November, 1964-<br />and move-<br />That the House take note of the statement.<br />Debate ( on motion by Mr. Calwel)<br />adjourned.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
