<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5215</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED FOR &#039;SUNDAY REPORT&#039;, RICHARD COLVILLE, CHANNEL 10</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/12/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005215.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F1/ 7 _ I<br />
EMBARGO:_ 6: 00 pm ', SUNDAY, 9 DECEMBER 1979<br />
PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED FOR<br />
" SUNDAY REPORT", RICHARD COLVILLE, CHANNEL<br />
( Please acknowledge Channel 10 Sunday Report)<br />
Colville Prime Minister, I suppose the initial reaction of a lot of<br />
people to the Ministerial reshuffle will be that you must be<br />
rather disappointed with the performance of an awful lot of your<br />
Ministers. Prime Minister<br />
I don't think so at all. There are a couple of pretty obvious<br />
things. Peter Nixon couldn't go on doing Transport and<br />
Primary Industry. He is giving up Transport. It was natural<br />
that Ralph Hunt take that as a minister coming into Cabinet.<br />
I think it is also very natural that a senior Minister, a very<br />
senior Minister, should have charge of National Development<br />
and Energy. This is of increasing importance in a whole range<br />
of areas of Commonwealth and State activities. It impinges<br />
upon the activities of a number of other Departments' portfolios;<br />
Transport, Primary Industry. You name it, there are energy<br />
related elements in all those things. Therefore, I wanted a<br />
senior Minister, in Cabinet to be handling these matters. In<br />
addition to that many people think that there are only<br />
negative aspects flowing to Australia from what is happening<br />
in the OPEC countries, Iran and all the rest there are, in<br />
terms of price. But we also need to understand that because<br />
Australia is rich in energy resources, particularly in coal<br />
and in coal-based electricity, there is potential for great<br />
advantage, in greater generation of electricity and bringing the<br />
processing of our raw materials and of our minerals together.<br />
This is happening in the aluminium industry, and a significant<br />
part of Senator Carrick's charter will be to work with the<br />
States in helping to promote a greater use of these sorts of<br />
things...<br />
The development of overall energy policy, which has been carried<br />
on well to this point by Kevin Newman. It requires an<br />
increasing interaction with other Departments, and with the<br />
States, and especially for the development of electricity based<br />
on coal and the processing of raw materials. This is a very<br />
important job, and indeed, a lot of people have been writing<br />
and saying that a senior Minister should be in charge of these<br />
particular things.<br />
Once you make a couple of changes of the kind that I have just<br />
mentioned, there are necessarily I think, a number of consequential<br />
changes. Senator Webster has retired. That involved one<br />
element of change. Quite plainly, not all ministers are to the<br />
same extent suited for all jobs. It is a question of, therefore,<br />
matching Ministers with the jobs which you believe that they<br />
will do best. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
That is what has involved a number of changes, perhaps slightly<br />
more than I would have liked, but I think the ministers are<br />
particularly well suited to the tasks that they will be<br />
undertaking. Colville You are saying that none of these changes represent any<br />
dissatisfaction on your part with the job that any of these<br />
people have been doing?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No. It is a function of the two things that I have mentioned.<br />
Those two changes in the senior area then flow through to<br />
another to make sure that people are'in the best places.<br />
Colville On energy for instance, though, there was a situation where you<br />
had responsibility split and in fact Ministers were making<br />
conflicting statements at various times about the same subjects.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Not really conflicting. So often people can be looking at<br />
different sides of the same coin. When they talk about<br />
different sides and it gets reported that way, it makes one appear<br />
as though there is a conflict. I think in the statements on<br />
energy which I think you are referring to, they were very much<br />
in that context. Plainly, if Iran goes on and if Iran stopped<br />
exporting oil-we don't buy much oil direct from Iran but<br />
if all that was taken away from the normal world supply of oil<br />
over a period it is bound to affect Australia. I think the way<br />
it was reported appeared to lead to some sort of difference.<br />
I think it was looking at it through different windows.<br />
Colville Speaking of Iran, and getting away from domestic matters for<br />
a moment, the current unrest in Iran and other parts of the<br />
Muslim world does this -seriously concern you. Do you see this<br />
as a widespread revolt against the Western way of life in a great<br />
part of the world?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Not against Western way of life so much, but I think what is<br />
happening in Iran has got to be of enormous concern to all of us.<br />
Now what has happened to the United States Embassy and to those<br />
hostages is a matter of very, very serious international co ' ncern.<br />
I believe that President Carter has behaved with commendable<br />
restraint against enormous provocation, because what is happening<br />
is going against all of the accepted modes of international<br />
behaviour with countries dealing with countries, in diplomatic<br />
terms. It is going against all of that. If this sort of thing were<br />
to become commonplace, for example, normal communication between<br />
nations would become quite impossible. Against that sort of<br />
./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
background. I believe that President Carter deserves our<br />
sympathy for a very grave and serious situation, and also our<br />
support for acting with, I would think, commendable restraint<br />
under enormous provocation,. and I suspect under a growing<br />
impatience by the United States' people.<br />
Colville It seems to be an impossible situation, doesn't it? Can you<br />
see anything that could be done if you were in that position,-<br />
that President Carter is in.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Individually, I think it would be very, very difficult indeed.<br />
The United States is the most powerful country in the world,<br />
but you are in a position in which any exercise of that power<br />
could well place in jeopardy the lives of the hostages. Again,<br />
I think it is to the President's credit that he has clearly<br />
placed the lives and the well being of those hostages as a<br />
paramount concern. There is a point here that I think is very<br />
worrying indeed: there have been reports that there is going to<br />
be'some sort of revolutionary tribunal that will try those<br />
hostages. The whole of history is studded, especially in this<br />
century, with the actions of revolutionary tribunals and<br />
revolutionary trials. It is not necessarily the best way. It has<br />
not been a way in which justice has been carried through.<br />
What has happened has often been arbitrary, and pretty summary<br />
and pretty brutal. I think that element is something that again<br />
adds greatly to our concern.<br />
Colville Getting back to Australia, and I suppose Australia's place in<br />
the world another year coming up, I think the fifth for<br />
you in Government how do you see Australia in the next year.<br />
Briefly, what do you think will happen?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I see more confidence in Australia, more confidence from<br />
Australians in Australia and more confidence from people outside<br />
this country than I have known for a very, very long while.<br />
We went through some difficult periods: some downs and some ups<br />
and damage to be repaired in the 1970' s. But I have said on a<br />
number of occasions, that I think there is a difficult trading<br />
situation in the world. Inflation is too high in North America.<br />
Too high in Britain and in other countries of Europe. Against that<br />
background, world trade is not going to grow all that rapidly.<br />
How then, do we look after ourselves? We don't just sit back and<br />
bemoan our fate and say the world trading situation is lousy, we<br />
are going to be hurt. It will make it tougher for us. It will<br />
make it harder for us. But what do we do about it, to try and<br />
look after ourselves. I believe that economic policies that have<br />
our inflation rate below that of our major trading partners that<br />
is one point in our favour. That encourages investment and confidence<br />
activity, makes it easier for Australians to sell Australian goods, </p>
<p>4<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
here and overseas. But then, couple that with our supplies<br />
of energy, electricity based on coal, couple that with our<br />
minerals and resources, and the prospects of bringing energy<br />
together and the development and processing of our minerals<br />
and resources together in this country, then I think we are<br />
going to see much greater investment and much greater development.<br />
This is already happening. It is part of the rationale of<br />
the Department of National Development and Energy in Senator<br />
Carrick's task. , Against that background, even if the world<br />
trading situation is somewhat difficult through the next decade,<br />
I believe Australia is much better placed than virtually any<br />
other advanced industrial country. If we have the courage<br />
to have confidence in ourselves, I believe that we can have<br />
an exciting decade in the 1980' s, and maybe even the decade<br />
of this century. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
