<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1496</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE NODULAR IRON FOUNDRY AT GENERAL MOTORS-HOLDEN&#039;S FACTORY FISHERMEN&#039;S BEND, VICTORIA - SPEECH BY  THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT - 10TH FEBRUARY 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/02/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001496.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENINJ OF THE NODULAR IRON FOUNDRY<br />
AT } EKERAL MOTORS-HOLDEU' S FACTORY<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Holt<br />
February, 1967.<br />
Mr. ' ilson, Mr. President of the Senate, my colleague<br />
the Minister for Labour and National Service, and many other<br />
distinguished guests that I see in front of me here this afternoon,<br />
and my greetings to the employees of 3MH who are also here with us.<br />
It's a personal pleasure for me, Mr. Wilson to have this<br />
opportunity of saying welcome to another important adaition to<br />
Australia's range of manufacturing capacity. You have pointed out<br />
that there are few such foundries as this to be found outside of<br />
North America itself and I gather from the information you've been<br />
good enough to supply to me, that not only will this new and valuable<br />
equipment be able to supply your needs here in Australia, but that<br />
you have a market for its products already with your Vauxhall plants<br />
in the United Kingdom, and that the crankshafts manufactured here<br />
will go to supplement the other automotive parts which already are<br />
being sent to the United Kingdom from Australia. A quite remarkable<br />
achievement in itself.<br />
It is, of course well known to all Australians that the<br />
manufacturing industries of this country have been playing a growing<br />
part in our prosperous development. There are just on 60', 00<br />
factories in Australia; more than double the number we had at the<br />
beginning of World War II and the employment in those factories<br />
represents an increase of 125% on the number engaged in manufacturing<br />
in 1959. It now aosorbs through the range of manufactures around<br />
Australia, just on 28% of our work force and when we look at the<br />
number of migrants whom we must place in employment if they are<br />
to build a satisfactory new life in this country, the percentage<br />
would be even higher and certainly in this automotive industry,<br />
it would rank among the Aighest proportions of any section of<br />
Australian industry.<br />
The automotive industry has become the biggest single<br />
employer in Australia today. It absorbs, iether in production or<br />
in repair, just on one in ' ten of ill those employed in manufacturing<br />
industries and, thanks largely to this domestic manufacturing<br />
capacity of automotive parts and asseaoled cars, we rank now amongst<br />
the third or fourth motorized nation per capita in the world. I<br />
like to think we rank third. I'm told there is a uit of an argument<br />
whether we or New Zealand rank third, but if you talk about modern<br />
up-to-date cars, I've no doubt that we compare more than favourably<br />
with our sister Commonwealth country '. hich I have visited so<br />
pleasurably so recently. And so I'm here to claim that we rank<br />
third in the world, falling behind only the United States . and Canada.<br />
A pretty remarkable circumstance in a country whose manufacturing<br />
history is of such comparatively recent origin, certainly so far as<br />
this phase of it is concerned. There is at the nresent time, as we<br />
are all made rather uncomfortably aware as we go about our daily<br />
occasions or our weekend excursions, a car for just on every four<br />
men, women and children in this country and the proportion of cars<br />
to people is tending all the time to increase.<br />
One of the encouraging features of the growing and<br />
diversified manufacturing capacity of the country is the expanding<br />
success we have achieved in placing our manufactured exports aoroad<br />
and just on 12% now in value of our total exports is made up of the<br />
products of our manufacturing ildustries and that percentage is<br />
tending all the time to increase. . e not only make the goods but we<br />
are increasingly capable of placing them competitively with other parts </p>
<p>-2-<br />
of the world and some products which formerly we imported, we<br />
are now exporting to the countries from which they came. For<br />
example, we are exporting now, as Sir Ian McLennan would be happy<br />
to confirm, steel to the United States and to the United Kingdom.<br />
And I have already mentioned one of the basic components of the<br />
motor car, the crankshaft, is to " o from this country to one of<br />
the -reat automotive centres of tEe world, the United Kingdom, as<br />
an illustration of how competitive we have become.<br />
Now, undoubtably, one of the leading contributors to<br />
Australia's success in the automotive field has been the General<br />
Motors-Holden's organisation. They not only helped and indeed<br />
were largely responsible in the pioneering stage for establishing<br />
in Australia the techniques and the knowhow of the equipment and<br />
the large scale production necessary for successful manufacturing,<br />
but they have gone on rapidly and steadily with this process of<br />
innovation with the kind of research and development which is<br />
carried out in the technical area which I had the pleasure of<br />
opening less than three years ago.<br />
Every now and then, somebody takes a poke at General<br />
Motors, feeling that there could be room for some Australian<br />
equity participation and I subscrioe of course in principle to<br />
this concept, but it would be quite a mistaken belief to imagine<br />
that there is not a very sustantial Australian equity in suostance<br />
in the profitable conduct of this mighty and vast organisation<br />
here in Australia. It now has ten plants, taking on something over 20,000<br />
employees. Through the sub contracting and supply that it<br />
receives from other Australian owned and operated factories there<br />
is employment given prooably to another 30 000 people, and I was<br />
aware when I was Treasurer of the country ow much this company<br />
contributed by way of our revenue receipts to the well being of<br />
the Australian nation. I've ueen doing a little research on that<br />
subject not, I haster to assure you, with the connivance of the<br />
Commissioner of Taxes who, of course is bound to secrecy on these<br />
matters, but I have it direct from the stable itself that since<br />
1948 the company has paid either in company tax or customs duties<br />
or matters of that sort a total of 357,000,000 to the revenue<br />
of the Commonwealth and sales tax on its products has brought<br />
us in another 0700,000,000. Now that is think you'll agree, a<br />
very substantial equity contrioutinI to the funds availaole for<br />
defence, social welfare or the manifold circumstances that modern<br />
Governments have to take to themselves. And so I speak in<br />
appreciative vein here today for the contribution which this great<br />
company has made to the prosperous growth of Australia to the<br />
well-oeing of our people and to the strengthening of the nation's<br />
industrial face.<br />
e are these days producin a widely exnanding and diversified<br />
range of nroducts. I had to record quite recently a little talk for<br />
the 1967 Canadian Exposition. Somebody thought out the bright idea<br />
that unfortunate people visiting the Australian pavilion who are<br />
looking for a little rest and relaxation, would sit in some of the<br />
" talking chairs" we will provide. They will immediately be addressed by so."<br />
notable public figure or an expert in his particular field. They<br />
asked me if I would talk about our manufactures. And this is how I<br />
happen to be so well equipped with all the statistics I have been<br />
rattling off to you. But 1 myself was interested to learn that<br />
included now in the range of more sophisticated products are radio<br />
telephone equipment tr . nsistorized airways beacons, the pilotless<br />
jet aircraft we call Jindiviks the anit-submarine guided missile<br />
Ikara, and the anti-tank guided weapon Halkara and all of these<br />
items have found markets abroad including the United Kingdom and<br />
the United States. It's good I repeat, to feel that not only can<br />
we do the job but we can to it on the basis that is sufficiently<br />
competitive and attractive for these products to find their way into </p>
<p>-3-<br />
markets even in industrialised countries, with highly sophisticated<br />
manufactures themselves.<br />
Now this nodular foundry is as you've said a comparatively<br />
rare oeing in the areas of the worlA outside of North America and<br />
it speaks volumes for the confidence your company has in the future<br />
of Australia and for its capacity to export a ' rowing proportion of<br />
its manufactures to other parts of the world that you should have<br />
established the foundry here, that you should have been capable of<br />
doing this with Australian designers, Australian technicians and<br />
workmen and to have produced such an impressive result as we see<br />
around us here today. I am certain that you look forward to a<br />
successful life for the foundry.<br />
I understand that one of my more hazardous tasks is to press<br />
a green button. I've never been mechanically minded, nor mechanically<br />
efficient, and if anything goes wrong following the pressing of the<br />
button it will be a case of human error not through any fault in the<br />
equipment itself. And so formally declaring open, as now do, this<br />
nodular iron foundry, wishing you and your company continued success<br />
hoping that you in your turn will one of these days become a succe; sful<br />
ambassador abroad for Australia, joining that select company which<br />
includes Sarl Daum Harlow Jsae and David Hegland, I now have pleasure<br />
in pressing the button and hoping to hell that the thing works. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
