<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10291</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP PRESS CONFERENCE, GREAT HALL OF THE PEOPLE - FOLLOWING MEETING WITH PREMIER LI PENG - BEIJING, CHINA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/03/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010291.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Monday 31 March 1997<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, GREAT HALL OF THE PEOPLE<br />
FOLLOWING MEETING WITH PREMIER LI PENG<br />
BEIJING, CHINA<br />
E 8&amp;<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, the Premier and I had a discussion for just over an hour and a half It<br />
was a very comprehensive discussion. Both of us expressed a strong wish to build an even<br />
stronger relationship between the two countries based on mutual benefit and mutual respect.<br />
We spent a good deal of time talking about the growing economic links between Australia and<br />
China. I reminded him of the quality and depth of the business delegation that had<br />
accompanied me to his country. We noted the historical strength of Australia as a reliable<br />
supplier of raw materials and a supplier of such commodities as wheat, often through difficult<br />
times. I thanked him in advance on behalf of the ANZ Bank for the decision to grant the bank<br />
a license. I also raised with him the interests of Colonial Mutual and National Mutual in<br />
securing insurance licenses in Australia and I specifically invited him to send, and he has<br />
agreed to do so, a party from China within a short period of time to conduct a feasibility study<br />
into directly reduced iron as a source of supply to the arc furnaces of China. This particular<br />
process produces a commodity which as I understand it, and I am not an excessively technical<br />
man, as I understand it gives you something like 90 96% iron versus 30 60% in the<br />
traditional iron ore.<br />
That has enormous benefits for China lower transportation costs, lower contamination,<br />
greater compatibility with modern furnaces and it also has great benefit for Australia because<br />
we have plenty of the raw material and we have plenty of the LNG that I think would be<br />
needed in order to process it. I also made it plain that as far as the Government was<br />
concerned, that is the Australian Government is concerned, we would welcome direct equity<br />
investment from China and they have agreed to send a feasibility study. There are a number of<br />
players on the Australian scene who are interested in investing in this but it all depends on the<br />
feasibility study. If it were to get off the ground it would involve an investment of over a<br />
billion dollars and very considerable job opportunities and something like half a billion dollars </p>
<p>of export income for Australia. But I stress, it's not a done deal and I am not pretending for a<br />
moment it is but it's another example of the complementarity of our economies. I also<br />
reminded him that if they were disposed, and I understand they're considering it at present, if<br />
they were disposed to shift to a greater reliance on LNG, once again Australia was a ready<br />
supplier and a ready customer.<br />
As I foreshadowed during my press briefing this morning I also offered the services of the<br />
Australian bureaucracy in areas such as social security. China is transforming and this is a<br />
point the Premier spent talking about, transforming its society in so many ways and one of the<br />
things that it has to develop is a different social security infrastructure. Australia has a great<br />
deal of expertise in that area and some considerable success and he's very anxious to pursue<br />
that further. We both agreed that we ought to resuscitate the, if I can put it this way, the<br />
regularity of contact at a political and official level between our two countries and it's been<br />
agreed that the joint Ministerial commission should meet at least once every two years and the<br />
Vice Minister, that's a departmental head level, should meet at least every year. We also<br />
agreed in general terms that he and I should meet regularly. We didn't specify what that<br />
regularity would represent and in that context I invited him to visit Australia. He last visited<br />
Australia in 1988. So the large part of the discussion was involved in tracing the economic<br />
dimension of the association and there's a very clear commitment by him and therefore by the<br />
Chinese Government on the process of economic liberalisation and opening up the Chinese<br />
economy. I emphasise that Australia wanted China to join the World Trade Organisation both<br />
for its own sake and also for the benefits that it would bring to China. I made some comments<br />
about there perhaps being a need for more flexibility in relation to China's provisional offer on<br />
tariff quotas for wool and we had a discussion and an exchange on that but overall, it was a<br />
very positive discussion.<br />
On other matters, let me say that I made it very plain that so far as my Government was<br />
concerned we wanted China to be fully involved in the affairs of the world and to be engaged<br />
not only in the affairs of our region but also in the affairs of the world, that we didn't see<br />
China as a threat and that that was a view that we would put to and had put to other<br />
countries. I repeated my Government's support and indeed that of all Australian Governments<br />
for the last 25 years for a one China policy although I did say that we had legitimate<br />
commercial interests in the association with Taiwan and that we would, in the conduct of<br />
those legitimate commercial interests, we would endeavour to respect sensitivities in relation<br />
to the one China policy. He also repeated the Chinese position regarding Tibet. I<br />
acknowledge the sovereignty issue but I pointed out that what had been done in the past in<br />
relation to individuals there reflected the values and the mores of Australian society.<br />
A point that both of us made was that we respected each other's sovereignty and we respected<br />
the right of each country to have a different value system. I said that it was important that if<br />
the relation was to work effectively that we recognise that although we had a lot in common<br />
we had some things that we didn't have in common and it would be a good idea to have a<br />
framework to manage differences as they arose. I said that inevitably, in the area of human<br />
rights there would be differences and I proposed it to him that we should establish a dialogue<br />
on human rights. I did that because I don't think it's realistic to imagine that human rights<br />
issues are not going to crop up and obviously no Australian Government can ever say that it's<br />
not going to raise, it won't be concerned about human rights issues as they arise. He raised<br />
with me the question of Australian sponsorship of the UN resolution on human rights. I said </p>
<p>that we would be taking a decision on our position In relation to that if and when the<br />
resolution was in fact proposed.<br />
I indicated that we would be prepared to consider in a positive frame of mind the Chinese<br />
proposal to have a specific consular agreement. In the past Australia has taken the position<br />
that the Vienna protocols, I think they are Vienna protocols, maybe they are Vienna and<br />
Geneva but there are protocols which govern consular exchanges between nations. China has<br />
always argued that because of the particular circumstances of her position that we ought to<br />
have a particular agreement. Now I have said today that we would be very happy to have<br />
further discussions on that with a view perhaps to concluding that agreement.<br />
I raised specifically the position of Mr James Peng, an Australian citizen who is in jail in China.<br />
I said that he, that the Chinese Government should release him on compassionate grounds and<br />
that that would make a contribution towards the relationship between Australia and China. He<br />
said that it was a matter for the courts but he would pass on my request to the relevant<br />
authorities, I think was the expression that the Premier used. I said that it was a matter that<br />
properly should be raised because of Mr Peng's status as an Australian citizen and that his<br />
release on compassionate grounds would have a beneficial effect. I also said that the<br />
absorption, or should I say the transfer, or the incorporation of Hong Kong into China raised a<br />
number of issues that it was an important year for China and I understood the historical<br />
significance to China of that. I said that the course of Australia's very significant interest in<br />
Hong Kong, including but not only of a commercial kind, we naturally wanted a maintenance<br />
of the legal system and a free flow of information in that country. His response was that Hong<br />
Kong would remain a society of the rule of law but the basic law would in effect be the mini<br />
constitution of Hong Kong and that the Hong Kong people will continue to enjoy the<br />
freedoms they now have. They were the responses that the Premier gave me on that issue.<br />
We have of course concluded a specific consular agreement with China in relation to Hong<br />
Kong so that there is a mechanism to cover that situation.<br />
So ladies and gentlemen, it was a very good discussion. It was a detailed discussion, it was a<br />
candid discussion. I believe that the Chinese Government sincerely wants a good association<br />
with Australia. We have it. The economic links are there to be seen and they've been<br />
demonstrated amply in both Shanghai and Beijing over the past few days. The presence of so<br />
many men and women from business in Australia has helped enormously to drive home that<br />
point. The attendance of so many senior members of the Government at the luncheon today<br />
from the Chinese part also drove home the point. But none of that is to diminish the fact that<br />
we are as both of us acknowledged, different societies and we will have differences and it's<br />
important to recognise that in advance and to have a framework for dealing with them so that<br />
they can be handled properly and I believe that the Premier and I have gone some distance<br />
towards establishing that framework today and I regard myself as very well pleased with the<br />
discussions that have taken place.<br />
JRNLST: Could you sum up his response to the human rights issue?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well he understands that there will be differences on this issue and he understands that it is </p>
<p>inevitable from time to time that Australia will want to raise issues and I made that, that was<br />
evident from the nature of the discussion that we've had.<br />
JRNLST: Did you agree with the dialogue from...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well he gave no specific response to that.<br />
JRNLST: What other dialogue were you proposing?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it would be at an official level. When you have a dialogue at an official level, that's the<br />
framework but that doesn't mean to say that specific issues can't subsequently be raised at a<br />
ministerial level.<br />
JRNLST: Just how firm was he in terms of raising the question?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
How firm, well he raised it. It wasn't something that occupied a lot of discussion but he put a<br />
point of view and I put a point of view in response.<br />
JRNLST: I just wonder if he did that on any other issue such as Taiwan for example?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
He sought reassurance on the one China policy and I gave him that but with the rider, well,<br />
rider is perhaps the wrong word, with the accompanying comment that Australia has<br />
legitimate commercial links with Taiwan.<br />
JRNLST: Prime Minister, what were your personal feelings about meeting Mr Peng so close to<br />
Tiananmen Square given that he's the man responsible?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well as I said this morning my one responsibility overseas is to represent and promote the<br />
interests of Australia and I have endeavoured every minute I've been here to conduct myself in </p>
<p>a way that promotes the interests of Australia and I am satisfied that everything I have done<br />
does promote those interests. I think that is the appropriate response to that question.<br />
JRNLST: Did the Premier talk about Australia's relationship with the US?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, no it was not raised. Australia's relationship with the United States was not raised and<br />
there is nothing really more I can say. It was simply not raised by the Premier and it was not<br />
raised by me because as I've said repeatedly in the past, that association is a stand alone<br />
association. It's borne out of our own clear headed assessment of our national interest.<br />
JRNLST:<br />
What would you classify as the concrete steps towards this new era of economic growth?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I don't know whether new era. It's a question of building on what we've already<br />
achieved and also taking advantage of the fuirther opportunities. I think the greatest possible<br />
facilitation by the Government where appropriate, of commercial links between China and<br />
Australian business men and women is the best way of doing it. As I said in Shanghai, that it's<br />
important that the Chinese see the Australian Government and the business community of<br />
Australia working together in economic matters because that is more the custom here and we<br />
have to be sensible enough to tailor our approaches and synchronise our approaches in a way<br />
that gets the best results and that's what I want to do.<br />
JRNLST: who Australia's players are that are interested in the iron ore processes?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I think I could get my colleagues to give you some of that information, yes. I mean, let<br />
me make it clear that we naturally will want the normal market forces in Australia to sort out<br />
who gets it but I think there are three but I am sure Max or the Ambassador or Arthur<br />
Sinodinos can give you some help on that but it's certainly, if it takes off will be a very<br />
exciting project.<br />
Thank you very much. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
