<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7560</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF JOINT NEWS CONFERENCE WITH JOHN KERIN, MINISTER FOR PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 10 APRIL 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/04/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007560.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF JOINT NEWS CONFERENCE WITH JOHN KERIN,<br />
MINISTER FOR PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY, PARLIAMENT<br />
HOUSE, 10 APRIL 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Well, I want to just make a few general observations by<br />
way of introduction to the important announcement that my<br />
colleague, John Kerin, has got to make in regard to the<br />
deregulation of the wheat industry.<br />
The basic point I'd make is that, of course, from the very<br />
beginning of our time in Government in 1983, this Government<br />
has embarked not only on rescuing the Australian economy and<br />
of pursuing appropriate macroeconomic policies, but putting<br />
in place consistent microeconomic reform which is calculated<br />
to make the Australian economy increasingly efficient and<br />
competitive.<br />
my press release sets out those decisions that we've taken<br />
and which are quite well known. I point out in the<br />
statement that during the last election campaign, on 6 July<br />
1987 in Ballarat, I set out there twelve areas of<br />
microeconomic reform which would characterise the third<br />
period of the Hawke Government.<br />
In the attachment I indicate the way in which a slight<br />
majority of those areas have been addressed and those that<br />
are left will be dealt with in the next two months in a<br />
series of statements to be made from here through to the end<br />
of May. That will, by that stage, mean that we have totally<br />
covered all those areas which I promised that we would do in<br />
July of 1987.<br />
So this period of Government generally from ' 83 and in<br />
particular from 1987, has seen a greater period and<br />
intensity of microeconomic reform than at any other period<br />
in Australian history.<br />
I invite anyone who is interested in this area to make the<br />
comparison between the performance of this Government in the<br />
area of microeconomic reform and the previous seven years of<br />
conservatives. As in virtually every area of relevance to<br />
the welfare of this Australian economy, they were barren and<br />
inept. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
( PM cont): Our period in Government stands in marked<br />
contrast to that. I say that by way of introduction to the<br />
important decision that John Kerin is going to announce.<br />
The background of that of course is that we recognise the<br />
great importance of the wheat industry, it provides the best<br />
part of $ 2 billion of exports to this country. It was<br />
almost $ 2 billion in 1987/ 88 and while it's shown its basic<br />
efficiency, there are further things that can be done, we<br />
believe, to increase that efficiency and the profitability<br />
therefore of the industry to the producers in it.<br />
We established the Royal Commission in cooperation with the<br />
States, the Royal Commission into Grain Storage, Handling<br />
and Transport. We've taken the action that we can in that<br />
area, but there are limits to what we can do.<br />
We have, as a Cabinet, made decisions that more now needs to<br />
be done. John Kerin will go into the details of that.<br />
KERIN: Thank you very much Prime Minister. It's very<br />
difficult to know where to start, but the last IAC Reports<br />
have said that on balance it would be very sensible to<br />
deregulate the domestic wheat market.<br />
The reason they've been saying that is mainly to get<br />
efficiency gains right across the cropping sector.<br />
The Balderstone Committee also examined this whole question<br />
of domestic market deregulation and said that cost savings<br />
could be achieved in this manner. We put in place the Royal<br />
Commission into Grain Transport, Handling and Storage and<br />
they said that there's potential gain to cost savings off<br />
farm of $ 10 per tonne.<br />
If you look at that for wheat and barley alone, that's about<br />
$ 170 million for the industry off farms. It varies for<br />
about $ 6 per tonne in South Australia to $ 13 per tonne in<br />
Queensland.<br />
Now in the negotiations with the Grains Council who have<br />
been vehemently opposed to any deregulation, mainly because<br />
they've been taking the National Party view or more<br />
accurately the National Party's been taking their view,<br />
which is really a status quo view they have pointed out<br />
that we also need to make sure that we get these changes in<br />
the transport and handling and they're in the arms of the<br />
States.<br />
We did what we could at the Commonwealth level. We removed<br />
the road provision in South Australia, but more importantly<br />
we gave the Wheat Board additional powers by saying that<br />
they no longer need to deal with only one grain handler in<br />
each State. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
( Kerin cont): Through that they've been able to get some<br />
savings for the wheat industry in this year.<br />
Now what we are announcing today following Cabinet<br />
consideration, is that we will be giving the Wheat Board a<br />
transport override power.<br />
We've been advised that Constitutionally we can do that with<br />
the export power and we believe that that will give the<br />
Wheat Board even more power to negotiate with the States<br />
where those States aren't passing on savings, where those<br />
States are simply extracting a rent from the grains<br />
industry.<br />
Now there will be a lot of opposition to this from quite a<br />
few people, mainly I guess from the National Party, from the<br />
Grains Council, from the States in some instances. But the<br />
simple proposition is for this country, if you are going to<br />
impose an additional $ 170 million or $ 200 million worth of<br />
cost on yourself, that is less production, it is less<br />
exports and it is less additional need for the facilities.<br />
The situation the way it's all just grown up like topsy,<br />
does mean that we have storage in this country today for<br />
about 43 million tonnes of grains and the biggest wheat crop<br />
ever was about 22 million tonnes.<br />
Now, putting this into political terms, John Howard now has<br />
no reason to weezel out of what he said last week in the<br />
press release with Bruce Lloyd from the National Party. He<br />
laid down four conditions and of course there had been a lot<br />
of discussion about the word reasonable progress.<br />
Today's announcement shows how far we're going to go. Mr<br />
Sinclair of course, even a couple of weeks ago, trying to<br />
find impossible conditions to put upon us pointed out that<br />
we really need to get deregulation of the world's wheat<br />
markets, if not the world itself, before the National Party<br />
would agree to it.<br />
Well, I'd also point out with the breakthrough in Geneva<br />
over the weekend, we can even go quite a way in<br />
agricultural trade reform, but we haven't quite fixed up the<br />
world yet. But it was really a churlish attitude to say<br />
that you've got to do everything at once rather in seriatum<br />
and I think what the Prime Minister points out is, where we<br />
have the opportunity, where we can take action, where we can<br />
really effect real change, we will do it.<br />
I repeat, Mr Howard has no choice now but to go along with<br />
the Government's legislation. If he doesn't he will be<br />
weezelling out of it and have absolutely no credibility in<br />
terms of microeconomic reform or sensible non idealogical<br />
deregulation. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you deliver though in terms of the rail<br />
union KERIN: It's not a question of delivering with the rail<br />
unions. If the Board has the power to negotiate with the<br />
State Rail Authorities, it is my view that the wheat will<br />
travel by rail. The question of jobs being at risk because<br />
of this doesn't come up.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you anticipate there will be a<br />
Constitutional challenge to this move?<br />
KERIN: Given the stupidity of the National Party in<br />
Queensland, I would think so.<br />
PM: I think the basis of the Constitutional power is very<br />
clear though. Clearly within Section 51.1 of the<br />
Constitution, the Commonwealth has power to legislate in<br />
regard to trade and commerce with other countries and among<br />
the States. Very clear, unequivocal power and while, in<br />
their desperation, some may seek to make a Constitutional<br />
challenge, we believe and are advised that we have very<br />
sound Constitutional basis for the decison we've taken.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you had any talks with the Victorian<br />
Government about this?<br />
KERIN: No, the focus is centred on Victoria rather than<br />
Queensland mainly because of the Grain Council's views in<br />
that State. They don't choose to select out Queensland<br />
where the most expensive system is in place. But the short<br />
answer is<br />
JOURNALIST: any discussion with the Victorian<br />
Government about this matter?<br />
0 KERIN: The Prime Minister wrote to the Victorian Government<br />
after the McColl Grains Commission, Royal Commission on<br />
Grains and we are still waiting for a response. We have<br />
indicated quite clearly that we are going to try to put in<br />
place the recommendation of McColl and so far really only<br />
the NSW government has responded.<br />
JOURNALIST: The statement says you're going to override<br />
restrictive state regulations but for some curious reason it<br />
doesn't say what they are. Is it a secret or are you<br />
prepared to tell us?<br />
KERIN: The restrictive regulations are manifold in the<br />
whole freight transport and handling system. They involve<br />
many practices by the States but the main one of course is<br />
the extraction of rent from the grains industry. 1 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Kerin poor position, does that mean that<br />
you are also proceeding with the 95% underwriting<br />
KERIN: The reality of that is that that is a figure plucked<br />
out of the air because there was a 95% net underwriting at<br />
one stage. I'm informed in terms of discussions by the<br />
Opposition they're not going to die in a ditch over 95 or<br />
JOURNALIST: So you've had discussions with the opposition?<br />
KERIN: No, but I know what goes on.<br />
JOURNALIST: How do you know what goes on?<br />
PM: You're not the o nly one that has contacts.<br />
KERIN: My people talk to their people.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would the Commonwealth be prepared to negotiate<br />
at the Premiers' Conference to offset any losses to the<br />
States through<br />
PM: There needn't be any.<br />
JOURNALIST:-KERIN: There need not be any losses. we are trying to get<br />
more efficiencies. If you get more efficiencies and you get<br />
greater product, you will get greater turnover and you will<br />
probably get a more efficient use of the system.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you like to do something similar with<br />
coal, which is also the subject of..<br />
KERIN: I'd like to but I'm not so sure this path would<br />
work. I'd have to get more legal advice on that but<br />
basically I think we can quarantine this because we're using<br />
the Wheat Board. But this could flow on into some of those<br />
areas. JOURNALIST: Is overriding a state legislation the trump<br />
card you've been holding until the Coalition position came<br />
out or only just come in?<br />
KERIN: I guess it's truthful to say a bit of both. We're<br />
aware generally of the powers, we're used to being lectured<br />
by the States about what Constitutional powers are. We<br />
decided to investigate this fully during our discussion on<br />
the whole question of wheat deregulation when the debate<br />
intensified so much to see what additional options were<br />
available to us.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, your statement foreshadows<br />
announcements of coastal shipping waterfront and the<br />
waterfront. The ACTU </p>
<p>PM: Only the waterfront once, not twice.<br />
JOURNALIST: I'm sorry, I repeated myself.<br />
PM: Once is going to be hard enough I can assure you.<br />
JOURNALIST: Exactly. Mr Kelty seems to have set himself<br />
against it.<br />
PM: Why do you misrepresent Mr Kelty setting himself<br />
against waterfront reform? You've got not one piece of<br />
evidence to support that proposition.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well I have camera tape<br />
PM: No, what you can report I'll tell you now, I haven't<br />
seen your tape but I'll tell you what's on it and that is<br />
that Mr Kelty did not embrace all the recommendations that<br />
were brought down by the IAC. That is not the same<br />
proposition that he set himself against reform on the<br />
waterfront and the opposite is true because I've had<br />
detailed conversations with Mr Kelty and I know that he<br />
supports reform. So please get it right.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, is the big hangup the question of the<br />
coverage of the WWF is that where Mr Kelty sees real<br />
difficulties PM: That's one of the areas because quite clearly you've<br />
got a situation where the waterfront, Waterside Workers<br />
Federation is a body which has had its membership<br />
drastically reduced in the last generation, basically as you<br />
know as a result of the fundamental move towards<br />
containerisation. They are now relatively a very small<br />
union and they are naturally enough going to be concerned<br />
about any suggestions which regard to outlying ports or<br />
in other aspects of the report would involve a significant<br />
further reduction in their membership. That's<br />
understandable. The important point to understand is that<br />
the core elements of. the IAC report in regard to reform<br />
don't turn on those issues. So I believe that it is going<br />
to be possible to achieve through negotiation some<br />
significant reforms in a way which will not meet the<br />
understandable opposition of the Waterside Workers<br />
Federation in regard to issues which from their point of<br />
view are quite understandable, which I repeat are not<br />
central to the thrust of reform.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think there can be effective reform on<br />
the waterfront as long as the labour system continues?<br />
PM: Let me put it this way, that one of the central<br />
elements of the IAC report is the concept of single<br />
employment. I believe that there is a basis for getting<br />
towards that position. I don't think that is necessarily<br />
something which is </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Why are you flagging these reforms in this<br />
statement today? Is it good political timing to go with the<br />
tax cuts, or what's the reason for putting this out today?<br />
PM: To give I think there are a number of reasons<br />
Heather. There's been a fair amount of extraordinarily<br />
loose and ill-based talk about this Government having lost<br />
its impetus, never one basis of foundation for that loose<br />
sort of talk. So we thought, one reason, it's not a bad<br />
idea therefore to get out clearly the range of very<br />
significant action which has been consistently going on<br />
under this Government during our third term that's point<br />
one. Point two, I have made the point recently that the<br />
April Statement that Paul was bringing down is not of itself<br />
one which is going to contain significant micro-economic<br />
reform proposals and I have said that there would be however<br />
a series of decisions in this area around this time. So<br />
what I've decided is that I would take this opportunity of<br />
setting down the sort of timetable and program for those<br />
further areas of reform which will complete the Ballarat<br />
process, if I can put it that way. Thirdly, I wanted to<br />
have the opportunity of putting this very significant reform<br />
that John Kerin is announcing into the wider program of<br />
reform. It is important in its own right obviously for the<br />
reasons that I and the Minister have outlined. But it's<br />
properly to be seen as part of a total program of<br />
micro-economic reform.<br />
KERIN: To quote John Howard, the timing has suited me.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, in your statement you note that you<br />
needed to make change, a precondition of that change<br />
responsive financial sector freeing up the banks. Well they<br />
certainly are freed up. One of them, Citibank, is talking<br />
about home loan rates going to 18% now. Is that kind of<br />
talk helpful?<br />
PM: I've got nothing to add to the rather concise answer<br />
that the Treasurer gave on that matter in the House today.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Kerin, in your statement you speak of<br />
exempting the AWB and other grain trading corporations etc.<br />
What are the other corporations that you have in mind?<br />
KERIN: In terms of the route we're going down this could<br />
apply to the State Barley Board and virtually other<br />
corporations. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke do you concede there has been a large<br />
rise in housing affordabilty and do you concede the<br />
possibility that interest rates could reach 18% under this<br />
term of your Government? </p>
<p>-8-<br />
PM: I'm not conceding that possibility. I've said that I<br />
don't speculate about immediate short term possible<br />
movements in interest rates because the very fact the Prime<br />
Minister or the Treasurer speculate about possible short<br />
term movements can of itself be a factor in what happens to<br />
those movements. So both Paul and myself don't do that.<br />
That's different from what I said at the beginning of the<br />
year, when I talked about, when I was asked what would<br />
be the situation at the end of the year, I was quite<br />
prepared to make that statement but I'm not going to<br />
speculate about short term movements.<br />
JOURNALIST: And you still believe that will be the case,<br />
that by the end of the year the rates will come down<br />
PM: I have no reason to change the observation I made in<br />
January. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke speaking about the will<br />
Wednesday's statement see the Government child poverty?<br />
PM: Well I think it really is fair to wait until then. I<br />
mean I'm not going to pre-empt the statements that will be<br />
made then. But I think you'll find not only in that area<br />
but in other areas of social welfare that it will be a very<br />
well received statement.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you still stand by your comment Mr Hawke<br />
that the top marginal tax rate won't be reduced unless<br />
PM: I'm not going to be making announcements that will be<br />
properly made by the Treasurer on Wednesday night. I mean<br />
you don't really expect me to<br />
JOURNALIST: announcement, you actually said previously<br />
PM: Anything I said on that would be a pre-emption of what<br />
the Treasurer will announce. He'll make the announcements<br />
for and on behalf of the Government on Wednesday evening.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you agree that someone seems to have<br />
pre-empted it?<br />
PM: Well let me put it this way Laurie. We haven't yet<br />
reached the " Oakesian" deluge of our conservative<br />
predecessors. But there does seem to have been some sort of<br />
hints about what may be coming out. I will not add to those<br />
but I simply add I'm pleased that we haven't seen the<br />
proportions of deluge that were associated with your coup.<br />
JOURNALIST: blaming the unions for that? </p>
<p>-9-<br />
PM: I'm not blaming anyone. I mean it would be a little<br />
bit unfair wouldn't it because I mean even when unions<br />
haven't been associated with discussions, when it's just<br />
been a matter of Ministers and Departments, they haven't<br />
been leak-proof in the past.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does this mean Mr Hawke that the tax<br />
pledges are now back in the melting pot? For example what<br />
does this mean that all your<br />
PM: It means it's nothing more complex, sophisticated,<br />
esoteric or difficult to understand than this; that the<br />
announcements will be made on Wednesday night by the<br />
Treasurer and not on Monday by me.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke in your list of microeconomic reforms<br />
you've got reference to the change in defence industries.<br />
Could you give us a bit of an idea what that means?<br />
PM: I'm sorry?<br />
JOURNALIST: In your list of microeconomic reform statements<br />
in May, amongst them you've got defence industries. I<br />
just wondered if you could be<br />
PM: That further announcements will be made? waiting<br />
for the Ministers to make those.<br />
JOURNALIST: But if you can just give us some idea of what<br />
this microeconomic reform in that area will mean?<br />
PM: Well it will be to do with the increasing commercial<br />
nature of the operations of industries in that area. But<br />
all I've done there is to indicate the areas where<br />
announcments are going to be made. I mean that's not an<br />
invitation from me to you to be asking what those<br />
announcements will be.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke one of the things you were saying<br />
continue to encourage the elimination of outdated work<br />
practices. We've had the in the second tier agreement.<br />
Now none of these things show up in the statistics<br />
having substantially boosted productivity. Do you think<br />
that we've got any reason to believe that the award<br />
restructuring will be any different?<br />
PM: It's not fair of you Milton to say that those<br />
initiatives have petered out. The initiative that I began<br />
in Melbourne some three years ago moved logically into the<br />
second tier and now it's been tuned into the processes of<br />
award restructuring. I don't think you need to rely on my<br />
assessment, Paul Keating's assessment or Bill Kelty's<br />
assessment, I mean you turn to the employers themselves. I<br />
suggest that the enthusiasm of the Metal Trades' Employers<br />
where the initial detailed negotiations have taken place<br />
confirms our belief and assertions the implications of this </p>
<p>PM ( cont): restructuring process. The Metal Trades'<br />
Employers who talked to Mr Evans on behalf of the trades<br />
industry association, they are excited and understandably<br />
excited about the implications of the restructuring process,<br />
and so they should be because I mean I don't know why people<br />
as they are have any sceptisism about this. It seems to me<br />
to be beyond argument that if you take the metal trades,<br />
which is the major award in the manufacturing sector, if you<br />
are going to take that award 350 classifications wipe<br />
that out and get down to 8 classifications which is going to<br />
create a career structure and a remuneration basis related<br />
to that career structure so that the classifications are<br />
relevant to the modern processes of production and give you<br />
a firm and sensible and relevant basis for training and<br />
retraining programs, you have to have a degree of sceptisism<br />
which is even beyond what we tend to find around this place<br />
at times, to argue that that's not going to have significant<br />
impact in industry, it will. That's why, let me say, the<br />
employers concerned have entered into this process with<br />
enthusiasm as well as the trade unions. It's the most<br />
revolutionary thing that's happened in industrial relations<br />
in this country in this century. Because it's not just a<br />
question of what's happened in the past where if the<br />
employers have had the power they've been able to impose it<br />
and cut wages or where the unions have had power they've<br />
imposed there's or have had wage increases which are beyond<br />
the economic capacity of the country. Uniquely now what<br />
you've got is a joint commitment of employers and unions to<br />
tackle a whole process of wage fixation and industrial<br />
classification in terms of what's going to meet the<br />
interests of the industry unique.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke are you concerend that very large pay<br />
increases for lower paid workers may impact on their<br />
employment? PM: If it were handled rationally yes that could occur.<br />
But I think you'll find that the processes of phasing which<br />
we spelt out in more detail are such that they will be<br />
able to be accommodated in a way which you're not going to<br />
have adverse employment effects. I mean in the end I mean<br />
the unions concerned in these areas are not going to act<br />
against their own interests. I mean if you are looking at<br />
this concept of supplementary payments and say we're going<br />
to whack it all in in one go, then I think you would run<br />
that risk. I think you avoid it by the process of phasing<br />
over a considerable period of time.<br />
KERIN: The fruit pickers award in Queensland is $ 231 a<br />
week. It would be a terrible thing to do anything about<br />
that, wouldn't it?<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister do you have any information on<br />
why the Belconnen branch of the Labor Party is suddenly<br />
being mentioned in connection with the Winchester case? </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
