<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3427</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE, CANBERRA, TUESDAY 22 OCTOBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003427.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE, CANBERRA,<br />
TUESDAY, 22 OCTOBER 1974<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Are there any questions?<br />
QUESTION: Do you expect to get support of any or all of the<br />
States for the Federal Government's initiatives in building<br />
hospitals? What indications do you have of their reaction<br />
to the proposal? If you don't get support from any or all<br />
the States, will the Federal Government still go ahead on its<br />
own initiatives?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There is more than one matter upon which I<br />
have writen this financial year to the States concerning<br />
hospitals. I was asked at Question Time today about the specific<br />
proposal that my Government had made to the Governments of New<br />
South Wales, Victoria and Queensland. I had suggested to the<br />
Premiers that since the money which had been made available<br />
last financial year to the Governments for specific projects<br />
planning or construction hadn't been spent to any degree at<br />
all, they should let us take over the sites, complete the plans<br />
and construct and operate the hospitals. The particular<br />
hospitals concerned were Westmead and Campbelltown near Sydney,<br />
Sunshine in Melbourne and Mount Gravatt in Brisbane. In each<br />
case the Premier has replied. In each case I think I could say<br />
that they didn't accept the proposition. I expect that the<br />
Government will be going ahead. Ever since the 1946 referendum<br />
the Australian Government has had the opportunity we would<br />
therefore say the responsibility to provide medical services.<br />
Clearly hospitals are a crucial item in the provision of medical<br />
services. There are not adequate hospital facilities within<br />
ten miles of Westmead or Campbelltown or Sunshine or Mount Gravatt.<br />
The population in each of those areas is growing very rapidly.<br />
It is quite clear that hospital facilities will be needed in<br />
each of those areas much earlier than the States would ever be<br />
able to provide them. In some cases the States haven't got<br />
plans. In the case of Westmead, where New South Wales has had<br />
plans for six or eight years and where, in the last financial<br />
year, we made $ 4k million available, the State was only able to<br />
spend, I think, about 10 per cent of that amount. It is clear<br />
that we shouldn't wait any longer before seeing the people in those<br />
rapidly growing areas are able to have a full range of medical<br />
services at a modern hospital.<br />
QUESTION: Has the Royal Commission into Australia's security<br />
services begun its hearings yet?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There won't, I expect, be open hearings.<br />
QUESTION: Has it begun its work yet?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes. Mr. Justice Hope, the Royal Commissioner,<br />
has alreay consulted many people.<br />
QUESTION: Will you ensure that as many public hearings as<br />
possible will be held and where, for security reasons, they won't<br />
be held in camera will you arrange for a list of witnesses to be </p>
<p>-2-<br />
made available so that the public are kept informed of the progress<br />
of the Royal Commission?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I will do nothing of the sort. The Royal<br />
Commissioner is free to conduct his Commission as he sees fit.<br />
I have no doubt that he will conduct it in a completely proper<br />
way none whatever.<br />
QUESTION: If unemployment is increasing at the rate of 5,000<br />
per week, what hope can you offer to the huge number of young<br />
Australians leaving school this year?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There is a debate going on in the House at<br />
the moment on this, among other aspects, and I don't propose<br />
to duplicate it.<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Cameron in the House last week in reply to a<br />
question by Mr. Cairns said " No" to the question: " Will he<br />
guarantee full employment to the Australian workforce, including<br />
school leavers, by March/ April next year?" Does this mean, sir,<br />
that; jou are presiding over the demise....?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, before you go any further, Mr. Power,<br />
you.. know that I don't comment on things like this. If you<br />
want an elucidation of this matter, you ask Mr. Cameron.<br />
Mr. Cameron is never reluctant to go on radio.<br />
QUESTION: You said yesterday that you and other ministers would<br />
be talking to trade union leaders to explain the Government's<br />
decision on wage restraint. What steps are you contemplating<br />
specifically to secure return of business confidence? Have<br />
you given any more thought to the question of investment allowances?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't want to specify any particular measures.<br />
As I said last week, this is one of the measures which I am quite<br />
happy to consider and my colleagues too. We have shown ourselves<br />
completely flexible in considering proposals to have business<br />
confidence. Business confidence is quite necessary, obviously,<br />
if there is to be adequate employment or investment for the future.<br />
QUESTION: If the Opposition in the Senate amends your Budget<br />
legislation to restore the $ 400 education allowance, would there<br />
be an election in December?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I won't speculate on that matter.<br />
QUESTION: Are you planning or have you planned a second bid for<br />
prices and incomes powers by a referendum?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have taken no steps.<br />
QUESTION: Do you have it under consideration?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have taken no steps.<br />
QUESTION: Will you be able to assure Mr. Tanaka, do you think,<br />
when he arrives here later this month that the Australian Government<br />
won't be stood over by trade unions to impose import quotas on<br />
Japanese exports because of unemployment in Australia? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You are, I think, referring to something that one<br />
union did in respect to Japanese cars last week. The trade union<br />
movement itself properly handled this matter.<br />
QUESTION: Did Dr. Cairns consult with you before writing to the<br />
Associatd Chambers of Manufactures in support of the campaign<br />
to have the general review of tariffs deferred and its criteria<br />
changed? Do you support that campaign?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I answered a question on this subject in the<br />
House this morning. Dr. Cairns was acting as Prime Minister<br />
when he wrote the letter which was published in today's<br />
Financial Review. I stated today, at Question Time, that if<br />
ACMA, to whose representation Dr. Cairns was responding, chose<br />
to give its views to the Jackson Committee then it would be very<br />
welcome to do so. I am sure the Jackson Committee would expect<br />
to get the views of ACMA on tariff matters. The Jackson Committee<br />
has been asked to look into tariff matters in the course of its<br />
review of manufacturing industry generally.<br />
QUESTION: Do you support that campaign though?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I % am inviting ACMA to put its point of view to<br />
the committee which the Government has set up to prepare a Green<br />
Paper on all aspects of manufacturing industry, including tariffs.<br />
ACMA is certainly entitled to put its point of view, but obviously<br />
its views should be put, among other places, to the Jackson<br />
Committee. QUESTION: Further to Mr. Jost's question on the prices and<br />
incomes, do you intend to discuss this matter with Mr. Hawke<br />
at the weekend?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I wasn't proposing to.<br />
QUESTION: When will you take further steps regarding prices and<br />
incomes? PRIME MINISTER: I have got no further answer.<br />
QUESTION: Do you hope to get the Japanese beef market re-opened<br />
during the talks with Mr. Tanaka next week?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: obviously all our exports to Japan will be<br />
discussed and-among them beef.<br />
QUESTION: Can you explain the logic of the Government's moves to<br />
insist that the oil companies in Australia charge world parity<br />
prices for aviation turbine fuel to international airlines?<br />
Why should the Government be so determined to bood-the. profits<br />
of oil companies at the expense of the airlines, particularly<br />
Qantas and their passengers?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You ought to ask Mr. Connor about that.<br />
QUESTION: Have you had drawn to your attention remarks made by<br />
Mr. Tony O'Reilly in Albury at an advertising conference last<br />
Sunday? </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, I have the cutting here.<br />
QUESTION: Got any comments on it at all, sir? In particular<br />
he gave a drubbing to the Prices Justification Tribunal?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: But he gave a terrific boost to the Trade<br />
Practices Act.<br />
Comment: That's right, he did. I think he thinks they ought<br />
to be centralised.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't want to comment on the Prices Justification<br />
Trubunal. Its President is a distinguished judge He has made<br />
some statements himself. He has given prepared addresses himself<br />
on the operations of the tribunal. As you know the tribunal has<br />
been in operation for less than a year and a v~ ery great deal<br />
of pioneering work has had to be done. A great number of companies<br />
don't like what has been done but the Government will introduce<br />
amend;..,-ents to the Act we have done so already in the last month<br />
where those amendments are seen to be necessary or desirable.<br />
The Tribunal will be consulted on any amendments, as it was<br />
concerning the amendments which were made last month. But I don't<br />
want to comment on the operations of the Tribunal; it is properly<br />
constituted and it has been a very effective body indeed.<br />
But I am very happy to quote what Mr. Tony O'Reilly said about<br />
the Trade Practices Act. He approved of the Act. In fact<br />
it was modelled on two United States Acts, the Sherman and the<br />
Clayton Acts, and if it was applied with the same vigour and<br />
capability, it would sharpen competition, obviate monopoly,<br />
increase above-the-line spending, decrease below-the-line spending<br />
and frustrate discriminatory business dealings. Mr. Tony O'Reilly,<br />
you might have pointed out, is the head of the H. J. Heinz company,<br />
so while I don't want to comment about what he said on the Prices<br />
Justification Tribunal T am delighted to quote what he said about<br />
the Trade Practices Act. If it had been in a year longer, as<br />
it should have been if the Senate had passed it when it first<br />
got it, then obviously we would be in a better position than we<br />
are today.<br />
QUESTION: I believe Mr. O'Reilly also had something to say about<br />
the way depreciation of capital assets was counted by the Income<br />
Tax Commissioner in regard to company profits. Did you also take<br />
note of that or not?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, I didn't get that far. I don't know whether<br />
he said it but I don't remember seeing it.<br />
QUESTION: Apparently, it was reported?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, I am going naturally on a paper of record,<br />
teSydney Morning Herald. It doesn't report that.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, further down at the bottom of that<br />
article he talks about a proliferation of nuclear devices by<br />
hungry countries. Does that strike a chord with you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have said a few things, naturally, about the<br />
proliferation of nuclear weapons. I did so at the United Nations<br />
three weeks ago. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Do you see any possibility of speeding up the processes<br />
to introduce wage indexation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This matter will be before the Conciliation<br />
and Arbitration Commission. I would expect a decision would be<br />
given before Christmas. We will be supporting the application<br />
as you know.<br />
QUESTION: This morning Mr. Hawke called for a series of supplementary<br />
action to the Budget including a cut in indirect taxes, a cut in<br />
imports, grants to the States to enable them to keep down fuel<br />
and transport costs and both tax indexation and wage indexation.<br />
How many of these things are you sympathetic towards?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: These seem to be matters which were covered<br />
by the resolutions of the A. C. T. U. meeting of unions about three<br />
weeks ago. Several of my colleagues and I have discussed these<br />
with Mr. Hawke, Mr. Souter and Dr. Jolly. Discussions will take<br />
place on other occasions over the next few weeks.<br />
QUESTION: Is the Government considering introducing a supplementary<br />
Budget between now and Christmas?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No.<br />
QUESTION: Has any of the working parties set up after the last<br />
Premiers Conference held any meetings? Have you 7Z-ad any...?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Most have made reports.<br />
QUESTION: They have made a report?<br />
PRIME MINISTER,: Most of them have made reports.<br />
QUESTION: Are you going to make the reports public?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'll consult with the Premiers about this.<br />
QUESTION: Are there any worthwhile ideas flowing from these meetings?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, there are. The State and federal officials<br />
concerned have made a very good examination of the matters which were<br />
referred to them by the Premiers and me.<br />
QUESTION: Are you satisfied with the quality of advice and<br />
submissions flowing to your Government from the Federal Treasury,<br />
and are you finding them valuable in the fight against inflation<br />
and unemployment?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Federal Treasury is one source of advice.<br />
My colleagues -and I get advice from several sources and all of<br />
that advice is valuable and is given proper consideration.<br />
Treasury advice is valuable on many matters.<br />
QUESTION: In relation to the CPIs yesterday, both yourself and<br />
Mr. Crean used the word " disturbing". Does the Government therefore<br />
intend to take any more measures...?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This matter is being debated in the House at<br />
the moment. I don't propose to duplicate the debate. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
QUESTION: Are you leaving it all to the trade unions to show<br />
wage restraint?.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I expect them to show wage restraint but it<br />
is not a matter for the trade unions only, quite clearly. I put<br />
the point about wage restraint yesterday to ACSPA, and also to<br />
the Miscellaneous workers' Union one of the very largest unions<br />
in Australia and one of the biggest three on Monday of last<br />
week. But it is not the unions only. I believe that the<br />
discussions several of my colleagues have had with Mr. Hawke,<br />
Mr. Souter and Dr. Jolly will help to bring about wage restraintwhat<br />
we are doing, for instance, to urge and support the case<br />
for wage indexation is one instance of that. As a result of<br />
discussions which have taken place between the Government and<br />
the various trade union organisations, ACTU and ACSPA, I believe<br />
there will be fewer and smaller claims for wage and salary<br />
increases. Most employees will find that their needs are<br />
satisfactorily and more promptly met by wage indexation.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, is there any possibility of changes<br />
to your ministry in the near future in the light of the<br />
economic problems? And, in particular, have you given any<br />
consideration to using Mr. Crean' s considerable talents in<br />
another portfolio?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I would want to discuss this with the Governor-<br />
General before I mentioned it in this wider circumstance.<br />
QUESTION: When does the Government intend to announce its<br />
plans for the development of the Northwest Shelf gas deposits<br />
in sufficient detail so that work which has been held up now<br />
for about nine months can proceed?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Government hasn't held up any of these matters.<br />
It is the Petroleum and Minerals Authority legislation which has<br />
been held up again and again, of course; just as, for instance,<br />
were some of the regulations under the Atomic Energy Act.<br />
The Australian Government has been trying to get the necessary<br />
legislative framework to implement its resources policy, its<br />
resources program. We haven't held it up.<br />
QUESTION: If this legislation takes another year or two to get<br />
clear of the High Court will there be no development until then?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I hope that it won't take another year to get<br />
clear of the High Court but we didn't take the matter to the<br />
High Court, as you realise. This bill was three times rejected<br />
in the Senate. It was passed at a joint sitting. It is now<br />
under challenge in the High Court.<br />
QUESTION: When would you be seeing the Governor-General about<br />
any possible changes in the ministry?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Of course that was a purely facetious answer,<br />
as you know. I know 2SM is a fun station but I don't wish people<br />
to think that everything Laurie Oakes asks or every answer I give<br />
him is dead serious.<br />
QUESTION: Hasn't one of the major pieces of the legislation<br />
involving the development of the north west shelf gas already<br />
passed, namely the Pipelines Act and isn't it a matter... </p>
<p>-7-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That's under some challenge too, isn't it?<br />
QUESTION: No, not that 7, know of. Secondly, doesn't the<br />
dee-omn hinge on two things that are not connected with the<br />
PIR, whether or not there should be ex ports and what price<br />
the Pipelines Authority should pay for the gas and when will<br />
arrwers be given to these questions which so far seem to have been<br />
d Iayed until 1981, instead of 1977, the '.') ringing ashore of gas?<br />
PRI1ME MINIS TER: There are challenges in the High Court to all the<br />
Australian Parliament's legislation concerning offshore matters<br />
including, for instance, the Act which we got through the<br />
Parliament based on the bill which was introduced on Mr. McMahon's<br />
behalf when he was Foreign Minister in April 1970. There has<br />
been a long delay in getting the matter through the Parliament<br />
and now that it is through the Parliament there is a challenge before<br />
th. n High Court. Natural gas cannot come ashore for a few years<br />
yet. I think it is about four years.<br />
Comment: Six years.<br />
PR'. cME MINISTER: I didn't think it was that long, but nevertheless<br />
ot-s6bviously not an imminent matter. There is plenty of time<br />
to miake proper arrangements concerning the Australian control of<br />
this resource and a proper international price for it. The<br />
Government has successfully resisted the attempt to sell off<br />
Australian resources too cheap. You know that the world price<br />
for many of our potential exports, such as uranium, is now very<br />
much higher than the price which we contracted to sell it, or<br />
at least the price that our predecessors approved in the<br />
contracts to sell it overseas. In some of the matters where<br />
contracts came up for renewal we have been able to get a very<br />
much better price. For instance, the price of coal exports is<br />
now three times what it was when we came into office. So, by<br />
the time natural gas comes ashore, four or six years from now,<br />
we would certainly get very much better prices than people would<br />
have been disposed to settle for a year or two years ago.<br />
QUESTION: You renewed your Government's commitment to full<br />
employment yesterday. In this context would you be prepared<br />
to impose quotas on Japanese car imports?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The whole of the Government's attitude towards<br />
the car industry is under examination. The IACs report was<br />
released as soon as it was got and there have been very full<br />
consultations bigger consultations than have ever been held<br />
bc. fo': e between Government departments and the various companies<br />
cr~ rncerned. I wouldn't give an off-the-cuff reply to your question<br />
at this stage.<br />
QUFSTION: What stage have the Government's discussions reached<br />
on the uranium policy? Has the uranium policy been finalised and<br />
will it be ready in time for the visit of the Japanese Prime<br />
Mii'ister, Mr. Tanaka, later this month?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This matter has been discussed between the<br />
WX31Histers who went to Tokyo twelve months ago and I would expect<br />
that this matter, like the other exports which I was asked about<br />
p;: eveiously, will be discussed when Mr. Tanaka is here. I expect<br />
thiat Mr. Tanaka is very interested in this matter. </p>
<p>-8-<br />
We want to ensure that there are proper arrangements made for<br />
the supply by Australia to Japan of this resource, which we<br />
have in abundance and of which Japan stands very much in need, k<br />
and I would hope that we would also discuss the possibility<br />
of enrichment of uranium or maybe together acquiring some<br />
technology to enrich uranium.<br />
QUESTION: Which one of the mining companies would be the<br />
first to begin exploiting the deposits?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, let's tell them first.<br />
QUESTION: Is not the production of uranium in Australia contrary<br />
to your policy on world pollution?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There are some processes concerning uranium which<br />
would produce pollution, that's true. I don't believe that our<br />
Government is carrying out any of those processes or has any of<br />
those processes in mind. We are very much aware, of course, of<br />
that aspect. I might add, because I was asked earlier a question<br />
here and I was asked also a-. question about it in the House this<br />
morning, about some of the uses of uranium under various treaties<br />
and so on. Now, we have made an arrangement with the International<br />
Atomic Energy Authority that we will not sell uranium to any country<br />
except under safeguards approved by the International Atomic<br />
Energy Authority. Accordingly, even if a country hasn't<br />
ratified the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty it can still receive<br />
uranium from Australia under the safeguard arrangements we have<br />
made with the IAEA, so all these aspects of proliferation of<br />
weapons,. peaceful uses, pollution are very much in mind in the<br />
whole of our uranium policy. There are some domestic matters<br />
such as pollution, Aboriginal rights and overseas ownership.<br />
QUESTION: Disposal of radio-active material?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, all those matters are obviously ones which<br />
we have to bear in mind, and when we are discussing which company<br />
will get the rights to extract or process or export uranium, we<br />
will obviously bear in mind overseas ownership and Aboriginal<br />
rights and environment.<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Whitlam, can we clear up a misunderstanding.<br />
In your reply to my questions....<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't think there was any misunderstanding<br />
by anybody else or by you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
