<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2896</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER TO ATTEND SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/04/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002896.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 72 15 April 1973<br />
PRIE MhINISTOTO ATTETN-D SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM<br />
The Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs,<br />
Mr E. G. Whitlam, said today that he was greatly looking forward<br />
to attending the Fourth meeting of the South Pacific Forum, to<br />
be held in Apia, Western Samoa from 17 to 19 April, 1973.<br />
He and Mrs Whitlam will fly from Sydney on Tuesday<br />
( 17 Anril) and arrive in Apia the same day.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that meetings of the Forum provided<br />
an invaluable opportunity for the Heads of Government of the<br />
independent and self-governing countries in the South Pacific<br />
region to exchange views on matters of mutual concern at<br />
first-hand and to get to know each other better.<br />
In addition to the regular Forum members ( Australia,<br />
Fiji, Nauru, New Zealand, Tonga and Western Samoa) the Apia<br />
meeting would be attended for the first time by Papua New<br />
Guinea and Niue.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that ratters to be considered at the<br />
meeting would include French nuclear tests, relations with the </p>
<p>-2-<br />
European Economic Community, regional shipping, and the South<br />
Pacific Bureau for Economic Cooperation.<br />
" Long before my Government assumed office the Australian<br />
Labor Party had carefully considered Australia's relations with<br />
the Island States and Territories of the South Pacific region,"<br />
Mr Whitlam said.<br />
" It is the wish of the Government that Australia should<br />
deepen its cooperation with its Pacific neighbours and, where<br />
suitable opportunities present themselves, to initiate positive<br />
proposals for increased cooneration."<br />
Mr Whitlam said that Australia would be presenting to<br />
the South Pacific Forum at Apia some new ideas to enhance<br />
cooperation within the South Pacific region.<br />
He regretted he would be unable to remain in Apia<br />
for the full period of the meeting owing to his commitments in<br />
London, but he was very pleased that Senator the Hon. Don<br />
Willesee, the Special Minister of State and Minister Assisting<br />
the Minister for Foreign Affairs, would be with him in Apia<br />
and would take his place on the last day of the meeting.<br />
Mr Wfhitlam said both The and Senator Willesee would be<br />
accompanied by their wives. The Prime Minister's narty will<br />
also include Miss Cathy Wbitlam and a team of senior advisers<br />
from t" he Departments of Foreign Affairs, the Prime Minister<br />
and Cabinet and Overseas Trade. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
After Apia, the Prime Minister and his party will<br />
proceed to London, and then return to Australia via Rome<br />
and Mauritius, arriving in Canberra on 30 April. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
