<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15695</transcript-id>
    <title>Appointment of Departmental Secretaries    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/12/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce the new arrangements for Departmental Secretaries of the Commonwealth Public Service.</p>
<p>To reduce unnecessary disruption to my government's program of work, most Secretaries will remain in their existing portfolios. </p>
<p>In the newly established departments, Mr Mark Paterson will move to head up the Department of Innovation, Industry, Science and Research; Dr Peter Boxall will be Secretary of the Department of Resources, Energy and Tourism and Ms Patricia Scott will head the Department of Broadband, Communications and the Digital Economy.</p>
<p>Ms Lisa Paul will be Secretary of the Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations.  Given its immediate responsibilities, an Associate Secretary for Employment and Workplace Relations will be appointed to this portfolio.</p>
<p>Dr Martin Parkinson will be Secretary of the new Department of Climate Change within my portfolio. Dr Parkinson is a Deputy Secretary in the Commonwealth Treasury and recently headed the Secretariat of the Task Group on Emissions Trading.</p>
<p>In line with our pre-election commitments, all Departmental Secretary appointments will be for five years.</p>
<p>As I have already announced Dr Peter Shergold, the Secretary of my Department, indicated to the former Prime Minister earlier this year that he intended to leave at the conclusions of his five year term in February 2008.</p>
<p>I am still considering who will replace Dr Shergold as the Secretary of my Department.  I will make an announcement on this matter prior to Dr Shergold's retirement.</p>
<p>Canberra</p>
<p>Press Office (02) 6277 7744</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
