<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7259</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OEPENING OF PEACE AND DISARMAMENT BUREAU SYDNEY - 11 DECEMBER 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/12/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007259.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-7<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING OF PEACE AND DISARMAMENT BUREAU<br />
SYDNEY 11 DECEMBER 1987<br />
Mick Young<br />
Bob McMullan<br />
Deborah Walton<br />
We could hardly be meeting at a more appropriate or<br />
auspicious time.<br />
while we in Sydney are opening a Bureau to advance the work<br />
of the Australian Labor Party in the vital field of Peace<br />
and Disarmament, the leaders of the two superpowers are just<br />
now finishing their meeting in Washington which has promoted<br />
that cause at the highest level.<br />
The point I want to make today is that these two events,<br />
while taking place on very different levels, are<br />
nevertheless related in a direct way.<br />
The agreement which President Reagan and General Secretary<br />
Gorbachev have already signed is an agreement of lasting<br />
international significance.<br />
It is an agreement which eliminates an entire class of<br />
nuclear weapons from Europe and Asia.<br />
It will result in the removal of more than 2000 intermediate<br />
range and shorter range nuclear warheads.<br />
It is in fact the first time that the word " elimination" has<br />
appeared in the title of a nuclear arms-control treaty.<br />
Previous treaties, as you know, have only reduced the rate<br />
of growth of the nuclear arsenals.<br />
Now the leaders are talking about further progress in the<br />
arms control field.<br />
They have characterised the INF Treaty as a first step.<br />
They have talked seriously about the possibility of fifty<br />
per cent cuts in strategic nuclear forces. 063tj </p>
<p>of course no one would believe the nuclear genie can be<br />
somehow put back in the bottle from which it was released<br />
with the first nuclear explosion in the desert of New Mexico<br />
in July 1945.<br />
But we are remain confident indeed, we must remain<br />
confident that we can contain that genie and prevent it<br />
from being used to obliterate mankind.<br />
That is what links events at the Summit in Washington and<br />
the opening of this Bureau in Sydney.<br />
Because I believe the leaders of the superpowers made their<br />
historic decision to seek nuclear weapons cuts in part<br />
because of their awareness of the great weight of public<br />
concern throughout the world on this grave issue.<br />
They know that nuclear war could never be won and must never<br />
be fought.<br />
And that realisation has come about because of the diligent,<br />
painstaking work by thousands of people around the world<br />
committed to nuclear arms control.<br />
When we came to office in 1983, we moved quickly to appoint<br />
Australia's first Ambassador for Disarmament.<br />
we have followed that up by using all the available world<br />
forums to argue for a comprehensive ban on nuclear tests,<br />
the elimination of chemical weapons and a reduction in<br />
strategic nuclear forces.<br />
The Secretary-General of the United Nations Committee on<br />
Disarmament, Mr Komatina, told me earlier this year that<br />
Australia now played a leading role for the cause of peace<br />
and disarmament. It was his view that those causes would be<br />
better served if other countries foll. owed Australia's<br />
example of strong political commitment and technical<br />
expertise. We took a leading role in creating, with our friends in the<br />
South Pacific Forum, the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone<br />
Treaty.<br />
And as I told the Parliament only this week, we will have a<br />
major role to play in the verification of the INF Treaty<br />
through the monitoring role of the joint facilities on<br />
Australian soil.<br />
Australia has been in the fortunate position of being able<br />
to speak frankly to both superpowers.<br />
We are firmly and fully allied to the United States and have<br />
used that close friendship to support our American friends<br />
on the many cases where we agree with them and, on the rarer<br />
occasions where we disagree, such as their proposed<br />
Strategic Defence Initiative, we have put our opposition<br />
frankl1y. OG( 7~ </p>
<p>3.<br />
As for the Soviet Union, it was very clear from my own<br />
discussions last week with Mr Gorbachev that the Soviet<br />
leadership is committed to the process of perestroika and<br />
that this process of restructuring includes new thinking in<br />
foreign policy.<br />
We welcome the Soviets' involvement in the INF Treaty and we<br />
made it clear we would welcome a constructive role for them<br />
in our own region. But I cautioned them that we would judge<br />
them not by their words but by their actions in for example<br />
Kampuchea and Afghanistan.<br />
So Australia has cause to take some pride in the role it has<br />
played in creating a favorable environment for the current<br />
progress we have seen.<br />
And of course the fact that there is the hope for greater<br />
progress makes it all the more important that we keep up<br />
this work.<br />
The Peace and Disarmament Bureau will have an important role<br />
to play in our Party's work in this field.<br />
It is a pleasure to open it today and I do so while making<br />
one plea, which I recognise may be preaching to the<br />
converted. In this time of great hope for further progress in arms<br />
control, let us not underestimate the difficulty of the task<br />
ahead. Progress in achieving further cuts in the nuclear arsenals<br />
will be slow and incremental and will take place only by<br />
patiently negotiated steps.<br />
It will demand hard work and close attention to detail.<br />
But its sometimes glacial speed must not be allowed to<br />
overwhelm us with the paralysis of despair.<br />
If the Bureau is able to harness people in the real work of<br />
arms control not raising expectations, and not breeding<br />
cynicism then it will be doing its job well. 003 088 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
