<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5120</transcript-id>
    <title>ECONOMIC INTERVENTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/08/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005120.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
MEDIA 2 AUGUST 1979<br />
ECONOMIC INTERVENTION<br />
I was very taken by the theme that you provided for us<br />
in you opening remarks yesterday that the int.. rnatir-a1<br />
situation calls for vision, courage and initiaLf-ve. In'<br />
a very real sense that is the challenge which faces us at<br />
this conference.<br />
I have no doubt whatsoever that there is an important.,<br />
constructive role for the Commonwealth to pla-y in re]. itj. om) r<br />
to world economic development issues.<br />
We can do much to create and sustain an international.<br />
climate of opinion which is conducive to bold and im~ jinative<br />
action. We can produce stimulation, well considered<br />
proposals. We can help generate a will and a vision commensurate<br />
with the scale of the problems.<br />
At our last meeting in 1977, the Commonwealth took a<br />
successful initiative on the Cormmon Fund, at a time when<br />
its prospects seemed far from good. That initiative<br />
demonstrated the potential the Commonwealth has to contribute<br />
in the economic area. Excessive modesty on our part therefore<br />
would be entirely mis-placed.<br />
This meeting is taking place at a -time when authoritative<br />
ass~ essments for the medium term outlook are for a continuation<br />
of the slow growth experienced since 1973, or even<br />
a further deterioration of that growth. The sombre prospects<br />
which face us could threaten not only the economic wellbeing<br />
of the world but ultimately, its social. cohesion<br />
and political stability. We must act to re-medy the sit-uation.<br />
Yet the question must be asked: Has the world have we<br />
responded with the urgency and determination which the gravity<br />
of these problems demands?<br />
Central to Australia's perception of these problems are<br />
two tenets First, that-in the contemporary world there is<br />
a very substantial degree of economic interdependence<br />
between all countries, and second, that the major issues<br />
facing us are not separate and descrete, but are Closely<br />
interrelated. The concept of economic interdependence i~ s not without its<br />
ambiguities arylit is sometimes put to questionable polemical<br />
use. But when all reservations have been registered the<br />
fact remains: our fates are inextricably intertwined and<br />
in the contemporary world no society is an economic island. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
A full recognition of the interdependence between north<br />
and south and of the trgent need for a greater accommodation<br />
of developing countries within the global economy is vital,<br />
both in political and economic terms.<br />
A key element in achieving this accommodation is overcoming<br />
inflation. The linkages are clear. The developed countries<br />
provide over 70 percent of the market for the goods of the<br />
developing countries, and the volume of capital flows to<br />
the developing countries is linked to the demand for their<br />
exports. Those exports and capital flows can only grow as<br />
western economies grow. And those economies will only<br />
grow when inflation is overcome.<br />
Beyond this, it is well established that sustained high<br />
inflation has a corrosive effect on social and political<br />
institutions. Unless it is brought under control it ' Till<br />
not only result in economic havoc but in social disin-egration<br />
and political chaos.<br />
While no countCry can ignore the need to follow sound ntiinflationary<br />
policies, the major industrialised countries<br />
of Europe, North America and Japan have a clear, overriding<br />
responsibility in this regard. To say'fthis is not<br />
to make an onerous demand on those countries. It is merely<br />
to recognise a fact. Their role, function and weight in<br />
the international system makes their responsibility<br />
inescapable. Indeed the fact that these countries come together for<br />
periodic economic summit meetings acknowledges their<br />
responsibility. The rest of us are only spectators as<br />
far as -these meetings are concerned and often uninformed.<br />
spectators though we all have to live with their<br />
consequences. I believe therefore that this meeting has the right to call<br />
on the major industrialised countries, in the most forthright<br />
terms, to adopt policies to bring inflation under control.<br />
Equally, of course, the developed countries have a vital<br />
responsibility to reduce their consumption of oil and to<br />
develop alternative energy resources, if growth is not to<br />
be constrained. It is important too, that oil producing<br />
countries should have regard to the effects of oil price<br />
rises on inflation and the importance of the continuity of<br />
oil supplies for the world economy.. It is not a matter<br />
of altruism. It is in their own interest to do so, as well<br />
as in the interests of everyone else, not least the developing<br />
countries. The Australian view is that there is also an inescapable<br />
link between inflation and protectionism. Each feeds the<br />
other and each frustrates the aspirations of developing<br />
countries. There is no doubt that the adverse effects of<br />
higher inflation in recent years are largely responsible for<br />
the drift towards protectionism. This proposition was fully<br />
recognised '* and accepted by those government leaders<br />
from developed and developing countries who came together<br />
in the meeting convened on the initiative of Michael Manley<br />
in Jamaica last year. </p>
<p>3<br />
Defensive protectionist policies exacerbate the situation<br />
they are meant to deal with, in that they result in an<br />
inefficient use of labour and capital resources. They are<br />
inimical to general economic recovery and put the future<br />
growth of developing countries in jeopardy.<br />
The risk of increased protectionism is all the greater now<br />
that the M~ TN negotiations have concluded. Whatever our<br />
assessment of the results of those negotiations and in my<br />
view they were far from satisfactory, particularly in<br />
relation to agricultural products the very fact of their<br />
being conducted provided some degree of restraint against<br />
pressure for increased protection. That restraint is now<br />
removed. It is all the more important therefore that attention be<br />
focused on the development of a definitive program of action<br />
to implement positive structural adjustment policies. We<br />
need policies which will free those resources of capi 1<br />
labour that are at present locked into unproductive uces<br />
and allow them to reflect the operation of market for-s,<br />
including, most importantly, the competitive forces oi_.<br />
international trade.<br />
The adoption of such a program would have economic and<br />
political costs. It would require courage to implement.<br />
But the compensating benefits for the industrialised countries<br />
themselves and for developing countries would much more<br />
than offset the costs.<br />
It should be recognised that some progress has been made in<br />
important areas. I have already mentioned one such areathe<br />
Coramon Fund which has been a major achievement of<br />
effectively supported by the Commonwealth.<br />
The agreement is important . not only because is provides<br />
hopes for coramodity Qxporters, but because it gives evidence<br />
of a growing willingness to approach the problems of trade<br />
and development in a proper spirit.<br />
But even here, much work remains to be done both on matters<br />
of principle and detail. And if the common fund is to be<br />
a hollow shell, there must be such progress on the negotiation<br />
of individual commodity agreements. ' It would be<br />
difficult to describe as anything but cynical an acceptance<br />
of the Common Fund which was accompanied by a refusal to<br />
enter into the commodity agreements necessary to give it<br />
substance. I have stressed the need to combat inflation and protectionism.<br />
That is an absolute imperative. But I do not want to end<br />
my remarks there. For we have to face the likelihood that<br />
the world wide fight against these twin evils will be a<br />
protracted one. We also have to fact the possibility that<br />
even when it is won, the rate of growth might still be<br />
inadequate. And thirdly, we have also to recognise that<br />
there are other powerful forces ecomonic, political and<br />
cultural ones-which work to impede growth and inhibit<br />
enterprise. / 4 </p>
<p>.4-<br />
Let me briefly set the problem in an historical context. In<br />
the quarter century after the second world war roughly from<br />
the mid 1940s up to about 1970 the world experienced a<br />
period of unprecedented economic growth. This reflected<br />
some very special circumstances in the industrial countries<br />
of the west. The great depression, followed by the war,<br />
had created a huge pent-up demand for consumer goods, for<br />
the material " good life" which had been denied p; sople for the<br />
previous two decades. That, together with the Marshall<br />
Plan, the widespread adoption of Keynesian policies and the<br />
rapid introduction of new technology, led to a sustained<br />
upsurge in economic growth and real income in the developing<br />
countries as well as in the industrialised world.<br />
In those two decades, the material conditions of the mass<br />
of people in western societies was transformed. But the<br />
very success of that process meant that by the mid 1:-160s<br />
conditions were changing and by the early 1970s the :-onsumer<br />
boom was clearly running down. It would be an exagge ti)<br />
to say that people were satiated, but the tempo was<br />
perceptible slackening.<br />
At the same time, a combination of factors some oi-L them<br />
directly related to the affluence resulted in incr,--asing<br />
impediments to enterprise and investment. Governemnu: s<br />
conditioned to believing that Keynesian policies were the<br />
answer to all problems stubbornly continued to pursue those<br />
policies. They pursued them despite the onset of inflation<br />
and they were encouraged to do so by electorates increasingly<br />
accustomed to believing that governments could<br />
provide for all needs.<br />
A cast of mind developed which took for granted and regarded<br />
as endless the extraordinary growth of the period and let<br />
to increasingly unrealistic demands being made on the<br />
economy. This was particularly true of the trade unions<br />
which now assumed unprecendented power within the pluralistic<br />
balance of western societies. At the same time significant<br />
and vocal sections of western societies indulged in the<br />
luxury and hyprocrisy of decrying material possessions and<br />
focusing on the so called " quality of life" issues. In<br />
doing so they ignored the fact that the majority of the<br />
worlds peoples were still living in comparative poverty and<br />
want. A legitimate concern for the need to protect the<br />
enviroment as exaggerated into an ideological cause which<br />
became essentially anti-growth.<br />
An increasingly formidable system of statutory road blocksvery<br />
demanding environmental laws, harsh trade practices<br />
legislation,, prices justification regulations were placed<br />
in the way of development and investment*' The result was<br />
that many investment opportunities which had been highly<br />
attractive twenty years ago now became ' uneconomic.<br />
At the same time, and for a variety of ' reasons, the authority<br />
and confidence of some western governments were weakaned,<br />
and the quality of leadership they were able to provide<br />
suffered. </p>
<p>This combination of factors has given rise to a state of<br />
affairs which is not conducive to growth which is in<br />
some respects positively hostile to it. The result has been<br />
that in recent years the growth of world trade has fallen to<br />
half what it was in the previous decades from 8 to 4 percent.<br />
Paternalistic, defensive attitudes have largely replaced<br />
a spirit of enterprise as witnessed by the 25 billion<br />
dollars spent by western industrial countries on wage and<br />
export subsidies to prop up inafficient industries. If<br />
only resources of this magnitude could be devoted to more<br />
productive purposes, the consequent expansion in investment<br />
and demand would be a very real contribution to growth<br />
in the world economy as a whole.<br />
The new industrialising countries, those countries which<br />
have dramatically shown that high growth is still pos-ible<br />
in the later 1970s, have increasingly met with " selec--ive<br />
safeguards~ and been seen in terms of a threat. They .; houi~ d<br />
have been congratulated and welcomed for the opportui, i'_. F<br />
they provide for the growth of the newly industriali. rig<br />
countries creates significant new markets for the dev ~ opec-_-<br />
, States. Given the effort these countries have made, nothing<br />
is more likely to embitter relations between develope'!<br />
and developing States, or to descredit the case for a<br />
liberal economitc order than such an ungenerous and shortsighted<br />
response.<br />
In sum, the conditions which generated and fuelled the<br />
great surge of growth in the last quarter century have<br />
now largely disappeared. It is against this background that<br />
I ask whether the lowering of inflation will, in itself,<br />
be enough to generate the growth in world trade necessary to<br />
reduce world unemployment and to promote a resurgence of<br />
sustained high growth.<br />
Do we not have to face the possibility that a whole range<br />
of constraints may need to be tackled in order to achieve<br />
these goals?.;<br />
Do we not have to ask what in the next two decades could<br />
restore the vitality and dynamism which the system showed<br />
in the late 1950s and 1960s?<br />
Is there a way in which the resources of the world can<br />
be better deployed and allocated to provide this dynamism?<br />
What would happen, for example, if the vast amount of<br />
money expended by developed countries on wage and export<br />
subsidies were to find a more productive use?<br />
Is it not possible to protect the environment and the, interests<br />
of consumers without-systematically frustrating investment<br />
and enterprise?<br />
Are there not ways in which resources in developing countries<br />
could be more effectively utilised,, so as to increase growthon-<br />
a sustainable basis and reduce the intolerable burden of<br />
poxerty in' the world? / 6 </p>
<p>' 6<br />
Should we not do more to accommodate the newly industrialised<br />
countries, the one group of countries which is still achieving<br />
the growth rates of the earlier decades?<br />
I will say frankly that I do not know the answer to these<br />
questions. But I believe they are essential questions,<br />
questions we must address at this time.<br />
Le me recall again that the American Marshall Plan, the<br />
first great transfer of resources in our time played an<br />
important, perhaps a crucial pa*, in initiating the great<br />
post-war expansion. In doing so, I want to make it clear<br />
that I do not believe that what is called for at the present<br />
time, is a replica of that plan. The mechanical repetition<br />
of past solutions in changed circumstances rarely works.<br />
But what I do believe, and believe very strongly, is that<br />
something corresponding to the political will and vi ion<br />
which inspired the Marshall Plan is needed now. We i<br />
respond in a manner which is commensurate with the chi llenge<br />
we face with imagination. andboldness, and with a willingness<br />
to look beyond the convetional wisdom.<br />
00 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
