<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8028</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JANA WENDT, A CURRENT AFFAIR PARLIAMENT HOUSE - 6 JUNE 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008028.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
t
0<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JANA WENDT, A CURRENT AFFAIR<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE 6 JUNE 1990<br />
EMB$ ARGOED UNTIL BROU~' CAST<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
WENDT: Prime Minister, thank you very much for your<br />
time. PM: Pleasure Jana.<br />
WENDT: I have to ask you, how do you feel?<br />
PM: I feel great.<br />
WENDT: No problems?<br />
PM: No problems.<br />
WENDT: Cabinet met in your absence and made some<br />
important decisions. How much input were you able to<br />
have into all of that?<br />
PM: All those issues that were decided in my absence had'<br />
been a subject of discussion with me beforehand.<br />
WENDT: So you were confident that you knew exactly what<br />
was going on in the Cabinet Room?<br />
PM; Yes.<br />
WENDT: There seems to be at the moment some questioning<br />
of your ability to keep on doing this job. Are you<br />
tired? PM: No, Itm not tired. I've never felt better really.<br />
I feel on top of things mentally in a way I haven't<br />
before really. I mean I've always felt good mentally but<br />
I feel better than I have ever before. And physically<br />
I'm great.<br />
WPENDT: Dr Hewson has not so delicately suggested that<br />
you're too old for the job.<br />
PM: I noticed that with a bit of amusement. I think it<br />
said more about Dr Hewson than it said about Bob Hawke. </p>
<p>K j L_ rlhwr\ L H I-2<br />
WENDT: What do you think it does say about him?<br />
PM: He's got a lot to learn.<br />
WENDT: Do you think it wa too rough a remark to make?<br />
PM: N'o, no. In politics you've got to be prepared for<br />
rough stuff. I don't think it was rough. I thought it<br />
was stupid.<br />
WENDT: Do you believe that you have a responsibility to<br />
your Party to bow out while you are still on top?<br />
PM: No. The way they put it to me I have a<br />
responsibility to stay in, and for a considerable period<br />
of time. I mean this is in the ring now, the question of<br />
my leadership, so let me cast aside those very strong<br />
shackles of modesty which always chain me down and refer<br />
you to the recent research which talks about the last two<br />
elections and the Hawke factor. Now I don't want to<br />
spell them out but you know what that research shows.<br />
WENDT; But do you think the time will come when you will<br />
have to, for the sake of the Party, say to yourself well<br />
now is the time to<br />
PM: No, the time will come when, not only for the sake<br />
of the Party but according to good sense, I will have to<br />
give it away. But that's not for a long time yet. I<br />
mean, I am not immortal, I'm not going to go on forever.<br />
of course there'll come a time.<br />
WENDT: The rumour mill about Paul Keating taking over is<br />
gaining momentum again. Do you believe that he is ready<br />
now PM: It's a very narrow-based rumour mill and it's one<br />
which causes amusement both to me and to Paul.<br />
WENDT: Well let me put it to you this way. When do you<br />
think he might be ready to take on this job?<br />
PM; if you take the bus syndrome, if I were to go-under<br />
the bus, he would be ready now. I mean none of the<br />
comments I've made to this point imply that I don't think<br />
he's incapable of doing the job now. It's simply that<br />
the position won't arise.<br />
WENDT: Why did Paul Keating take it upon himself to read<br />
the riot act to Ministers who supposedly had stepped out<br />
of line. Why<br />
PM: particularly did with John Button and as I've<br />
said, I have no problem about that at all. Because the<br />
question of economic management is very much within<br />
Paul's bailiwick although I am involved there too. It's<br />
fl-IWRiL-LU U2 i-eo 91b: 10 No. U-u-4 '. U6 </p>
<p>HHWr\ L H U<br />
p 3<br />
a joint effort between Paul and myself. He felt that he<br />
needed to say what he did. I had no problem with that.<br />
WENDT: And you supported him in that?<br />
PM: I did. I do.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, there's been some suggestion that it<br />
may be time for a reshuffle of your Ministers.<br />
PM: I've never heard anything more ridiculous than this.<br />
I mean that is, you often hear me saying that things get<br />
shoved into the public arena which are legless. Well<br />
this is the thing that was amputated at birth.<br />
WENDT: Well we were just talking about Mr Keating having<br />
bucketed Senator Button. I mean do you think it's time<br />
for Senator Button to move on?<br />
PM: No, and neither does Paul.<br />
WENDT: The other name that's been thrown into the ring<br />
is Ralph Willis. Is it time for him to move on ? 7<br />
PM: Certainly not.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, do you think there comes a time when<br />
you just get sick of the abuse, and you're copping it<br />
obviously from the Opposition, that's predictable, but<br />
you've copped it from within your own ranks from people<br />
like Peter Walsh. Do you get sick of that?<br />
PM:* No. If you looked at the question of the<br />
relationship between the Party and myself I think it has<br />
probably never been closer than it is now.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, you wouldn't be human would you if you<br />
didn't react to something like the ' old jellyback' line?<br />
PM: It worries me not at all. I can assure you I lost<br />
not a moment's sleep about it. I'm the one who knows<br />
myself. I know the tough decisions I've had to take, I<br />
know the arees I've had to kick, the ears I've had to<br />
belt. But you see I don't do those things in a dramatic<br />
public way. I go about the business of running this<br />
Government by first of all indicating to my Ministers<br />
that I have confidence in them. I am not an interfering<br />
Prime Minister. In the more than seven years now of this<br />
Government in that Cabinet, in the end not that it<br />
comes to this sort of thing normally but in the end if<br />
there's a question and the Prime Minister says this is<br />
what's going to happen, that's what always happens.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, I'd like to move on to something very<br />
different. The events that took place in Beijing twelve<br />
months ago<br />
PM: Yes. K. JL~ 1HWR HL. LL: U2-6t) 41b2 u2 hei joIt): I I No UU4 F U4 </p>
<p>FJ. L. tMWNL ItLLU2-6! D641b2 02 Feb 93 15: 11 NO. 004<br />
4<br />
WENDT: are now the subject of intense debate. In fact<br />
there is a point of view that there never was a massacre<br />
in Tiananmen Square, for instance.<br />
PM: That's nonsense. I know there's a view, but it's a<br />
nonsense view.<br />
WENDT: Why do you say that?<br />
PM; Because, let me say this, I have access to<br />
intelligence and information as well as the public<br />
information which simply doesn't sustain that.<br />
WENDT: There's also an echo of those events in our own<br />
country obviously with thousands of Chinese<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
WENDT: -students here<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
WENDT: seeking refugee status. What are you inclined<br />
to do with that problem?<br />
PM; There'll be an announcement about that very soon.<br />
In fact just yesterday I was having lengthy discussions<br />
with Mr Hand about this.<br />
WENDT: Your current immigration program allows for<br />
something like 12,000 refugee places in this country.<br />
Are you prepared to stretch that for those people?<br />
PM: I think that we've got to have a, a ' separate<br />
category for these people. I mean, this is a situation<br />
which is unique and we will deal with it on those terms.<br />
WENDT** I understand there's something like 8,000<br />
applications for refugee status. If your quota is<br />
12,000, there is going to be a blowout there, isn't<br />
there, albeit in a special category?<br />
PM: I'm saying there'll be, there'll be a separate<br />
category. I don't think anyone's going to argue that<br />
you see we've got more than 20,000, more than 20,000, who<br />
are here who were pre-Tiananmen Square. Now for, for<br />
those in particular, we have to have a special approach<br />
and, of course, in regard to those who came post-<br />
Tiananmen, we'll make the cut off point there of probably<br />
about the 20th of June last year.<br />
WENDT: We woke up this morning to read that we're asking<br />
the Cambodian Government to take back some of the<br />
Cambodian boat people who came to our shores. Why are we<br />
doing that? </p>
<p>F~ IHJILL . ILL: U2-65584162 02 Feb 93 15 : 12 NO. 004<br />
PM; For the obvious reason. I mean, we have a<br />
compassionate humanitarian policy which will stand<br />
comparison with any other country in the world. But<br />
we're not here with an open door policy saying anyone who<br />
wants to come to Australia can come. These people are<br />
not political refugees.<br />
WENDT: How can you be sure of that, Mr Hawks?<br />
PM: simply there is not a regime now in Cambodia which<br />
is exercising terror, political terror, upon its<br />
population. WENDT: what do you make then of these hundreds of people<br />
PM: What we make<br />
WENDT: who get on their tin boats and travel across<br />
PM: What we make of it is that there is obviously a<br />
combination of economic refugeoism, if you like. People<br />
saying they don't like a particular regime or they don't<br />
like their economic circumstances, therefore they're<br />
going to up, pull up stumps, get in a boat and lob in<br />
Australia. Well that's not on.<br />
WENDT: And risk their lives to do it?<br />
PM: Well, risk their lives is not, I mean, we have an<br />
orderly migration program. We're not going to allow<br />
people just to Jumip that queue by saying we'll jump into<br />
a boat, here we are, bugger the people who've been around<br />
the world. We have a ratio of more than 10 to 1 of<br />
people who want to come to this country compared to the<br />
numbers that we take in.<br />
WENDT: And you personally have no qualms about that?<br />
PM: Not only no qualms about it, but I will be forceful<br />
in ensuring that that is what's followed?<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, the 20 percent foreign ownership limits<br />
on Australian television networks, do you accept that<br />
your Government's decision on that led directly to the<br />
re-entry of Kerry Packer into the television game, if you<br />
like? PM: No. I do accept that it probably made it easier<br />
but, if you like, we were in a dilemma then if you're<br />
going to look at it in terms of the judgement that people<br />
made about who you helped. if we'd gone another way we<br />
would have been Bond's mate. This way I was Packer's<br />
mate. The fact is that we didn't make the decision in<br />
terms of Packer's mate or Bond's mate, but being the<br />
peoples' mate if I can put it that way. You had to make </p>
<p>F I M Uj 1\ L-ri t-I~ L. LJ~ o~ uz UZ eo j,<br />
6<br />
a decision which, in the end, you thought was the best<br />
for Australia.<br />
WENDT: Do you worry about the fact that your move may<br />
now restrict competition in the Australian television<br />
mark~ et to the extent that we today hear that the Seven<br />
and Ton Networks may become one?<br />
PM: well, again, you see, there's a speculation that<br />
there might be a swallowing of Seven by Ten and it's<br />
totally hypothetical and I wouldn't believe it would<br />
happen. WENDT: Would it disturb you, Prime Minister, if in fact<br />
that did occur?<br />
PM: Well, you couldn't have a situation where one<br />
ownership entity could have two stations, 8s YOU<br />
appreciate. That wouldn't be allowed under the law. I<br />
think it is true to say that we have a good television<br />
system in this country and it's good for people like you<br />
not that you have lots of potential employers it's<br />
very good for the, for your bargaining position. I'd<br />
hate you to see a position, Jane, where you and all the<br />
good people who are performing on television would have a<br />
lesser number of people clamiouring for your services and<br />
in the process, providing us with a smaller range of, of<br />
choice. I don't believe that will happen.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, thanks for your time.<br />
PM: Thanks very much, Jana.<br />
ends 1512 No. 004 F'. u7 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
