<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15134</transcript-id>
    <title>Weekly Radio Message - Climate Change</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/02/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...</p>
<p>Listen to this speech (MP3 - 2.0Mb - 135secs)</p>
<p>There are many views about the impact of global warming - some conservative, some more alarmist - but there can be no argument that greenhouses gases are having an adverse impact on the earth's environment. </p>
<p>I am a climate change realist. Australia contributes very little to overall global emissions, but like all other countries we have a responsibility to play our part in tackling the problem. </p>
<p>We are already doing this through practical, sensible measures such as our multi-million dollar investments in clean coal technology, solar power and other renewable energy sources, carbon-burying programs and projects. </p>
<p>All of my government's many initiatives to tackle global warming and its symptoms are sensitive to the nature of our industries, our major-power sources and our natural abundance of fossil fuels. We are not going to sell out the many thousands of workers in the mining and power-generation industries by hastily agreeing to proposals that unfairly disadvantage Australia. </p>
<p>We must have a measured, sensible approach to climate change that includes clean coal technology, the possibility of nuclear power and the use of renewable energy sources recognising always that solar and wind energy cannot maintain power stations. </p>
<p>Market mechanisms, including carbon pricing will be integral to any long term response to climate change. The joint business government taskforce met last week to continue work on the design and nature of a workable emissions trading system. The taskforce will this week release a discussion paper outlining a set of issues regarding the development and implementation of a workable global emissions trading scheme and the role Australia can play. </p>
<p>There is undeniable evidence that our climate is changing but the answer is not knee-jerk responses that harm the national interest. The Government will continue to put forward practical and sensible measures to tackle climate change. </p>
<p>[ends]</p>
<p>  Listen to this speech (MP3 - 2.0Mb - 135secs)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
