<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2708</transcript-id>
    <title>RURAL CREDIT - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/11/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002708.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS PM. No. 93/ 1972<br />
RURAL CPREDIT<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. William<br />
McMihon, CH, MP<br />
For some time past, the Government has been<br />
investigating the availability of longer term credit to the rural<br />
sector and has already taken a number of policy initiatives in<br />
this field. In 1960, it established the Commonwealth Development<br />
Bank, a high proportion of whose lending is to farmers on<br />
long term. To supplei'. ent trading bank lending on overdraft,<br />
Term Loan Funds were established in 1962 and Farm Development<br />
Loan Funds in 1966, in each case by transfers frnm . the trading<br />
banks' Statutory Reserve Deposits with the Reserve Bank and from<br />
the banks' other assets. The Funds have been added to from time to time<br />
in subsequent years. In 1971, the Commonwealth offered the States<br />
$ 100 million to finance the rural reconstruction scheme, under<br />
which long term loans are ma. Xe to farmers to repay existing debt<br />
and to finance property purchases to build up their holdings to<br />
a viable size. $ 44 million has boeen provided up to June 1972<br />
and a further $ 56 million is included in the 1972-73 Budget.<br />
Also in the Budget is $ 4 million for marginal dairy farm<br />
reconstruction. These steps have resulted in substantial new<br />
long term funds being made available to rural industry.<br />
However, the Government felt that there was a<br />
need for a detailed review7 to be undertaken of the adequacy of the<br />
credit facilities available to the rural sector. The Minister<br />
for Primary Industry therefore directed the Bureau of Agricultural<br />
Economics to undertake such a review.<br />
The Bureau in its report " Rural Credit in<br />
Australia" reached the conclusion that the facilities available<br />
to farmers from existing lending institutions to borrow on long<br />
terms were deficient. / 2 </p>
<p>It came to the view that the amount-of long<br />
term lending being undertaken was inadequate, compared with that<br />
desirable to allow shorter term debt to be restructured, to<br />
facilitate property transfer and amalgamation, and to assist<br />
rural industry to adjust to the longer term Pressures facing it.<br />
The 1972/ 73 Budget provided an amount of<br />
million, to be appropriated for purposes of facilitating the<br />
increased availability to farmers of long term loans. The<br />
Government has not yet carried to conclusion its consideration of<br />
the many complex issues involved. Consequently, it was not<br />
possible to bring down legislation in the recently concluded<br />
Session of Parliament. Issues arising include, for example, the sources<br />
of funds from which such lending could be financed and how it<br />
would fit in with existing rural term lending.<br />
The Government has decided that an enquiry should<br />
be held to examine and renort on the feasibility and desirability<br />
of creating a new, separate and viable institution which, taking<br />
its place along with existing financial institutions, would engage<br />
in financing the repayment of existing short term debt and in the<br />
provision of longer term loans for rural industry.<br />
In order to achieve an immediate increase in the<br />
availability to farmers of long term loans, arrangements have<br />
been made between the Government, the Reserve Bank and the<br />
Trading Banks under which the Banks will increase the amount of<br />
long term lending from the Farm Development Loan Funds, for a<br />
wider range of Purposes than hitherto undertaken, and with the<br />
Funds being supplemented for this purpose.<br />
The new pur oses will include finance for<br />
property purchases, assistance in holding together a farming<br />
enterprise where the death of a farm 9proprietor creates financing<br />
difficulties and finance for the repayment of existing short-term<br />
debt. The present maximum term of 15 years for loans from<br />
the Funds will also he remaovea; the general aim will be to match<br />
the terms and conditions of long-term loans to the situation of<br />
the individual borrower. While the present preferential interest rates on<br />
lending for developmental purposes will continue to apply, interest<br />
rates charged on this longer term lending will be commercial rates.<br />
The rates charged in individual cases will, of<br />
course, vary according to the circumstances of the particular. cases,<br />
such as the purpose and term of the loan and the degree of risk.<br />
The interest rate structure, and changes in it<br />
from time to time in accordance with chancges in the general level<br />
of bank interest rates, will be subject to the approval of the<br />
Reserve Bank and the Treasurer. / 13 </p>
<p>3<br />
The Governor of the Reserve Bank will be<br />
making a separate statement about the arrangements; the Funds<br />
are being supplemented by an amount of about $ 65 million.<br />
The Government believes that this initiative<br />
will improve the access by farmers to long-term credit and be<br />
of major assistance to them in achieving a more appropriate<br />
debt structure. Property transfers and amalgamations will be<br />
facilitated, and financing problems arising from the death of<br />
a farm proprietor will be eased.<br />
CANBERRA, 1 November 1972 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
