<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>217</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES AT THE CHAMBER OF MANUFACTURES DINNER IN SYDNEY ON THURSDAY, 15TH SEPTEMBER 1960</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/09/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000217.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
0 SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.<br />
G. MENZIES AT THE CHAMBER OF MANUFACTURES<br />
DINNER IN SYDNEY ON THURSDAY, 15TH SEPTEMBER,<br />
960<br />
Sir: I am delighted to be here in such delightfully mixed<br />
company at the top table. I say nothing of the rest of you<br />
who, after all, are paying for us, but I must say I've never<br />
seen you look more relaxed or more human.<br />
The first time I ever attended a dinner of the<br />
Chamber in this place, in which I felt instinctively as I<br />
looked around, " After all, they are all human beings"<br />
( Laughter) Rather a pleasant sensation.<br />
But up here of course, we're a mixed grill: I have<br />
Dr. Heffron ( Laughter my old friend. Je both became<br />
Doctors on the one day, did you know that? Of course not:<br />
you're very ill informed. You are so busy attacking the<br />
Government that you have no time for more interesting matters.<br />
( Laughter) Bob Hoffron and I became Doctors on the one day ho<br />
a Doctor of Letters, not including letters to the Sydney<br />
Morning Herald ( Laughter) and I a Doctor of Law.<br />
And also 1e have at the top table if I may make a<br />
brief selection, my distinguished telegenic friend, Arthur<br />
Calwell ( Laughter, Applause) who has torn himself away from his<br />
television fans ( Laughter) for this night only, bringing with<br />
him his Deputy, Gough 4hitlam. He's here somewhere tall,<br />
good-looking fellow. They always have to travel together<br />
otherwise they might disagree. ( Laughter)<br />
So that wc at the top table here very properly<br />
are the dead heads tonight and you, thank Heaven, are the<br />
contributors. Judging by the Company reports that I have been<br />
reading, you can jolly iell afford to entertain us ( Laughter)<br />
at dinner. Now I've been tricked tonight. In the past what has<br />
happened has been this: I've been about number five on the<br />
list and somebody has got up and made a most offensive speech<br />
about meno which has increased my blood pressure to such a point<br />
that it has become normal. And then I've sort of fought my<br />
way out. And tonight some low cunning I think it must be<br />
the new secretary some low cunning has been exercised and I<br />
have to break the ice. I go first. I can't feed on the<br />
crumbs that fall from the poor man's table. I have to go<br />
first and break it up. And I have to say something, I believe,<br />
about Australian industry.<br />
Nov, Sir, this is a most interesting title because I<br />
can remember young as I am I can remember a time when the<br />
toast would be " Australian manufacturing" or, in another<br />
setting, " The / ool industry", or, in another setting, " The<br />
Wheat Industry" according to where you were, and the particular<br />
political circumstances in which you found yourself.<br />
But tonight it is " Australian Industry". And that<br />
very title tells me all that I want to tell you. Because<br />
Australian industry has now begun to see itself as something so<br />
closely related, one part to another, that it is almost<br />
indivisible.<br />
-j </p>
<p>No longer do we need to go along and say to<br />
manufactures, " Oh, it's quite all right, we ought to havo<br />
manufacturers. Whatever they say against you, my dear boy, I<br />
think there is a little to be said for you, you know,."<br />
That day has gone. And the day has gone when<br />
people in the great primary industries devoted their waking<br />
hours to denouncing the existence of manufacturing in their<br />
own country. And the day has gone by when both of the, or either<br />
of then, occupies any time in talking about, what shall I call<br />
it? " tertiary" industry: all the complexities of modern<br />
commercial existence upon which, in the long run, we all<br />
depend. And so " Australian Industry" it is. Industry<br />
inter-dependent; industry in a country, a great and growing<br />
and marvellous country, which itself enjoys inter-dceendence<br />
with other groat free communities in the world.<br />
It is really one of those occasions. I think it is<br />
almost historic when the very name of the Toast conveys to us<br />
something of the quality of the now Australia.<br />
In my very earliest days when I was a boy, if you<br />
can exercise your inagination to think of such a time, it was<br />
many, many years before I ever became Prime Minister it is a<br />
long time ago and in my very earliest days, born and bred<br />
in the bush with whoatcrops nodding over the fence, I had a<br />
father who used to say to me in the long winter evenings:<br />
" Robert we must have manufacturing in Australia. you must grow<br />
up to be a protectionist". Well at the age of ten you don't<br />
quite know rhat a Protectionist is, do you? But I learned, I<br />
learned. The old man gave me the works. By the tinm I was<br />
fourteen I was a much more bigoted protectionist than a ro) dern<br />
member of the Country Party. ( Laughter)<br />
But those wore the days when it all had to be done<br />
defensively. Those wore the days when Australia was thought<br />
about in other countries, and perhaps even in the nother<br />
country of our race, as a farming community. Those days have<br />
gone. Australia today is two things. And it is worth<br />
remembering them: It is a great industrial country and it is<br />
a great trading country. are one of the groat tr; oaing<br />
nations of the world. And how do we trade? Not just by<br />
buying; not just by selling. But by doing it buth ways. A<br />
great trading country'<br />
Now up to now, or up to the oti-r day, owhe . ave sold<br />
to the rest of the world predomrinantly the products of the<br />
soil and of the pastures and of the skill of the c. untry. As<br />
manufacturers we have predoninantly provided for ourselves.<br />
We have said, 1oll we have a good ho-e market;<br />
it's adequately protected". I say that loosely and<br />
rhetorically gentlnmen ( Laughter) because I know that you all<br />
feel that it never has been. But still, by and largo, you're<br />
out of the Bankruptcy Court. Therefore I venture to say that<br />
on the whole our manufacturing industry has been adequately<br />
protected. But primarily we have sold to ourselves, to our<br />
neighbours in our own country. Australian manufactu-ing<br />
doesn't need to come of age in Australia: it came f ' go a<br />
long time ago in . ustralia. But it does need to come of ae<br />
in the internatio nal sensc. </p>
<p>3.<br />
I can't believe that Australia will occupy the place<br />
that she ought to occupy in the world if her balance of<br />
payments, her overseas reserves, depend primarily and substantially<br />
on the price of wool, or the wheat crop, or the<br />
price of wheat, or the prospects of the beef industry, or<br />
whatever it may be.<br />
These are, of course, troeendously important things.<br />
But what has any groat exporting country in the manufacturing<br />
field, what has it got that we haven't got? More skill? I<br />
decline to believe it. I'n vain enough to say that in any<br />
comparable fields of human activity, Australians ought never to<br />
take second place in skill, or character, or quality, or<br />
courage ( Applause). So wo don't give way in that field,<br />
Somebody says, " Well, of course, we don't have the<br />
same turnover; we don't have the same volume of business". I<br />
don't suppose they did, once. I am prepared to assert that if<br />
we have enough imagination to get up out of our own backyard, we<br />
will find, in this new world which is blossoming all around us,<br />
a field for our activities which will make those who were<br />
gloomy about business turnover today, wonder what happened to<br />
them in ten years tine.<br />
All this requires an imaginate effort. We must get<br />
up over the border of our c) untry and have a look at the world,<br />
And if you look at the world, well what do you see?<br />
You see new-nation after new nation coming what to? To<br />
political independence? Yes. That is perhaps relatively easy.<br />
But it is of no importance whatever unless they also cone,<br />
perhaps not quite so fast, but in the quick run, to economic<br />
independence. You look across Africa. You read the newspapers an.,<br />
you see that there are eight, nine, now African countries<br />
seeking to join the United Nations. oleo pen the newspapers and<br />
we read all the horrors of the Congo internal disputes. We open<br />
our papers and we read about Asia and Sjuth-East Asian countries<br />
and all the turbulence that exists in countries from Laos to<br />
Cambodia, to South Vietnam, moving down into Indonesia, our<br />
nearest neighbour. Jell do we just look at this? And fool afraid? And<br />
feel apprehensive? Or do we take enough time off to say to<br />
oursclves, " What's going It nay be extraordinarily<br />
uncomfortable at present; it may be marred by all sorts of<br />
revolting incidents. But what is joing on is that you have<br />
hundreds of millions of people struggling, not only to the<br />
political life, but to a new standard of life and of living.<br />
And here we are, Australia, right on the corner of<br />
this development: the most advanced country, industrially, to<br />
be found in the Southern Hemisphere, with people all of whom<br />
are free and intelligent and active at least 49-or 50Jo of<br />
them are intolligent politically ( Laughter). But let us use<br />
it broadly and metaphorically: an intelligent people, a<br />
people accustomed, each of him, to a standard of living, a<br />
material standard of living better than his father's and ruch<br />
better than his grandfather's.<br />
This is a wonderful country to be in. And here we<br />
are with all the advantages of technique, of technology, of<br />
experience, of skill, of courage, of imagination. Why can't<br />
these things bring about a result that in 50 years' time we<br />
needn't worry: we won't be here but in 50 years' time<br />
Australia is one of the great exporters of the product of her<br />
factories, one of the leading exporters, and is able to say<br />
that so far as she goos with the rest of the world her oconomy </p>
<p>is as soundly placed as any of the groat exporting nations of<br />
the first half of the twentieth century.<br />
Now I just say that to you. Not to be rhetorical,<br />
but to urge you to soe with the eye of imagination what a<br />
remarkable opportunity we have.<br />
I know you nay , o away and say, " Well, of course we<br />
could do that if it were not for the Government". Well<br />
Governments, I'n happy to say, cone and -o and if we happen to<br />
enjoy your favour we begin to think that we did a fri htfully<br />
good job. We nay not be right.<br />
As an old political sweat I want to toll you this:<br />
That all the good things that have been done in Australia,<br />
all the wonderful adhiovenents that have been made in<br />
Australia, have been made by ordinary Australian non and wonen<br />
with courage and with enterprise.<br />
And because I believe that, I have the greatest<br />
pleasure in the world in standing up before you tonight, never<br />
having yet, contrary to all precedent, boon hooted even once,<br />
and propose to you, not just as Manufacturers, but as prominent<br />
citizens of a great all-round country, with groat all-round<br />
industrial achievement, I stand and ask you to drink the<br />
health of " Australian Industry". </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
