<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>587</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY MR ROBERT G MENZIES - PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AT THE OPENING OF THE &quot;SOUTHERN CROSS&quot; - AUGUST 24TH, 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/08/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000587.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY MR. ROBERT O. MENZIES PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA<br />
AT THE OPENING OF THE " SOUTHERN CROSS" AUGUST 24th, 1962.<br />
Sir, I have not been told whether I am to open the hotel or give a general address<br />
on the state of the nation, but I think it might be agreeable if I declare that<br />
this hotel has been well and truly opened, and indeed it may be noted that we<br />
are standing on historical soil, or a little bit above it, as it is here where<br />
the old Eastern Market used to be.<br />
If any of you came to live here in this city and wandered around the old<br />
premises you might have encounted a woman who told fortunes and may<br />
also have done something else on the shadier side of the law.<br />
Looking at the hotel with all its facilities, in comparison to the Eastern<br />
Market with its so called facilities I would say it has taken 15 or more<br />
years than it should have to disappear, and now it has disappeared and<br />
we have in its place a great modern hotel which is a pacesetter for hotels<br />
in this country.<br />
I recall, in the days of my youth, as no doubt some of you can, what was<br />
regarded as an average hotel, say in one of the provincial centres, was<br />
a good old established nineteenth century hotel most likely with the light<br />
in the wrong place and windows that wouldn't open, and when you found<br />
you wanted to follow certain rules of nature no doubt you found you had to<br />
do a fifty yard march to the bathroom and then unconcernedly stand in a<br />
queue for another half hour.<br />
Not so many years ago, while travelling through the United States I<br />
stayed in many hotels some with over a thousand bedrooms and a thousand<br />
bathrooms. A hotel with a hundred bathrooms would have put our<br />
Victorian great grandparents in a state of great excitement to think of<br />
all that water being wasted but now we have moved on and the progress<br />
of the world we are living in is such that we can come to a hotel such as<br />
this one and regard it as a matter of course.<br />
Time is marching on and in Australia this hotel venture represents the<br />
bringing together of Australian talent and research and American talent<br />
research which we have all come to look on as a happy association more<br />
and more since the last war. And so we have a happy marriage between<br />
Australian and American talent, capital and experience all brought<br />
together by one hotel. </p>
<p>2.<br />
There are some countries in the world which have for a long time<br />
understood that the tourist in the world is an important element in the<br />
industry of the world. The Swiss and the French are two examples.<br />
I can remember going to Tasmania and trying to convince them to cater<br />
for tourists with good hotels to handle people but we have, for too long<br />
in Australia thought that nothing could be called an industry if there was<br />
no smoke coming out the top.<br />
Development of this section of industry in Australia is remarkable and I<br />
promise to help, without a subsidy, to bring it to the attention of the<br />
prospective tourists for Australia.<br />
Ending as I began I declare this hotel well and truly opened. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
