<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5653</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF ABC&#039;S &#039;NEWSVOICE&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/09/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005653.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER WEDNESDAY, 23 SEPTEMBER 1981<br />
From the Press Office SUMMARY OF ABC'S " NEWSVO 2 4"<br />
The Federal Government plans to lodge court on Fr yer<br />
for the de-registration of the Builders Laboureis edeotion.<br />
The Prime Minister told Parliament today that recent<br />
retaliatory action by the BLF against Costain Australia would<br />
be added to the case the Goverment had prepared.<br />
Warwick Beutler<br />
Only two weeks ago the Government said it would hold off its<br />
de-registration proceedings against the BLF because of the<br />
legal implications associated with the Royal Commission into<br />
the union. But the latest action against Costain Australia<br />
has made the Government determined to go ahead. The BLF<br />
retaliated against Costain after the Minister for Industrial<br />
Relations, Mr Viner tabled a document last week which Costain<br />
was named as one company providing help to the Government in<br />
its case for de-registration. Mr Fraser warned today that if<br />
the BLF continued with bans or placed new bans on companies<br />
giving evidence against it, the Government would not hesitate<br />
to use its weight to uphold respect for legal processes.<br />
Mr Fraser was speaking during debate on a motion of no<br />
confidence in Mr Viner. Moving the motion, the Opposition<br />
Spokesman on Industrial Relations, Mr Hawke, claimed that<br />
Mr Viner had misled Parliament last week in his statement<br />
about the state of unpreparedness of the case against the BLF<br />
when he assumed the portfolio in April. The debate produced<br />
little that was new. Mr Hawke repeated many of yesterday's<br />
assertions. Mr Viner and Mr Fraser said there was no basis<br />
for the extravagent claims that had been made. Mr Fraser<br />
also defended Mr Viner outside the House.<br />
Mr Fraser<br />
There is no conflict between a statement which says substantiaL<br />
progress has been made early in May and one in the middle of<br />
April which says that the case is unprepared.<br />
Question Sir, it seems that you are backing Mr Viner all the way.<br />
Mr Fraser<br />
Obviously, I am relating to the facts. Of course I am backing<br />
Mr Viner because the facts support Mr Viner. Obviously<br />
Mr Viner, when he got that Attorney-General's advice at<br />
the middle of April pulled all the stops out on a matter<br />
which the Government up to that point, over three or four<br />
months had made the great play of. But over the succeeding<br />
period it had proved very difficult to get all the evidence<br />
and inform the Attorney-General's Department because they are<br />
the ultimate judges, believed was adequate and ready to go<br />
before the Federal Courts. / 2 </p>
<p>Warwidk Beutler<br />
One of the few interesting features of today's debate was that<br />
the former Minister for Industrial Relations, Mr Andrew Peacock,<br />
found that he could neither support the Opposition, nor the<br />
Government, he abstained.<br />
The BLF Federal Secretary, Mr Gallagher said today he had a<br />
complete list of companies which had co-operated with the<br />
FEderal Government in its attempts to de-register his union.<br />
Report from Allan Knight.<br />
Mr Gallagher<br />
What happened was that there was a conference called one weekend<br />
during the the transport workers strike in Melbourne and<br />
Mr Viner ushered all the journalists in to the file room of<br />
his office and on the table there was the Builders Labourers<br />
de-registration application with all the names of the companies<br />
who have given statements. So a very good friend of ours<br />
got the names for us.<br />
Question So will you be considering taking action against these other<br />
companies?<br />
Mr Gallagh'er<br />
We will play it our own way. We have known for a while that<br />
Costain had done it, but at this stage we will just deal<br />
with Costain.<br />
Question Will you be considering bans against those other companies?<br />
Mr Gallagher<br />
At this stage we will just continue in the dispute with<br />
Costain. Question Are you coficerned about the new moves towards de-registration?<br />
Mr Gallagher 1<br />
No, I am not concerned about it, because I don't believe that<br />
the Government will be able to convince the court that the<br />
unionsmen should be de-registered. I don't think they have<br />
sufficient information. The reason why they are now going<br />
to put the application in is because he is trying to save<br />
Mr Fraser and his job.<br />
The ARbitration Commission today called a compulsory conference<br />
for next Friday in a bid to end action by the Builders Labourers<br />
Federation against the Costain company. The Masters Builders<br />
ASsociation said that bans applied last week were crippling<br />
the company and threatening standdowns in some areas. / 3 </p>
<p>33 -<br />
There has been a breakthrough in the dispute which has been.<br />
holding up shipping around Australia and disrupting fuel<br />
supplies in some states. A new vote on a return to work<br />
by marine engineers is to be taken tomorrow as Garry Scully<br />
reports.<br />
The FEderal Opposition has called for a Royal Commission into<br />
the circumstances of an aircrash at Sydney. airport last<br />
year in which 13 people died. The call'came up at a<br />
tabling in Federal Parliament today of a report on the crash<br />
by the Transport Department. Report from Barry Cassidy.<br />
Barry Cassidy<br />
All 12 passengers and the pilot were killed when the<br />
Beach 200 aircraft crashed into the Western sea wall at<br />
Sydney's Kingsford Smith Airport one and three quarter minutes<br />
after it had taken off for;. a flight to Temora. The Air Safety<br />
Investigation Branch of the Transport Department has found<br />
that the aircraft was 128 kgs over weight when it took off.<br />
IT also concluded that the company Advance Airlines of<br />
Australia required its planes to take off on reduced power<br />
below the flight manual limit to extend the life of the engine.<br />
The Opposition wants a Royal Commission because the investigation<br />
also concluded that officers of the Department of Transport<br />
knew of the practice but did nothing about it. The Opposition's<br />
Transport%-Spokesman, Mr Morris spoke with Warwick Beutler.<br />
Question Are you suggesting that there was incompetence?<br />
Mr Morris<br />
One can't tell from the report whether it is incompetence,<br />
it seems rather there was a studied neglect.<br />
Question Had it been going on for some time?<br />
Mr Morris<br />
Yes, the Department was aware of it, it was more or less<br />
accepted practice in the industry and the Department, the<br />
responsible authority knew about it, the IMinsiter knew about<br />
it, did no-t~ hing about it. We had raised this matter. I<br />
had raised it in the Parliament in late 1978 and I appealed<br />
to Mr Nixon, the then Minister for Transport, for a bi-partisan<br />
approach to the whole question of air safety. That appeal<br />
was rejected with abuse and invective and in this report<br />
we are seeing something of the results of that neglect<br />
of the Minister.<br />
Question Could it still be going on? / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Mr Morris<br />
of course.<br />
Military authorities in the Philippines have reported that<br />
about 35 men women and children have been massacred by a<br />
band of heavily armed men. Report from Keith Dalton.<br />
HEavy rain and tough security kept protesters at bay during<br />
the second match of the South African Rugby Team's tour of<br />
the United States. Report.<br />
There have been more arrests in South AFrica as blacks resist<br />
Government attempts to evict them from so-called white<br />
residential areas. Nine people have been detained in the<br />
latest security clamp down. Report.<br />
Government backbenchers today added their voice to supporters<br />
of the Community Youth Support Scheme asking the Government<br />
to continue a training scheme for those young unemployed<br />
who will not be covered by other programmes. The Government<br />
announced in the Budget that CYSS woul~ d be disbanded af ter<br />
the end of next month, but today at the weekly joint government<br />
party meeting in Canberra backbenchers urged the Government<br />
to institute a new programme to preserve the best features<br />
of CYSS.<br />
Jeff Leach<br />
There are 274 schemes operating throughout Australia, but the<br />
Government has decided that from the end of October, their<br />
role of training young unemployed and keeping them occupied<br />
will taken up by other youth support schemes. The decision<br />
has lead to widespread demonstrations, focusing on the<br />
Minister for Employment and Youth Affairs and to Parliamentarians<br />
coming under pressure from the churches, welfare organisations,<br />
and CYSS employees. Delegates from CYSS have spent the past<br />
two days in Canberra lobbying politicians. The Government<br />
has already been forced to admit it will reconsider. Today<br />
answering the backbenchers, Mr Brown said the Government was<br />
obliged to empahasis youth training programmes and to take up<br />
its responsibilit~ y to those who might not be provided for<br />
in other programmes. Mr Brown said the Government was now<br />
evaluating the proposals before it.<br />
Conservationists will be denied a no-damns option in the<br />
November ref~ rendum on the next major power sheme for<br />
TAsmania. This was decided today by the Tasmanian ParliamentEary<br />
Labor Party reversing an earlier promise to conservationists.<br />
Report. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
