<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18980</transcript-id>
    <title>Happy New Year 2013</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/12/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Australians enjoy ringing in the New Year. It's a time of fun and celebration, of optimism and of making New Year's resolutions.</p>
<p>As we mark the start of 2013 we have so much to be thankful for.</p>
<p>We live in the best country in the world.</p>
<p>We enjoy the benefits of peace and security.</p>
<p>Unlike the rest of the world, our economy has proved itself to be resilient.</p>
<p>We are improving health care and aged care.</p>
<p>We are tackling climate change and protecting our environment.</p>
<p>We have a clear plan for our nation's future in this century of growth and change in the region in which we live.</p>
<p>Australia is a wonderful country.  But even for our great nation, every year brings its challenges.</p>
<p>Let me be clear about the ones that confront our nation in 2013.</p>
<p>Our world faces ongoing security challenges.</p>
<p>In this year, as a member of the United Nations Security Council, we will be involved in addressing pressing problems like Iran's nuclear program and the missile tests of North Korea. </p>
<p>We will also continue our difficult and dangerous mission against global terrorism in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>Five years on from the global financial crisis and despite some progress in the US in recent weeks, problems there and in Europe still threaten global growth. </p>
<p>Once again we will need to manage our economy carefully to keep creating jobs and economic growth.</p>
<p>And, as always, our future is not assured. We have work to do to ensure that today's children enjoy lives of better opportunity, better health and higher living standards than we do today. </p>
<p>But as we face these challenges we can enter this year with the confidence that comes from having the right policies and capabilities to ensure we succeed in a changing and sometimes worrying world.</p>
<p>Friends, amongst the many New Year's resolutions made, we should make one for our nation. </p>
<p>Let's start 2013 with a resolution to embrace a renewed national spirit of unity and confidence.</p>
<p>We have much to do and we will do it best by working together.</p>
<p>I am determined that 2013 will be the year when we together write the next great chapter in our nation's history. A chapter about jobs, opportunity, a better education for our children, a better deal for Australians with disability, and that we do so with a renewed Australian spirit.</p>
<p>Happy New Year. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
