<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11402</transcript-id>
    <title>29 April 1999                                                  TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS TO BUSINESS LUNCHEON,                 ADELAIDE, SOUTH AUSTRALIA                                              </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Economy; taxation system, tax plan, drugs,</p>
<p>E&amp;OE...........................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well thank you very much Corey, and can I say how pleased I am to</p>
<p> be back in Adelaide to express my thanks to you as a group for your</p>
<p> continued support of the Liberal Party cause. It is true that on a</p>
<p> straight percentage basis, might I also say on a straight quality</p>
<p> basis too, that the representation in South Australia in terms of</p>
<p> seats is the best across Australia, and without doubt is the best</p>
<p> across Australia. 9 out of 12. If we'd achieved that all around</p>
<p> Australia we'd have probably had an even bigger majority than</p>
<p> we secured in 1996.</p>
<p>But on top of that we have of course in the Cabinet a very high and</p>
<p> very high quality level of representation from the State of South</p>
<p> Australia. And I was certainly reminded of that earlier this week</p>
<p> in Indonesia when I had at my side our Foreign Minister Alexander</p>
<p> Downer who I believe has done an absolutely outstanding job in that</p>
<p> portfolio over the past three years. And that of course is not to</p>
<p> denigrate in anyway the contribution of the other Ministers from your</p>
<p> State.</p>
<p>But I wanted, given the nature of the gathering, to say something</p>
<p> to you today of where I see the Australian economy, and where I see</p>
<p> the Government's reform programme for its second term. Reform</p>
<p> is something that will always be with us in the modern globalisation</p>
<p> economy. There are those who periodically write about reform fatigue.</p>
<p> There are those who periodically write about the fact that the community</p>
<p> will no longer accept ongoing economic reform. Whatever may be their</p>
<p> motivations for saying that the reality is that we have no alternative</p>
<p> but to go on reforming our economy, to go on making changes to ensure</p>
<p> that we remain as competitive as we can with the rest of the world.</p>
<p>We don't have any option in the modern world other than to be</p>
<p> part of the global economy. There's no way that we can, in the</p>
<p> words of that old song Stop the World Because We Want to Get</p>
<p> Off'. We can't go back to an old cloistered protective existence,</p>
<p> unless of course we are to give away the high living standard, and</p>
<p> the opportunities for our children that we all value so dearly So</p>
<p> the challenge for modern governments in Australia and elsewhere is</p>
<p> to take advantage of the opportunities that globalisation offer, to</p>
<p> make certain that we are competitive enough to get our share of what</p>
<p> globalisation offers, but at the same time to recognise that globalisation</p>
<p> for some people can carry social and economic costs, and to ensure</p>
<p> that those costs are cushioned, to ensure that those costs are explained</p>
<p> and understood, and that the advantages of globalisation for the rest</p>
<p> of the community far outweigh any costs for one section of the community.</p>
<p>And that is what we are doing. And I've always held the view</p>
<p> that you can win acceptance in the Australian community for economic</p>
<p> reform if you satisfy two conditions. The first of those is that you</p>
<p> must explain to the Australian community that the reform that you</p>
<p> are committed is in the best interests of the country. In other words,</p>
<p> it passes the national interest test. And the second condition that</p>
<p> you must meet is that it is fundamentally fair and seen to be fair</p>
<p> by the Australian community. And if you can pass those two tests than</p>
<p> I believe the Australian community will accept and embrace reform.</p>
<p>Now since we've been in office, which is now a little over three</p>
<p> years, we have brought about some very major reforms to the Australian</p>
<p> economy. The most important is of course the fiscal reform, turning</p>
<p> a deficit of $10.5 billion into a surplus. We've brought about</p>
<p> major reforms in the area of industrial relations, and the process</p>
<p> goes on in that area. It's never ending. And we've done</p>
<p> it in a way that has been fundamentally fair to the Australian community.</p>
<p> And that has been demonstrated today by the living wage case which</p>
<p> has delivered a fair increase to the low paid in the Australian community.</p>
<p>Now we were told by the unions and the Labor Party before 1996 that</p>
<p> that wouldn't happen. The reality is that wage and salary earners</p>
<p> in Australia now are better off than they have been for more than</p>
<p> ten years. Not only have they had real wage gains, but they've</p>
<p> also had another very precious gain and that is a fall in housing</p>
<p> interest rates. And the fall in housing interest rates has been worth</p>
<p> more than $320 a month to the average wage and salary earner. And</p>
<p> if you add that to the real wage increases that many have achieved,</p>
<p> and you add to that the safety net wage increases typified by today's</p>
<p> decision of the Industrial Relations Commission, you have an environment</p>
<p> of wage fairness, and justice.</p>
<p>Now that's a commitment I made in 1996 when I was Opposition</p>
<p> Leader, and I'm proud to say to you today at this business gathering</p>
<p> that we are a government that has delivered wage and salary justice</p>
<p> to the ordinary wage and salary earner in Australia. And that's</p>
<p> one of the reasons why we continue to enjoy the support of the large</p>
<p> number of average wage and salary earners in Australia. It's</p>
<p> one of the reasons why the Liberal Party won so many seats here in</p>
<p> South Australia at the last election. And it's part of our creed</p>
<p> that we continue to do that. Of course we are a party that's</p>
<p> committed to the interests of the business community as the wealth</p>
<p> generators of our society. We're also a party that is committed</p>
<p> to a fair go for the average wage and salary earner within our community.</p>
<p> And I'm very pleased to say that we have delivered on that and</p>
<p> delivered on it in a very significant way.</p>
<p>We've undertaken of course major privatisation polices in relation</p>
<p> to Telstra and other former government business organisations. But</p>
<p> of course by far the biggest reform that we have embraced as a government</p>
<p> was our commitment in September of last year to fundamental reform</p>
<p> of the Australian taxation system. The Australian taxation system</p>
<p> has needed root and branch reform for more than a quarter of a century.</p>
<p> In May of this year I'll celebrate 25 years in Federal Parliament,</p>
<p> and I remember only a few months after I was elected to Federal Parliament</p>
<p> there was a report on the Australian taxation system that bore the</p>
<p> name The Aspry Report', some of you may remember it, after</p>
<p> a former judge of the New South Wales Court of Appeal, Ken Aspry.</p>
<p> And surprise surprise 25 years ago it recommended the introduction</p>
<p> of a broad based indirect tax. And it said that that tax should have</p>
<p> essentially no exemptions. It said that the existing wholesale tax</p>
<p> system was ramshackle and broken down. It said that rates of personal</p>
<p> income tax were too high, that personal income tax took greater share</p>
<p> of revenue, and for a number reasons you needed the introduction of</p>
<p> a broad based indirect tax.</p>
<p>Now that was 24 to 25 years ago. And we have been debating that issue</p>
<p> ever since. And at long last that debate is coming to its conclusion.</p>
<p> It's coming to its pinnacle, its grand ending I hope. And by</p>
<p> the 30th of June we will have an answer from the Australian</p>
<p> Senate as to whether the Australian people are going to be listened</p>
<p> to. Because you will remember that last October we went to the Australian</p>
<p> people, not promising in general terms taxation reform. We didn't</p>
<p> say if you re-elect us we'll make the tax system fairer. I often</p>
<p> scratch my head and think in amazement that in 1979 when the British</p>
<p> Conservative Party, under Margaret Thatcher, won office from the Labor</p>
<p> Party under the former Prime Minister Jim Callaghan, and that's</p>
<p> almost exactly 20 years ago today, they had a taxation policy. And</p>
<p> the taxation policy essentially said: well will tax more of what you</p>
<p> spend and less of what you earn. There wasn't much more detail</p>
<p> to it than that. And I can remember asking a former British Chancellor</p>
<p> of the Exchequer what was in his tax policy, and he said: John, essentially</p>
<p> that is what we said. They didn't go into a whole lot of detail.</p>
<p> They got elected, they then proceeded to do it.</p>
<p>We by contrast, because of the nature of the Australian political</p>
<p> system, because we knew that we might face hostility in the Senate,</p>
<p> we knew that people would try and deny the mandate of the Australian</p>
<p> people, we went to the length of laying out in total detail what we</p>
<p> were going to do. We mentioned the rates, we mentioned the cuts in</p>
<p> personal income tax. We went into enormous detail. And we ran the</p>
<p> extraordinarily high political risk of going through a campaign and</p>
<p> somebody making some inconsequential nitpicking publicity hit against</p>
<p> us on the basis of something of comparative irrelevance. And we survived</p>
<p> all of that. We won the election and no government in the history</p>
<p> of Australia has received a mandate on such an explicit change to</p>
<p> a fundamental area of economic policy since federation.</p>
<p>And you cast your minds back. No government has done that. And we</p>
<p> were successful in winning that election and we have the right therefore</p>
<p> to say to those who hold the balance of power in the Senate, to the</p>
<p> Labor Party, and the Democrats and the Australian Greens, that they</p>
<p> ought to listen to the will of the Australian people. And you've</p>
<p> probably heard me say that before and you'll here me say it again</p>
<p> and again over the weeks ahead because we are coming to the crunch</p>
<p> time. We are coming to the moment of truth as to whether the political</p>
<p> system in this country really works effectively. Of whether you're</p>
<p> going to provide an incentive for governments and oppositions in the</p>
<p> future to actually go out and try and win support on the basis of</p>
<p> what they intend to do to the Australian public, and what they will</p>
<p> do, or whether in future we're just going to have election campaigns</p>
<p> entirely devoid of policy content and entirely composed of one-liners</p>
<p> invented by PR consultants based on focus group polling.</p>
<p>Now that essentially is what is the sort of political choice that</p>
<p> we in a way are going to face. Now I know there are people who don't</p>
<p> like aspects of the taxation plan. There are arguments about the fine</p>
<p> detail of it. And I've indicated time and time again that the</p>
<p> government is amenable to some kind of fine-tuning in certain areas.</p>
<p> That's always been our position. But we're not going to</p>
<p> alter the fundamental thrust of what we put to the Australian people.</p>
<p> We're not going to start exempting large areas from the goods</p>
<p> and services tax. We don't believe that the poor are helped by</p>
<p> exempting food. In fact on a straight quantitative assessment you</p>
<p> do more to help the rich by exempting food than you do to help the</p>
<p> poor. And we believe that the best mechanisms in relation to that</p>
<p> are of course the mechanisms of compensation.</p>
<p>There are enormous benefits for rural Australia out of this taxation</p>
<p> plan. We're going to cut the national fuel bill by $3.5 billion</p>
<p> a year. We're going to reduce the cost for Australian exporters</p>
<p> by $4.5 billion a year. And of course we're going to make business</p>
<p> costs overall cheaper by about $10.5 billion a year because no tax</p>
<p> will be paid on business inputs. And there are major gains under this</p>
<p> plan for the Australian States. Over time the Australian States will</p>
<p> be significantly better off under the proposed GST than they would</p>
<p> be if the existing arrangements continue. They will have all of the</p>
<p> GST revenue. Every last dollar of the GST revenue will go to the Australian</p>
<p> States. And that's why they all signed up a week and a half ago</p>
<p> at the Premiers' Conference. It was the most harmonious, loving</p>
<p> Premiers' Conference that I have ever been to. I mean the Labor</p>
<p> Premiers loved it as much as the Liberal Premiers. Bob Carr said:</p>
<p> you know Prime Minister, my party doesn't support this, where</p>
<p> do I sign. Peter Beattie was no different. He was just as good. And</p>
<p> without exception they all signed up, and so they should have. Because</p>
<p> they were signing up to a deal that is much better for their State.</p>
<p> And as that revenue grows the States will have more money to provide</p>
<p> more services, for government schools, and for hospitals and for police,</p>
<p> and for roads - the basic functions of State governments - and so</p>
<p> they should. And we'll have a far more dignified, and we'll</p>
<p> have a far more orderly way of distributing the national economic</p>
<p> pie, the national revenue cake, than that sort of annual charade or</p>
<p> pantomime that passed as a Premiers' Conference over the years</p>
<p> where, you know, each Premier does a doorstop on the way in and one</p>
<p> on the way out, and then you have a joint press conference from the</p>
<p> Prime Minister and the Treasurer saying how, you know, we are sadly</p>
<p> misunderstood and we're really there to help all the States.</p>
<p> Now we did help them on this occasion and I think one of the greatest</p>
<p> assets to come out of the taxation reform plan is the new deal for</p>
<p> the States. And that is of enormous benefit and it will underpin the</p>
<p> revenue base that the States need to provide all of those services.</p>
<p>So a lot hangs on what the Senate does over the next few weeks. We</p>
<p> make no bones about it that we need obviously the support of people</p>
<p> who are not members of the Coalition parties. We need the support</p>
<p> of cross bench or independent Senators. But we need their support</p>
<p> on the basis, and we need an understanding from the Labor Party and</p>
<p> from the Australian Democrats that we took all of the political risks.</p>
<p> We put our bodies on the line politically, we won support, we won</p>
<p> support in the open, honest, orthodox, authentic way. And if the political</p>
<p> system is to retain its credibility and its integrity then we ought</p>
<p> to have the right to have the wishes of the Australian people implemented.</p>
<p>So we intend to press ahead with our taxation reform plan. And I'm</p>
<p> telling every audience I address in Australia, I addressed one in</p>
<p> Melbourne last night, I addressed a large one in Perth a week earlier,</p>
<p> every audience I address I make it perfectly clear, that we have no</p>
<p> intention of backing away from our commitment to taxation reform.</p>
<p> It is the largest piece of unfinished economic reform business that</p>
<p> this country faces. We've cleared a lot of hurdles. We've</p>
<p> broken through a lot of other barriers in the area of economic reform</p>
<p> and this is the big one that lies in front of us. And having gone</p>
<p> to the Australian people and got their support, I for one, and I know</p>
<p> I speak for all of my colleagues in saying it, we will persevere until</p>
<p> we win the support of the Australian Parliament to implement those</p>
<p> particular reforms.</p>
<p>But ladies and gentlemen, government is not just of course about economic</p>
<p> matters and one of the reasons I'm here in Adelaide is to address</p>
<p> probably the most challenging and gripping social issue of our time,</p>
<p> and that is the drug problem.. And I don't come here, and I don't</p>
<p> go anywhere in Australia pretending that I have all of the answers</p>
<p> to that. And I don't seek to politicise the issue. I'm as</p>
<p> happy to work with Bob Carr and Peter Beattie in tackling the drug</p>
<p> problem as I am with Jeff Kennett and John Olsen, because deep down</p>
<p> it is a social challenge that requires a bipartisan response. It's</p>
<p> a social challenge that also has to be kept in perspective.</p>
<p>The great bulk of our young people do say no to drugs and I applaud</p>
<p> them, but a portion of them don't and society has to tackle the</p>
<p> problem in three ways. It's not just a law and order problem, although</p>
<p> that's an important dimension of it. And you do need as we have provided</p>
<p> increased resources through our police and customs services. It is</p>
<p> also an education problem. We do need to have a clear understanding</p>
<p> of the dangers of drugs and communicate those dangers to our young,</p>
<p> particularly through our schools. And schools are entitled to lay</p>
<p> down rules, they are entitled to stipulate codes of behaviour and</p>
<p> nobody should complain if those rules are enforced and enforced rigorously.</p>
<p>We also have to provide, and I think this has been one of the areas</p>
<p> where we have perhaps fallen behind as a community in recent years,</p>
<p> we have to provide some assistance and help to those people who are</p>
<p> addicted and need support in order to break their addiction. And I</p>
<p> went to the Adelaide Central Mission this morning to announce the</p>
<p> details of one of the programs of the Mission that we are funding</p>
<p> out of our increased commitment to rehabilitation and treatment. And</p>
<p> after I'd made my presentation I had the opportunity of talking to</p>
<p> some of the people whose lives had been so devastated by drugs and</p>
<p> who were seeking the assistance of the mission. And two or three of</p>
<p> them in talking to me, their common theme was that as things stand</p>
<p> at present, somebody who's been addicted to drugs wants to try and</p>
<p> break the habit, it often takes too long a period of time between</p>
<p> them taking of that decision and when some help is available. And</p>
<p> that is not the fault of the welfare organisations. They all do in</p>
<p> my view, a magnificent job and they deserve our praise and our thanks.</p>
<p> I think in the past perhaps we haven't, governments generally, not</p>
<p> just federal government's but state governments as well, we are all</p>
<p> in this together, have perhaps not put enough resources into the treatment</p>
<p> and the rehabilitation end of the problem. And that is why in our</p>
<p> "Tough on Drugs" strategy, which has now committed more</p>
<p> than $500 million additional over a period of four years, that that</p>
<p> includes a very significant component of extra support for treatment</p>
<p> and rehabilitation.</p>
<p>And I'll have the opportunity later this afternoon of talking in more</p>
<p> detail when I close the major conference on drugs strategy which has</p>
<p> been going on in Adelaide over the past few days. I mention that issue</p>
<p> ladies and gentlemen because these challenges can't be put in watertight</p>
<p> isolated compartments. The health of the economy is influenced by</p>
<p> the health of our society. The health of our society in turn is very</p>
<p> heavily influenced by the strength of our economy. The two are inextricably</p>
<p> linked and bound up. And increasingly as I find in my responsibilities</p>
<p> that we need more than ever before, we need an effective social coalition</p>
<p> in this country.</p>
<p>The Government can't do everything. It doesn't have the resources</p>
<p> to do everything nor does it have the wisdom to do everything. The</p>
<p> welfare sector, magnificent though it is, can't do everything either.</p>
<p> It certainly doesn't have the resources and it certainly in many areas,</p>
<p> although it has the human understanding and the expertise, there are</p>
<p> other areas of expertise that are needed.</p>
<p>Individuals who have difficult and broken lives need help to change</p>
<p> their lifestyle and they need help to change their attitudes. The</p>
<p> business community which many members contribute magnificently to</p>
<p> charitable and welfare causes can't do it all on its own either. And</p>
<p> therefore, I've talked a lot recently about building a better social</p>
<p> coalition. The Government, the welfare sector, the individual and</p>
<p> the business community, each playing it's own part, each making a</p>
<p> contribution according to its capacity. And this is not the soft cell</p>
<p> for the Government getting out of its financial responsibilities,</p>
<p> it's quite the contrary. There are ongoing financial responsibilities</p>
<p> in the social welfare sector which the Government, and only the Government,</p>
<p> on behalf of the tax payer can carry. And this is not in any way a</p>
<p> soft cell to say: well we're going to reduce our contribution and</p>
<p> we expect the welfare sector and the community to pick up more. No,</p>
<p> it's really an aim of mind to try and build a stronger and more effective</p>
<p> social coalition that harnesses the resources that the Government</p>
<p> has and the expertise it has with the resources that other sections</p>
<p> of the community have and the expertise that they have.</p>
<p>And all of that of course in the end does depend very much on the</p>
<p> strength of our economy. And although the economy is not the only</p>
<p> thing in life, and I've never argued that, and I've indicated that</p>
<p> today with my reference to other issues. But it's a very, very important</p>
<p> part of our capacity, unless we have a healthy economy there are a</p>
<p> lot of things we can't do. And we do have a healthy economy at the</p>
<p> present time and it hasn't happened by accident. We have been able</p>
<p> to stare down the worst of the Asian economic downturn. We have got</p>
<p> a stronger economy now than we've had for 30 years. We've got the</p>
<p> lowest inflation, the lowest interest rates for 30 years, the lowest</p>
<p> unemployment for almost 10 years, an enviable level of business investment,</p>
<p> a growing respect around the world, a growing interest in the economic</p>
<p> strength and attractiveness and stability of Australia and the Australian</p>
<p> economy.</p>
<p>Now those things have happened as a result of policy resolve. And</p>
<p> we did some very unpopular things in our first year in office and</p>
<p> we got a lot of criticism and we lost a bit of skin and a bit of paint</p>
<p> and I understand that. But if we hadn't have done that, just imagine</p>
<p> where the Australian economy would be now if we still had a $10 billion</p>
<p> deficit. Just imagine where we would be now if we still had interest</p>
<p> rates of four or five percent higher than what they are now. Just</p>
<p> imagine where we would have been if our inflation rate was much higher</p>
<p> now than what it is.</p>
<p>We would have then felt the full brunt of the Asian economic downturn.</p>
<p> The reason we were able to escape that brunt was that our fundamentals</p>
<p> were much stronger. And that's something that we can all feel particularly</p>
<p> proud of and it's something to which every Australian has made a contribution.</p>
<p> And to which as Prime Minister of our country I am extremely grateful.</p>
<p>So Corey, ladies and gentleman thank you very much for having me here</p>
<p> today, I think I can report to you that the Federal Liberal Government</p>
<p> is in good heart, in good voice. We think the policies that we've</p>
<p> implemented continue to be successful but we're not complacent. And</p>
<p> it's when you think you're going extremely well in politics that something</p>
<p> can suddenly go wrong. I've been around a long time and I've experienced</p>
<p> that phenomenon probably about 150 times and I've no doubt that I'll</p>
<p> experience it again as time goes by.</p>
<p>But the other thing I've learnt from almost 25 years in politics is</p>
<p> that if you are prepared to stand up and boldly state what you believe</p>
<p> in and you go out to the Australian public and you argue it strongly</p>
<p> and you defend your point of view, in the end you win the argument.</p>
<p> Now we did that with the GST. We won the political argument all we've</p>
<p> got to do now is get it through the Senate.</p>
<p>Thank you very much.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
