<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16052</transcript-id>
    <title>Australian Business Opportunities in Beijing Beijing   </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/08/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister Kevin Rudd today congratulated Australian businesses involved in preparations for the Olympic Games and pledged continuing Australian Government support to further strengthen trade and economic links with China.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister made the comments as he officially opened Business Club of Australia (BCA) Beijing 2008  -  the government's official business program for the Olympics.</p>
<p>More than 40 Australian companies secured contracts to assist with the Beijing games, including PTW Architects which designed the Beijing National Aquatics Centre - (the ‘Watercube') - and Athletes Village.</p>
<p>Other projects Australian companies have worked on included the design of the National Aquatics Centre; the International Tennis Centre and Athletes Village; transport planning; engineering works; financial and telecommunications services and security.</p>
<p>At the BCA Beijing 2008 event the Prime Minister witnessed the signing ceremonies for two memorandums of understanding (MOUs) between Australian and Chinese companies.</p>
<p>One agreement involves AIMS Financial Group and a commercial arm of Beijing University that will establish a joint venture funds management company to invest in biotechnology.</p>
<p>The other MOU between National Australia Bank (NAB) and the Agricultural Development Bank of China (ADBC) is the first between an Australian bank and a Chinese financial institution in the area of agri-finance.</p>
<p>The Rudd Government is committed to further strengthening Australia's economic relationship with China - already our largest trading partner with two-way trade in 2007 valued at $58 billion and Australian exports valued at $27.7 billion</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
