<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1605</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO U.S. , CANADA AND U.K. - NEW YORK, U.S.A. - ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT TO THE FAR-EAST AMERICA COUNCIL AT THE ALDORF HOTEL - 9TH JUNE, 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/06/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001605.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
S16 JUN1967<br />
LIBRAN<br />
VISIT TO CANADA A. D U. K.<br />
YORK, U. S. A.<br />
; DDRES iY HE RME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HIOLT<br />
TO THE F~ r-,. ST iL. ETR IC COUICIL AT THE ALDORF HOTEL<br />
9TH JUIE, 1967.<br />
" 7e are, in Australia, a community with a<br />
strone European tradition and history but we find<br />
ourselves increasingly involved in Asia, and whether we are<br />
classed by the geographer as part of asia or not we<br />
increasingly think of ourselves as involved in its<br />
problems and concerned with its potentialities. And so<br />
I want to speak particularly about the region of Asia<br />
in general. It is misleading, in a sense, to sreak of the<br />
problems of Asia as if Asians are oneset of people. There<br />
are wider differences of anpearance, hauits of life,<br />
historical uacksroun. and culture to be found in Asia than<br />
is to be found in a-iv other area of the world. I have<br />
just come oack from i tour not the first by any means<br />
but my first to the four countries, Cambodia, Laos,<br />
Taiwan and Korea.<br />
I was particularly struck with these differences<br />
which existed in countries with adjoining boundaries or<br />
which w'ere located close to each other. The dissimilarities<br />
were more obvious than the similarities. Yet, I suppose<br />
it is not so surprising when one thinks of the history of<br />
the British Isles and The marked differences in language,<br />
in approach in temperament, in physique, hajit of life<br />
of the people of E. land, Scotland, Ireland and . ales.<br />
The differences are even more manifest in the<br />
countries of Asia. do well to bear this in mind, because<br />
so many of those who speak about the region adopt broad<br />
descriptions which i thLnk could be quite misleading and<br />
dangerous if they are to form the basis for policy-making.<br />
Even the people of the area, themselves, talk about settling<br />
things the Asian way, repudiating, at times the efforts<br />
being made by others outside the region to deal with their<br />
problems as thouh settling thin s the Asian way meant<br />
that all Asians tried to settle things in the same way.<br />
I would be very surprised to learn that the<br />
people of South Korea settle things the same way as the<br />
people in India, or the Indonesians the same way as the<br />
Burmese, or the Chinese even the same way as the Vietnamese,<br />
and so on. Therefore we do well to remember that we are<br />
speaking of a very diverse range of peoples with different<br />
problems and often different aspirations, and certainly<br />
different attitudes to the problems of life.<br />
Then, we get the other sort of cliche which is<br />
popularised in some of the left wing and more doctrinaire<br />
ournals such as the Iew Statesman, which occasionally<br />
is taken up by thi politicians who hold that it is wrong<br />
something immoral to have white faces either in uniform<br />
or in industry on the mainland of Asia.<br />
Many of you represented here today are on the / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
mainland of Asia in industry, and you will find to varying<br />
degrees that your presence is welcome there that you can<br />
do a great deal to assist in the prosperous growth of the<br />
people of this region.<br />
But more particularly I speak today about the<br />
question of havi n white faces in uniform on the mainland<br />
of Asia, and to challenge the proposition that this is<br />
either in some way immoral or unwelcome to the people of the<br />
region. I would go so far as to say that the contemporary<br />
trend is entirely in the opposite direction. Nowhere is<br />
this better exemplified than in the recent experience of the<br />
United States of America. Even some Americans, I think<br />
would ue surprised to learn how many security cormitments your<br />
country has gladly accepted in the countries of Asia and<br />
around the periphery of Asia. Those commitments cover<br />
South Korea, Japan, Taiwan, Thailand, the Philippines and<br />
now actively in South Vietnam.<br />
In Australia and New Zealand we have our<br />
associations with you of a security kind in the AlZUS Pact<br />
and the South-East Asia Treaty Organisation, where again<br />
we co-operate on a multilateral basis to combating communist<br />
infiltration and aggression in the region.<br />
But that is not the end of the story. Your military<br />
participation has not only been welcomed by these countries,<br />
in some instances it has nreserved them from being overrun<br />
by the forces of communism. This is particularly true of<br />
course, in South Korea. I am proud to say, were the<br />
first country to declare ourselves alongside you when you<br />
made that historic decision to intervene and help in checking<br />
communist aggression there.<br />
I think of this as one of the two critical and<br />
historic policy decisions made by the people of the United<br />
States in contemporary times. The other was the Marshall<br />
Plan, which for the first time that I can recall in human<br />
history, set out in a disinterested way to assist other<br />
nations to build up their economic strength, reconstruct<br />
after the devastation of war and build again a secure place<br />
in the expanding world.<br />
The jesson of the Marshall " lan should have been<br />
taken up by ticse countries who were assisted as a result<br />
of it to establish themselves again in economic strength.<br />
I find myself dissatisfied with the extent to which they<br />
have taken up their share of the burden of helping to improve<br />
the lot of the rest of mankind, less fortunately placed. The<br />
United States continues to set a fine example in this particular<br />
direction. The other historic decision which I believe opens<br />
up a new watershed of human history, a new phase in the<br />
history of man, was the decision and all that has since<br />
flowed from it, to intervene in the crisis which developed<br />
in South Korea. Had you not decided that way at that time,<br />
South Korea would, of course have been overrun and been<br />
part of the Chinese Communist dominion. There would have<br />
been no South Vietnam conflict because not having chosen<br />
to intervene at one point, it would not have seemed worth<br />
the cost an the struggle to intervene at the other.<br />
I question whether Taiwan could have been held<br />
from communist incursion. Down through that whole region<br />
of South-East Asia there would have been no effective / 3 </p>
<p>check on communist penetration. I know there is a school<br />
of thought which believes that because these people have<br />
strong national sentiments they would not have welcomed the<br />
Chinese. That may be so. But they would have proved<br />
incapable of resisting the incursion of the communist<br />
philosophy and the so-called wars of national liberation,<br />
which are not national in sentiment and certainly do not liberate.<br />
As far as the national aspect was concerned that<br />
would have been submerged by the general Peking-oriented<br />
nhilosophy of communism. So far as lioeration was concerned,<br />
they would not have been free.<br />
I; e would have been faced with a very different<br />
kind of world from that which, with reasonable fortune,<br />
and by our own endeavours, we can sustain in the future.<br />
It is my conviction that we would not have had<br />
the favourable turn of events in Indonesia had the United<br />
States not been present in strength in South Vietnam. There<br />
in Indonesia, you not only had a very strong communist<br />
party but the administration was leaning increasingly<br />
towards it, and I question whether there would have been<br />
the encouragement for resistance to these forces in<br />
Indonesia had they not seen that America was in strength in<br />
South Vietnam, determined to resist communist penetration<br />
and further communist expansion through the area of South-East<br />
Asia. That gave them heart to take un the struggle<br />
themselves, and you have now a reasonable prospect that<br />
Indonesia a potentially rich country of more than 100,000,000<br />
people will be, if not part of the free world camp at least<br />
a co-operating member of the international community<br />
developing its resources for its own uenefit and that of<br />
international trade generally in the years ahead.<br />
As you turn around the neriphery of Asia you<br />
find a receptiveness to people from beyond the mainland.<br />
I could instance country after country. In Thailand there<br />
are protective forces of the United States and even a<br />
small representation from my own country. In Malaysia we<br />
are more strongly represented with the British and other<br />
Commonwealth forces. In Korea, Vietnam and Taiwan there<br />
has been substantial assistance, military and economic,<br />
by the United States.<br />
There is an increasing tendency to co-operate in<br />
such institutions as the Asian and Pacific Council in the<br />
Asian Development bank, in ECaFE, in SEATO and in the Colombo<br />
Plan. I feel that, in view of the conjecture going on<br />
about the British position East of Suez in future years<br />
acknowledgement should be made of the contribution of the<br />
United Kingdom, first in combating the communist inspired<br />
guerillas for many years in what was Malaya, and then in<br />
more recent times, with considerably expanded forces helping<br />
to resist, and successfully doing so over a period of three<br />
years the confrontation of Malaysia by Indonesia, This<br />
underlines, I believe, the importance of a continuing British<br />
presence in the area. Around the whole arc of South-East<br />
Asia, the only area in which the United States has not taken<br />
up a defensive obligation has been in relation to Malaysia<br />
and Singapore. This area they have regarded not<br />
unreasonably as a Commonwealth and primarily a British / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
responsibility. 3ut on that matter there will be further<br />
discussions before the final British decisions are taken.<br />
-e can all sympathise with the United Kingdom's<br />
view at a time when the country is under very heavy economic<br />
pressure. But over recent weeks, there have been in two<br />
areas East of Suez in Hong Kon and in the Gulf of Aqaba<br />
dramatic illustrations to the British Government of its<br />
involvement, in a world role whether it wishes it or not.<br />
The rioting in H ong Kong and the short war in the Middle<br />
East have shown thit Britain is directly concerned in a<br />
significant way.<br />
There are, I know some in this great and<br />
powerful country who would like to leave the problems of<br />
the world where they are. Just as in the long, long ago<br />
there were many who felt you should stay out of Europe.<br />
But you didn't stay out of Europe, because you responded<br />
to the call of free men for help in desperate days, and<br />
now as the new area of crisis has moved to Asia you are<br />
committed again in strength and to a different type of war.<br />
The undeclared war. But war nevertheless.<br />
I was in South Korea very recently, and was<br />
heartened by what I found there. There is a tendency<br />
to think of these countries as small countries, weak<br />
countries not very much worth bothering about. But<br />
most of the world is made up of relatively small countries.<br />
There are great powers, of course and their<br />
aggregate populations are a very substantial portion of<br />
the world as a whole. But if you examine the membership<br />
of the United Nations there are many countries which are<br />
not all that large but which do have a significance in the<br />
scheme of thin. s. South Korea has 30,000,000 fine,<br />
vigorous, to uh, industrious people and it was heartening<br />
to me to see how they had taken on the problems of<br />
industrial development.<br />
Whether you look there, whether you look at<br />
Taiwan whether you look at Malaysia, Thailand or even at<br />
neutral Cambodia, where Prince Sihanouk has personally<br />
directed himself to the task of economic development you<br />
will see progress being made. I was shown with some pride<br />
the new port of Sihanoukville. There the Cimbodians are<br />
trying to secure, for the first time, an outlet to the<br />
sea instead of having all their goods come through what<br />
has in the past proved dangerous territory along the Mekong<br />
River. In each of these countries there is something to<br />
see of growth and progress. In Malaysia Tun Razak, the<br />
Deputy Prime Minister, outlined to me the developmental<br />
objectives of his country. In Thailand you can hear the<br />
same story. In Taiwan which like Korea can noint to one<br />
of the highest rates of increase in gross national product<br />
to be found anywhere in the world, there is much to see<br />
which most of the western world knows little about.<br />
Unfortunately most of the countries of Western<br />
Europe know very little about the developments which are<br />
occurring in this area. I cannot recall, for example, any<br />
senior member of the British Cabinet going through this area<br />
over recent years. Some may have touched in Singapore or<br />
Kuala Lumpur. But none has made a run of an instructive </p>
<p>kind. If you were to speak of most of the countries of<br />
iiestern Europe, you would get the same kind of result.<br />
Yet, east of Suez, there are currently nearly<br />
three fifths of humankind, and they are stirring as they<br />
shake off the shackles of the past, as they find<br />
themselves capaule of resisting the aggression of the<br />
past. These are the things that have held them back,<br />
not lack of auilities, not lack of skills, not lack of<br />
culture. Most of them have cultures and skills older<br />
than those of your country and mine. But, for the first time<br />
in centuries they are getting a chance to exoress themselves<br />
in a constructive and positive way.<br />
This holds tremendous promise for us all. I<br />
was canvassing this with the Prime Minister of Canada, Mr.<br />
Pearson. Canada has a Pacific border but that nation<br />
has been oriented for most of its history to the North<br />
Atlantic and North America. The Canadians are pretty<br />
capable international traders, and when they see the<br />
potentialities in Asia I do not think they will long<br />
persist in that kind of orientation. At least they will<br />
devote some of their view to what can happen across the<br />
Pacific. I give full credit to your own administration<br />
for their recognition of Asia. The first senior America<br />
representatives I can recall passing through my country,<br />
who had made their own personal assessment of what was<br />
happening in this area of the world, were Governor Dewey<br />
and John Foster Dulles. These men paved the way.<br />
Your own President made the first historic visit<br />
of a United States President to the region and to Australia,<br />
and his recognition of the area's potentialities has been<br />
shared by the administration.<br />
There is hope in this for mankind as a whole.<br />
My own country since the 1950' s has built up its export<br />
trade east of Suez from 15 percent Pf our exports to more<br />
than 40 percent of our exports. Japan, with whom we had<br />
virtually no trade right into the 1ite 1940' s now ranks<br />
as the largest purchaser of Australian goods in value in<br />
the world and it is rapidly rising.<br />
The potentialities may Je better understood by<br />
some comparisons. India, with forty-two times our<br />
population, only possessed twice our gross national product<br />
in value. Indonesia, with nine times our population, only<br />
rates one third the value of our gross national product.<br />
As these countries build their economies, with assistance<br />
from the stronger countries of the world, they will in the<br />
years ahead show tremendous growth.<br />
My country is committed to growth. believe<br />
we are favourably placed with those of you who have<br />
already come to help and share to serve as a springboard<br />
to the burgeoning economies of Asia. W. e hope more of you<br />
will come. Those of you who do will, I am sure, stay<br />
happily with us and build the greater Australia of the<br />
future. But this prospect, can only be secured if we<br />
are firm in our resolution to resist aggression where we<br />
find it in that area of the world and elp the Asian<br />
people to be free. These people aspire to a better order<br />
of life and are prepared to work for it and give their<br />
skills to it. / 6 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
The United 3tates, with its ima-inative realistic<br />
anpreciation of the problems and potentialities ol the<br />
region, is contributing to the hopes expressed by us in<br />
our declarations for freedom at Manila.<br />
CANLE . IA. ~ i </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
