<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3237</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER - PERTH LUNCHEON MEETING</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003237_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH NOTES FOR 1WPRIM'E MIiNISTER F<br />
PERTH-LUNCNEON-MEETING 2 KAY 1974<br />
Or ALL T HE ISSUES THAT HAVE EMERGED DURING<br />
THIS CAMPAIGN THE GREATEST OF THEM INVOLVES THIS BASIC<br />
QUESTION: WILL AUST. RALLANS CONTINUE TO CONTROL THEIRj<br />
OWN ECONOMIC DESTINY OR ARE W'E TO BECOME TENANTS IN<br />
OUR OWN LAND? SEVENTEEN MONTHS APO IPUT TO THE AuSTRALIAN<br />
PEOPLE CERTAIN PROPOSALS DESIGNED TO REVERSE THE<br />
INSIDIOUS PROCESS BY WHICH THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT<br />
ALLOWED CONTROL OF OUR ECONOMIC DESTINY TO PASS OUT<br />
OF OUR HANDS. THE POLICIES OF THE OPPOSITION IN THIS 1<br />
tRE SPECT SHOW NO REAL CHANGE, THIS ELECTION M1AY WELL B3E<br />
THE LAST OCCASION ON wHicH AUSTRALIANS ARE ABLE TO CHOOSE<br />
THEIR FUTURE COURSE, ' TO CONSERVE AN INDEPENDENT ECONOMIC<br />
INHERITANCE FOR OUR CHILDREN AND OUR CHILDREN' S CHILDREN$ </p>
<p>-2-<br />
WH-EN THE AUSTRAL IAN LAnOR PARTY WAS [ N Oo p IPOSITION<br />
PREPARED AND PRESENTED CERTAIN POLICIES BASED ON A BELIEF.<br />
AT AUSTRALIANS; COULD, AND INDEED MUST,. CONTROL THEIR'BASIC<br />
NDUSTRIES AND RESOURCES. LET' ME SAY TI[ S,, WE HAVE NOW HAD<br />
/ EXPERI-ENCE OF GOVERNMENT., WfE.. A1AVE HAD ' ACCESS TO THEEXETS<br />
AND THE INFORMATION AVAILABLE 1TO' GOVERNMENTS I AND ALL* OF'A<br />
* MY-MINISTERS, HAVE BROADENED OUR EXPERIENCE, EXTENDED OUR<br />
KJOLDGEAND HORIz'ON31 IY C fIWCrO0SN77 -I VA TT ER, AND<br />
UNF I TED CONV ICTI ON* OF MYW tABINET AND OV MY PARTY, HAVE BEEN<br />
A MEDAND STRENGTIHENED. AUSTRALIANS MUST-PRESERVE OUR<br />
ECONOMIC INDEPENDENC-IE. WE MUST-ftEJECT. THE SEDUCTIONS OF THEoujcK<br />
DEAL AND RESIST THE 7FMPTATIONS TO PROJF'IT' AT THE EXAPENSE<br />
OF-OUR. CHILDREN'S INHERITANCE, WE HAVE FOUGHT. FOR OUR. 3-<br />
INDEPENDENCE IN SEVERAL WARS, WHAT ARMS COULD NOT CONQUER,<br />
MUST NOT BUY'i, I AEHERE TO WE STERN AUSTRALIA BECAUSE IT IS'<br />
H THATIN RECENT Y EAR Ir THE CHO01CE IHAVE DESCRIBED HAS BEEN<br />
MOST ACUTE# ICAME HERE PARTICULARLY TO CHALLENGE THE MOST<br />
INSIDIOUS OF ALL PROPAGANDA IMPOSED I N THIS DEBATE. OUR OPPONENTS<br />
H4AVE SWALLOWED THE MULTINATIONAL LIE : THAT WITHOUT UNRESTRICTED<br />
FOREIGN INVESTMENT, CUR DEVELOPMENT IS-RESTRICTED. IDON ' T<br />
ACCEPT THIS PROPOSITION AND IDON'T BE L IEVE AUSTRALIA COULD<br />
1AFFORD TO ACCEPT THIS PROPOS ITIO101 w. </p>
<p>' I 3-<br />
THE QUESTION IS NOT W4HETHER WE PERMIT OVERSEAS CAPITAL<br />
TO DO LESS THE QUESTION IS WHETHER WE CAN ENSURE THAT<br />
AuSTRALIAN CAPITAL DOES MORE, OUR Ot1JECTIVE SHOULD BE<br />
TO MOSILISE THE RESOURCES OF OUR PEOPLEj HUMAN AND CAPITAL,<br />
AND THE POWERS OF OUR GOVERNMENITS, 90TH STATE AND FEDERAL,<br />
WE'MUST SIOP THE ABILITY OF MULTINATIONALS TO DIVIDEt AND<br />
O1ULE OUR STATE GOVERNMENTS AND PRIVATE COMPANIES#<br />
WESTERN AUSTRALIANS SHOULD KEEP * IN MIND THE FACT<br />
THAT M4ANY OF THE CORPORATIONS WITH WHICH YOUR STATE GOVERNMENT<br />
DEALS HAVE A BUDGET TEN. TIMES THE BUDGET OF YOUR STATE<br />
GOVERNMENT, AuSTRALIANS MUST UNITE 1O MOBILISE THEIR<br />
RESOURCES'. N4o AUSTRALIAN COMPANY ALONE CAN DEAL ON THE<br />
LEVEL OF MULTI-NATIONAL CORPORATIONS. NO AUSTRALIAN<br />
* STATE ACTING ALONE CAN DEAL-WITH ' THEM, ONLY THE NATIONAL<br />
GOVERNMENT HAS THE RESOURCES AND THE STATURE TO DO SO,<br />
U WE'MU-ST MOB* ILI* S'E OUR RESOURCES AND OUR SKILLS.<br />
THERE ARE FIELDS WHERE THE COMMONWEALTH ACTING ALONE CAN BE<br />
MOST EFFECTIVE. THERE ARE FIELDS WHERE THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
CAN BE MOST EFFECTIVE IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE S) TATES.<br />
THERE ARE FIELDS WHERE THE COKMONWEALTH CAN BE MOST EFFECTIVE<br />
IN PARTNERSHIP HITH PRIVATE CAPITAL, F]<br />
F ~ j~~ jft<br />
12 1 Ar<br />
I I<br />
I t t y-, jjr: 2~ R<br />
4 U.<br />
-v<br />
U<br />
I;-I'<br />
ii<br />
Ii II<br />
' I </p>
<p>145<br />
WHAT WE MUST DO AS-A NAT ION 3 S TO DEVE LOP THE POLICIES AND<br />
ESTABLISH THE INSTITUTIONS WHICH VAKE SUCH ACTION AND SUCH 1<br />
PARINERSHIP WORK, I'l<br />
OF THE MANY MEASURES FRUSTRATED AND BLOCKED BY<br />
THE SENATE, TWO OF THE MO ST' SI1GNIF I CANT INVOLVE THIS<br />
~~ ESTION, THE OPPOSITION HAS FRUSTRATED OUR PLANS TO<br />
BROADEN THE SCOPE OF THE AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY DEVELOPMENT ~ U~<br />
SRP ORATION AND TO ESTABLISH THE PETROLEUM ANDMNLSf. kL<br />
THORITY, OUR OPPONENTS' RESISTANCE TO THESE MEASURES l^<br />
TO PROMOTE AUSTRALIAN OWNERSHIP FORMS PART OF A PATTERN o F<br />
ENCOURAGEMENT OF FOREIGN OWNERSHIP WHICH THEY SET WHEN IN<br />
GOVERNMENT, THEY ASSERT THAT AUSTRALIAN PRIVATE CAPITAL<br />
SHOULD BE LEFT UNIMPEDED.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT IS NOT PREPARED TO LEAVE THIS<br />
SIC ISSUE IN THE HANDS OF THE COMPANIES AND THE MEN WHOr<br />
KNONE OF THE RISKS NECESSARY TO OBTAIN FOR AUSTRALIA<br />
A LARGER SHARE IN OWNERSHIP, CONTROL AND DEVELOPMENT OF<br />
OUR NEW RESOURCES. UNDER OUR PREDECESSORS, SIXTY-EIGHT PER<br />
CENT OF OUR ENERGY RESOURCES FELL INTO THE HANDS OF FOREIGN<br />
COMPANIES, NOTHING CAN CONVINCE ME 7HAT THIS WAS NECESSARY. 71<br />
VutlS tt~ f* S fl </p>
<p>' I~ r CAPACITY OF THESE COMPANIES TO SHOW INITIA7IVE AllD<br />
ENTERPRISE /% ND TO0 T AKE R ISKS CAN ONLY B E STRENGTHENED B~ Y.<br />
MOL1i. N IUSTRALIAN RESOUIRCES AND PO WERS lNHcIs, I s wHY<br />
WE NEE D TO EXPAND T H E ROLE OF THE AhSTRALIAN' INPDUSTRY<br />
lkVCLOPMFmT CORPORAl ION AND ESTABLISH THE-Pu TROL EllM A ND<br />
MINERALs AUlTHORITY. SNI C(-WE WERF ELECTED 10 GOVERNMENTW4E H-AVE.'<br />
ALRrADY SHOWN 711E ADVANTAG-ES O F SUCH AC: TION FOR THE<br />
F IRST TIME I N OUR HISTORY 11W-AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS*<br />
INIERVENED P. Y SUPERV I I ON OF iNENAL EXP'ORTS TO S71, GHE<br />
THlE BAfKGAININ( c-POWER OF OUR EXPORTERS, WE WFRE DETERMINED<br />
THAT OUR RESOURCES WOULD NOT t SOLD ON TIfI E CHEAP. N<br />
LONG~ ER CAN F OR E I GN BUYERS PLAY THE GAME OF DIVIDE AND RULE<br />
T1O0 XTkA CT LOWER PRICE S FROQM OUR COM PA Nl tS~ AN D COCSION-S<br />
FROM OUR STATE GOVERNMENTS. lIfE Or'OS IT ION s POLICY: IS<br />
P OMINOUSLY SILENT IN THIS RESPECT. WILL THEY ABOLISH OUR<br />
EXP'ORT CONTROL REGUJLAT IONS?.<br />
THlE ACTIONS OF THE USTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAVE<br />
RESULTED 114 SIGNIFICANT INCREASE, IN THE PRICE OF OUR' ) RON<br />
ORE AND COAL EXPORTS. THE mET ULTOF, TI-S POLICY PAS<br />
MEANT AN EXTRA $ 67 MILLION P ER A NNU M IN INCOME FROM IRON ORE<br />
AND AN, EXTRA $% MILL10ON PEP, ANNUM IN iXPOfT INCOME FROM COAL. N<br />
V ' I I<br />
r .4-<br />
j; A,<br />
I 1'* i. </p>
<p>j<br />
IN THIS tvAY ALL JAUS7RALIAfIS INEF IT F R TPE COrJCE NTRAI I CJHs<br />
OF OUR BARGA) NIN6 POW'ER, WIE MUcST UNITE IN I HF SAME MANNER<br />
TO fPRCSFR 01H-4N rc HI P AND CO1NTROL Or 0 UR INDU*&gt; TRI Es<br />
AND RESOURCES.-<br />
DEEP OFI SMHOSCKR AT HTHTEW SNAETNIOANSARLL ASSCSANADEA. YL SREENVSEAEL ED BYC<br />
W THE FITZGERALD REPORT, MIANY WESTERN AUSTRALIANS PROfA13LY~ 4<br />
BELIEVED THAT 114CI R MINFRAL INDUSTRY WAS PAYING SIG; NIFICANT V<br />
AMPOUNTS IN TAXATION, SOME OF YOU ALLFGED THAT THIS MONEY<br />
WAS BEING DRAINED OFF T0 711E OTHER Si,-fss L n ME MAKE<br />
T1IS CLEAR IF THFERE WAS ANY DRAIN OF 7HE WEALTH PRODUCED<br />
IN WFSTERN AuSIRALIA 1T DID NOT GO TO THlE OTHER STATES;<br />
IT WENT OVERSEAS* H FITZGFRALD REPORT REVEALS THAT OVER<br />
THE LAST SIX YEARS THE IMINING COMPANIES MADE $ 2,072 MILLON<br />
IN PROFIT, THCY RECEIVED FROM THE AuSTRALIAN TAXPAYER i<br />
$ 341 MILL110N IN SUB~ SIDIES AND PADOL,$~ bMILLONITA<br />
D AND ROYALTIES % MILLION LESS, AND SIXTY PER CENT OF<br />
THIESE PkROF TS ACCRUE TO OVErSE. Zf* A0-INVESTORS, INDEED, THE<br />
ANNUAL AMOUNT Orr PROFITS'PAYA13LE OVERSCAS fROSEL SIXFOLD IN<br />
THE F IVE YEARS tEDING JUNE. 197 3. </p>
<p>TtiE AUSTRAL I AN GOVERNMhENT IS OU! T1[) T HF<br />
CON~ T INUAT I O' OF S I 611 I F I CANT CAP ITAL INV[ STMENT [ fI M[ N[ ING.<br />
lii IN'E STiFNT SHOULD 1\ OT INVOLVE Lb S S E. 1T0 THE AI Of IAL<br />
REVFNU1, NOR SHOULD. 1T PR IMAR ILY PROiMOTE FORE I Gf<br />
PROr ITA) I. t17Y, AM AWARE orF THE BENEF I TS'IHA THE MI14 1 NG<br />
INDUSTRY HAS 1DOL'GHT TO THEL Fsr. 11 WHOLE THRUISI of-MY<br />
ARGUMENT IS THAT 14SIERN AU,' TRALIANS-I-IKL' ALL AUSl) TRAL IANSJ<br />
SHUD HAVE BENEFITED MORE FROM THIS' DEVELOPMENTO WlE HAVE<br />
-NOT TAKEN FLL1. ADVANTAGE OF OUR RESOURCES IN TERMS OF<br />
PROM01 ING THlE WELFARE OF THE A uSTRALIAN PEOPI F 141 INTEND<br />
TO 110 S0 I N THE FUTURE,.*.<br />
S S 4<br />
4 f. </p>
<p>14F HAVE ALfREADY ANNOUNCED OUR 114TENTION TO EXTEND<br />
AND STRENGTHEN THE FOREIGN TAKEOV/ ERS LEGISLATION,<br />
THIS IS ONE Or THE MEASURES WHICH WA S FRUSTRATED BY THE<br />
OBSTRUCTFION OF -THE %. ENATE, W4E PROPO. SE AND I ANNOUNCE -I<br />
HERE FOR THE FIRST TIME"-THREE BASIC EXTENSIONS OF THIS<br />
LEGISLATION1 THE MOST SERrOUS OMT-oioN IN THE* PRESENT ACT<br />
I S THAT I T APPLIES ON[ LY TO THE PURCHASE Or SHAPES.<br />
IT DOES NOT PREVENT AN OVERSEAS3 COMPANY BUYING ALL OR PART<br />
OF THE ASSETS OF AN AuSTRALIAN COMPANY AS DISTINCTK.<br />
rROM THE SfAREHOLD INGSS T HIS I S A MAJOR LOOPHOLE.<br />
THE EFFECT OF AUYING SHARES OR BUYING ASSFTS IS THE SAME,<br />
Ta Ecr)! THE LFGISLATION IS THAT<br />
IT DOES NOT INCLUDE COMPULSORY NOTIFICATION RE. QUIREMENTS<br />
FOR [ OREIGN COMPANIES PROPOSING TO MAKE SUCH A TAKEOVER<br />
OF ASSETS, WE WILL iNCLUDEF SUCH PROVISIONS# </p>
<p>' 7'<br />
WE PROPOSE A THIRD AMENDMENT,<br />
THE LEGISLATION DOES NOT EXTEND TO COMPANIES At-READY UNDER<br />
FOREIGN CONTROL BUT IN WHICH THERE IS A SIGHIFICANT, MINORITY<br />
AbSTRALIAN INTEREST, THFRE HAVE' BEEN A NlJMP[ VR OF-OCCASiONG<br />
W4HEN THE AoST RAL IAN EQUITY fIN A VENTURE I IAS BPE[ EN DIMIIN1 SHED<br />
BY A SHARE ISSUE OR A'SHARE SVAP, 1WE P ROP OSE THAT;<br />
t -ON CERTAIN CRITERIA, ANY AITIMPT TO DIMIN1-1i A SIGMIF ICANT<br />
AI sRAL IA14 INTEREST; EVENIF IT IS A lnOl-CONTROL LINMC<br />
INTEREST, SHOULD DL MADE EXAMINABLE IN1 ACCORDANC. E WITH<br />
THE PROCEDURES DEVELOPED BY THlE FOREIGN TAKFEcV[ R COtMMIrTEE<br />
CONTROL OF FO0R EI G f TAKEOVERS Is0O NE ASPFCT OFI<br />
MOICY DESIGNED TO MAX I m i s AusTRALIAN OWNERSHIP AND CONTROL.<br />
TUE GOVERNMENT IN ITS At'M IN I STRAT IVE ARRANGEMENTS, 14AS CESTABL ISt<br />
A BROADER SYSTEM OF SURVEILLANCE OF FORFEIGN INVESTMENT PROPOSAL_' i_...<br />
NOT INVOLVING DIRECT ACQUISITION OF AUSTRALIAN BUSINESSES.<br />
' ANNOUNCED IN MY POLICY SPEECH TH-AT VIE WHOULD FORMALISE THESC<br />
ARRANGEMENTS, WE WILL ESTABLISH A BROAD sCREENING, PROCESS1<br />
WHICH WILL-COVER BO0TH THE FOREIGN TAKECOVERS PROCEDURES,<br />
AS AMENDEDi AND NEW DIRECT FOREIGN I NVE STXENT. ANY. NEW<br />
FOREIGN COMPANY PROPOSING TO SeET UP IN AoSTRALIA'FOR THE<br />
FIRST TIME, OR ANY' FORE'IGN COMPANY PROPOSING TO EXTEND ITS<br />
INVESTMENT INTO NElq AREAS, WILL BE REOUIRED TO APPL* Y TO 111E<br />
Y AD HE ETILS* OF THE PROPOSED -INVESTMENT WILL BE-<br />
,4EAURY ND T DET 04 </p>
<p>7 1 sIENN RCS JLElSUETA N<br />
FRANC HE SR E ENIC ND DOEVSL L H SRTE THATD ANRE<br />
' ROPOSIN FEGTL IHNVESTGE WICHSIS POLICIES CNORAX<br />
AVIDACE OVERAR ALP ATIODAL tTIE GUDZ NE THEIE SE<br />
WHIC HWILL BECEOE MOR CULA TENTOR EXPRIEC GRPOST<br />
RINCOMPANIES ALREADY OPERFAT ! NG ' AN AUSTRALIA WILL<br />
E EXPECTED TO CONFORM, W~ ITH THESE GUIDELINES PROORESSIVELY.<br />
IN TH1S WAY WE WILL ENSURE TVAT THE FOREIGN INVESTMtNT<br />
TH~ AT HAS ALREADY BEEN ALLOWED IL COFR T H<br />
AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL INTEREST AS WELL AS ANY NEW FOREIGN<br />
INVESTMENT THAT 1S ALLUKID.-</p>
<p>No AusTRALIAN, NO MATTER HOW STRONGLY( HE BEL 1EVES<br />
IN 11AE RAPID DEVCLOPMENT OF OUR l) UIRAL RESOUC<br />
StIOULD PAY FOR THE PRI'/ lLE. G O) F liii 11,16 LXPLOITED.<br />
THE MESSAGE OF THlE F112GEWILD REPORT IS CLEAR,<br />
WE HAVE SOLD OURI'; ELVES SHORT IN OUR RECENT MIN) ERAL DEVELOPMENTr<br />
Tal PEOPLE WHO HAVE SUFFERED MOST FROMi THE FAILUJRE OF THE<br />
PREVIOU1S GOVERNMENT TO CkT TI FL I2FITS For AUJSTRALIANS9<br />
ARE THE PEOPLE OF THIS STAII, WHERE MINEVAL t'E-VEl.. OPMENTSl<br />
HAVE BEEN THE MOST DRAMATIC. ThE FA . ILURC I( O MAXIMI . SE<br />
OUR REVENUE IS A FAULT OiF THE LAST FEDERAL GOVERNMENT AS<br />
WELL. AS THE ft. CSENT STATE IGD V ERN K[ INT<br />
THE REVE14UE wHict TrHE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WILL<br />
RECEIVE) t. VEN FPOh~ THE DECISIONS AI. PSEAPY ' TA KE No WILL ENABLE<br />
US TO COMWVf CONSIDERABLE ADOUNTS TO0 EXPELORATION FOR<br />
FURT11ER RESOURCES AND THE DFVELOPMElT OF THOSE RESOURCESBy<br />
itHE AUSTRALIAN fOVERNMENT DIRECTLY AND 1IN PARTNERSHIP<br />
WITli PRIVAt AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL. MUCHi OF THIS EXPENDITURE<br />
ON EXPLORAT ION AND D) EVELOPMENT VMLL OF NECESSITY BE<br />
rJIRCCTED TO' THE GREAT MINERAL RESOURCES IN THE wEST. OnfLY<br />
IF THlL ' AusTRALIAN GOt-VERNMIENT PLAYS A DIRECT ROLE IN Tlic<br />
PROVISION AND MORILIGAT ION OF CAPITAL WILL OUR RESOURCES<br />
ttE DEVELOPED' IN A MANNER CONS I ST) ENT WII1H MAXl1MW~ AIST R AL-I At<br />
CONT ROL AND 0OWNERSHIP. K] ' 1' S .1<br />
iv<br />
Q~ A. A.. 74<br />
-A ' I<br />
ñ 11 </p>
<p>THE R~ E VEFL A I) N S OF 7HC FIT ? GFRALD. kEPORT APE<br />
pis iOWEVEtR ' T I S C! FAR FP.' M THEI P RECENT<br />
STITE IENITS THAT THE-GUL TY MEN COF THE: PR~ EVIOUS GOV/ ERNMENT<br />
TtHE INEi WHO At. LO'IED T F S S 1 -TUIAT 1O TO EMiERGE AAP . E<br />
UN RElf-E N TANT THXE Y HAVE NO PLAN -NO I NT E. N 7' ON -TO<br />
* REDUICE FORET1GN CONTROL OF OUR RESOURCES, OiN THE ATF<br />
OF TAXAT 1O0N CON~ CE S ONNP N D LS0~ Slt THEY CONTINUE TO i~<br />
~ CT AND TALK AS THE APOLOGISTS-OF FOREF IGN 111ING INTERESTS,<br />
HAUSTRALIAN PEOPLE HAVE THE RIGHT TO KNOW HOW T HE<br />
EXTRAM INARY CRUSANC, r -) LprWt HICH MADE<br />
AuST RAL IANS3 PAY FOR THE E$ RIVIL EGE OF BEING; E\. DL01T E D3<br />
W4E WILL E N' 01.0A GE AND 1) EV71LOP onR M f,!" AL7<br />
WINJ( JSTRJ-E* S BULT WE ARE EQUALL YD, k" 1NF TO MAXIMISE<br />
THE CONTR [ ULT I CN THE SE rNDUSTR IE orMAAKE TO OUR NATIONAL<br />
' F AT H ' A HAVE TODAY SIGNE1L1 A REFFRENCF TO THE D S RE<br />
# Ass! ISTANCrE CO MM I S t' ASKING ! T TO INQ:) UIPE ANI' REPORT ON<br />
THE EFF-ECT 0 r T A XATNIC 0~ ICE Sf ON SSA ND R0 LT7 IE ON THE,<br />
DE V EL C) PMLN T A-N D EF F I C .1IVNY O THE PETROLEUM IAit N IING<br />
I L ST R IE A i T 0 A D'yIIS E F~ H P% A ND N1W14H AT WAY0. WE<br />
SHOULD OFFER ASSISTANCE T0 r'R IMPOSE R0Y A L T I , S ON THEE<br />
411t J" </p>
<p>S. t-THE FITZGERAL) REPORT REVEALtED TIlE SEERITY OF<br />
THF LOSSES AND LOST OPPoRtU! ITIE I IHAT UUCO-ORDINATFL)<br />
AND t4BUSINES5LIKE POLICY-MKAIN IN MI! lftljUG OPERATIONS<br />
HAS ALREADY INFLICTED ON 09, THE REPORT OF THE COMMISSIOI 1<br />
WILI ENSUIRE 1110 THE LOSSES WlILL. NOT CONTI NUE AND MY -i<br />
GOVCRNMENT WILL CNSORE THAT THE GREAT LBENEFITS ACCRUIG<br />
fiRM THF IEVELOPM'ENT Or OUR NATURAL RE8OirPCES ouR<br />
NATURAL HERITAGE WILL PE SHAPIEr FAIRLY BY ALL<br />
S -AUSTrALiANS I1N THI-1E INTERESTS OF ALL AUSTRALIANS.-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
