<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4908</transcript-id>
    <title>MEAT INSPECTION INQUIRY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/12/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004908.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F78/ 250<br />
FOR PRESS 3 DECEMBER 1978<br />
MEAT INSPECTION INQUIRY<br />
The Prime X~ inister today announced that he had written to<br />
State Premiers and the Chief Minister of the Northern Territory<br />
seeking their agreement to the establishment of an independent<br />
committee to inquire into and report on Commonwealth and State<br />
meat inspection arrangements.<br />
The Prime Minister emphasised the necessity of obtaining<br />
State Government co-operation to enable the committee to<br />
effectively conduct its wide ranging investigations. State<br />
Governments are responsible in most States for the inspection<br />
of meat for domestic consumption while the Commonwealth has<br />
responsibility for export meat.<br />
The Prime Minister recalled that he had written to Premiers<br />
on 4 May seeking their co-operation in rationalising the<br />
present system of separate Commonwealth and State meat inspection<br />
systems. Premiers generally had replied that improvements could be<br />
made to the present arrangements, and had expressed the view<br />
that State Government should exercise a greater role.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the Commonwealth had nominated<br />
the Hon. C. R. Kelly, a former minister of State and long time<br />
Chairman of the Parliamentary Standing Committee on Public<br />
Works, and M*. r W. A. Buettel, a former General manager of the<br />
Commonwealth Development Bank, Queensland, serve as members<br />
of the inquiry.<br />
The Commonwealth Government proposed that the inquiry have<br />
the following terms of reference:<br />
The Corcmiztee of Inquiry will be required to investigate<br />
and report to the Minister for Primary Industry on:<br />
the merits and demerits of the meat inspection system<br />
as presently operated by State and Federal bodies;<br />
whether the present system of meat insepction administration<br />
should be retained and, if so, with or without modification;<br />
an alternative system if the present meat inspection<br />
administration systems should not be retained; </p>
<p>2<br />
the recommended organisational structure and control<br />
of an alternative meat ' inspection system if the<br />
present system should not be retained;<br />
the industrial relations and any other considerations.<br />
These terms of reference are sufficiently wide to allow the<br />
Committee to investigate and evaluate the present system of<br />
separate meat inspection administration arrangements. They<br />
would give the inquiry scope to suggest alternatives to the<br />
present arrangements. Its findings should be of great<br />
assistance to governments in finding means of rationalising<br />
meat inspection services, and reducing costs. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
