<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3296</transcript-id>
    <title>SCREENING OF FOREIGN INVESTMENT PROPOSALS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/06/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003296.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUS! HALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER 12 JUNE 19711<br />
Press Statement No. 266<br />
SCREENING OF FOREIGN INVESTMENT PROPOSALS<br />
In his 29 April Policy Speech the Prime Minister said<br />
that the Government would proceed with the further definition<br />
of guidelines for foreign investment in Australia and would<br />
extend the present systems of surveillance into a general<br />
screening process under the co-ordination of the Treasurer.<br />
Mr Whitlam today announced the establishment of new<br />
machinery as part of the development of more extensive<br />
systems of surveillance by the Government of foreign investment<br />
in Australia. A new interdepartmental committee is to be estalished<br />
to examine and provide advice on foreign investment proposals.<br />
which come under notice through the exchange control mechanism<br />
and do not involve the takeover of Australian businesses.<br />
The new committee will report to the Treasurer and<br />
will comprise representatives of the Treasury, the Department of<br />
the Prime Minister and Cabinet, the Department of Overseas Trade,<br />
the Department of Minerals and Energy, the Department Manufacturing<br />
Industry and the Reserve Bank. Representatives of other<br />
departments will be co-opted to the committee as appropriate in<br />
the examination of particular proposals.<br />
The new committee will thus parallel and complement<br />
the existing Committee on Foreign Takeovers. Like that committee,<br />
its functions will be purely advisory.<br />
The establishment of the new committee will not affect<br />
the existing procedures under which applications for exchange<br />
control approval for individual foreign investment proposals<br />
are processed through the Reserve Bank.<br />
Mr Whitlam added that, in addition to~ reporting on<br />
foreign investment proposals arising through the exchange control<br />
mechanism, the new committee will be asked to bring forward, for<br />
the Government's consideration, detailed proposals for the<br />
screening of foreign investment activities which do not involve<br />
exchange control approvals for example, investment proposals<br />
which would be financed by foreign interests from funds available<br />
to them from Australian sources. </p>
<p>-2<br />
" For the AAA to urge greater spending on rbads<br />
demonstrates that it is living in the past.<br />
" All the beautiful-looking freeways in the world won't<br />
stop cities from finally choking in atmospheric pollution and<br />
' seizing' in the streets from vehicle congestion. Sydney and<br />
Melbourne have been recording heavier-than-ever atmospheric<br />
pollution figures recently and fast, comfortable and economical<br />
public transport is the only alternative to the disaster that<br />
befell Los Angeles.<br />
" There. the building of more and more freeways simply<br />
encouraged greater use of cars until the point was reached where<br />
Los Angeles achieved doubtful fame for the size and density of<br />
its smog problem which brought with it respiratory and other<br />
complaints on a large scale.<br />
" Now, the city is turning away from the freeway, and<br />
the automobile, and reverting to urban public transport. In<br />
this it is doing what most major cities Of the world had done<br />
already. " Simply pouring out money for roads is outdated. if<br />
we had unlimited funds for them we would be pointing our cities<br />
down the same road to disaster as Los Angeles." Mr Jones added.<br />
CANBERRA 12 JUNE 1974 </p>
<p>AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
Second Whitlam Ministr'y<br />
1. Prime Minister<br />
2. Deputy Prime Minister and<br />
Minister for Overseas Trade<br />
3. Minister for Minerals and<br />
Energy<br />
4. Minister for Social Security<br />
Leader of the Government in<br />
the Senate, Attorney-General<br />
and Minister for Customs and<br />
Excise<br />
6. Minister for Foreign Affairs<br />
7. Treasurer<br />
8. Minister for Services and<br />
Property and Leader of the<br />
House<br />
9. Minister for the Media and<br />
Manager of Government<br />
Business in the Senate<br />
Minister for Defence<br />
11. Minister for Agriculture<br />
12. Minister for Northern<br />
Development and Minister<br />
for the Northern Territory<br />
13. Minister for Labor and<br />
Immigration<br />
14. Minister for Education<br />
Special Minister of State<br />
and Minister Assisting the<br />
Prime Minister in Matters<br />
Relating to the Public<br />
Service<br />
16. Minister for Repatriation<br />
and Compensation<br />
17. Minister for Urban and<br />
Regional Development<br />
18. Postmaster-General<br />
19. Minister for Housing and<br />
Construction THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.<br />
THE HON. JIM CAIRNS, M. P.<br />
THE HON. R. F. X. CONNOR, M. Pb<br />
THE HON. BILL HAYDEN, M. P.<br />
SENATOR THE HON. LIONEl MURPHY, Q. C.<br />
SENATOR THE HON. DCN WILLESEE<br />
THE HON. FRANK CREAN, M. P.<br />
THE HON. F. M. DALY, M. P.<br />
SENATOR THE HON. DOUGLAS McCLELLAND<br />
THE HON. L. H. BARNARD, M. P.<br />
SENATOR THE HON. K. S. WRIEDT<br />
THE HON. REX PATTERSON, M. P.<br />
THE HON. CLYDE R. CAMERON, M. P.<br />
THE HON. KIM E. BEAZLEY, M. P.<br />
THE HON. LIONEL F. BOWEN, M. P.<br />
SENATOR TIlE HON. J. M. WHEELDON<br />
THE HON. TOM UREN, M. P.<br />
SENATOR THE HON. R. BISHOP<br />
THE HON. LES JOHNSON, M. P. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Minister for Transport<br />
21. Minister for Health<br />
22. Minister for Manufacturing<br />
Industry<br />
23. Minister for the Capital<br />
Territory<br />
24. Minister for the Environment<br />
and Conservation<br />
Minister for Aboriginal<br />
Affairs<br />
26. Minister for Science,<br />
Minister Assisting the<br />
Minister for Foreign Affairs<br />
in Matters Relating to<br />
Papua New Guinea and Minister<br />
Assisting the Minister for<br />
Defence<br />
27. Minister for Tourism and<br />
Recreation and Vice-President<br />
of the Executive Council. THE HON. C. K. JONES, M. P.<br />
THE HON. D. N. EVERINGHAM, M. P.<br />
THE HON. KEP ENDERBY, M. P.<br />
THE HON. GORDON BRYANT, M. P.<br />
THE HON. MOSS CASS, M. P.<br />
SENATOR THE HON. J. L. CAVANAGH<br />
THE HON. W. L. MORRISON, M. P.<br />
THE HON. F. E. STEWART, M. P.<br />
JvF: / 1 7k </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
