<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4360</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE NATION - 6 APRIL 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/04/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004360.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F'OR PRESS 6 APRIIL 1977<br />
BH13AGO: 7.. 15 p. mn. '-ST<br />
ADDRESS TO THE NATION<br />
Good evenving. Now that the wage case is over, ' I would likte<br />
. speak to you for a ew moments a-bout where we stand as<br />
a nation ,. and -aboxit where we are qoiicT in : 1977.<br />
We all know there have been significant problems for the economy.<br />
Th is concerns you-lt certainly concerns your Governmrent. We<br />
a! lI know that i4f wages go up, price. c up. We know the<br />
destructi ve of fect that infiation has on the economy. That is<br />
Why we argued sio s~ tzcngly for wage restraint before ithe<br />
A-rbitration Co-mmission. We have not done this as some<br />
cartoonists, some columnist~ s, might like to suggest because<br />
we believe -that life is not meant to be easy. We have dIone<br />
it becauaE itc is important for the well being of Australia, for<br />
the well being of every pevson. it is important fox providaing<br />
the jobs that Australians want~.<br />
We all kniow that wheni the Goveinment took office fifteen months<br />
ago~ the economy was in bad shape, inflation was much tco high.<br />
unenployment was much too hiuh, and Government apending ,, as<br />
craite out of control. qe took up the fighrt against inflation<br />
irmrediately because defeating inflation is ixrrortant to the well<br />
being of all Australians. -We hatve tackled this job with all the<br />
resources available tZ. o Gover-rnent. We have cut Government<br />
spending significantly, because Governmrent spending is a major<br />
cause of inflation.<br />
In simple terms, a Government is somewhat like a amily.<br />
It has to live within it~ s means. We all k-now in our own families<br />
th~ at if we spe-nd too much for too long we will discover<br />
eventually that are too much in debt to the bank,-c We also<br />
kno-v that debts can take a lonq while to pay off. WE! know that<br />
4iewe are paying off debts we are going to have to give<br />
up other things that we would. normally want. So it is with a<br />
nation. Australia has spent too much f'or too long. The Government<br />
of: the ay went to the printing presses so it could clo on<br />
sye-nlirq more and more. The inevitable result had to be more<br />
anid more inflation.<br />
The other major cause of Australia' a inflation has hiee Itoo xrapid<br />
wage increases. For example, in the two years to October _ 19-i<br />
hourly Wage. ; rates paid in Manufactulring industry went up by<br />
5A7 while at the same time production from' manufacturing,<br />
in~ dustry actually fell. The result can only be inflation. </p>
<p>2. I<br />
Peopic WNPd a lot 0or C Money Lo oel. btwe w* erc ac C.<br />
~ ci~: r :~ s~ Pr" c t he r oore atoou.<br />
T~ of assc Awus~ tr li. als jiflation have been too g r cat<br />
Gocn~ n pniiad to 7id w-a g t er s1; Ca t CVvr n nrt<br />
ha8 actedl, quite drastiCEaL1-y, tO rC AucC itS 0" in seri." ing. 1<br />
we are to overcom'. o in'flat -oQa, wage r-_ trai Dt is also cos ent ial.<br />
. T xnc-a~ x~ er sc'ri,, peo'pl who claiLm that ,., hen the Govern~ merit<br />
points to thle needf for wa! c; s r. estraint, tlien are att-ckina wiage<br />
anid salac-f. arner.-:. That . s niot so-. I belicve thero arairior<br />
and ruv; re neople iaround AunStrajlek Who0 are C--in to -A<br />
t'Lhat wage restraint is in theIr own 13est Ift the ini. orefst<br />
o f e -jPrvy At. r aii an in tha neet of thei-r mates 1' P-, o ido not<br />
have -ob8; and,' that it-is in the J ta,: rest of resi-0r2. lq C<br />
to the A-1itralialn a: ConormV . an1 Cstalblishi trp ie CfILrts ta . e S<br />
w'he. re cvQ) yoone can again look forward,' to risinig livir.-g tda.<br />
The Governent 1-bns not sa Lid onl-that there ought to be wacia<br />
ref-trdimt. The '~ vrntnh&amp; as~ odelibe. r&amp;;-eiy set 0 ut to<br />
~ tablxh the 3tanic-S An w4i'jich it is reaso'nabl t a<br />
for wage rsa.-The Ti policy Of aml lo'. zShas do-ne<br />
C7.' 4: at d'eal to ! Iei;? income I-amiJ~ liCs. Tens oi ouh. v._ tands<br />
o~ famtilies arc -1eaitsr c -a r c ilt. 73-1 adlitiori, taxz<br />
indiexation i8 helping all famili-es. 7xa'ov lastE July, taxfs<br />
wer yS C0o0: urem i 111 o q a s a 8ulIt t ax -ati11<br />
11-a-_ is a vary lar'; vsurr, a n aybe it is hard to ch7d<br />
ITC mnaan that for a &amp; n easvoe raqie earmin.," s, wit-n' a wift amii1<br />
. two cvc-rtaxes by ie , t Ju:) e $ O9 a lOe3Ks . Lhdr) tl-oV"<br />
WonuAfm v beeni wthiout Indexation-' That iz near'ly a ar<br />
It is more th-an a curter of tlie tax that would oth; erwiss have.<br />
been pa.-A withiout cur r= efor-Ms. Tax indexation is thie ffars-t<br />
system in our history that autzc-atiCally protects you, thee.-L<br />
automat3_ Ca7Lly pjrotects exrE-TY tax payer agains-t tax rese<br />
nmereiv because of infiat.-ion-Unb~ these cir~ zwrstances, : 1<br />
be1~. i-t ' is jite r( easonable to ask fEor a greatdalo<br />
Wage res; trairnt.<br />
In all. 1: 1e mreas under elirect GovPrr7nt 0oto V; hae atiw<br />
A44I , m e 2S We have greaUIy reducc CTOvernm~ ent spen dinl1.<br />
TDhat Js staiin the 7:+ ight against infLltion. W4e have anl<br />
ap~ rpr: Lrate -and prope-r m05Et+-ary poL3cy. Our Qx'ternal policy i8 in<br />
' the ric~ t bal,-ince. AZll of theso acticns are essential if w<br />
ar o ~' ecm&amp; e flton fwe arc to Crealc the jobs thaLt: we11a_ l .<br />
rqe have ha" sjqnificarit ='. Icess ill the fiqhtli against infElation.<br />
Inte % ete m o -jth11s t o 6 t D c Qe mb e r o n th best rigures wte have,<br />
2.* LT~ c riwe rno ata ite over 10 percent. A year earlier<br />
thefic~ wmar p~ C'flt No matrwhat anryone mid,, ht 2a Iyt ) S e<br />
twa fii--: L nd i c-t! a very ro~ alI itnpvrolemenit i n the coaLirse oJ. onre<br />
ye. 7u'. ~ tthat cani Ybe arot; 1cc if ther. e is -no cont inued wa ge:<br />
rest~~ a~ naQinw~~ TA'C ic . s n area that is not umler the<br />
di UCt coflt,. z0l of Ioi erJAe. ustralia Is circumstance~ s<br />
t. i~ s vmy lirt: 7y the Aribtration Commission that de-termines the<br />
./ 3 </p>
<p>* ol of wacis ' oaid. Th e A jtr a Ion Co mi-Ssion is not just a<br />
tereor tosetle industria" 64irputes. Itis also ' I<br />
-1e c-stoi~ o n have a gireat impact on Elie wnolct economny.<br />
af~ fect youi, they affect every ome 1. s.<br />
L~ t -Wee% 4Vhe_ lxbltratiori Coa-SS10.1 award: edl a $ 5,70 a we e'k<br />
14 Pe incre ase. tow that does mean-that-wear st--rtinq 1.977<br />
Ltn a qr e at or d eqre o f -, iaq0 r L. s t -, Iilt than w-a laas t %/ era<br />
tnd that in-itself iL3s-0011~. But th $ 5.70 ir i t L a<br />
th tCeh q e Goerne nt b elev es is3 in te intere ts of<br />
\ utstralia' s econxomic~ well being in the interests of tjhe wall<br />
Aiq of ca-ch person. Lt cdoes menthat there will be delay in<br />
ducticn in the level of inflationi, and that4 there wll1<br />
delay~ Un -ed-" uctions in \ 1ncrmplo% ent. it d~ oes eathat it aiil1<br />
e tar d the p-. rocess 0j: -cvery that is now under1 way, t<br />
herefor e t-here is no reason for com-; placency, ~ n titpriu<br />
dhisicn-" he GOvarrtmerlt will co-Ptinue to argue I' ut 1re for<br />
wage caSes -For the cgreatc-st possible degree of 4aerestri.<br />
tbe Cois3iol ha. s m~ ade it ! acisin and not I k. u t<br />
eve,-yorit-to acccpt it, and to work~ within T~ ~ fi<br />
leaders who are threateniing to go oatside thedecision and<br />
who azc threateningq -o break tIChe aair~ ean~<br />
turedt-Ek) irg every pc3oxn in IAustralia. Thea ArbitLrzat1ion<br />
Cc i 9so _-LIs Cii -ust be suppox-ted. It will be sppotad<br />
;:) elieve wE a. 11 know in our bhearts that the-kind of wagia<br />
i. ncreaases we have hzad in recenL tilres only lead to higher anid high,<br />
That 14 wlhy we had to d value last4 NoebrL4 o oso h<br />
emnort ot-? srax obs. Auis. tralian rnanu~ actrr s were ;~ table<br />
to s eJ 1 their gcods b -ause thiey werc too e'~ penslVr.. More and r'o<br />
importk-s wcre Qoran into the cotny. JA s a r es ul t 100, 0 0<br />
A\ st-rallans Lost their' Jobs in nanufactturin,-indust zy. ah~ t<br />
had to ;, top. ] jundreds oi millions of dollars wcre flowing oi. L Ot<br />
country andl th-at had -to ste-p. That ; s why we devalku.: d.<br />
Devaluati'on Stopped und flowing ouLt of AustraliLa.<br />
] Devaluatiori has gTiven Thstralian itn&amp;_ stry a chance -to com~ pete aciaai:<br />
and that is essential) if there are to bea tba iobS that Australia<br />
nei~ ds. ~ i t-he chance of: work for tens of thousands<br />
Au~ tralians -will bo-lost _ if t-herc -1s riot wace -estr;, a4 t,<br />
UnemploFyment is still tcxn bigh-I ?-now y: ou -are concerned about thaaa<br />
T am, and as the Gove!_ rL-ient is. We have, as youa k1now,<br />
introduced it nlwnber of piclprograi-aes to heir ' uen eMIlo'e<br />
and espeaicily to help the young iiarrployed. W2 Wiill i3-prcnv<br />
on tl-osa p-oranrames as we. ocanV. But the o7n11 way reallyV to<br />
ovrcmeun oo'~ eiv. ~ to overcome ria~ nandw<br />
U~ t~ l~. l~ lto d" o that. -iniflation create3 nmlvet<br />
It hbur-ts the por. It mak; es it harder to bya hc1-ne..<br />
It destroys tiie value of savings and in~ o: res. ~ earta leterT -1ne'-<br />
to oec einfElatior. an.-restore to Australia the jobs andi<br />
opportunitic~ s thatl-Aiustralia wants.<br />
we can establish the policies. Wecan'e thfe .4q1 0i-; 1 inC'_ 1, bu t<br />
) restor-ig Autralia t; Lo economic hjealth is not 4ust a j-' cb for<br />
the Govo~-, nert alone.. Tt is alIso a ob for you, to-, every g . roup<br />
in the APwstralian bui. ss foiiin. ROvo2u r~ ny </p>
<p>4.<br />
a ~~ iii er-conrac recovery. R~ vcrYcne has a role irt<br />
r s ta-rinrl Astral. ia to c: cj~ iomc heal. th.<br />
Now I can upderst-ad it if you think that your own per52oylaL<br />
decisions3 are so smnall th t tey oQi-uot real&gt; y iava any<br />
on c~ r~ y that sete arears so Ifir; a rIf~)'<br />
iirE~ emte ut t, e A'ustralinan ezorto-mii made<br />
ao: ther Tt:' S like yol-xs, all arouznd<br />
AusTr~ ets: e~~ r th hat ma-kze thep A-ustx ala<br />
1t thes 3cr0oSs on'I thInt hav0 1 ar -gTe -2 t 0 Y) ia<br />
in eietermininc wO-ethi-a haive a helth econocmv. SDO rC_ tor_; j C<br />
PAustic. afia to cf--nacmic health~ is a j'ob for evarvamn-. it is<br />
iob for You a-nd it O certainly a -1. b MrE. It i a<br />
ifor ell101r* DcrSCMon ric e very g9tml: I in the Austrnli-. n omri.<br />
. lf WC-Qan undi-zrL-tani tiand 1-1 we c. n wark tocjcthe:-r I have,-<br />
n~ ot the sliq-ht-est dcub,-th1iat we wf. 11 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
