<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40379</transcript-id>
    <title>New AFP Forensics facility now operational</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/08/2016</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Today Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull and Justice Minister Michael Keenan opened a new purpose-built forensic facility for the Australian Federal Police, which will be one of the most advanced of its kind in the world.</p>
<p>The $106m forensic facility, located at the AFP’s Majura Complex in the ACT, will be a global centre of scientific excellence which will position the AFP to respond effectively to Australia’s evolving threat environment, including organised crime and terrorism.</p>
<p>More than 200 experts in digital forensics, weapons intelligence, fingerprint and facial identification, and biological and chemical criminalistics will be brought together to enhance the investigative and forensic capabilities of federal law enforcement officers.</p>
<p>They will work in a cutting-edge environment that will support collaboration and intelligence sharing with the AFP’s domestic and international law enforcement partners.</p>
<p>World-class technology, including an innovative Search Precinct which provides a central hub for the examination of evidence, will ensure the AFP maintains its world-leading capacity in forensic operations, forensic science policy, research, training and capability development.</p>
<p>This facility will expand the AFP’s capacity to conduct major investigations and respond to crisis situations, including those involving disaster victim identification.</p>
<p>It will enhance the important role the AFP already plays in domestic and international investigations, including its leading role in the ongoing international criminal investigation into the downing of Malaysian Airlines flight MH17. </p>
<p>Providing our law enforcement and intelligence agencies with the tools and resources they need is a priority for the Coalition Government. It is vital that our law enforcement agencies have the necessary facilities and resources to enable them to be effective.</p>
<p>The Government will continue to support the AFP on its progressive approach to meeting the current and future demands of a complex and increasingly global law enforcement environment.</p>
<p>This facility represents the future of the AFP. </p>

]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
