<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4330</transcript-id>
    <title>MINISTERIAL STATEMENT - AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL GALLERY: DIRECTOR AND SECRETARY/MANAGER</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/02/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004330.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4jj&gt; A U~ IAL! A~!<br />
FOR PRESS 23 FEBRUARY 1977<br />
MINISTERIAL STATEMENT AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL GALLERY:<br />
DIRECTOR AND SECRETARY/ MANAGER<br />
The Government has decided to recommend to Executive Council the<br />
appointment of Mr James Mollison as the first Director of the<br />
Australian National Gallery for a term of seven years. The<br />
Government has also decided to appoint a Secretary/ Manager to<br />
manage the administrative and financial affairs of the Gallery.<br />
These two statutory appointments will ensure a proper complement<br />
of artistic and administrtive skills within the Gallery's<br />
top management.<br />
Mr Mollison has carried out the duties of Director since 1971<br />
and was selected from a wide field of applicants who responded<br />
to an advertisement placed in Australia and overseas in September<br />
last year.<br />
Mr Mollison had already made a major contribution to the development<br />
of the National Collection. The quality of acquisitions purchased<br />
under Mr Mollison's guidance has already established an<br />
international reputation for the National Gallery. The new<br />
Director's knowledge of and commitment to the visual arts is<br />
well known and the Government is confident he will continue to<br />
bring imagination and flair to the important task before him.<br />
The Director will, as executive officer, be responsible for the<br />
overall conduct of Gallery affairs. In particular, the<br />
Director will concern himself with the direction of artistic<br />
policy, the development of the National Collection and all<br />
professional matters relating to the acquisition of works of art,<br />
conservation and research and the exhibition of the National<br />
Collection. Negotiations with the successful applicant for the position of<br />
Secretary/ Manager are almost finalised. The Secretary/ Manager will<br />
be Secretary of the Council and will be responsible for the<br />
important administrative and financial affairs of the Gallery in<br />
all their aspects. This will free the Director to undertake<br />
those tasks for which he was primarily appointed and make the best<br />
use of the professional skills of both. / 2 </p>
<p>The CGovernmnent will also be proposing new administrative<br />
procedures to the Gallery Council designed in association with<br />
the~ se appointments, to ensure the development of a distinguished<br />
National Collection on the most favourable terms in the<br />
national interest. 000000000 n= I. ' 77, 1 I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
