<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7904</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH VITALI ILYASHENKO, SOVIET TELEVEISION, 15 FEBRUARY 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/02/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007904.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH VITALI ILYASHENKO, SOVIET<br />
TELEVISION, 15 FEBRUARY 1990<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
ILYASHENKO: Mr Hawke, we are very optimistic in Moscow<br />
about our relations. Are your expectations fulfilled<br />
now? PM: Yes. We've had a marvellous visit from Prime<br />
Minister Ryzhkov. The good personal relations which I<br />
was able to establish with him, as with President<br />
Gorbachev two years ago in Moscow, have now been renewed<br />
here in Australia. They've been reflected in the signing<br />
of six agreements fisheries agreements, a commodities<br />
agreement and other agreements covering a range of areas.<br />
We have had meetings with him at the political level. He<br />
has had meetings with very many of our businessmen. I'm<br />
confident that as a result of the visit of Prime Minister<br />
Ryzhkov that there will be an expansion of our economic<br />
relationships and indeed a strengthening of the<br />
relationships between the Soviet and Australian people in<br />
very very many areas. May I also say that the Prime<br />
Minister extended to me an invitation to visit the Soviet<br />
Union again and I've indicated that I have very much<br />
pleasure in accepting that. So we're going to keep up<br />
this high level communication.<br />
ILYASHENKO: Thank you very much Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Thank you very much.<br />
ends 1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
