<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5641</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT COMMONWEALTH-STATE REVIEW OF ASSISTANCE TO TASMANIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/08/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005641.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1,, AUSTRA~ 1<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY AUGUST 23 1981<br />
JOINT COM, 4MONWEALTH-STATE REVIEW OF ASSISTANCE TO TASMANIA<br />
A review of the Callaghan Special Assistance Plan for Tasmania<br />
is to be undertaken by the Coimmonwealth and State governments.<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Fraser, and the Tasmanian Premier,<br />
Mr Lowe, said today the review would seek ways of improving<br />
S the scheme and its benefits for the State.<br />
The review follows a request by the Premier to the Prime'Minister,<br />
and subsequent discussions on detailed arrangements between the<br />
Premier and the Minister for Administrative Services, Mr Kevin Newman.<br />
Mr Lowe indicated that while both governments remained firmly<br />
committed to a joint assault on Tasmania's special problems,<br />
he believed present arrangements could be improved.<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Lowe said the ten point plan of Special Assistance<br />
to Tasmania was adopted by the Commonwealth from reconmendations<br />
by Sir Bede Callaghan in his 1977 report on Tasmania's industry<br />
and employmnent structure. They said that'since then, action had<br />
been taken under a variety of the ten points. Assistance by way<br />
of grants and loans amounting to $ 10.02 million has been<br />
approved, with the full anibunt payable over a period of years.<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Lowe said work on the review would begin in<br />
August and should b~ e completed by the end of 1981. They said the<br />
proposed terms of reference for the review would comprise:<br />
1. An assessment of the operation and impact of the present<br />
arrangements.<br />
2. A re-assessment of Tasmania' s disabilities and development<br />
opportunities. This would include the present and projected<br />
situation of other States, and the implications of accelerated<br />
resource development.<br />
3. Consideration of the broad strategies and particular.<br />
kinds of projects that would seem to be best suited<br />
to alleviat. e the disabilities and exploit the opportunities<br />
identified in the reassessment.<br />
4. Evaluation of the appropriate policy framework and associated<br />
arrangements for assistance in the future. This would<br />
incorporate the most efficient and cost effective forms<br />
of providing assistance. </p>
<p>2<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Lowe said the review would be carried out for<br />
the existing Commonwealth-State Official's Committee on<br />
Tasmania by senior State and Commonwealth officers. They<br />
would possibly seek technical assistance from the Centre<br />
for Regional Economic Analysis which was recently established<br />
by the University of Tasmania with assistance under the<br />
Callaghan programme. oOo---</p>
<p>COMMiONi1' WTEALTH SPECIAL ASSISTANCE TO TASIMANIA<br />
This paper summarises progress on implementing the Callaghan<br />
Point Plan<br />
Action has been taken under eight of the ten points.<br />
Assistance amounting to $ 10.02 million has been approved.<br />
Actual payments to 30 June 1980 totalled $ 2.06 million<br />
whilst payments to 30 June 1981 totalled $ 4.08 million.<br />
Details are sunarised below: Total ApprovedPayments To 1979/ 80To 1980/ 81<br />
$ 136,000 per annum for five<br />
years under the Native<br />
Forestry Program with<br />
additional assistance of<br />
$ 100,000 for four years<br />
( Point 1)<br />
$ 234,400 for the establishment<br />
of education facilities<br />
at the Tasmanian Fish Centre<br />
( deferred) ( Point 2)<br />
$ 200,000 for the development<br />
of the Legana Industrial<br />
Estate ( Point 4)<br />
$ 343,000 loan for the re-<br />
. equipment of the Launceston<br />
Precision Tool Annexe ( Pt. 5) 1,080,000 234,400 200,000 343,000<br />
2: 1 Assistance for the restoration<br />
and development of Port<br />
Arthur estimated at $ 6 million<br />
over 7 years ( Point 81: 6,000,000<br />
$ 1,802,000 for six Tasmanian<br />
projects under ' the Commonwealth<br />
Regional Develooment Program<br />
( Point 9) 1,802,000<br />
$ 200,000 for a program for<br />
the acceleration of mineral<br />
and. coal exoloration 400,000<br />
1,389,000<br />
200,000 1,200,000 1,549,000 200,000<br />
$ 40,000 per annum for four<br />
years commencing in 1980/ 81<br />
for the establishment of a<br />
centre for Regional Economic<br />
Analysis at the University<br />
of Tasmania 160,000<br />
10,019,400 2,061,000 4,075,000<br />
These proposals were not part of the 10 Point Plan; they were<br />
approved by the Government in the context of the 1980/ 81<br />
Budget following requests from the Ta.: manian Government. 2/<br />
272,000608,000 195,00 323,000<br />
I </p>
<p>Other decisions undur the Plan not involving payments to<br />
Tasmania are:<br />
-Relocation of the CS1RO Division of Fisheries and<br />
Oceanor-ra; hv (-initial estima~ ted cost of -' 25 million)<br />
-Airlinv between Christchurch and Hobart. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
