<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8523</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP RECEPTION TO COMMEMORATE THE 25TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE REFERENDUM, 27 MAY 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/05/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008523.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
8 0 1 ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
RECEPTION TO COMMEMORATE THE 25TH ANNIVERSARiY OF THE<br />
REFERENDUM, 27 KAY 1992<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
We are here to commemorate a highly significant event in<br />
Australia's history.<br />
In 1967 the Commonwealth Government asked the Australian<br />
people to give it the power to legislate for Aboriginals<br />
and Torres StraitIslanders,. and the Austral 1an peopl-e--<br />
reso-uEdfingly answered " Yes".<br />
Australians do not readily give assent to _ referendum<br />
proposals. Of forty two questions which have been put to referendum<br />
since Federation, only 8 have been passed.'<br />
In 1967, asked if Aborigines should at last be counted in<br />
the census, if they should be counted equally with all<br />
other Australians, and if the Australian Government<br />
should have responsibility for legislation relating to<br />
their affairs, more than 90 per cent of Australians<br />
answered " Yes".<br />
It was en unprecedented result and one wh4ich will<br />
probably never be bettered.<br />
It is a result well worth commemorating today.<br />
But, as with many commemorations, our celebrations are<br />
tinged with regret.<br />
The truth Is we have not succeeded in meeting the<br />
challenge which the triumphant referendum result required<br />
us to meet.<br />
The inequality, the injustice and the racism remain.<br />
The memory and the consequences of injustices done in the<br />
past continue. </p>
<p>2<br />
We cannot erase these facts.-nor should we seek to.<br />
We should remember them. All Australians should know'the<br />
facts of conquest, of dispossession, of the brutal<br />
treatment and equally inhuman neglect, and they should<br />
recognise the attitudes and motives which inspired them.<br />
As I said, we cannot erase the past but it is our long<br />
overdue duty to erase the attitudes which informed it.<br />
If we wish to lay claim to being truly 8 decent,<br />
civilised advanced nation, the arrogance, intolerance,<br />
ignorance and complacency which for so long characterised<br />
the attitudes and policies of White Australia has to go,<br />
Today I think we white Australians should consider how<br />
much it will do for our own self-esteem if we can<br />
eradicate the prejudice and injustice.<br />
We have made some progress in the last twenty years.<br />
Young Australians are better informed than anly previous<br />
generation about the extraordinary pre-European history<br />
and culture of their country.<br />
Through the education system, but equally through the<br />
achievements of Aboriginal artists, writers and<br />
musicians, we have learned to value the culture and<br />
history of Aboriginal Australia as never before.<br />
We now know much more about what happened on the pastoral<br />
frontier, on the missions and reserves, and in the towns<br />
and cities of Australia.<br />
We know about the crimes committed in the name of white<br />
supremacy, enlightenment and progress, including perhaps<br />
the most shameful of all the removal of Aboriginal<br />
children from their families.<br />
But I think we are also learning to recognise the<br />
contributions Aboriginal Australians have made to this<br />
country and to the contemporary Australian identity.<br />
The Aboriginal story, including the heroes of their<br />
resistance to the European invasion, has become very much<br />
a part of the Australian story as Europeans understand<br />
it. in the past the profound Aboriginal knowledge of this<br />
land was essential to the survival of European<br />
Australians on the frontier.<br />
Today through their art, music and writing, they deepen<br />
our understanding of the Australian environment and point<br />
the way toward a proper relationship with it.<br />
They deepen our understanding of what it is to be<br />
Australian. tj 14W VV_ I Q4.1 </p>
<p>3<br />
Aboriginals and Torres Strait Islanders have served this<br />
nation in peace and war,<br />
In sport and other fields they number among our legends.<br />
In the 1990s there can be no excuse for failing to<br />
recognise either our debts or our duties to Aboriginals<br />
and Torres Strait Islanders.<br />
In this decade all Australians should come to recognise<br />
that there is no true loyalty or affection for this<br />
country which does not include them.<br />
in all this, it becomes very clear that those people who<br />
fought for more than a decade to see the 1967 Referendum<br />
proposed arnd passed were doing all Australians a great<br />
service.<br />
Some of those people from the Federal Council for the<br />
Advancement of Aboriginals and Torres Strait Islanders<br />
are with us tonight and I think we should acknowledge<br />
their achievement.<br />
The passing of the Referendum was the prerequisite of<br />
change. It was also a necessary tool of conservation and<br />
protection. It was the mandate-to act in Aboriginal interests given<br />
the Commonwealth in 1967 which just last week made it<br />
possible to protect sacred sites near Alice Springs.<br />
It is appropriate tonight that we acknowledge the many<br />
positive achievements since 1967.<br />
In addition to that broader awareness of Aboriginal<br />
history and culture, there are concrete indications of<br />
change for the better.<br />
Last year we established the Council for Aboriginal<br />
Reconciliation. Its creation, by unanimous vote of the parliament, is<br />
itself evidence of the feeling in Australia that this<br />
must be the decade of change.<br />
I have great faith in the Council I think it offers us<br />
our best ever chance.<br />
The ground for its success has been better prepared than<br />
at any time in the past.<br />
Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islanders are~ increasingly<br />
participating in the mainstream of sociezy. </p>
<p>4<br />
There are more graduates. In 1979 just 8 per cant<br />
completed secondary school in 1991 that figure was<br />
thirty per cent.<br />
Perhaps the most outstanding achievement is the extent to<br />
which Aborigines and Torres Strait Islanders have been<br />
given power to decide programs and policy directions.<br />
Having an Aboriginal head of a statutory authority in<br />
1967 was unthinkable beside me tonight are Um such<br />
people. Having an organisation like ATSIC, all of whose leaders<br />
and decision makers must be by law Aborigines or Torres<br />
Strait Islanders, was unthinkable.<br />
Having Aborigines and Torres Strait Islanders in<br />
positions of real power was unthinkable.<br />
Today they have such positions it is unthinkable that<br />
they should not.<br />
There is another development which is I think the most<br />
heartening of all.<br />
It Is that more and more Australians are identifying<br />
themselves as Aboriginal.<br />
There is a growing pride in being an Aboriginal or Torres<br />
Strait Islander, in being descended from the first<br />
Australians I-holieve that is a good sign for all of<br />
US. it suggests the pride we will all need to have in<br />
ourselves if we are going to overcome those inequities<br />
and attitudes which shame us.<br />
I believe that this year can be a turning point, as 1967<br />
was. We can change attitudes through education, through all<br />
manner of interventions and support, through our own best<br />
efforts. But we will not change them satisfactorily and for all<br />
time until we begin to bridge the great gulf in living<br />
conditions. In pursuing our goals we should adopt as our guiding<br />
philosophy the achievement of real and measurable<br />
results; on establishing the building blocks of change,<br />
those concrete improvements in living conditions which in<br />
the end will be the surest guarantee against prejudice<br />
and discrimination.<br />
In 1992 you can be sure that the Australian Government<br />
does not regard these issues in the way they have s0<br />
often been regarded as marginal. </p>
<p>They are central. They are central to the notions of<br />
democratic justice and human progress which are at the<br />
heart of our traditions.<br />
They are central to our identity and self-esteem.<br />
They are central to our reputation in the world.<br />
They are central to the debate about what kind of society<br />
we want.<br />
It is the issues which are central now. It is the people<br />
the Aborigines and Torres Strait Islanders who must<br />
be central in the future. Central, I mean, to Australian<br />
society, the Australian nation.<br />
And I firmly believe that if we pursue our goals with the<br />
same determination which brought about the Referendum<br />
twenty five years ago we will do that.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
