<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11389</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          ADDRESS TO HAY CITIZENS          HAY, NEW SOUTH WALES</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/08/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................</p>
<p>  SUBJECTS: Australia's economy, rural Australia, health services in rural</p>
<p>   Australia, education, tourism, taxation reform, Centenary of Federation.</p>
<p>  Well thank you very much Kay. To my colleague, Senator Bill Heffernan, to</p>
<p>   his worship the Mayor, all the other distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>  This, may I say in a way for a travelling Prime Minister around Australia,</p>
<p>   is about as good as it gets in so far as you can meet under one roof in</p>
<p>   one location all of the different groups that make up a vibrant local community.</p>
<p>   And I do want to thank you, Kay, and I want to thank the Mayor and all the</p>
<p>   others that are organising this gathering to give me an opportunity just</p>
<p>   for a couple of minutes to say a few things to you.</p>
<p>  I am here today for two reasons. Firstly and most importantly I was invited</p>
<p>   by your local member, Kay Hull, who has only been in the national Parliament</p>
<p>   for a little under a year but in that time has demonstrated a great energy</p>
<p>   and a great commitment to the diverse problems of her electorate. And I</p>
<p>   want to compliment her on that and I want to commend her to you for the</p>
<p>   first class job that she is doing as your representative in Federal Parliament.</p>
<p>  But I am also here because I have made it a point in the time that I have</p>
<p>   been Prime Minister to systematically visit the less populated areas of</p>
<p>   Australia, to ensure on a methodical basis that I don't spend all of my</p>
<p>   time in Canberra or in Sydney or in Melbourne. And not only to visit the</p>
<p>   less populated State capitals and the larger country towns like Bendigo</p>
<p>   and Ballarat and Toowoomba and Kalgoorlie and Mt Isa and Ipswich but also</p>
<p>   on a regular basis to come to smaller communities.</p>
<p>  And there's a reason for that and it's bound up in a way in the paradox</p>
<p>   we have in Australia at the moment. Nationally, if you look at the Australian</p>
<p>   nation and you look at the Australian economy it's doing very well. We are</p>
<p>   probably stronger economically as a nation than we have been for more than</p>
<p>   30 years. Our inflation is low, our interest rates are low, we have a strong</p>
<p>   budget surplus, we are embarking upon very important reforms. And that's</p>
<p>   the big picture, that's the national picture. But I know that in different</p>
<p>   parts of Australia that is not the universal experience. I know that in</p>
<p>   many parts of the bush people are doing it very tough. I know how hard it</p>
<p>   is in the wool industry. I know how year after year many parts of rural</p>
<p>   Australia have been badly crippled by drought. And to have a drought imposed</p>
<p>   upon years when interest rates were very high and commodity prices were</p>
<p>   very low is to inflict a great deal of pain and difficulty on a lot of local</p>
<p>   communities.</p>
<p>  And I therefore am taking the opportunity on visits like today to tell people</p>
<p>   that I do understand that although it 's going well nationally it's not</p>
<p>   always going well locally and it is very tough going locally. I understand</p>
<p>   that and the members of my Government understand that. And we are trying</p>
<p>   in different ways to deal with particular concerns that people have. It's</p>
<p>   obviously of assistance for a rural community if interest rates are lower</p>
<p>   than what they used to be but it's also a disappointment to a rural community</p>
<p>   if it can't get adequate health services. And can I say to you, Mr Mayor,</p>
<p>   that I am very aware of the priority of health. And that's one of the reasons</p>
<p>   why John Anderson, the Deputy Prime Minister, and Michael Wooldridge, the</p>
<p>   Health Minister, recently undertook a tour of different rural areas to talk</p>
<p>   directly to people about the problems with the retention of medical practitioners.</p>
<p>   And how a number of measures that we have introduced in that area have begun</p>
<p>   slowly but it will gather pace, begun slowly to turn the tide on that.</p>
<p>  I am very aware of the need for areas like Hay to diversify. I am glad to</p>
<p>   hear that some of the changes that were made in relation to the rice industry</p>
<p>   have been of benefit to this town and to this town's surrounding district.</p>
<p>   And I am also conscious that the contribution that we are making to the</p>
<p>   establishment of the Australian Shearers' Hall of Fame will help to develop</p>
<p>   the tourist potential of this district.</p>
<p>  I experienced first hand when I went to the Claughton Hostel this morning</p>
<p>   the day-to-day challenges of rural families who don't have high incomes</p>
<p>   to merely get their children physically to schools that are meant to be</p>
<p>   provided "free" under our education system. And it was a reminder</p>
<p>   to me as somebody who was educated within the New South Wales public school</p>
<p>   system in a suburb of Sydney and then went to a high school in the suburbs</p>
<p>   of Sydney just how difficult some of the challenges are. And I think you</p>
<p>   know that we provided some emergency assistance last year but I want to</p>
<p>   say to you that keeping that hostel going is very important for the basic</p>
<p>   amenity of this area. And I am very impressed with the importance of that</p>
<p>   occurring.</p>
<p>  Visits like today are an opportunity for me to meet you, to listen to you,</p>
<p>   to understand better or even more the challenges of rural life. But, of</p>
<p>   course, also to understand the particular quality that the bush brings to</p>
<p>   the national fabric of our country. We are going to celebrate 100 years</p>
<p>   of federation in two years time. And when I think of the Australian story</p>
<p>   and the Australian achievement of the last 100 years and indeed the years</p>
<p>   that went before federation it is quite impossible to conceive of what our</p>
<p>   country would have been like. Indeed it would have been almost unrecognisable</p>
<p>   without the bush and without the contribution that country people have made.</p>
<p>  I understand that you have the only high school in New South Wales, perhaps</p>
<p>   in Australia, which is a war memorial public high school. And that is a</p>
<p>   consequence of the fact that in World War I this town on a per capita basis</p>
<p>   produced more volunteers or almost more volunteers than any other town in</p>
<p>   Australia. And it's typical going back all those years of the, sort of,</p>
<p>   national and community spirit that existed. And it's an opportunity for</p>
<p>   me to be in touch with that.</p>
<p>  We are trying to make life easier for people in all parts of Australia.</p>
<p>   We are particularly conscious of how the corruption of world markets and</p>
<p>   low commodity prices have made life difficult for many country people. We</p>
<p>   believe that the lower diesel and fuel prices of taxation reform will be</p>
<p>   of benefit to rural Australia. And when taxation reform comes in in July</p>
<p>   of next year we think the cost reductions involved in that will provide</p>
<p>   benefits. We are confident that the lower interest rates that you have seen</p>
<p>   over the last three years and which we naturally hope will continue but</p>
<p>   you can never give any guarantees about because they're influence by general</p>
<p>   economic circumstances we believe that they have provided a tremendous amount</p>
<p>   of help.</p>
<p>  I am also very proud of the fact that the Government in its last budget</p>
<p>   provided a very effective choice in relation to the education of children</p>
<p>   in both government and independent schools within our community.</p>
<p>  But the most important message that I do want to leave with you today is</p>
<p>   not a tabulation so much of individual initiatives but rather to tell you</p>
<p>   that I lead a Government that first and foremost appreciates immensely the</p>
<p>   contribution of country people to our society, that cannot conceive of what</p>
<p>   our country would be like without the bush. That our understanding for those</p>
<p>   of us who grew up in the cities, and that is most Australians, that they</p>
<p>   have always seen the bush as being a very special and precious part of the</p>
<p>   Australian story. And what we understand to be the Australia that we love.</p>
<p>   We do understand that things have been difficult. We also know that the</p>
<p>   spirit of people in towns like Hay is tremendously strong and I have been</p>
<p>   reminded of that in the couple of hours that I have been here today. To</p>
<p>   meet the children of your schools, to meet your local representatives, to</p>
<p>   meet the people employed in different pursuits and tasks in the town is</p>
<p>   a reminder to me of that tremendous spirit.</p>
<p>  And I hope that by being here today in a small way I can say to you on behalf</p>
<p>   of not only the Government but the rest of your fellow Australians that</p>
<p>   you are very much an important part of our community. We understand that</p>
<p>   although things are going well nationally, and that's a source of great</p>
<p>   pride to all Australians, we also appreciate that in different parts of</p>
<p>   the community things are not so easy and things are very difficult. And</p>
<p>   I want to thank all of you for the contribution that in your different ways</p>
<p>   you make to the strength of the Australian community.</p>
<p>  We are going to focus a great deal over the next year or two on the history</p>
<p>   of Australia over the last 100 years in particular. And that's been a century</p>
<p>   of tremendous achievement. And there is no society in the world that has</p>
<p>   a greater right to look back in pride on 100 years of massive achievement.</p>
<p>   This, of course, is one of the less than 10 countries that have been continuously</p>
<p>   democratic for the whole of the 20th century. We pioneered many</p>
<p>   things in this country. We gave rights to people in Australia before they</p>
<p>   were given in other parts of Australia. We had to seed into our community</p>
<p>   people from all around the world and they have become part of our society</p>
<p>   and we are building, I think, a sense of hope and optimism for the future</p>
<p>   as a nation that is tremendously important. But in the process of doing</p>
<p>   that we have to understand that some in our midst are not finding it as</p>
<p>   easy as others.</p>
<p>  But, ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much for coming. I can't express</p>
<p>   to you adequately how important I regard occasions such as this. This is</p>
<p>   a long way from Question Time in Parliament. It's a long way from a press</p>
<p>   conference with the Federal Parliamentary Press Gallery. It's a long way</p>
<p>   from what you might say the more detached and the more rarefied air of Federal</p>
<p>   Government. And that's what makes it authentic and makes it important to</p>
<p>   me and important to my colleagues, Bill and Kay, that we have the opportunity</p>
<p>   of relating in this fashion to a local community.</p>
<p>  I know that there are some difficult stories in Hay. I know how hard some</p>
<p>   of the industries have been. I also know from my discussions this morning</p>
<p>   that there is a tremendous amount of hope and optimism about the future.</p>
<p>   And you have been able to transmit that to me today and most particularly</p>
<p>   I am delighted to have met the girls and boys from your various local schools</p>
<p>   and had the opportunity to talk to the older ones to inquire about what</p>
<p>   their hopes are when they leave school and what their prospects are. Some</p>
<p>   more optimistic than others but all of them basically very enthusiastic.</p>
<p>   I want to thank the teachers. I always thank teachers. I was taught to do</p>
<p>   that early in my married life because I married one. And I thank the teachers</p>
<p>   most warmly for the contribution that they are making in both the government</p>
<p>   and the independent schools to the education of so many young Australians.</p>
<p>  But most importantly can I thank the people of Hay for having me as your</p>
<p>   guest. Thank you for extending traditional Australian bush hospitality to</p>
<p>   a visitor. It's a great experience for me and I enjoy immensely being amongst</p>
<p>   you. Thank you.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
