<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4702</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004702.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 7 MAY 1978<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The Government's decision to continue with the mining and export<br />
of uranium for peaceful purposes announced last year was<br />
taken only after months of exhaustive examination.<br />
Because of our vast uranium reserves, we made it clear that as<br />
a nation we had special responsibilities., We had responsibilities<br />
to protect the environment and the interests of the Aboriginal<br />
people in Northern Australia, and we also had an international<br />
responsibility. The Government has stressed that there was no way we would not<br />
maintain our firm stand in meeting in full each of these obligations.<br />
Australians, and the world community, know that.<br />
Some events in recent days have again focussed attention on<br />
Australia's position in these three critical areas. I want to<br />
re-iterate, and make the point stronger than ever, that our<br />
promises and our commitment on these questions remain absolute.<br />
Nuclear proliferation the spread of a capacity to manufacture<br />
or acquire nuclear weapons is something that concerns people<br />
throughout the world.<br />
Australia, as a nation, has the capacity to strengthen the international<br />
regime of controls and incentives preventing countries<br />
from acquiring nuclear weapons. We can and are doing this by<br />
setting an example through our own acceptance of the Non-Proliferation<br />
Treaty and the I. A. E. A. safeguards on nuclear activities.<br />
The stringent safeguards policy I announced last year demonstrates<br />
the Govei~ nment's concern and sets conditions for the supply of our<br />
own uranium to other countries as firm and stringent as those<br />
adopted by any nuclear supplier country.<br />
I have made the point on a number of occasions: those requirements<br />
will not be reduced or weakened. This will allow Australia's<br />
uranium help meet the world's energy needs, and strengthen the<br />
non-proliferation regime. / 2 </p>
<p>As a uranium exporter we will exert considerable influence in<br />
international nuclear forums concerned with non-proliferation.<br />
My Government is very aware of the obligations this places upon.<br />
us. We will not compromise our safeguards policy tar commercial<br />
advantage. Equally, those saEeguards will be applied without<br />
discrimination. We must be sure that the world's needs for nuclear energy are<br />
met without encouraging the destabilising force of nuclear<br />
weapons proliferation.<br />
The Government is actively negotiating safeguard agreements<br />
with other countries and working on international initiatives,<br />
such as the International Nuclear Fuel Cycle Evaluation, which<br />
is a major new world endeavour to find ways to meet national<br />
needs for energy, consistent with non-proliferation.<br />
The Government has also committed Australia to active participation<br />
in current negotiations on on a new international convention on<br />
physical security in the nuclear field. Australia has accepted<br />
the rules on nuclear exports developed by the Nuclear Suppliers<br />
Group which brings together the world's major nuclear supplier<br />
countries. Initiatives such as these are complementary. Above all, they<br />
are designed to support the major international objective of a<br />
safer and more stable world.<br />
Within Australia, our commitment to full environmental protection<br />
remains firm. Legislation recently introduced into the Federal<br />
Parliament sets out to make sure that the nuclear industry in<br />
Australia is regulated to give the utmost protection to people<br />
and the environment. We seek a uniform code of protection in<br />
all States and Territories following consultation with them.<br />
The Government has already announced that a supervising scientist<br />
will oversee all research programs connected with the protection<br />
of the Alligators River Region in the Northern Territory. This<br />
scientist, directly responsible to the Government, will also<br />
advise on the specific environmental requirements for the Ranger<br />
project, and any uranium project in the Region.<br />
On top of that, the Government will set up a Research Institute<br />
to help develop programs necessary for protection of the Region's<br />
environment. These programs will be co-ordinated by a committee<br />
that will not only represent the mining companies and various<br />
governments, but also the Northern Land Council representing the<br />
Aboriginal people of the Region.<br />
of course, the Aboriginal people are vitally involved in any<br />
decisions taken in relation to the mining of uranium. Almost<br />
all the known uranium prospects in the Northern Territory are on<br />
land which is or is likely soon to be Aboriginal land. ./ 3 </p>
<p>I have already assured the Aboriginal people that no mining<br />
interests will be granted in Stage 2 of the Region until<br />
Aboriginal land claims are dealt with.<br />
In the case of Ranger, the Government, having regard to the<br />
recommendations of the Ranger Uranium Environmental Inquiry,<br />
decided the project should go ahead.<br />
The Government has accepted the recommendations of that Inquiry<br />
that special programs be developed to minimise the social impact<br />
of uranium mining on the 800 or so Aboriginals who live in the<br />
Region. Many Aboriginals have expressed a wish to return to some of<br />
their traditional land to live. The Government supports this<br />
wish. Our commitments to the Aboriginal people, to the environment,<br />
and our international responsibilities to help make a safer<br />
world are being met.<br />
Our promise has been met with performance. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
