<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4380</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT OPENING OF SEBEL PLANT, BANKSTOWN - 29 APRIL 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/04/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004380.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
iJj AUSTRALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 29 APRIL 1977<br />
ADDRESS AT OPENING OF SEBEL PLANT, BANKSTOWN<br />
It is a great pleasure for me to be invited officially to<br />
open the plastics moulding division factory of Sebel Limited.<br />
I understand that pre-tax profits of Sebel Limited rose<br />
by six percent last year, and that there is to be a bonus<br />
share issue, I congratulate you on that performance.<br />
I should also say I am a bit envious it would be a happy<br />
day for politicians if we got a bonus everytime we got<br />
satisfactory results. We did in fact receive a. type of<br />
bonus yesterday when the latest C. P. I. figure was released<br />
only 2.3 percent for the March quarter.<br />
This figure was far below that which some learned commentators<br />
forecast. It shows that the annual inflation rate, after<br />
adjusting for Medibank is only 10.2 percent.<br />
Inflation is coming down, and that is most satisfying. But of<br />
course there is still much to be done. Inflation must be<br />
reduced further, and unemployment greatly reduced.<br />
Our objectives are to reduce inflation and unemployment and<br />
have a full economic recovery. If this is to happen, we need<br />
increased capital investment. New investment, like this new<br />
plant, is vital to the future prosperity of this country,<br />
and there is an increasing amount of capital investment. To<br />
ensure that this occurred, one of our first actions as a government<br />
was to institute a 40 percent investment allowance.<br />
This action triggered off Sebel's decision to go ahead with<br />
this plant. This new Sebel's factory is a good reminder that<br />
Australian industry can compete effectively on international<br />
markets. We can only compete when a number of factors are present:<br />
good industrial relations; effective management; sound<br />
product development; good design work; and sympathetic government<br />
policy. First on my list is' industrial relations, and I particularly<br />
noted your comment, Mr Sebel, that without employees' goodwill<br />
and cooperation you would not have been able to raise production<br />
as much as you have done.<br />
Good communications between employers and employees benefits everyone<br />
Management, unions and every employee have a responsibility in<br />
bringing it about. Good industrial relations depend on.<br />
consultation on issues such as the working environment and industrial </p>
<p>safety. The Government believes employees and employers should<br />
establish consultative machinery of their own choosing, which<br />
will improve communication and an understanding of the common<br />
interests of employers and employees.<br />
A company's actions are vitally important to its employees.<br />
I see no reason why employees should be th6 last to learn of<br />
decisions vitally affecting their future. And company management<br />
should give a great deal more attention to taking employees into<br />
their confidence on the company's performance, its investment<br />
opportunities, and the possibility of creating new jobs.<br />
Management should make every endeavour to encourage employees<br />
to look on the company they work for as their company, and<br />
be proud of that fact.<br />
Sebel's policy of sharing the benefits of increased efficiency with<br />
employees and the special share issue to fifty nine Sebel<br />
employees are good examples of this philosophy in practice.<br />
Another important factor in competing successfully in export<br />
markets is a commitment to product development and design.<br />
Sebels caln be justly proud of their record in this respect.<br />
One of the company's designs recently received the<br />
Australian Design Award. It is largely due to.. product<br />
development and design that Sebels has competed successfully<br />
in the South Africa, New Zealand, Singapore and elsewhere.<br />
The Government actively encourages such development by supporting<br />
the Design Council. And this year we are providing $ 15 million<br />
for industrial research and development grants.<br />
There are, as all television addicts know, Australian inventors<br />
of great talent and ingenuity. It is up to industry to harness<br />
their inventiveness and to develop new Australian products<br />
which are the equal, if not superior, to any similar products<br />
in th6. world.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, I congratulate you on this fine new factory<br />
and have pleasure in declaring it officially open.<br />
00000o000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
