<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1949</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS : P.M NO.88/1968  VIETNAM BOMBING HALT COMMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/11/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001949.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FCR PRESS: P. M. No. 88/ 1968<br />
VIETNAM BOMRING HALT<br />
Comment bythe Prime Minister, M. 2_. Lhn Gorton<br />
As you have heard, President Johnson has announced<br />
that all air, naval, and artillery activity on or within the territory<br />
of North Vietnam will be stopped at 8. 00 a. m. Friday morning,<br />
Washington time. ( That is 11 o'clock EST tonight).<br />
We have been consulted by the Government of the<br />
United States, and kept fully informed of developments leading up<br />
to this announcement. It has been the attitude of the Australian Government<br />
that a suspension of bombing in North Vietnam would be justified only<br />
if in response some corresponding reduction in North Vietnamese<br />
military activity was occurring or could be expected to occur.<br />
The Americans have sharad with us the information<br />
which has led them to conclude that they can be co. nfidentc there will<br />
be such a response. We believe there are good grounds for their<br />
judgment and sincerely hope it will be proved right by future events.<br />
A further cxpected result is that representatives of<br />
the Government of North Vietnam intend to enter into serious and<br />
direct talks with the Government of the United States, and the<br />
Government of the Republic of Vietnam, on the substance of a<br />
peaceful settlement. As these results occur we believe that they hold out<br />
real hopes of future progress towards a just peace. We will not be<br />
seeking to participate in these talks at this stage.<br />
CANBERRA I November 1968 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
