<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22012</transcript-id>
    <title>Securing Water for Townsville and Thuringowa  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/10/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Today I am pleased to announce Australian Government investment in a project that will significantly increase the certainty of water supply to the Queensland cities of Townsville and Thuringowa.</p>
<p>Through the $2 billion Australian Government Water Fund, the Australian Government will provide capped funding up to $40 million over five years towards a $48 million project to construct a pipeline, a transfer pump station and a new water treatment plant at Toonpan, south of the cities. The managers of the infrastructure development, NQ Water, will contribute $8 million towards the project.</p>
<p>The Australian Government Water Fund has now provided more than $333 million for 11 major water projects across Australia, with a combined value of more than $912 million.</p>
<p>The Toonpan infrastructure development will substantially augment the current and future water supply of Townsville and Thuringowa by providing up to 40 megalitres of treated water a day.</p>
<p> The new treatment plant at Toonpan will be connected to the existing pipeline that supplies water from the Burdekin Dam near Ayr.</p>
<p>The Ross River Dam and the Douglas Water Treatment Plant will continue to provide the bulk of Townsville and Thuringowa's water supply, with the new Toonpan development providing an important safety net by diversifying the water supply system.</p>
<p>The new development will provide security for the growing population and encourage industry growth in the region.</p>
<p>This is a significant investment by the Australian Government to secure the region's future water supply.</p>
<p>  I encourage water users in Townsville and Thuringowa to continue to make every effort to preserve and conserve water. This ongoing effort will be assisted by the full implementation of the range of water management principles and tools contained in the National Water Initiative, particularly in relation to best practice water pricing.</p>
<p> The project gives effect to the Government's commitment during the last election to improve the security of Townsville and Thuringowa community's water supply.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
