<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5077</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW ON WESTERN AUSTRALIAN DISPUTE AND NSW OIL DISPUTE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/06/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005077.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT 1 UE17<br />
INTERVIEW ON WESTERN AUSTRALIAN DISPUTE AND NSW OIL DISPUTE<br />
Question Mr. Fraser, the ads in the national press today are said by<br />
the Acting Premier of Western Australia to have been suggested<br />
by you. Is that a fact?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
What I told Mr. O'Neil when he spoke to me some-time ago and<br />
gave the facts as he understood it, I said " well, look that's not<br />
understood in the Eastern States. I don't know if you are making<br />
any effort to try and make sure that what you believe to be the<br />
situation is understood and if that's your story I think you<br />
should -trv and tell it" l. It didn't go any further than that.<br />
But I think we need to understand that in re. lation to Thursday's<br />
national stoppage and the Kurnell refinery dispute which we will both<br />
be discussing in a short while, that the AMSWU and one or two<br />
other major unions had already made up their own minds to have<br />
a national stoppage of their own unions in support of what I<br />
am advised was a $ 40 a week wage claim. Now, that is obviously<br />
totally destructive and totally irresponsible. W4e have<br />
an arbitration system and the Government has said on a number<br />
of occasions it's necessary and important that that arbitration<br />
system be accepted and supported. Individual trade unionists<br />
do not need to lose wages. They do not need to penalise their<br />
families and damage their own industries and destroy the<br />
prospects of increasing jobs by going on strike in an utterly<br />
destructive and irresponsible manner. The point I am making is<br />
that a large part of the prospective national stoppage on<br />
Thursday is going to take place straigh-t out in support wage claims,<br />
and we need to have that clearly in mind. 19 JUNE 1979 </p>
<p>2-<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think that says something about the mood of some of the<br />
trade union leaders in relation to it.<br />
Question ( Peter Harvey)<br />
On the immediate petrol issue though<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Could I just stay on Western Australia for a moment. It might<br />
be better if we deal with the issues separately because they<br />
are quite different.<br />
I said a couple of days ago that whatLever the nature of the<br />
dispute_ we need to understand that the damage done to Australia,<br />
to Aus'ralian industry, is just no way justified by the nature<br />
of the dispute itself. Tens of thousands of people in hardship<br />
and difficulty, and industry is damaged. WNhen there were major<br />
dispu-tes in Victoria a year or two ago a number of private<br />
firms, small firms, were just not able to re-employ the numbers<br />
they had employed earlier because they had been so damaged by<br />
-that major dispute.<br />
One of the matters that I understand the ACTU Executive is<br />
considering is the prospect of continuing bans on the State of<br />
Western Australia. I also understand that one or two Labor Party<br />
Conferences have supported continuing bans on the State of<br />
Western Australia sea, rail and air, and transport. Quite<br />
plainly, the idea of a continuing ban on any particular State would<br />
be something new in industrial anarchy within Australia and for<br />
any State Labor Party convention or council to support that is<br />
pr ttv much beyond my comprehension. I am reasonably hopeful<br />
after the discussions which I think you know that I have had<br />
with Ithe Secretary, Peter Nolan, that that additional step of<br />
a destructive and damaging kind will not be supported by the ACTU.<br />
That's what a good deal of the discussions over the weekend between<br />
Peter Nolan, Ian Viner, and Doug Anthony and myself was involved<br />
in trying to achieve a realisation that whatever happens on<br />
Thurxsday.-1 ought to be the end of it. I don't think<br />
I've 9-crt a.. yt1-ing more to say about the national strike, until<br />
we have a discussion about the matter...<br />
Quest-( Laurie Wilson)<br />
Just one question the ' legislation at the centre of this. Do<br />
you feel it should be repealed or do you support it?<br />
Prime.' Minister<br />
Sir Charles Court has said that the legislation will be reviewed.<br />
Now that's been a commitment given and I think that commitment<br />
ought to be accepted. But it will be reviewed. There are many<br />
different stories about what actually happened at Karratha and<br />
I find it difficult we didn't have our own direct observers<br />
there and there are different stories. But the Western Australian<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
Prime Minister ( continued).<br />
Government has indicated that legislation will be up for review<br />
and again, against that background, against the fact that on<br />
Thursday it is most unlikely that thos e court cases would be<br />
brought to finality, if the normal course of events is followed,<br />
they would be adjourned for quite some time. Now, that would be<br />
the normal course of events. Now, against those two contingencies<br />
it seems to me all the more unreal to seek to de-mobilise the<br />
whole nation for a while as a result.<br />
Question ( Laurie Power)<br />
Mr. Fraser, Mr. O'Neil said that he thought he had your support<br />
after talking with you on Saturday morning. Does the Commonwealth<br />
still adopt an impartial view in this national dispute?<br />
Prime :% linister<br />
I don't think I want to say anymore than I have at the present time.<br />
I do say, in the strongest and most categoric terms, that th~ e proposed<br />
strike on Thursday or the nature of a dispute which has given rise<br />
to this in no way condones a dispute, a stoppage, of the kind that<br />
is contemp~ lated for Thursday and whatever view one takes of the<br />
nature of the dispute, that can't be justified. And continuing<br />
bans on the State of Western Australia all the more seriously<br />
cannot be justified because that would establish a new precedent<br />
I thiz::_ in industrial anarchy in this country and if that were to<br />
be the decision, it's a matter that I think all Governments would<br />
have to take with the utmost seriousness and would have to consult<br />
with each other as to what should be done in relation to it.<br />
If I could turn now to the Kurnell Refinery. Here we have a long<br />
history of industrial disputation as you know. There are many<br />
people who believe that the only possibility to end that industrial<br />
disputation is to get under one award, and obviously if its to be<br />
one aw,, ard it has to be the Federal award because it is an industry<br />
that extends beyond the boundaries of one State.<br />
I think well I am glad now to see the more forthright statements<br />
by the Premier, but I really believe that this dispute has<br />
simmered and has broken out in this way because the State Branch<br />
of the A11U, which has its own internecine fight<br />
with the.-Federal Branch of the AWU, which it is not really affiliated<br />
with, has believed that up to know it has had the support of the<br />
State Government. That just isn't good enough. Quite plainly, if<br />
there is a separate jurisdiction for the Kurnell Refinery, there is<br />
gcknz zbe the prospect of leap-lfrogging and playing off one award<br />
agaizzz zhe other and that was-the circumstance before it came under<br />
a Federal Award. And what the State AWU are fighting for is the<br />
right to play that game again on a continuing basis down into the<br />
future. Now, the Commonwealth Government has said on many occasions<br />
that in these matters we've got an umpire. We don't always like<br />
the umpire's verdict but we ought to accept that verdict when we<br />
like it and when we don't like it. That applies very much in the<br />
Kurnell Refinery case. The judgement has been made; it's under<br />
the Federal Award and it is just as much up to Mr. Neville Wran, / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
Premier of to accept that umpire's verdict, as he should<br />
have done weeks and weeks aao make it perfectly plain that<br />
he offers no semfblance of moral or material support to the State<br />
Branch of the AWU. I believe that if he'd done that, the prospects<br />
aid hope for victory through industrial turmoil and industrial<br />
anarchy in N. S. W. would have faded, and the chances of this<br />
dispute would have been very much less. But now, as a result of<br />
walking down the centre of that particular fence instead of being<br />
firmly on the side of arbitration, firmly on the side of the umpire,<br />
we have a dispute which is potentially much much more damaging<br />
than the national one-day stoppage on Thursday, because we all<br />
know the seriousness of the world oil situation; we know that<br />
our supplies are stretched thin; it is difficult to keep<br />
refineries going; if oil can't be passed through those refineries<br />
it's going to be very difficult to get the additional oil to make<br />
up the backlog at a later point. And the people of N. S. W. are<br />
going to start feeling the very real difficulties and problems<br />
that are coming out the Kurnell dispute virtually forthwith.<br />
Question: ( Peter Harvey)<br />
Prime inister, it's not only the people of N. S. J.. it is starting<br />
to spread to the other States as well. Mr. t-ran has already taken<br />
emergency measures. The Federal Government has powers to look<br />
after the rest of Australia. Are you going to start exercising those?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
In many of these emergency areas it is State powers that you have<br />
to rest on the Co._ nonwealth's major emergency powers come under<br />
a Defence Act and they don't apply under current circumstances<br />
as you would understand, but you are right when you say that some<br />
of this will start to be felt by other States because plainly<br />
N. S. W. would be seeking additional supplies from other States as<br />
they would believe, for a more equal sharing of the burden. Now,<br />
I strongly believe that if Mr. WIran is to expect that to occur,<br />
he should come down fairly and squarely on the side of the Federal<br />
Arbitration Commission and support the one-award situation throughout<br />
the oil industry. Quite plainly, the Commonwealth will have to<br />
be doing what it can to see that hardship is minimised, to see that<br />
difficulties are faced in an equal and reasonable manner.<br />
Question So you will use the measures under the Defence...<br />
Prime Minister<br />
You are, I thinkrunning down a very odd street. The Defence Act<br />
is there for defence purposes.<br />
Question power to transport. </p>
<p>5<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Yes, but whether I think you would find<br />
difficulty with those powers in the current circumstances. The<br />
States have total emergency powers in civil circumstances.<br />
To talk of the Defence Act in these circumstances is not really<br />
relevant. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
