<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11176</transcript-id>
    <title>4 March 1999                                                   TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH                   MR GOH CHOK TONG                 PRIME MINISTER OF THE REPUBLIC OF SINGAPORE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, ladies and gentlemen, the Australia Government has been very</p>
<p> pleased to welcome the Prime Minister of Singapore to this country.</p>
<p> He and I got to know each other very well when I was Treasurer and</p>
<p> he was the Finance Minister for Singapore. And I have been particularly</p>
<p> pleased since becoming Prime Minister to renew that friendship at</p>
<p> various international forums and now for the first time on a visit</p>
<p> to our country.</p>
<p>We have a very close bilateral relationship. The best feature of it,</p>
<p> of course, is the large number of people-to-people contacts exemplified</p>
<p> by the fact that Australia is still preferred as an education destination</p>
<p> by more Singaporeans than any other country. It's a proud fact</p>
<p> that four members of the Government of Singapore were educated in</p>
<p> Australia, the President of Singapore was educated in Australia and</p>
<p> those people-to-people links are very close. We have very strong trade</p>
<p> and investment links and we share a largely common view of the challenges</p>
<p> facing the region and the need to respond to those challenges in a</p>
<p> coordinated fashion.</p>
<p>We have had a very useful discussion both today and last night at</p>
<p> the Lodge where I was accompanied by three of my senior Ministers,</p>
<p> Mr Costello, Mr Reith and Mr Moore. We have discussed in great detail</p>
<p> regional issues, not the least of course Indonesia and Malaysia, circumstances</p>
<p> surrounding East Timor but very particularly the domestic challenges</p>
<p> facing Indonesia which are very important, of course, to both of our</p>
<p> countries.</p>
<p>So can I say, Prime Minister, that I am delighted that you were able</p>
<p> to come, you are very welcome, your country is warmly respected in</p>
<p> Australia. And as I say again the people-to-people links between our</p>
<p> two societies are very close indeed and they, of course, underpin</p>
<p> the relationship in a quite emphatic manner.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>Thank you. I was last here in 1994 when Prime Minister Paul Keating</p>
<p> invited me. I am happy to be back to discuss foreign matters with</p>
<p> Prime Minister John Howard. It's always a pleasure to come over</p>
<p> here because we never get out of this close bilateral issues. I mean,</p>
<p> there are just no bilateral problems between Singapore and Australia.</p>
<p> So what we have done is to see how we can advance our common interests</p>
<p> internationally. Our interests converge in many areas and we discussed</p>
<p> some strategies and tactics on how we can further advance our mutual</p>
<p> interests. In APEC in the discussion over this new international financial</p>
<p> architecture and also in terms of observing, with concern, developments</p>
<p> in the region and see how we can assist the region to recover. We</p>
<p> have common interests and we would like to work on how we can advance</p>
<p> our common interests in these three major areas in the coming months.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Any questions?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Can I just ask you, in light of the concerns you have expressed in</p>
<p> Sydney the other night about civility in Indonesia. What sort of contribution</p>
<p> would Singapore [inaudible] consider making towards an international</p>
<p> effort to help East Timor through a transition?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>Well, I think East Timor as of now is part of Indonesia, is an issue</p>
<p> to be handled primarily by Indonesia then what comes after this is</p>
<p> a little premature. If East Timor is given independence by Indonesia</p>
<p> then at a point of time they can discuss what it can do. But at this</p>
<p> stage it seems to me to be rather premature to discuss a transition</p>
<p> in East Timor because it is still very much a matter, internal matter</p>
<p> for Indonesia to decide.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If both Prime Ministers or either could comment on the five power</p>
<p> defence arrangements. I understand there ....[inaudible] exercise</p>
<p> in April and there were some doubt as to whether that would go ahead</p>
<p> [inaudible]. Do we have any resolution on that yet?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>Yes, the officials have met I think about one or two days ago. They</p>
<p> have agreed that there should be an exercise in April. In other words,</p>
<p> is to resume what they set out to do some months ago, the exercise</p>
<p> which was postponed. They are working on the details of the exercise.</p>
<p> The Malaysians wanted to modify, I think, some of the exercise format.</p>
<p> The officials are working that out but there will be an exercise.</p>
<p> It's whether they can get maximum professional value without</p>
<p> modifying the form of the exercise which is being discussed at the</p>
<p> moment.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you generally satisfied that the arrangements are back on track</p>
<p> after a period of tension?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>At the moment it is back on track, yes.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Can I just add to that that this was one of the issues I raised with</p>
<p> Dr Mahathir when I saw him in Kuala Lumpur last year at the APEC meeting</p>
<p> and he undertook to revive activity on it and I am very pleased that</p>
<p> that has been carried out in accordance with what he said. And the</p>
<p> Prime Minister has indicated what is now likely to occur.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] focus on election process in Indonesia [inaudible] because</p>
<p> it is not guaranteed that the democratic election will bring stability....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, what the Australian Government is doing is to be as it has in</p>
<p> the past a good and constructive friend towards Indonesia. We are</p>
<p> naturally anxious to see as free and open an election process as possible.</p>
<p> We are contributing something in the order of $10 to $15 million towards</p>
<p> it which is a significant amount of money. We are making officials</p>
<p> at the Australian Electoral Commission available and we will do everything</p>
<p> we can to ensure that the process is as transparent as possible. I</p>
<p> think it is very important from Indonesia's point of view, particularly</p>
<p> her economic future, that the rest of the world judge the election</p>
<p> in Indonesia to have been conducted in an open and transparent manner.</p>
<p> Because if the judgement is that it is then that will give far more</p>
<p> credibility internationally to the government that emerges from that</p>
<p> process. It's very important that economic stability be returned</p>
<p> to Indonesia as effectively as possible. Part of that process is political</p>
<p> credibility. The two are completely intertwined and the one effects</p>
<p> the other. There's just one other from the Singaporean group.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] the best way to assist in the [inaudible] stability?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, there was no specific decision taken in the sense that there</p>
<p> was a package of measures between the two countries but the Prime</p>
<p> Minister and I have been talking about Indonesia's difficulties</p>
<p> now for about two years not only in our bilateral meetings but we</p>
<p> have had frequent telephone discussions about the situation in Indonesia.</p>
<p> I think both of us believe that the broad direction taken by the IMF</p>
<p> has been correct. Australia, of course, has contributed very generously</p>
<p> to the Indonesian Rescue Package and as we have to the rescue packages</p>
<p> in Thailand and Korea. You won't get a lasting economic recovery</p>
<p> in Indonesia without an improvement in the transparency of its banking</p>
<p> system. You obviously have to restore a credibility in relation to</p>
<p> things like that and the broad direction of the IMF programme we think</p>
<p> is correct. We, of course, played a role in mitigating some of the</p>
<p> more unreasonable demands that were being made on Indonesia in the</p>
<p> first instance and I think Singapore had a similar view to Australia.</p>
<p> So our dialogue on the Indonesian economy is very much a continuum</p>
<p> and we have been talking about it an exchanging ideas on it and putting</p>
<p> views to other people now for a period of almost two years.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Goh, the Australian Prime Minister, Mr Howard, [inaudible]...Australia</p>
<p> the financial centre of Asia through into the next century to make</p>
<p> Australia...which essentially means taking on Singapore. Does Singapore</p>
<p> feel threatened by Australia's economic push to take over the</p>
<p> headquarters of the region or feel you will lose much business?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>We are a firm believer in market competition and we welcome this competition</p>
<p> from Australia and we wish Australia success.</p>
<p> If I may explain, this is not a pie of a fixed size. In the</p>
<p> nature of economics if there's two centres they're going</p>
<p> to find two centres trading with one another. And, of course, if Australia</p>
<p> continues to grow at five per cent per year, which I hope you will</p>
<p> for the next few years, and the region recovers you're going</p>
<p> to have the pie getting bigger and bigger and you're going to</p>
<p> see the existence of two centres. We will lose some business to Australia</p>
<p> just like they will lose some to us. But overall I think both of us</p>
<p> will be better off with both of us succeeding as financial centres.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On Indonesia, [inaudible] what if the electoral judgement may meet</p>
<p> international approval but does not satisfy the Indonesian population's</p>
<p> aspirations. What is Australia's stand on that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, that is a very hypothetical question and I'm not going</p>
<p> to try...</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] after the elections in Indonesia.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, I'm not going to start canvassing how Australia might react</p>
<p> after the election, I'm telling you what we're going to</p>
<p> do to try and help the process and that is to be a very constructive</p>
<p> contributor to the electoral process. We'll naturally be urging</p>
<p> transparency. We'll be contributing resources. And that is the</p>
<p> appropriate thing for Australia to do at the moment.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister Goh, if I could just bring you back to the subject</p>
<p> of defence. The Australian Army has foreshadowed sending expeditionary</p>
<p> forces or having the ability to send expeditionary forces into the</p>
<p> region. Does that cause you some concern or do you welcome it, and</p>
<p> how do you think your other countries in the region would react to</p>
<p> that sort of a posture?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>Maybe you should explain what you mean by sending expeditionary forces...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, I think it's been rather, if I may say so, rather inelegantly</p>
<p> put. I mean, what they're really saying, as I understand it,</p>
<p> is they're altering the response capacity so that if the need</p>
<p> arises  I don't think we're sort of unilaterally going</p>
<p> to send a whole lot of expeditionary forces for no reason.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>... ability to do so, though, do you think that that represents</p>
<p> an unhealthy shift in Australian policy in this regard?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>I don't think so because Australia is a member of the five power</p>
<p> defence arrangements. And when the situation warrants it the members</p>
<p> who consult, so of course they consult and there are decisions on</p>
<p> follow-up actions. We do hope that Australia has got a capacity to</p>
<p> send forces beyond its shores or do so under certain definite circumstances</p>
<p> when Australia would have to send forces to help the region under</p>
<p> the agents of the five power defence arrangements. It doesn't</p>
<p> worry us. It's a capacity which any country must have, the ability</p>
<p> to project forces and prevent yourself from being swamped by others.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What extent does this new army doctrine put pressure on the defence</p>
<p> budget to increase the capability to take part in these high intensity</p>
<p> conflicts? Will you be increasing the...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, the Australian defence budget as you know has been quarantined,</p>
<p> at my insistence from the very day I became Prime Minister, from budget</p>
<p> cuts. And that will, of course, remain the situation. I don't</p>
<p> rule out at some stage in the future an increase in defence spending.</p>
<p> You never do and you have to adjust those things according to national</p>
<p> need. But it is important to make the point that defence has been</p>
<p> quarantined from expenditure cuts and we're obviously, as any</p>
<p> responsible government, concerned to ensure that the appropriate level</p>
<p> of resources is available and that means I don't rule out some</p>
<p> increase in the future.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]...shared commitment to the  as open a world economy</p>
<p> as possible, did you discuss any ways in which you might be able to</p>
<p> encourage Malaysia to reverse the position it's taken?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>Well, we did not discuss Malaysia in particular regarding the aspect</p>
<p> of opening up this economy. But we did discuss the importance of the</p>
<p> coming APEC meeting in September in New Zealand. And we'll be</p>
<p> working together with other like-minded countries to sustain this</p>
<p> momentum in getting the trading system open and if possible to have</p>
<p> another new round of negotiation under the WTO. So Malaysia's</p>
<p> cabinet control would, I'm sure, come into discussion if we do</p>
<p> have this discussion on how we can proceed with a new round for WTOs.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you mentioned earlier Australia's growth rate.</p>
<p> Does it surprise you, and how important is it for your region?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>Oh, it surprised me to be very frank. When I was here five years ago</p>
<p> I would not have expected Australia to grow by four or five per cent</p>
<p> per year. Two or three per cent was more in the order of my reckoning.</p>
<p> Certainly it's going to help the region because whatever growth</p>
<p> there is in Australia, small as the economy is compared to Japan,</p>
<p> it is still helpful. For example, we are now buying more services</p>
<p> from Australia - education, some financial services, information technology</p>
<p> and so on, although we are buying but you're helping the economy</p>
<p> otherwise we would not be buying from Australia. That contributes</p>
<p> to the growth in Australia but that also makes our economy more competitive.</p>
<p> So we welcome that. We just hope Australia can sustain this for a</p>
<p> few more years.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister Goh, what's your assessment of the stability problems</p>
<p> that Indonesia is having and some of the comments that President Habibie</p>
<p> has been making specifically about Singapore, do you see Indonesia's</p>
<p> problems affecting, as an immunity, having some impact on regional</p>
<p> organisations?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>Neighbours sometimes behave like husband and wife. When the husband</p>
<p> is under stress because the husband might have lost his job, it's</p>
<p> the wife who gets the beating. Or, if it's the other way around,</p>
<p> the wife neglects the husband if she's under stress. So we accept</p>
<p> [inaudible]. What we hope to do in Singapore is to try and avoid being</p>
<p> a party in their own domestic elections. We would therefore say the</p>
<p> minimum to cause any provocations whatsoever from Indonesia. But certainly</p>
<p> the dire economic situation in Indonesia erode into its political</p>
<p> problems are affecting us, yes. Indonesia is a very important member</p>
<p> of ASEAN, the largest member. And if Indonesia is preoccupied with</p>
<p> its own domestic problems the [inaudible] to Indonesia is not able</p>
<p> to lead us in. And, of course, if you have this [inaudible] stresses</p>
<p> from time to time that will weaken us, yes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, was Costello right to warn Australian republicans there'd</p>
<p> be no second chance after the referendum?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>Well, I think it was fair to say that there's a range of views</p>
<p> on this whole issue inside the Government because being a free, open,</p>
<p> progressive, forward-looking political party, we allow an open vote.</p>
<p> I think it is right that you don't have referendums every day</p>
<p> of the week in this country. But it is also the case that if this</p>
<p> referendum is defeated, there is nothing to stop the emergence of</p>
<p> pressure within the Australian community for another referendum on</p>
<p> the issue at some time in the future. And it's entirely a matter</p>
<p> for the Australian people but Mr Costello is a supporter of the model</p>
<p> being put up in November. A lot of people agree with him. A lot of</p>
<p> people don't. We'll wait and see and we'll let the</p>
<p> Australian people decide this thing. But ultimately these things are</p>
<p> in the hands of the Australian people, not in the hands of us. If</p>
<p> the Australian people vote yes in November, we'll become a republic</p>
<p> on the 1st of January the year 2001. If the Australian</p>
<p> people vote no in November then there's nothing to stop another</p>
<p> referendum emerging, although I wouldn't think you'd have</p>
<p> another referendum within 12 months. It might take somewhat longer</p>
<p> than that. But there's absolutely nothing to stop another referendum</p>
<p> being held in the future. Now, I don't say that in any way to</p>
<p> influence how people vote. I think that is a fair and flat and honest</p>
<p> statement of the position. Referendums don't happen every day</p>
<p> of the week but on an issue like this it could well be that there</p>
<p> will be several votes before there's a final resolution on it.</p>
<p> I don't know. I find it very hard to read. You should remember</p>
<p> that in the lead up to Federation we had a number of votes. And, in</p>
<p> fact, the history of this country on referenda is that we've</p>
<p> had quite a number of votes on the same question. I seem to remember</p>
<p> we've had several referendum votes on simultaneous elections.</p>
<p> I think we've had several referendum votes many years apart on</p>
<p> the transfer of prices on incomes powers to the Federal Government.</p>
<p> So if you look at the history of Australia, we are more referendum</p>
<p> than many other countries because unlike other countries we put into</p>
<p> our constitution this provision that you couldn't change the</p>
<p> basic document without...</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, when you say it could take several referendums before there's</p>
<p> a final resolution...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>No, I didn't say that. I said that that could be the case, I'm</p>
<p> not saying it will be.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So you're not suggesting then that eventually it's inevitable</p>
<p> that there will be a Constitutional change.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>No I'm not saying that. I mean you could...I'm allowing</p>
<p> the possibility that there could be several votes. I mean if this</p>
<p> referendum is defeated all I'm saying is that at some time in</p>
<p> the future a Government will come back with another proposal. And</p>
<p> that could be defeated. I don't know, that's all I'm</p>
<p> saying.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Tax credits. Do you think that tax credits still have little merit</p>
<p> given the support that the Business Council seems to be giving to</p>
<p> them, ...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD:</p>
<p>We have a view in relation to tax reform. It was put to the Australian</p>
<p> people at the last election and the Australian people voted for us</p>
<p> and we intend to implement that policy.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you and Singapore concerned that the international community including</p>
<p> Australia maybe too preoccupied with the election process of Indonesia</p>
<p> rather than what happens after that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER GOH CHOK TONG:</p>
<p>Well I think we are not, you know, overly occupied with the extra</p>
<p> process in Indonesia because that's a matter for the Indonesians.</p>
<p> But Prime Minister Howard has made an important point that the Indonesians</p>
<p> themselves must accept that the process is fair and clean otherwise</p>
<p> Indonesia will miss out on an opportunity for political stability,</p>
<p> because if there's no substance to the process then Indonesia</p>
<p> will reel into further problems. But beyond that I think we are concerned</p>
<p> with the general state of the region, politically as well as economically.</p>
<p> And of course the emphasis is on the economic side. Politics is beyond</p>
<p> us. It's the country's concern. On the economic side we</p>
<p> can discuss with international fora to see how we can help the region</p>
<p> to recover. So we are very seized with this economic crisis in the</p>
<p> region.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
