<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3425</transcript-id>
    <title>INDUSTRIES ASSISTANCE COMMISSION INQUIRY INTO THE PERFORMING ARTS IN AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003425.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
jj A USFHALIA J,<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 347<br />
22 October 1974<br />
INDUSTRIES ASSISTANCE COMMISSION INQUIRY INTO THE<br />
PERFORMING ARTS IN AUSTRALIA<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, announced today that<br />
he had referred the question of assistance for the Performing<br />
Arts in Australia to the Industries Assistance Commission for<br />
inquiry and report. He said that he had been informed that<br />
the Commercial Theatre in Australia is experiencing difficulties<br />
at present and he considered it desirable that the question<br />
of assistance for the Performing Arts as a whole should be<br />
subject to a full and public inquiry by the Commission.<br />
Mr Whitlam recalled that the Tariff Board ( the<br />
predecessor of the Commission) inquired into the production of<br />
Motion Picture Films and Television Programs in Australia and<br />
its report had been well received by those involved in the<br />
industry. He felt that this new inquiry should similarly be<br />
welcomed by those involved in the Performing Arts.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that for the purpose of the inquiry<br />
Performing Arts including live performances of ballet, dance,<br />
opera, music, drama, music hall, vaudeville, puppetry and<br />
the like. The Commission was however free to take evidence on,<br />
and if considered necessary, to make recommendations on any<br />
other matter it considered relevant to the inquiry.<br />
CANBERRA A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
