<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4268</transcript-id>
    <title>DEPARTMENT OF PRODUCTIVITY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/11/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004268.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIMEJSTHAINISE<br />
FOR PRESS 7 NOVEMBER 1976<br />
EMBARGO: 6.00 p. m.<br />
DEPARTMENT O. F. PRODUCTIVITY<br />
The Prime IMinister, Mr Malcolm Fraser, announced today that<br />
a new Department of Productivity is to be established.<br />
This initiative has been taken in recognition of the need<br />
to provide a technologically orientated agency with the<br />
responsibility of providing increased industrial productivity.<br />
It is the-Government' s aim to encourage innovation and<br />
the exploitation of inventions so that Australian industry<br />
might benefit in two ways firstly by reducing cost<br />
st-ructures on the domestic scene and secondly by assisting<br />
in our competitive position overseas. It is envisaged that the<br />
Ministry will play an active -role in the development of<br />
Australian production..<br />
The Prime Minister also announced that the Governor-General<br />
has agreed to the appointment of Mr Ian Macphee, as<br />
Minister for Productivity when the Department is established;<br />
he will also become the Minister Assisting the Prime Minister<br />
in Women's Affairs and will be Minister Assisting the<br />
Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations.<br />
The new Ministry will draw together elements of Commonwealth<br />
Government activities directed towards productivity improvement.<br />
It will also stimulate and coordinate the activities<br />
ofl oth,-er Commonwealth Departments and authorities towards<br />
this end.<br />
Mr Fraser commented that, having regard to the central importance<br />
of people in the field of productivity improvement, the<br />
new Department would take over all those elements of the<br />
Government's administration that relate to the working<br />
environment human, organisational, social and physical.<br />
These elements are currently located in the Department of<br />
of Entplovment and Industrial Relations a Department with<br />
which the new Department will have strong links.<br />
Servicing of the Productivity Promotion Council and the<br />
Productivity Groups will also be transferred. ./ 2 </p>
<p>Having regard particuilarly to the purposes for which the<br />
new Ministry is being established, the Minister for<br />
Productivity will, in conjunction with the Minister for<br />
Employment and Industrial Relations, havc responsibility<br />
for developing and advancing national training policies<br />
for implementation by the, Minister for Employment and<br />
Industrial Relations and other Ministers.<br />
In carrying Out these responsibilities the Minister for<br />
Productivity will in cooperation with other agencies develop<br />
an overview of training; identify gaps in services or<br />
pregramnes; and develop approaches to remedy deficiencies.<br />
The Minister will, in conjunction with the Minister for<br />
Employment and Industrial Relations, be the principal source<br />
of advice to the Government on national training policy for<br />
industry. The Ministry will include the National Training<br />
Council.<br />
The Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations will<br />
continue to be responsible for the administration of<br />
individual training schemes. within the frameworkc of approved<br />
national policies.<br />
The Patent, Trade Markcs and Designs Offices will also be<br />
located in the new Ministry. Earlier this year the Minister<br />
for Business and Consumer Affairs announced the establishment<br />
of a Patent Information Service to assist research,<br />
manufacturing and industrial concerns in drawing on the resources<br />
of the Patent Office. Mr Fraser said the Government believes<br />
that further developments in this field would be best handled<br />
within a Ministry of Productivity.<br />
There are, within the Department of Industry and Commerce, a<br />
number of functions which are directed towards the development<br />
of industiial potential. These include work on industrial<br />
efficiency and the development of innovation and invention.<br />
These functions will. be included in the new department as<br />
a basis for future development.<br />
The Australian Industry Research and Development Incentives Board<br />
is also to be tranferred to the new Ministry.<br />
Currently located within the Industry and Commerce portfolio are<br />
a number of factories which are primarily for defence production<br />
purposes. The Government believes that the encouragement of<br />
innovative techniques can flow from the location of these within<br />
a productivity oriented department, and has therefore decided<br />
to transfer responsibility for them to the new Ministry.<br />
Also to be included in the new Ministry are the Materials<br />
Handling Branch of the Bureau of Transport Economics and the<br />
associated ' Materials Handling Advisory Committee.<br />
While the Government does not intend that the scientific<br />
establishments such as the CSIRO and the Defence Science laboratori<br />
be included in the Produictivity Department, the need for close<br />
working ic lationships with thoc aind other relevant agencies<br />
has been recognised und will be put into effect.<br />
000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
