<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3814</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE, ADELAIDE, 6 JULY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/07/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003814.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
ADELAIDE<br />
6 JULY 1975<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I believe you wish me to say something about the<br />
elections here next Saturday for your House of Assembly and for<br />
half your Legislative Council.<br />
The sole issue in these elections is whether you.. in South Australia,<br />
are to have the best State Administration anywhere in Australia<br />
replaced by an Opposition which is linked with -the Liberal<br />
negativism and obstruction in Canberra. Because -that's what it<br />
is all about. This election was brought about because of Liberal<br />
obstruction in the Legislative Council of South Australia, you had<br />
Liberal Members and an LM. Member voting against the Labor mihners-of<br />
the Council and also, of course, there were some, to their credit,<br />
there were some Liberal Members of the Legislative Council who also<br />
voted with the Labor members of the Council: which is a sufficiently<br />
extraordinary thing to do. But you have got this situation, that in the<br />
Legislative Council here you have some Liberals so cussed, so<br />
obstructive, that they will vote against something which is clearly<br />
in the interests of the State. You have the extraordinary situation<br />
that most of the Liberals in the Council and an LM. Member of the<br />
council voted against a Bill which had gone through the Federal<br />
Parliament without opposition.<br />
Now you all know very well that if there is any ground for opposition<br />
to any legislation that my Government introduces in the House of<br />
Representatives or the Senate there will be criticism of it and<br />
obstruction of it and frustration of it. But in this Bill, the Bill<br />
to ratify the agreement between the Australian Government and the<br />
South Australian Government for the acquisition of the non-metropolitan<br />
railways in South Australia, there was not only no vote against the<br />
Bill in either the House of Represenatives or the Senate but there<br />
was not even any criticism of it in either the House of Representatives<br />
or the Senate. It was in fact supported by many of the Liberals.<br />
It was supported by Senator Steele Hall, and it's unquestionably of<br />
benefit to the State. Because not only does the State gain outright<br />
an additional $ 10 million this year, but in addition to that it is<br />
saved the inevitable increase in railway deficits which occur as<br />
long as Australia' s railways are run in the separate State compartment </p>
<p>2-<br />
So it was an absolute bonanza for the State. It meant that the<br />
State got rid of something which could never fail in later years<br />
to be an increasing burden to it.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Prime Minister it will be alleged tonight on a televis~ fon<br />
program that you yourself k-new as far back as December last year<br />
when Mr Crean lost the portfolio as Treasurer, about the overseas<br />
loans issue. Also<br />
PRIME MINISTER: If you don't mind. There is no basis in such<br />
allegations at all. But I'm not answering questions on those<br />
matters. I gave a very full Press Conference yesterday in Sydney<br />
on this: I think you were represented there. Certainly it was<br />
shown on T. V. in Adelaide last night. So I have nothing to say on<br />
this, the Matter will come out in the proper form now, next Wednesday<br />
afternoon, in the House of Representatives. If anything is to be<br />
produced of that nature then the Liberals will be perfectly free to<br />
produce it. I invite them to do so..<br />
QUESTION: On the State issue then, may I ask you a question?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Of course.<br />
QUESTION: It has been reported that Federal taxes are crippling<br />
the South Australian Wine Industry. Can anything be done to<br />
assist the Wine Industry in this State?<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER: Yes, something is being done on this matter.<br />
Mr Dunstan was in touch with Treasurers this year, my Treasurers,<br />
and -there has been a thorough examination made of the situation of<br />
the wine firms in South Australia. The position is not the same<br />
with all of them, of course, nor is the seriousness of the situation<br />
the same in all cases. But I gave Mr Dunstan a note on this last<br />
night you know we were together at a function last night, a<br />
-thousand people or so there at the Juventus Ball and so he knows<br />
and he will convey the details of what we are going to do. But the<br />
net position is thist the people who produce wine in South Australia<br />
will be in no worse position than other business people in Australia<br />
as regards their taxation liabilities. </p>
<p>-3<br />
QUESTION: What about unemployment in that industry?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well this matter will deal with that. I mean that<br />
there is no question that the wine industry in South Australia has<br />
a very rosy future. There can be no question of that. This is one<br />
of those industries where there -rural industries -where there is<br />
not only a certain increase in domestic demand but there is also<br />
very largely due to the new markets being sought by my Government,<br />
which has made more trade agreements with other countries than any<br />
previous Australia Government a s a result of that there is a very<br />
much increased appreciation of and demand for Australian wines.<br />
And as you would say here, that obviously means particularly<br />
South Australian wines. anyway<br />
QUESTION: Is it true that Mr Lynch has claimed/ that Mr Dunstan<br />
asked you not to come to South Australia during the current.......<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Mr Dunstan gave a very effective reply to that.<br />
Nobody believes Mr Lynch; there was no basis in that at all. I<br />
would certainly have been here more occasions if I hadn't had other<br />
preoccupations. QUESTION: Do you believe your presence here during this weekend<br />
in particular Sir,.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Were you there last night., did you see the<br />
reception I got last night?<br />
ANSWER: No.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well it's a pity you didn't because we-were,<br />
I--could say, raptur-usly received. Don Dunstan and I separately<br />
and together.<br />
QUESTION: You don't believe that Federal Issues will have any<br />
part to play in this State election? </p>
<p>-4<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Indeed they will. The. whole issub is, well the<br />
whole basis of this election, is the nature of the cooperation<br />
between the Federal Government and a State Government. Now<br />
certainly my Government has been very generous to South Australia.<br />
But every other State could have got the same good deal from my<br />
Government as South Australia has got under the Dunstan Government.<br />
The fact is that the Dunstan Government had the nous to move<br />
quickly, to take advantage of the laws which we have been able<br />
to get through the Federal Parliament. And as a result South<br />
Australia was the first of the States, the only Mainland State,<br />
to take advantage of the proposals that my Government made to<br />
relieve the State Governments of two inevitably growing burdens on<br />
their budgets. One is the railways; there is no State which can<br />
look forward to anything other than an increased -deficit on its<br />
railways every year for the foreseeablea future. You just can't<br />
run railways in State compartments, and'we offered to acquire the<br />
railways of each of the States. Now South. Australia wa's the first,<br />
so far the only, Mainland State to respond. And the other thing<br />
of course is the hospital expenses; hospital services and health<br />
services in general are going to be an increasing burden on every<br />
State budget. The percentage of money which has to be spent on<br />
health services, and in particular, hospital services, is going to<br />
increase more than any other public expenditure, Federal or State.<br />
And the proposal we made was that we would pay half the cost of<br />
running the State hospitals if the people who entered the Standard<br />
Wards were not charged fees; if there was no means test, there were<br />
no payments and South Australia was the first of the Mainland States<br />
to accept that.<br />
Now the upshot of all this is that South Australia is the only<br />
State whose books are in the blacks the other five are all in the red.<br />
South Australia is the only State which balanced its budget in the<br />
year just closed or has any hope of balancing its budget in the year<br />
just entered upon </p>
<p>QUESTION: Providing railway transfer goes thr ough.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: of course. Well I have no doubt that it will<br />
go through, because I can't believe tkat tle people of-. South<br />
Australia would not return the Government which cooperated with<br />
the Federal Parliament on this matter. My Governmen * t introduced<br />
the South Australian Railways Bill, but if was passed by the<br />
Parliament. Now in those circumstances I don't believe for one<br />
minute that the people of South Australia would put in a Government<br />
which wouldn't cooperate with Labor or Liberal federally, whereas<br />
Dunstan, of course, he would cooperate with the Federal Government<br />
if it was doing som~ thing for the advantage of South Australia.<br />
And there can be no question, this is to the advantage of South<br />
Australia. South Australia, the Dunstan Government, is the only<br />
Government in Australia which can promise to remove any form of<br />
taxation in this new financial year: the only one in Australia.<br />
QUESTION: It's been suggested that it was probably a political<br />
bribe for this election. What do you think of that?<br />
PRIME MI1NISTER: The election wasn't due for another year. If one<br />
was having bri-bes one would have it closer.<br />
The promise<br />
QUESTION: No/ I mean the promise of the $ 10 million, if the deal<br />
goes through.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. What do you mean? What $ 10 million?<br />
QUESTION: If the, the announcement last week that $ 10 million would<br />
be forthcoming.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No but it has been paid. The money has been paid<br />
over. We kept our part of the bargain. That isfthe Federal Parliament<br />
authorised the payment of a certain sum of money in the last financial<br />
year. So we paid it.<br />
QUESTION: The money from the 1975/ 76 financial<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No the amount, but it is all in the Agreement. </p>
<p>6<br />
After all, there can't be much wrong with an Agreement which all<br />
the elements in the Senate support. You have got this extraordinary<br />
situation here where there are Liberals and. LM people who will vote<br />
against something which is supported by their Federal colleagues.<br />
And I don't think that anybody can doubt that this is, a bonanza forSoutl<br />
Australia. Because South Australia, more than any of the Mainland<br />
States, depends on good communications. But this is not just something<br />
we have done suddenly. In January 1973 I wrote to Don Dunstan<br />
offering to acquire the non-metropolitan Railways. Why we said<br />
non-metropolitan was, in South Australia alone the metropolitan<br />
railways can generally be separated from the others and there is<br />
the new one along to Christies Beach the first electric<br />
railway you have had in South Australia which obviously can be run<br />
as an urban entity of its own.<br />
Now this offer was made in January 1973 and we have been working<br />
on it, our officials, and our Ministers, Geoff Virgo, Charlie Jones,<br />
ever since: and we concluded the arrangement. Any other State<br />
could come into it but, as a matter of fact Sir Henry Bolte and<br />
Sir Robert Askin, before we came in offered their railways to the<br />
Federal Government. When we came in Mr Hamer said no, I won't now.<br />
And Sir Robert Askin was discussing it with us and about two or three<br />
months ago, Mr Lewis, you know very macho said'The discussions are<br />
off!" But we went on here. But you know in South Australia, you<br />
more than anybody else depend on being able to deliver your consumer<br />
goods to the other States or Territories and this is not only done<br />
by the acquisition of the railways which will certainly transform<br />
their capacity to equip, you know with signals and rolling stock<br />
and so on. But we also have undertaken the Crystal Brook-railway,<br />
the Adelaide to Crystal Brook, which means that there will no longer<br />
be a break of gb ge between any of the State Capitals. When that<br />
railway is finished -We are, of course, now totalling doing it it<br />
means that any of your goods will be able to go without break of<br />
gua. ge to Melbourne as they already can, but also without break of<br />
gua. ge to Perth, which they can't now; to Sydney, which they can't<br />
now; to Brisbane which they can't now. And furthermore we are<br />
also from Tarcoola to Alice Springs, a couple of months ago I<br />
inaugurated it, we are building the largest railway project which<br />
has been undertaken in Australia for over half a century. And there </p>
<p>-7<br />
too it will be a standard gauge heavy duty railw; ay. And so you<br />
will be able to'go without break of gauge and whatever the weather<br />
from Adelaide to the Centre. Now this transforms the transport<br />
position and immensely improves the economic position of this<br />
State. You've got an excellent deal from my Government. And it<br />
was always possible for the Australian Government to do these things.<br />
Everybody knew they had to be done, but it waited for us to do it.<br />
QUESTION: Sir in the wake of the Bass by-election -there has been<br />
predictions there could be a marked swing against the Labor Government<br />
in the coming elections. Does this concern you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, I don't think it-' s on: for two reasons, a<br />
by-election is never as good for a Government as a General election;<br />
that was a by-election and people took the opportunity to express<br />
displeasure with the Government in the Parliament to which they were<br />
electing a replacement member. But -this is a general election,<br />
a general election, and I have no doubt whatever that the Dunstan<br />
Government will be returned. well in the House of Assembly and'<br />
it will similarly at last get a majority in the Legislative Council.<br />
This is the first Legislative Council election where everybody will<br />
have a vote, man and woman, 18 and over and I have no doubt that<br />
they will rejoice in exercising the fran-chise for this historic<br />
chamber. QUESTION: Mr Whitlam, -taken that the Federal issues will play a<br />
part in this State election, why won't inflation, unemployment and<br />
high interest rates effect the votes of these South Australi ans?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well in most things there can be nothing said<br />
against the Dunstan Government in any way at all. As a matter of<br />
fact the Dunstan Government has achieved, by cooperation with the<br />
Federal Government, much lower land prices than you will get i; n<br />
any Mainland capital. I think it is $ 26 million that my Government<br />
paid to the Dunstan Government in 1974/ 75 to acquire land to be<br />
developed and subdivided and sold at cost. You know you have the<br />
cheapest urban land in any Mainland capital and this has been<br />
brought about because the Dunstan Government accepted the offer </p>
<p>-8<br />
made by my Government. I'm not saying that this is any favoritism<br />
to South Australia because we would have had to do the same to any<br />
State Government which accepted the offer. Because when we<br />
introduce legislation of this character it is of universal application<br />
through Australia. But the Dunstan Government was the first one on<br />
the mainland to accept the proposals and you've benefited from it.<br />
Now this is a very clear example~ despite all the carping of th. e<br />
Liberals and so on, this didn't have to go through the State<br />
Parliament. It just had to be done by an agreement between the<br />
Premier and the Prime Minister and of course, we have done that.<br />
It went through the Federal Parliament, it couldn't be frustrated<br />
by the State Parliament and Legislative Council and accordingly<br />
the Premier and I were able to consummate the arrangements.<br />
Now if you are worried about inflation, the State Governmenthere has<br />
done more to restrain it than any State Government in Australia.<br />
Furthermore they do have some regulationoprices here, the only State<br />
Government that does, and they are, when this Bill goes throughin<br />
the unusual position of being able to remove a tax, the petrol tax.<br />
The only Government in Australia which will be able to remove a tax.<br />
QUESTION: If South Australians want to lodge a national vote in<br />
protest against inflation and unemployment, don't you -think they<br />
could do so at this election?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: They would be very foolish to take this opportunity<br />
of getting rid of a Government which has/ all a State Government can<br />
do in these matters. done<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister do you think the loans business has hurt<br />
Labor in this State compaign and will a special sitting of Parliament<br />
help? PRIME MINISTER: The special sitting will undoubtedly help because<br />
the Liberals will then have to produce anything they have and justif<br />
it. They can't just hide behind a press campaign when the alme<br />
sits'they'll have to put up and shut up. </p>
<p>9-<br />
QUESTION: Mr Fraser says he would like to see the documents before<br />
Parliament sits. Will you make these available to him?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I am going to propose to him later in the day that<br />
we should give him the documents that my colleagues and I propose<br />
to table and that he should give me the documents that he and those<br />
behind him propose to table.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, the last time Parliament was called together in<br />
such circumstances. I blieve, was in World War II during a national<br />
crisis. Do you regard this as a major crisis?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, no I have no more to say on this.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Whitlan, just on that issue if I can.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No not on that issue.<br />
QUESTION: There was a development yesterday after your news<br />
conference in Sydney regarding the recalling of the Senate.<br />
PRIM1E MINISTER: No, no I have got no comment to make.<br />
QUESTION: The whole thing about South Australia seems to be on<br />
the stability of Govern~ nent. Do you think a coalition Government<br />
formied from the Opposition Parties would bring stability of Goverm~ ent?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There is no chance. I gather that what the<br />
non-Labor elements in South Australia are putting up is an<br />
extraordinary amalgam of Liberal, Liberal Movement and National<br />
Country Party. This is, of course, a recipe not only for obstruction<br />
to the Federal Government but confusion within the State. I don't<br />
suppose that anybody would really want to wish on South Australia<br />
the sort of collaboration between Liberal and National Country<br />
Party that occurred a month ago in Western Australia. Sir Charleos<br />
Court,, Liberal Premier was deserted and blackmailed by the National<br />
Country Party Ministers, his Deputy Premier and the other Ministers.<br />
And they left the Ministry and Mr Bjelke-Petersen had to come over<br />
and plead with him and so on and then they got a couple of new members </p>
<p>S-10<br />
to patch things up. This sort of thing made a farce of State<br />
Government in Western Australia. Similarly in Queensland you have<br />
a situation because of a gross malapportionment of electorates there<br />
are more National Country Party members of the Legislative Assembly<br />
than Liberal Members although the Liberal Party gets many more votes than<br />
the National Country Party does at State elections there. And there<br />
you've had this prolonged wrangle over Medibank Hospital Scheme,<br />
Queensland's hospitals were free but they were the most crowded,<br />
the longest waiting list, the worst equipped in Australia. And you<br />
had the Deputy Premier, the Treasurer, the Leader of the Liberal<br />
Party, you had the Attorney-General, a member of the Liberal Party;<br />
you had the Minister for Health, a member of the Liberal Partya11<br />
trying for months to get the benefits for Queensland hospitals of<br />
the Medibank hospital proposals. And Mr Bjelke-Petersen conducted<br />
. a vendetta within the Government Parties,. and bet een them. I was discussed<br />
in their Party rooms, it was then put to the Cabinet, the Cabinet<br />
couldn't make up its mind. It went back to the Party Rooms, they<br />
couldn't make up their minds; it went to the Cabinet again and<br />
finally Bjelke-Petersen was done.<br />
Now is that the soft of thing you want in South Australia? In<br />
Queensland they're at last wanting to enter Medibank. Though instead<br />
of entering it on the ist July they won't be able to enter it for<br />
a few weeks vet: they dragged the chain. And this<br />
was because of a w-ang-Ie between Liberals and Country Party. Now is<br />
that the sort of thing you want to import into South Australia South<br />
Australian politics has been disrupted sufficiently by the wrangle<br />
within the Liberal Party, the creation of the Liberal Movement<br />
arising from the quite monstrous attempt by the Liberal Party to<br />
preserve the electoral boundaries for the House of Assembly and<br />
when they lost their numbers in the House of Assembly then wanting<br />
to preserve a Legislative Council on monstous electoral boundaries<br />
and with a restricted franchise to exercise a veto over initiatives<br />
from the Government in the House of Assembly.<br />
Now that is the only good Government that you've been able to achieve<br />
in South Australia is under Labor which gives you a united Government<br />
in its own right, in the House of Assembly, and as a result of these<br />
first universal elections for the Legislative Council will be able </p>
<p>11<br />
to do so there as well. And the contrast with Western Australia<br />
a month ago and with Queensland up to a week ago shows that you would<br />
be foolish indeed to replace a constructive united Government, one<br />
that knows when and how to cooperate with the Federal Government, with<br />
a coalition ratbag of conservative elements who where they have been<br />
represented in State Parliaments have not been able to work together<br />
between themselves and not been able to work with the Federal<br />
Government. QUESTION: On that back tax, do you propose to drop that?<br />
PRIME MINISTE I have given the note to Mr Dunstan and he will<br />
be communicating this. You were not here earlier on.<br />
QUESTION: The Federal opposition has made itcl ear that itwi* ll<br />
drop that tax.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I have given it to Mr Dunstan and he will<br />
know how to conixunicate with this. He has been in touch with us for<br />
-quite some months on this; we have made the survey and I have told him<br />
what we are proposing to do and my Treasurer gave me this note for<br />
Mr Dunstan which I gave him last night. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
