<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6507</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW, RADIO 8DN TALKBACK, DARWIN, COL KROHN, 16 OCTOBER 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/10/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006507.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E. O. E. PROOF ONLY 41.4<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW, RADIO 8DN TALKBACK, DARWIN, COL KROHN-16/ 10/ 81<br />
CK: Welcome, the PM isn't with us yet He's on the campign trail,<br />
and I gather from what we've been told that it will be a very difficult<br />
job to win the seats in the Territory across to the ALP. The popularity<br />
of the Chief Minister, of course, running against Mr Reeves down there<br />
in Canberra. You may like to ask the PM questions on that subject, in<br />
fact Mr Hawke has just walked into the studio so we'll be with him very<br />
shortly. A few other questions, of course. Mr Geoff Stone, the previous<br />
Secretary to the Treasury, in an address yesterday said that a likely<br />
rnage of new taxes may well be introduced and possibly a mini-budget immediately<br />
after the election providing the Labor Party wins the eleciton. Defence<br />
another question, that has been raised in the last week, specifically that<br />
Australia is not geared to meet even a low level threat, and of course<br />
the ANZUS situation with the NZ Government, Mr Lange, and education another<br />
cne. I understand the PM has recently indicated that he is concerned<br />
with the standard of-education across the nation. These subjects something<br />
you can think about, and we will be back with the PM shortly.<br />
CKs WefCome" a6k. A very-good afternoon to the Prime Minister of Australia,<br />
Mr Bob Hawke.<br />
BH: Good afternoon.<br />
CKs Well I guess @ be could say that it'd4ideal-for politicians, particularly<br />
Prime Ministers to be one-eyed, but you went a little far, didn't you?<br />
BHs ( chuckle, chuckle) Yeah. I was going along so nicely. I had 28<br />
elegant runs under my belt and then I was told there were five overs left,<br />
it was a limited over match, so I thougttevery ball had to be dispatched<br />
for a boundary, so I went for a hook shot and didn't play it well at all.<br />
CKs Well that's very apt because last night on local TV they opened the<br />
series Bodyline. It's almost as if it was arranged.<br />
CK Just before we take our first call, the question of the liklihood<br />
of Labor winning or maintaining the House of Representatives seat. The<br />
Chief.. Minister, of course, Mr Paul Everingham, very popular, the evidence<br />
of that with the-devastating win of the CLP in the last NT election.<br />
How hopeful are you that you can retain this particular seat?<br />
I </p>
<p>BHi I'm confident. John Reeves will retain his seat, Col. There are<br />
a number of reasons for that. Firstly, John Reeves has been an outstandir,:,<br />
member for the Northern Territory I can say this with absolute integrity<br />
to all your listeners. He has been ceaseless in representations to us<br />
about the needs of the Territory. It's obviously much easier for the<br />
interests of the Northern Territory to be represented by a Government<br />
member: Hie has access to us, he's on our hammer the whole time, A member<br />
of the Opposition can't do that., And Mr Everingham has made It quite<br />
clear, he's made public statements, that not only will my Government be<br />
returned, but it will be returned with an increased majority. I believe<br />
that the people of the Northern Territory are intelligent, I believe they<br />
will see that they're most likely to have their interest better represented<br />
by a member of the Government. And certainly, there are many things that<br />
we've done in the Territory that have been done because of the persistence<br />
of John Reeves. So in saying all those things I'm not involved in any<br />
persval attacks on Mr Everingham. He has his views about the interests<br />
of the Territory and as Chief Minister he's tried to do certain things.<br />
But he wouldn't and it's hypothetical because I don't think he'll get<br />
there but as a member of the Opposition of a decreased Opposition<br />
he simply would not be able to do the job for the Northern Territory that<br />
John Reeves could as a member of the Government.<br />
CK: OK. We'll take as many callers as we can this afternoon. Please<br />
keep your calls brief. And Mr Hawke's on the line now. First caller Eddie.<br />
You're through to the* Prime Minister, Eddie.<br />
Caller: My quesiton is simple but it has vast implications: Will the<br />
American constitution trigger the nuclear holocaust?<br />
BH: No, the American constitution wouldn't tri gger it, Eddie. Whether<br />
the ( Eddie interjects)<br />
Caller: I can give you some reasons: Firstly, he is an autocrat, he<br />
has the power of veto over his Parliament, he's efficient to his ministers<br />
who are not responsible to Parliament, he can veto any Bill or simply<br />
let it lay on the table for the three months until it lapses, and he's<br />
also the lead of the army, navy and airforce.<br />
CKs Can you let the PM answer now Eddie?<br />
BHt Wells Eddie you seem to think that the world has gotta fear a nuclear<br />
holocaust frain the democracy of the United States, as though this takes<br />
.17: r~ </p>
<p>one to tango. It takces two to tango. And I say to you quite unequivocally<br />
that as far as I'm concerned, I don't attribute to the US under whatever<br />
President, the great threat to the peace of the world. We have the other<br />
super power which is a communist dictatorship, and I'm not here to engage<br />
in some attack upon the Soviet Union, you know that's not my caper to<br />
attack other coutries, but the fact Is that you have no democracy in the<br />
Soviet Union. You have the military industrial complex there, very much<br />
in charge of things, the evidence of the expansion of the Soviet Union<br />
into Afghanistan.... ( Eddie interjects)<br />
Caller: I'm not ringing for the Soviet Union, Bob, I'm ringing for mankind.<br />
EM: You are. You say you're talking for mankind, but you do that by<br />
launching an attack on the US and Its President. All P'm saying is that<br />
what we've got to do as concerned human beings is not to go around attacking<br />
President Reagan or attacking the Soviet Union. We've gotta be positive<br />
and constructive and say that the two superpowers have gotta sit down<br />
together. It's no good standing on dignity. They've gotta sit down together,<br />
Eddie, and talk through. They've gotta realise that the nuclear stockpiles<br />
that they've got now are more than enought to wipe out the world hundreds<br />
of times over and what they've gotta do is to sit down and realise that<br />
the future welfare of every man woman and child in the world depends on<br />
them sitting down constructively and talking together. We're not going<br />
to help that process by attacking one rather than the other.<br />
Caller: I'm not attacking one rather than the other, I'm attacking one<br />
for his actions. Now he's just gaven the Jews a terrific lot of money<br />
and in response they're gunna move out a Lebanon, possibly In six months.<br />
Now he has the game sewn up then-as a peacemaker. ofr Israel that<br />
they vacate the West Bank and cut out the master race business.<br />
CK: Eddie, I'm sorry. We've given you enough time. We do have other.<br />
callers ( cut off). And please folks, one question. There are many, many<br />
folk wating to talk to the PM. Our next caller John, you're through to<br />
the Prime Minister, go ahead John.<br />
Callers Hello Robert.<br />
BeM G'day John.<br />
Caller: Curley, mate.<br />
EM: Ohl G'day Curley.<br />
r7 2* 2 I. l. </p>
<p>Callers Listen, mate, I dunno wheither you get the copies of the local<br />
papers up here down there.<br />
BH: No. I don't.<br />
Callers You probably don't. Well every time something goes wrong up<br />
here you people down there get the blame for it.<br />
BHs Yeah?<br />
Callers Now this is the question. Do you or do you not get a budget<br />
submitted from the Northern Territory? Or let's put itbifl common language.<br />
Do you not or do you get bitten for a bite to cover funding of the Northern<br />
Territory for 12 months?<br />
BHz Yes, we get bites for a whole range of things.<br />
Callers Do they present a budget to you and say ' this Is the money we<br />
want'? BH: Well, it's not put in a total budget form Curley, but what we do<br />
get is a range of demands from the Northern Territory for the elements<br />
which go to make up their total budgetary program, and the fact is Curley<br />
that we provide 86% of their budget. That's the factual situation, and<br />
may I just throw In one statistic which would give you some idea Curley<br />
of how well the Territory does. In this budget, 84/ 85, the tax-sharing<br />
grant to the Territory Increased by 12% whereas the average for the states<br />
was So, they've done, under our government and the representations<br />
of John Reeves, they've done extremely well Indeed.<br />
Callers Well I agree with that. You give ' em a good cook, but you didn't<br />
answer my. question.<br />
BH: Well I did answer your question, Curley. I'm saying that they don't<br />
present a formal budget and say 1bre is our budget'. W1hat they do is<br />
present a series of demands saying ' well we need this amount of money<br />
for this purpose, we need this amount of money for another purpose' and<br />
then they get an indication from us as to what the tex-sharing money<br />
is that they're going to get. Then they have to make some other decisions<br />
In regard to their own fiscal program as to what they're going to do,<br />
and It's very interesting that in this most recent period as a result<br />
of their decision in regard to the Casino where they're foregoing revenue<br />
frmo the Casino by their expropriation of' private property, they've Imposed </p>
<p>very significant increases on the people of the Territory In regard to<br />
liquor and cigarettes. If they hadn't engaged in this unparalleled expropr Ion<br />
of' private property of Federal Hotels, the people of the Northern Territory<br />
wouldn't have had to pay those additional incosta which have been put<br />
upon them.<br />
CK: We must move on ( Ad break). Helen, you're through to Mr Hawke, go<br />
ahead. Caller: Hello. Urn, I'd like to a. ak you about the train. will there<br />
ever be a train service going to Darwin?<br />
131: Well, if you say ' ever' it's a very long time, Helen. But I would<br />
think not in the foreseeable future. When we came to government, Helen,<br />
we found that we had a 3.6 billion dollar greater deficit we'd inhereited<br />
than Mr Fraser and Mr Peacock and Mr Howard had told us about, so we had<br />
to review a program that we'd been looking at, so we had an independent<br />
inquiry, conducted by Mr Hill, and it was put to us quite clearly after<br />
a long Inquiry in which everyone was able to put their point of' view,<br />
that that would be an uneconomic use of resources. So what we did then<br />
was to say, and here Mr Beeves the local member was very helpful to<br />
us, we looked at what we could do to improve the existing means of communication.<br />
lie did a number of things, we made about 21 million dollars available<br />
1Vo improve the rail facilities to Alice Springs. That will involve the<br />
purchase of high speed rolling stock and improving the piggy-back loading<br />
f~ acilities there, and then from Alice Springs up to Darwin we've made<br />
in addition to the very significant nmount of money that was already allocated,<br />
we're putting about another $ 27 million through to 1987/ 88 to imprive<br />
the Stuart h~ ghway to make it an all-weather, all-purpose road and starting<br />
off' with $ 2.7 million this year so that in that way, according to the<br />
best advice we've got, we will use taxpayer funds more economically to<br />
proviude you with a service that you need. Now I know some people would<br />
like to see a train, jsut. because it's a train. But what a government<br />
has to do is to use its taxpayuers money in the most efficient way, and<br />
we think that In this way we will more economically provide you with the<br />
transport services that you need.<br />
CK: Thanks very much Helen. Just before we take our next caller, Mr<br />
Hawke$ on that question of the railway. I understand the Canadian Pacific<br />
Investigation, If you like, found It economically viable for a north-south<br />
rail link, and strategic studies by the ANU found it to be almost essential<br />
for defence and Support. Now we're investing in a very expensive defence<br />
T" f~ J4~ f. 41Vp~ </p>
<p>base in Tindal. Would it be the only major defence base in the world<br />
without a rail head or at least a railway?<br />
BH: Oh no, it wouldn't. But let's just get this sorted out. You talk<br />
about the Canadian Pacif i inquiry. A very different inquiry to the Hill<br />
inquiry. The Hill Inquiry was open. Everyone who wanted to make submissions<br />
to it could in an open fashion. A very different sort of thing has come<br />
up with this * Canadian... and I'm not attacking the integrity of Canadian<br />
Pacifict but it was a much less open and full inquiry than was the Hill<br />
Inquiry and It says ' break-even' at the very best. It doesn't suggest<br />
it is a sensible use of economic resources. Now I'm not prepared to accept<br />
that, but even if one were to, it's a less economic use of resources than<br />
the alternative that we're doing. Now as far as defence is concerned,<br />
the position is quite clear. The Australian Defence Department and Defence<br />
chiefs were asked about this and they made it quite clear that in terms<br />
of the limited resources available to the Defence Forces of this country<br />
where they had the responsibility of saying ' these are our priorities<br />
for allocating scarce resources for the defence of Australia this is<br />
not a top priority'. Now that's the defence chiefs, your Defence Department.<br />
And that cannot ba gain-sayed and I am not going to as Prime Minister<br />
bye undertaking some flash program because someone says ' oh yeah, that'd<br />
be a good idea from a defence point of view' when your defence advisors<br />
and your Defence Department say that would not be the best way of using<br />
resources. CK: How valid is the situation with defence on the.. across the nation<br />
In view of the reports during the week that we can't even meet a low-level<br />
threat? UsH Well, that; s not an accurate summary of it. Let me say firstly this:<br />
since 1 949, for 35 years, 30 of ' them have been in terms of' Federal Governemnt,<br />
under the conservative parties. And it there is anything wrong with the<br />
state of our defence preparedness which, of course, as you know involves<br />
years and years of lead time, then you know where to point the finger<br />
It's not at us, it's at the conservative party of this country. Thirty<br />
years out of the last 35 they've had the responsibility for preparing<br />
the defence of this country and If there is any inadequacy, that's where<br />
the finger should be pointed. But, having said that, I believe that we<br />
are in a position where as we go ahead now with the increase in defence<br />
expenditure udner this government and I remind you that in our two years<br />
we've had an average of 3.7% increase in real terms in our two budgets<br />
which is higher -than the increases in defence expenditure under the Liberal<br />
~--vr. iwaw ~_ WZ1y </p>
<p>and National parties. 3.7% real terms per annum under us.<br />
CKs Do you believe it's enough?<br />
BHs Well all I can say is that it's more than the Conservatives in the<br />
last seven years. Ours is a higher rate of real increase in defence expenditure<br />
than under them.<br />
CK; Does that necessarily mean that it's enough?<br />
BHt No, but it does mean as between alternatives that we're doing better<br />
than they did.. And that's what you've got to choose between. We're doing<br />
woore than they did. Now or course, I would like to be able to spend more<br />
but you've gotto say that you've got claims upon you in the f'ields of<br />
education, in the area of social security, and what you spend in one area<br />
you can't spend in others. Now all I can say is that 1. thinkc we've got<br />
reaosn to be proud of our defence forces. Yesterday I spent with the<br />
Navy out on HMAS Adelaide. I saw them go through their paces, and they<br />
are a highly dedicated, competent and efficient service. We've just made<br />
the decision to provide... to go into the purchase of the Sea Hawk helicopters<br />
which, when provided on our destroyers, will mean that they will have<br />
a very significant anti-submarine warfare capacity which I think Is very<br />
important. We are now, tomorrow going to start the building of the Tindal<br />
air base which will locate out of Katherine a very significant deterrent<br />
capacity in the north-weat of Australia, and we are doing our very best<br />
to ensure that both in terms of equipewnt and in other respects our defence<br />
forces will be equipped to meet what conceivable challenges there may<br />
be to Australia. Of course, when you're talking about defence you're<br />
not only talkcing about what you've gotta do In spending money on your<br />
defence forces, it's also very Important that you keep your alliances<br />
n good shape and I'm very proud to be able to say that now, after some<br />
2 years in government, the relationship of Austrlaia with the Unites States<br />
is in better shape than it's ever been before. And we also have very<br />
good relations with the countries in our region. So, all that this government<br />
is doing Is directed towards the security of this country.<br />
CKs We'll take a break ( ADS). Vincent$ you're through to the PM, go<br />
ahead. Calleri Good afternoon Prime Minister, I'd like to welcome you-to the<br />
Northern Territory. My name's Vincent. I. 9m ringing up about our concerns </p>
<p>and our [ and Rights legislation here in the Northern Territory. Landi<br />
Rlights working. We have $ 500 million uranium mine developments on our<br />
land such as Ranger and Jabiru, we've got $ 500 million more developments<br />
on the IMereenie and Amadeus oil/ gas fields in the Central Australia, and<br />
we've also cleared a line for the phantom railway line to come up to Darwin<br />
on Sacred Sites and all this type of thing, and also we have gold developments<br />
in our country. Also we bring into the Territory's economy over $ 200<br />
million arnd getting a little bit higher, in the tourist Industry with<br />
Ayers Rock, on Aboriginal land, Kakadu on Aboriginal land and Stanley<br />
Chasm on Aboriginal land. Also the fishing Industry uses out land for<br />
development. I'd just like to say that we are worried about our veto,<br />
the Federal Government was brought to power on social reform and one question<br />
I'Od like to ask you is: What is the m two uneiploded atomic bombs in<br />
our coutry down in the South Australian area?<br />
BH: Well, if I can come to the last one. I'm not aware of' two unexploded<br />
atomic bombs down South, Vincent. If' you have some details about unexploded<br />
atomic bombs I hopeyou'll let me know because if they're there no one<br />
else knows about it and no one has told me. And I would have thought<br />
it they knew about it, they would have bought it to the attention of the<br />
Government and the Prime Minister, so if you've got any information about<br />
it, please let me know. In regard to the first part of your question,<br />
I had a press conference earlier, Vincent, and this question about Land<br />
Rights was raised and I wonder If you'd just let me make a few general<br />
observations ab~ out this and I think listeners generally would be interested.<br />
What my Government has been doing in this area is to say that we don't<br />
wanbt to rush into a sensitive area in a way which Is going to have some<br />
apparent short term advantages for people without having to do it In a<br />
way which is going to ensure that through time the whole of the Austrlian<br />
people are going to be satisfi~ ed with what's done. Let me remind you<br />
that it was in 1 967 and by an overwhelming majorit y that the Australian<br />
people decided that the Commonewaith Parliament should have responsibilities<br />
and powers In this area. Now that's nearly 20 years ago and I think that<br />
what the people expect now of this govenrment is that we will go through<br />
the processes of consultation with the Aboriginal people, with miners,<br />
with farmers, with the state and Territory government to try and ensure<br />
that that power and responsibility which the people of Australia gave<br />
to the Federal Government nearly 20 years ago, is exercised in a way which<br />
will bring benefits to the Aboriginal people. That's what the great majorityr<br />
of Australians want. They want it done in a way which they can go along<br />
with and accept and which will mean that it will stick Into the future. </p>
<p>Now that's what Mr Holding and I have therefore been doing. We've been<br />
having negotiations with the Aboriginal Steering Committee, with the Australian<br />
Mining Industry Council, with the National Farmers Federation, and with<br />
the states. We're gonna keep on doing that, and it's my belief that if'<br />
we keep on doing that we can reach a position where the legitimate rights<br />
and aspirations or' the Aboriginal people will be recognised and given<br />
effect to and It will be done in a way which the Australian people will<br />
recongise, accept and be proud of'. Now, that's what we're about, we're<br />
committed to it and that's what will happen.<br />
Caller: Umn, well the Aboriginal people, we own cattle stations in the<br />
Territory here, we've restructured our cattle industry where the industry<br />
here in the Territory and we have taken the lead role in the BTB eradication<br />
program, so there is no need to be afraid of Aboriginal people. There's<br />
be fear built up in the community of not understanding....<br />
Dli: Yeah, Vincent we are not afraid of the Aboriginal people and I don't<br />
think the great majority of Australians are. Unfortunately, I think there's<br />
a fair bit of prejudice, the talk has been developed in some quarters<br />
I think for very narrow political advantage or percieved advantage<br />
but what my government is about Is to try and dissipate fear and prejudice,<br />
to get people talking together and to get people talking in WA at the<br />
present time, you're seeing the advantages emerging of discussions between<br />
the various groups, There'll be significant developments there for the<br />
Aboriginal people. I'M going to be seeing Mr Burke, the Premier of WA,<br />
later on this week, and I think you'll see that there in a context which<br />
will be accepted by the community as a whole Including the farmners, miners*<br />
you're going to see some announcements on friday in WA which will be of'<br />
significant advantage to the Aboriginal people, and in a way which will<br />
have broad community acceptance. And that's the sort of thing that we've<br />
got to try and do.<br />
CK: We must move on. Sarah, you're through to the PM, go ahead.<br />
Caller: Good afternoon Mr Hawke, It's a pleasure to talk to you. Mr<br />
Hawke I'd like to say first of all that I think you're the greatest Prime<br />
Minister Australia's ever had. But what I'm concerned about'is, the John<br />
Reeves and him image up here as compared with perhaps I could say the<br />
rather bombastic style oS' Mr Everingham. I don't know exactly where the<br />
problem lies, but I've been a Labor supporter for many, many years and<br />
I feel that what John Reeves has been doing down in Canberra just hasn't </p>
<p>been coming back to Territorians and I'm Just interested in your comments<br />
as to how Labor can get the word around when Labor's up against such a<br />
strong personality as Paul Everingham.<br />
BG: Yeah, well thank you very much Sarah for your observations and your<br />
question. Let me say these things. It's inevitable in an area like the<br />
Territory which has 8 small population of about 140,000 people, that the<br />
Chief Minister of the Government is going to get alot of exposure and<br />
I'mi not complaining about that, it's inevitable, it's going to be the<br />
case and so Mr Everingham is going to be able to get that exposure, publicity<br />
and certainly I pay him credit, he's very, very good very good at<br />
getting that exposure. I pay him unqualified tribute for jhis capacity<br />
in that respect. Now with John, of course, he's down there in Canberra<br />
and the sort of things he has consistently been doing in the interest<br />
of the Territory just don't, in the nature of things, get that daily exposure.<br />
But letme say this to you, that john Reeves, since he's been In there<br />
and since we've been in Government from March of last year, has been incessant<br />
in his approaches to me and to the relevent ministers saying day after<br />
day ' these are the real needs of the Territory, these are the things that<br />
you ought to do'. Just let me give you an example. We had this question<br />
about whether there was going to be the rail link between Alice Springs<br />
and Darwin. Now, I had to re-consider that in the light of the $ 3.6 billion<br />
additional deficit which we inhereited. So we had a look at it, had the<br />
independent Inquiry. Now Mr Everingham just said In the discussion<br />
I had discussions with him in my office in Canberra and In Sydney I<br />
said ' well look, if the independent inquiry is to come out and say no<br />
it's not appropriate, what will we do additionally to spend money on upgrading<br />
the Stuart Highway'. Now the Chief Minister said ' No, the Stuart HIghway<br />
is all right, we don't need to spend any more money on that. That's all<br />
right, there's no problem'. Now that was the Chief Minister trying to<br />
get his headlines, It had to be the railway line or nothing. Now John<br />
Reeves quietly and effectively said ' all right, well, if it does come<br />
out that way that the railway can't go ahead, of course the Stuart Highway<br />
should have more money spent on it. It should be upgraded into an all-<br />
:. purpose all-weather road'. And as a result of his quiet and effective<br />
and undemonstrative representation, we;' ve moved to the position where<br />
in addition to the money which has already been allocated, we'll be spending<br />
an additional $ 27 million during the rest of this decade, up until about<br />
1988, starting with $ 2.7 million in this year to bring up that Stuart<br />
Highway to an imprived standard which will help to meet the Transport<br />
needs of the Territory. Now, Sarah, you see that's the sort of contrast.<br />
Effective, quiet representation which produces the goods, and in the nature<br />
of things you don't get the same publicity about that. Now I just happen </p>
<p>to think, Sarah, that people of the Territory are intelligent people who<br />
will udnerstand the difference, as I said earlier. they will see that<br />
their interests are much better served by having that effective John Reeves<br />
down there as a member of the Government because Mr Everingham has<br />
said himself that he expects my Government to be returned and probably<br />
with an Increased majority the people of the Northern Territory are<br />
going to be much better of f having John Reeves, a government member there,<br />
continuing to do the job he done for them.<br />
CK: ANd we must move on. ( Ads). Penny, you're through, go ahead.<br />
Caller: Good afternoon, Mr Hawke. Like many other AU-voters, I applauded<br />
the government when you rebutted the racist misinformation over Asian<br />
immigration. However I've been profoundly disappointed by the almost<br />
total lack of defence over Aboriginal Land Rights In the face of the massive<br />
propaganda campaign by the mining Industry and pastoralists. The Government<br />
passivity, I believe, has allowed the campaign to tak~ e hold and there<br />
is now a community backlash. Now when you said to an earlier caller that<br />
you'll do what's acceptable to the Australian people, aren't you really<br />
saying that Land Rights are now negotiable? That's my first question,<br />
and secondly I want to know why don't you lend your considerably popularity<br />
to the defence of Australia's most disadvantaged people?<br />
MI~ Well Penny let me go into the first question by answering the second<br />
one first. But I must say that I don't accept that criticism. I will<br />
put my record up in regard to the Aboriginal people against anyone In<br />
this country and it goes back it's not a matter of this month, last<br />
month, it goes back over a twenty years or more in public life. It hasn't<br />
been jsut words, It's action. And I haven't changed In that respect.<br />
What I'm saying is to you, and the people of Australia, that if we are<br />
going to make our contribution to the Aboriginal people of this country<br />
stick and not somehting that's just going to be a. transient show, then<br />
we have to make sure that the Australian people are going along with what's<br />
done. Now I believe that we can do that. I believe that it is legitimate<br />
In talking about how we're going to move in regard to Aboriginal Land<br />
Rights, that we do have consultation with the states and the Territory<br />
Government with the mining Industry, with the farmers and with other interested<br />
or'ganisations. So that we can shape the understanding or this issue in<br />
Australia. It's not going to be any good simply saying ' look I've got<br />
the numbers In the Federal Parliament' wham, bang, here it goes, if in<br />
doing it that way you're going to create in the Australian community generally<br />
some fairly solid opposition. It's much better to move through consultation </p>
<p>with the Aboriginal people and others so that what comes onto the Statute<br />
books of this country through the Federal Government and through state<br />
governments is a lasting, durable, constructive reform. Now that's what<br />
we're going to do, and I haven't seen any indication In my discussions<br />
with the Aboriginal people that they quesiton our integrity. They might<br />
have some doubts about the wisdom of certain things that are said here<br />
and there, but they don't question out Integrity.<br />
CK: We must move on ( this is a recording) and our next caller, Corralee.<br />
BH: Good afternoon Bob. Like to welcome you to the Territory. I should<br />
think being an Important figurehead as what you are, it beenis to bring<br />
about alot of quick condemnation and negative criticism from other politicians<br />
and the media. It's not very often up here In the Territory that we hear<br />
of any positive criticism or encouragement, so I'd just like to say to<br />
you that considering the economic situation that this country was in with<br />
the former Prime Minister, in my opinion, you are doing a wonderful job<br />
and I'd just like to say thank you.<br />
BR: Well Corralee that's very kind of you and I certainly appreciate<br />
It. It does seem to be the case that the majority of Australian people<br />
share your view, perhaps they're not all as thoughtful as you are to come<br />
out and say openly and directly that. But I simply want to say this briefly,<br />
Corralee, that during the last Federal election, at the beginning of last<br />
year, February, March, I made one basic promise to the people of Australia<br />
and that was that I would try and bring an end to the confrontation and<br />
the devisiveness in this country and I said that if we can do that, then<br />
everything else will flow from it, we can have economic recovery and<br />
reconstruction If we can have national reconciliation. We started on<br />
that in our national summit in % April, of last year, we bought Australia<br />
together and in the event we've changed things from economic stagnation<br />
to having the fastest growing economy in the world now.. Now those things<br />
are not just the result of my government or the decisions I've taken,<br />
they're really the result of the Australian people all of us, working<br />
together in the way I wanted us to. So if there are bouquets to go to<br />
me, there really are bouquets to go to all of us.<br />
CK: We must take a break and we'll1 be back ( ADS) Our next caller Zel.<br />
Callers Good afternoon Mz' Hawke. I'd like to speak to you on the two<br />
airline policies. It appears that under a Liberal Government we couldn't<br />
get the break Out.-of it, and with your government now been in this length </p>
<p>-S<br />
of time we've heard nothing that they intend doing anything. And I feel<br />
Australia needs it very badly. All Australians, and particularly us here<br />
in the Territory. What is your view on it?<br />
BH: Well Zel the fact is that the two airlines' agreement was negotiated<br />
in the period of the previous government and goes through til later in<br />
the 1980s and it's not something that it we wish to I don't go to the<br />
merits of it but it is there and it goes to, I think.-this is subject<br />
to correction to 1986. It's negotiated, it's in place. And there is<br />
nothing that can be done to un-negotiate that if you wanted to. But in<br />
the area of aviation generally, I think what's recognised is that this<br />
government has now done more than any government to develop new initiatives<br />
in this area. That's applied not only from the-activitie3 of my Minister<br />
for Civil Aviation, Mr Beazley, but for Sport, Recreation and Tourism,<br />
Mr Brown, has also been responsible for many new initiatives there which<br />
have been calculated to make travel within Australia cheaper under particular<br />
circumstances. Cailler: I'm sorry, would you like to see more airlines travelling within<br />
Australia? Bit.-Well, it's a very complex issue, this, because what you find is if'<br />
you de-regulate the airline industry and sort of give almost open slather<br />
it is very, very much more difficult, Zel, to have your safety regulations<br />
operating efficiently. Now one of.. you may say rightly that there are<br />
certain limitations involved with having the two airline agreement, but<br />
i would point out to you that one feature of the existence of the two<br />
airline agreement has been that we have in Australia probably the best<br />
airline safety record of any country in the world. And if I can sort<br />
of use paradoxical language, it's no accident that you've had the co-incidence<br />
of a two airline policy and the world's best safety record. And I think<br />
therefore when you're talking about what sort of airline policy we're<br />
going to have in this country you've got to take all these factors into<br />
account. CKs We must leave It there, folk. If you're calling fromn Alice SPrings,<br />
please remember to turn your radio down because we get a massive feedback<br />
problem. ( Ads)<br />
7f-Lr </p>
<p>talk dzk<br />
CKI Before we take the next caller, I understand, Mr Prime Minister,<br />
. you want to clarify an issue.<br />
BHz Yeah, I was talking to that last caller, Zel, about the two airlines<br />
agreement and I observed that I said subject to correction about the life<br />
of the two airline agreement, I mentioned 1986. That's not when it ends.<br />
It's at the end of ' 86 or the very beginning of ' 87 that notice can be<br />
given 3 years' notice can be given about review. But the agreement<br />
goes through until 1990. And it's the end of ' 86 or the beginning of<br />
' 87 that you can give the notice of reivew. In fact the Minister, Mr<br />
Beazley, will be initiating the beginning of that review next year and<br />
through 85/ 86.<br />
CK: We'll take our next caller Ron, you're through to Mr Hawke, go<br />
ahead. Caller: Hello Mr Hawke. The question I want to ask is... I'm a Labor<br />
voter from way back, but what I want to ask you is that earlier on you<br />
said that you regarded the Territorian electorate as quite intelligent,<br />
the thing is that I remember when you came up here last time you made<br />
quite an effective case of why you couldn't afford to fund the-railway<br />
up here. And the result was that in the local election up here that<br />
the result was, In the local eleciton up here, was a landslide to the<br />
CLP. Now I just can't see how you can reconcile those two facts.<br />
BHs Well, there are two things... I was talking specifically, Ron, as<br />
you'll appeciate, as to what... I wps asked what did I think the Territorians<br />
would do in regard to the decision they have to take in this Federal election.<br />
And I made the point that I think they will see that John Reeves has been<br />
an excellent member for them and, , you get down to this bottom line, I<br />
think, Pon, and I think which is why I believe that they are intelligent<br />
and will make the sensible decision. Mr Everingham has said... it's not<br />
me saying it... Mr Everingham has said that the Hawke Labor Government<br />
will be returned at this election and he thinks with an increased majority.<br />
And I'm simply saying, Ron, that I think that the majority of Territorians<br />
will say that it's much more sensible for us in Federal politics to have<br />
a Labor member there so that he has direct access to the GOvernment and<br />
can represent the interests of Territorians. Now there are other considerations<br />
which obviously came into play in regard to the election for the NT Government.<br />
They made judgements, obviously, as to who they preferred to Labor and<br />
WMr; </p>
<p>non-Labor there. There were a different set of considerations. I would<br />
hiave hoped, of course, that they would have supported Labor. They didn't,<br />
But I'm certain that they will sef that their best interests are surved<br />
by having John Reeves, a Labor member, In the Hawke Labor Government.<br />
CK: OK we'll move along. Paul, go ahead.<br />
Caller: Hello Mr Hawke. First I'd like to say that I admire you courage<br />
in allowing yourself to be questioned by the poeple like this.<br />
Us: Ohs it's a pleasure.<br />
Caller: I'm a blue collar worker and a member _ of the local trade union<br />
and I'd like to say that I'm quite dismayed about the way that your Government<br />
has continued the Fraser Government's policy of triple-dipping into the<br />
pockets of the average workers for your tax revenues.<br />
BH: Yeah, what's that triple dipping, Paul?<br />
Callers Well, first we have to pay for the priviledge of producing by<br />
income tax. Then we have to pay more by heavy petrol taxes to get back<br />
and forth to work. And to top It all off we have to pay a very heavy<br />
tax for our beer at the end of the work day.<br />
BH: Ab ha.<br />
Callers If you could answer this question. Will you ask the voters<br />
for a mandate to introduce an equitable capital gains tax? I mean that's<br />
one that takes inflation over the years that the capital is held into<br />
account. Ust Well Paul, let me go to the first part of your observations and then<br />
I'll go the the latter part and I'll try to do it quickly. You referred<br />
to income tax, petrol tax and beer tax. Well, some people have observed<br />
over the years that there are only two things that are certain in life<br />
and that's taxes and death. Well, I guess in some senses that's right.<br />
It's funnyt you know, Paul, when people talk about taxes and they don't<br />
like to pay taxes, they never say that they don't Government; to spend<br />
money no defence, they never say that they don't want them to spend money<br />
on roads, they never say they don't want government to spend money on<br />
hospitals on pensions, unemployment benefits. There's never any suggestion<br />
~~ v </p>
<p>that Government should stop spending on the things that people need and<br />
-want. Now It's a simple, certain fact of life that if governments are<br />
going to provide what the citizens require, and that only governments<br />
can provide in terms of defence and so on and these sorts of things, then<br />
governments have to have revenue. Now the secret, Paul, is to try and'<br />
have a tax system which satisfies the two requirements of efficiency and<br />
equity and that's what we're about. Now, you talk about a capital gains<br />
tax. It's the Liberals who have said that a capital gains tax is an inevitable<br />
part of the reformed tax system. If you look at what their economic<br />
committee said In NSW, they said that you'd have to have a capital gains<br />
tax. We haven't said that, we've said that we will have a reivew of the<br />
tax system and we will do what'we've done since we've been in government.<br />
The reason why we've had such a successful economic policy is that we<br />
didn't impose decisions from Canberra. We talked to the trade unions,<br />
we talked to the business community, we talked to the welfare organisations,<br />
and out of that approach we developed successful economic policies. We'll<br />
do the same with regard with regard to tax. We w~ ill sit down and talk<br />
with the community and try and out of that process get a system which<br />
Is fair and equitable. We're not going to preempt that discussion by<br />
sying we'll do this or we won't do that.<br />
CK: We must move on ( ADS). Our next caller through to Mr Hawke, Thomas.<br />
Go ahead Thomas.<br />
Caller: Good afternoon, Bob. My situation is that alot of staunch ALP<br />
voters, Including myself, were absolutely shattered by the way your party<br />
adopted the abortion virtually on demand as part of the platform of the<br />
last conference. And I don't udnerstand how your party could even purport<br />
to grant as a right an even more extensive licence to kill, which<br />
Is basically what the party is doing. The question I've got is would<br />
you undertake to rescind, or revokei or repeal or whatever the word is<br />
the provisions of that platform of fertility control and abortion to<br />
delete that phrase ' and abortion' from the policy statement.<br />
BH: Thomas, what you've got to recognise and I'm sure you do, is that<br />
you're taling about an Issue on which there are very, very deep feelings.<br />
1 recognise and respect yours. There are others who, with equal integrity.<br />
to you and I hope that you will recognise that.... ycu're obviously a Christian<br />
beliver and I think you'll recognise that part or the Christian faith<br />
is that the Good Lord, If you believe in the Good Lords hasn't given wisdom<br />
and proof to one group only. That you've got to recognise integrIty in<br />
other people as well as in yourself. And if we don't start from that<br />
basis that you repog nise integrity in others as well as yourself, then<br />
; j. i~ A </p>
<p>we are in a very sterile and barren society. Now I accept the integrity<br />
-of yourself, I accept the integrity of people who have a different view<br />
to yourself. Speaking for myself, I would not be in favour of creating<br />
a society in which there was just an unlimited freedom in this area, but<br />
I do believe that ultimately it is the right of individuals to make their<br />
own choice In this situation. And I have said in respect to my own party<br />
that I would never be party to abrigating the conscience vote in this<br />
are. And I made that quite clear In the conference of the party. I have<br />
no right as an Individual to determine what the policy of the party will<br />
be, but I will certainly fight as hard as I can to fight off those within<br />
my party who would try and take away the freedom of conscience vote In<br />
this matter because I think that if you got to the stage where members<br />
of the Parliamentary Party didn't have the right of conscience vote in<br />
this situation, then that would be totally unacceptable. So, Thomas,<br />
.1 could easily just to satisfy you, say yes I will try to tip this over<br />
and have the policy that you agree with. But it wouldn't be honest if<br />
I said it, so I'm not going to say that.<br />
CK: Mr H~ awke, we have run out of time. I'd like to thank you very much<br />
for being guest on the program, and no doubt we can look forward to you<br />
coming through again In the near future.<br />
BH: Yes, I hope so, too, Col. Thank you very much to you personally<br />
and to your listeners. It was very worthwhile, thank you.<br />
ends-<br />
YA Y III </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
