<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4044</transcript-id>
    <title>DEPARTMENTAL SPENDING</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/02/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004044.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F 76/ 20<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 4 February 1976<br />
DEPARTMENTAL SPENDING<br />
As announced yesterday savings of about $ 9 million in the<br />
Childhood Services Programme will be achieved in 1975/ 76<br />
This will be possible as a result of the slowing down of some<br />
already approved capital projects and by curtailing further<br />
development of the programme this financial year through<br />
the approval of only a limited number of urgent Child<br />
Care services in the highest priority needs areas.<br />
Funds are available to meet all other existing commitments<br />
this financial year.<br />
The appointment is announced of Senator Margaret Guilfoyle<br />
as Minister assisting me in child care matters.<br />
An Interim Committee within the Department is continuing to<br />
administer-the Childhood Services Programme.<br />
As was also announced yesterday, reduced purchases overseas<br />
by the Australian National Gallery will save over<br />
$ 3 million in -the current financial year.<br />
The policy and programmes of the Australian National Gallery<br />
were discussed with the Chairman of the Gallery's Interim<br />
Council, Mr R. C. Crebbin last week.<br />
It was agreed that decisions could be deferred on the<br />
acquisition of certain overseas works which have been under<br />
consideration by the Council, resulting in a saving in the<br />
present financial year of $ 3 million. </p>
<p>It was also decided to negotiate payment for one particular<br />
work, costing $ 400,000, so as to spread the cost over<br />
the current and next financial. years.<br />
This giv3s a total saving in the present financial year<br />
of $ 3.2 million out cf the Gallery's appropriation of<br />
$ 5.6 million.<br />
At the same time, there was agreement<br />
that the Gallery's acquisition programme for Australian<br />
art should be strengthened by re-allocating an additional<br />
$ 200,000 from other proposed programmes.<br />
The Australia Council's budget of $ 23.7 million<br />
for the current financial year will be reduced by $ 605,000.<br />
Cuts will be made in both administrative expenditure and activities<br />
in support for the arts.<br />
Administrative expenses of the Public Service Board are<br />
to be reduced by $ 394,500 nrainly due to reductions in<br />
expenditure on computers, advertising, consultants' fees<br />
and staff engaged on full time training. These savings are<br />
in addition to general cuts on overtime and travel totalling<br />
$ 161,700.<br />
The Film and Television School's budget of $ 3.7 million will<br />
be reduced by $ 277,000 in the areas of administrative<br />
services and purchase of equipment.<br />
It is expected that expenditure in the current financial<br />
year in connction with the establishxment of the Australia/ Japan<br />
Foundation, about which a statement was made on<br />
January will not exceed $ 100,000. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
