<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>31841</transcript-id>
    <title>Delivering more to make your life easier</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/10/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Message</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">This past week we have seen very good news for Australian families flowing from the Government’s decision to scrap the carbon tax.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">The Bureau of Statistics has reported that households and businesses are benefiting from the largest fall in power prices since records began.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">And, in coming months, there will be further flow-ons – with less cost pressures on other goods and services.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">For the businesses that export and employ; and for the families who are saving for Christmas – lower electricity prices are very good news.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">But they’re just the start.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">The Government is implementing an Economic Action Strategy to build a strong and prosperous economy for a safe and secure Australia.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">This week, the second-ever Red Tape Repeal Day will remove almost 1,000 unnecessary pieces of legislation and regulation. </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">So far, the Government has moved to cut over $2 billion a year in red tape costs – that’s actually double the $1 billion a year cut that we promised before the election.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">Households are seeing the benefits – with the new MyTax service helping you with your tax return and the MyGov system making it easier to access government services like Medicare and Centrelink.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">And this week, I will be making an infrastructure statement to the Parliament on building the roads of the 21st century.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">The Government has a record $50 billion infrastructure programme underway that will improve traffic, reduce transport costs and make our country more efficient:  through big progress on major projects such as WestConnex, the East West Link, the Midland Highway, the North-South Road Corridor, the Swan Bypass, the Gateway upgrade and major works on the Pacific and Bruce Highways.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">These roads and projects like Sydney’s Second Airport are vital to our nation.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">The Government is delivering – scrapping bad taxes, cutting red tape, stopping the boats and building the infrastructure of the 21st century.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">This is just the start and every day we are delivering more – to make your life easier and our economy stronger.</p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;"> </p>
<p style="margin: 0cm 0cm 0pt;">26 October 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
