<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5191</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF ABC&#039;S 7.45AM NEWS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/11/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005191.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER THURSDAY, 8 NOVEMBER 1979<br />
From the Press office<br />
SUMMARY OF ABC'S 7: 45 am NEWS<br />
Relations between Iran and the United States are worsening.<br />
In the latest development, Ayatollah Khomeini is refusing to<br />
meet special emissaries sent by President Carter. In a radio<br />
broadcast the Ayatollah has warned that there will be no contact<br />
with the Americans until the Shah is returned from New York.<br />
He also supported the Muslim students holding the hostages but<br />
criticised them for threatening to kill the Americans.<br />
The American mission on its way to Iran has been told to remain<br />
in Athens until the State Department clarifies whether Iranian<br />
authorities will receive them.,<br />
The Minister for National Development,' Mr. Kevin Newman, say s<br />
any limitations on exports of crude oil from Iran will have very<br />
little immediate impact on Australia's crude oil supplies.<br />
Mr. Newman said Australia was 70 per cent self-sufficient in<br />
crude oil and imports from Iran so far this year represented<br />
less than 1 per cent of the total Australian requirements.<br />
Senator Edward Kennedy has announced formally that he will be<br />
standing for the Presidency of the United States. Senator Kennedy<br />
made the announcement in Boston and used the occasion to deliver<br />
a blunt attack against the Carter administration. His formal<br />
announcement is to be followed by a similar declaration tomorrow<br />
from another Democrat, Governor Gerry Brown of California.<br />
President Carter is expected to announce his candidacy early<br />
next month.<br />
Mrs. Roslyn Carter is on her way to Thailand. The American<br />
President's wife will be away for four days, inspecting refugee<br />
camps on Thailand's border with Kampuchea and conferring with<br />
the Thai Government.<br />
Britain is to abandon Australia's Woomera Testing Range. The<br />
Ministry of Defence in London has announced that missile testing<br />
at Woomera will end from June next year.<br />
Queensland Senator George Georges has undergone a number of<br />
tests after being admitted to hospital suffering from a heart<br />
attack. He was admitted to Woden Valley Hospital with chest<br />
pains early yesterday. He is expected to remain in hospital<br />
for some time.<br />
There is speculation about the health of the Soviet Prime Minister.<br />
For the first time in 15 years he has missed the parade to<br />
mark the 62nd Anniversary of the October Revolution.<br />
The Defence Department is considering court martialling an army<br />
officer alleged to have released details of Dr. Peter Solomon's<br />
military career.<br />
The next national wage case is due to begin in Melbourne on Tuesday.<br />
The ABC's Melbourne Office says the ACTU and other union groups<br />
are expected to seek a full flow-on of 5.1 per cent in the CPI.<br />
The employers are expected to argue that no wage increase is<br />
justified.' In line with a decision by its Executive last week, the<br />
ACTU will also press for an unspecified catch-up claim to make up<br />
for money lost by previous partial wage indexation hearings. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Authorities in Darwin are having difficulty processing the<br />
number of Taiwanese fishing boats arriving to fish in Australian<br />
territorial waters under the new fisheries agreement. The<br />
boats are arriving at such a rate that officials have run into<br />
unexpected delays into completing formalities because of<br />
communication difficulties.<br />
The CSIRQ is to charter a commercial fishing vessel to carry<br />
out research in the 200 mile Australian fishing zone. The<br />
Minister for Science and the Environment, Senator Webster,<br />
says the vessel will be chartered for 5 years at a cost of<br />
nearly $ 6 million..<br />
A challenge to Commonwealth sovereignty over land in the<br />
Northern Territory will be discussed,, in Canberra today by the<br />
Deputy Prime Minister, Mr. Anthony, and the Chief Minister of<br />
the Territory, Mr. Paul Everingham. The meeting stems from<br />
an option by the Territory Government two weeks ago in proclaiming<br />
52 sq. kms. of the Commonwealth-controlled Kakadu National Park<br />
as a town area.<br />
The functions of the former Federal Narcotics Bureau, which<br />
was disbanded on Tuesday by the Government, will be formally<br />
transferred today to the Federal Police Force. The decision to<br />
do away with the Bureau followed a recommendation by a judge<br />
heading the Commonwealth's Royal Commission into Drugs. In a<br />
brief statement last night,' the Minister for-Administrative<br />
Services, Mr. McLeay, said the formalities relating to the<br />
transfer had been completed and the new arrangements would take<br />
effect from today.<br />
Cricket: India has won the series against Australia.<br />
The President of Zambia is flying to London to discuss<br />
Zimbabwe-Rhodesia with Mrs. Thatcher. The British Prime Minister<br />
invited the President to stop in London on his way to a<br />
conference in Rome. 0 00---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
