<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5695</transcript-id>
    <title>25TH ANNIVERSARY DINNER OF THE OPENING OF THE MELBOURNE OLYMPICS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/11/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005695.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO; 8: 40 pmn<br />
ut CHEO AGAI-NST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY,_ 22_ NOVE" R 19 81<br />
ANtXVFSARY DINNER Or' THE OPENUNG<br />
OF THE MBLDO1JNF, OLYMPICS<br />
*-Gold medalbiatz, Mr. Premier, Dame Pattie Menzies, Lady Kent-1<br />
Riniste ra and-4' rli a~ ntary col3. leagues, la. tdies and gentlemen:<br />
' K( evin Go. sper, thank you very much for that introduotion and f
what you have said about the value and the fuature of sport, ai<br />
well as the increasing Government support for sport. Sport ik<br />
somehin w eA2jbelie in. It offers som~ ethingl to everyone.<br />
Atustralians together.<br />
We are celebrating tonight one of the greatest events in<br />
Aust-ralia's sporting history, anid we axe also paying tribute<br />
some of the greatest sportsmen and spoxt-swomen in Austxralia's iughes, r<br />
history. I . wish I could-pmy trib~ tite to every one of-their by--name, for<br />
all their successes deserve citation. And while I don't have the<br />
. time to do that, X do want to say how delighted we are that<br />
Betty Cuthbert is here tonight. We are also delighted that<br />
Dame Pattie Menzies and Lady Xent-liughes are here, and it is<br />
worcth remembering t-hat it was Wilfred 1ent-Hughes, as Cbairman-cT<br />
the Olymnpic Organizing Committee, who signed the invitatiors<br />
which brought the three and a half thousand athletes from sixty<br />
* s-even covxitriel to Melbourne twenty five years ago today.<br />
My mind goes back to that moment when Ron Clark ran down the race<br />
onto the carrying aloft the Olympic torch, because it wa3<br />
a great momnt for everyone here -and it was a great moment for<br />
Audst-ralia.<br />
I know that while most of us could see rno fault in that torch<br />
as it ciraedzed around the it was giving Ron's a= m some<br />
nasty burns. No-doubt Ron cursed the design--o the~ torch, but<br />
it was obvio~ us from the way he moved that the pain did nothing<br />
to dim~ inish his pride In what he had been chosen to do.<br />
At that moment, Ron symbol~ ised the pride which all. of us felt th~<br />
~ ra ~ aity asthe fl-a he-ias<br />
carrying syrabolized the high idealit o-f the DTyThp5 i reñ Q<br />
C) I L-i </p>
<p>-2<br />
The Melbourne Games meant a lot to Australia in te-rms of helping<br />
us to become more outward looking as a nation, and in terms of<br />
demonstrating to the world tevalue of the Australian way of<br />
lif e.<br />
M'elbourne has been Australia's front window to the world or)<br />
many occasions, and the people of Melbourne never fail to discharge<br />
their responsibility with the highest distinction.<br />
The MloreOlympics were an overall triumph in terms of<br />
sportsmanahip, and also in terms of the achievement of so many<br />
people here tonight whose names were household words throughout<br />
Australia * at that time, I am particularly pleased to be here<br />
tonight not only because I was-an, rrIUt; r atthe Melbourne Gamesl-'<br />
but also.-because.-I value-the K I of contact this* aes Possibe.<br />
There are: obviously;. several1 reasons why_ Aurai plcs-c~ vaJtiu on.<br />
.~ prsme and women and one of them comes out in a story abot<br />
that Bob would have enjoyed the story because it illustrates the kind<br />
of respect and deference that Prime Ministers can expect from<br />
Sportsmen. As everyone here knw, obe. a-ratlover of sport,<br />
and he went to the tennis one day with Norman Strange when<br />
Lew Road was playing. After Lew's match was finished, and I do not<br />
know whether fie won. or lost though being Lew. I suppose he won,<br />
Normnan-Strange took Menzies down to the Oressing xoom to give Lew<br />
a chance to meet him. Lew wa xtn ~ w rigto get a shoelace<br />
undone, and Norman Strange said " Lew; I've brought the Prime Minister.<br />
down here to introduce you to him". Road seemed not to have heard,<br />
so Strange raised his voice a bit, and repeated his words " Lew,<br />
the Prime Minister is here and I woxild to introdce you to him".<br />
Still no response. Road just kept f idd ling with his shoelace, and<br />
said nothing. Strange was starting to feel a bit awkward, but hie<br />
raised his voice a bit more and had a third try " Lew, here i-s<br />
the Prime Minister of Australia, Mr. Menzies, and I want to<br />
4introduce you to him" V. Hoad ~~ 3nally lo9ecd-up 7-ooked.. at both of<br />
emthf: lc, u4 4aid. Yes, kn~ ow.' I-loW many Of you Would h1ave yeainel I" ox; the<br />
Sopportunity to say that to Pie last vear. Onre of the'r -test--things about<br />
.'.. sportemen and woe sta hyare&amp; achi~ evers. They get out<br />
addothins, nd tey eep looking ahead.<br />
Sport provider. a challenge to-ZhVe s7uc. Ucess andf eieeta<br />
it is because'Australians have alwqays wanted to go out to meet that<br />
kind of challenge whereve'r it arises, not just in sport but in<br />
every field of achievement that Australia has made the sort of<br />
it<br />
Everyone here knows in one way or another how much better it is<br />
to win than to lose, and in international sport in particular the<br />
challenge to success becomes even more demanding with higher<br />
standard8 being set all the ti--4f-t4----ig-n-r'ed andK<br />
Thursdays after work was not enouagh in 1956, and everyone here<br />
knows that it wasn't, it certainly is not enough in the 1980s.<br />
: Et was parxtly in rrecoq1niti. on of thijs that the Australian Institute<br />
of Sport was established in Canberra iat the start of this year.<br />
The Institute is prxoviding wrdcs tain tclte and top<br />
level specialist coaching, backed up by Sport5 science a. pot<br />
medicine, to talented and promising young Astralian athletes. </p>
<p>~ sr 000---<br />
The A. I. S. has been successfully launched in its initial year<br />
using facilities at the Nationial Sports Centre in Canberra,<br />
which comprises at the moment the National Athletic Stadium<br />
which incorporates sports science laboratories, and the<br />
National Indoor Sports Centre as well as5 tennis and netball oouxts.<br />
A specialist gymnasium centre is due to be completed next March,<br />
a throwing area foar ethblete is being developed, and the Government<br />
has recently approved the construction of an indoor Swimming and.<br />
tennis training centre on which work will begin shortly.<br />
A major objective behind the Institute of Sport is to gjive<br />
these young peopl tfopportunity-to puirsue their sport to<br />
the highest level without interrupting their education or placing<br />
their careers at risk.' Australia has needed this Institute, and.<br />
its inception this year is timely. It should give a massive<br />
boost in the years ahead to top-class competitive sport in<br />
Australia and I am hopeful that : this concept will be taken up<br />
around Australia.<br />
The Government is keen to listen. to the many voices of sport in<br />
Australia and is rospoP' 1inq v -th-&amp; a-variety of important<br />
initiatives to the changing requirements of sport. The Government<br />
has wide-ranging programs which are aimed ' both at assisting those<br />
sportsen and womnen who have the capacity to scale the heights<br />
of -sporting achievement.<br />
in financial terms, the total allocation for sport and recreation<br />
in the 1981-82 Commonwealth Budget Jisaijnost $ 16 million<br />
andt hIss more than double the 1980-BI epniue<br />
We all have high hopes for the athletes of tomorrow, and we need<br />
to be loolking ahead to the challenge of next year'rs Commonwealth<br />
G'ames in Brisbane and to the 1984 Olympics. I want to say in<br />
relation to-the 1984 Games thAt I b elieve the bonds between the<br />
A. O. F. and the Commonwealth Government have never been stronger.<br />
and the Government will be giving early consideration to a formal<br />
request for assistance in Australia's preparations and participation<br />
inl the 1984 Olympics. But we need to be looking even further<br />
ahead than 1984. ' d dtcLe4okn to Australia's IDieentenary<br />
in 1988 because right around Australia, in every sport, people<br />
will be wanting special events to be at the centre in the<br />
celebrations which will take place in that year. I am suire youi<br />
will not mind me looking ahead l. ike this even' though we -are here<br />
tonight to celebrate a grea-T-Ueent from the part.<br />
' The memories of the Melbourne ' olympic8, which are Bo strong<br />
in the minds of, everyone here topigch, fragetpge-a<br />
great chapter I-in, Autraliall his3tory, and Australia salutes.<br />
again those athletes and organisers who wrote the story in<br />
that chapter. We also salute Ron Delaney, just as John Landy<br />
Saluted him 25 years ago after Ron had won the 1500 metres.<br />
There is just. orle more thing for-me to say. ThiP2 is; oD1Y the<br />
Silver Jubilee? and in the propcr Olym~ pic tradition, w. e must<br />
aspire to the gold, and I hope you will again invite me to<br />
join you when that occasion comes; around. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
