<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17181</transcript-id>
    <title>Investing in the future of health in Gladstone    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/04/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Australian Government is planning for Gladstone's future health workforce needs with increased local clinical training opportunities for health and nursing students.</p>
<p>Up to $3 million will be provided to the Queensland University of Technology to work with 3 GP clinics across Queensland, including at the Gladstone Super Clinic, to create clinical training placements for around 128 students in areas such as psychology, pharmacy, podiatry, physiotherapy, nursing and radiography.</p>
<p>It will also support training places at Strathpine GP Super Clinic, and Golden Beach General Practice.</p>
<p>In Gladstone today, the Prime Minister said the investment will help deliver new pharmacists, physiotherapists, nurses and more, to care for the city's rapidly growing population.</p>
<p>Member for Flynn, Chris Trevor, said students who live and learn in a community are more likely to stay after graduation.</p>
<p>"Gladstone is booming, and this initiative is part of the preparation to make sure we have a strong sustainable health workforce."</p>
<p>The projects are part of the Rudd Government's strategy to work with organisations involved in providing clinical training to build training capacity and enhance the long-term sustainability of the health workforce.</p>
<p>The Rudd Government is building a health system to meet the needs of all Australians, now and into the future.</p>
<p>Under the National Health and Hospitals plan, the Rudd Government will shoulder the majority of the funding burden - 60 per cent of all public hospital services - meaning more money is available to meet rising health costs.</p>
<p>The Rudd Government's plan will see health services funded nationally and run locally through local hospital networks to deliver better health for local communities. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
