<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9099</transcript-id>
    <title>MR KEATING WHO IS ON LEAVE IN SYDNEY THIS WEEK, TODAY ISSUED THE FOLLOWING STATEMENT ON THE DEATH OF MR JUSTICE BARRY MADDEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/01/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009099.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OFFICL. OF It-iL PRIME MINiSTER<br />
CANBERRA<br />
Mr Keating, who Is on leave in Sydney this week, today issued the following<br />
statement on the death of Mr Justice Barry Maddern:<br />
" I was saddened today to learn of tbe death of Justice Barry Maddern, the President of<br />
the Australian Industrial Relations Commission.<br />
" Justice Maddern presided over what was in world terms a novel wages system<br />
operating under an accord betwcen the Government and the trade union movement.<br />
The record shows that during this period inflation in Australia was broken, and a more<br />
profitable business sector led to higher investment and higher employment.<br />
6He also presided over the most fundamental award restructuring in the nation's<br />
history, and contributed to Innovative exercises in wage setting, such as the<br />
introduction of supplementary payments.<br />
" Industrial disputes fell significantly while he was in office. There was no wage<br />
explosion exacerbated by decisions of industrial relations tribunals, which is in no small<br />
way due to him.<br />
" Justice Maddern brought a sense of consistency to the decisions of the industrial<br />
relations tribunals of this country, and was very successful in developing the<br />
relationships among the various tribunals, and within the federal tribunal.<br />
" Justice Maddern displayed a considerable degree of independence in his work, and<br />
will be remembered for the larger view and sense of consistency he bestowed on the<br />
country's industrial tribunals.<br />
" I extend sincere condolences to his family."<br />
SYDNEY 14 January, 1994 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
