<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5185</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON FOR KING AND QUEEN OF TONGA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/10/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005185.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME AUSTRALIA L<br />
FOR MEDIA TUESDAY, 23 OCTOBER 1979<br />
ADDRESS TO PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON<br />
FOR KING AND QUEEN OF TONGA<br />
It is the first time, Your Majesties, that you have been here<br />
as King and Queen, and we welcome you very greatly for that.<br />
But also we understand that you spent some of your youth hereyour<br />
years in college, and at Sydney-University. We hope you<br />
will be able to, in re-visiting Australia, meet some of your<br />
earlier friends and at the same time renew your acquaintance<br />
and knowledge of this country.<br />
Australia, in recent years has been moving much closer in its<br />
relationships with many of the countries of the Pacific, and<br />
for that reason also we very greatly welcome your presence<br />
here on this occasion.<br />
Tonga and Australia are living in a changed area. It has been<br />
seeking its own identity in recent years to a much greater extent<br />
than ever before. I -think a great deal of progress has been<br />
made. New nations are learning to work together for their own<br />
advancement, for the safety and well.-being of the region. Most<br />
nations, most States, have now achieved a fully independent<br />
status. That trahsition has been undertaken calmly, smoothly,<br />
constructively. I think that is in marked contrast to the<br />
transition that has sometimes occurred in some other parts<br />
of the world.<br />
I believe, Your Majesties, that it is very much a tribute<br />
to your responsibility and sense of occasion, that one-so often<br />
finds in the South Pacific and amongst-South Pacific nations.<br />
The transition has been a smooth and a peaceful one, and by and<br />
large a prosperous one. I think that is greatly to the credit<br />
not only of former, as it were, colonial powers, but certainly<br />
to the credit of the newly independent nation.<br />
Regional co-operation I think is contributing greatly to that<br />
peaceful progress. There is a common approach in many of the goals<br />
that the nations-of the Pacific share amongst each other. There<br />
are many reasons why there should be that common approach: there<br />
are similar problems often of scarce resources; of very small<br />
land areas; problems of expanding population; exports finding<br />
it difficult to get adequate markets in other countries; exports<br />
that are often vulnerable to changes in demand, to changes in<br />
prices. Against that, there are small domestic markets which make<br />
it difficult to expand industry unless it is based on exports. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
There are often per capita costs. There are often high-based<br />
costs that make economic advancement difficult for many of<br />
the nations of the Pacific. But for all of these reasons,<br />
the problems that occurred, or difficulties that occurred in<br />
common, it means that a common approach to the solutions is<br />
very much to the advantage to the nations of the Pacific.<br />
There is a second and vastly important reason why the nations<br />
of the Pacific, together with New Zealand and Australia, seek to<br />
work together through common goals, through common objectives.<br />
We all want peace. We want a peaceful world. We want a South<br />
Pacific, in our own theatre, free of great power rivalry not<br />
under the dominance of any of the major powers or the super powers.<br />
Those common objectives I think do give us common ground in<br />
many aspects of our relationship with the wider world. I think<br />
enables us and helps us to put the case for moderation, for<br />
consensus, for reason. . Sometimes people suggest that a<br />
middle-ranking country such as Australia should keep its head<br />
down in the wider'areas of international politics. I do not have<br />
that view. The Government does not have that view. I do not<br />
believe it is one that would be shared by a majority of Australians.<br />
Because what happens in the wider world is so important that<br />
we cannot leave issues that affect us very greatly merely to be<br />
solved by others who have more power, a longer interest<br />
or. involvement in some of these major i-ssues.<br />
It is not adequate to leave solutions to the great powers, to<br />
the super powers alone. Nor is it adequate in some other forum<br />
merely to leave the solutions to the great mass of numbers that<br />
might be gathered in a particular forum. It is of vast importance<br />
for countries, for middle-rankJ-ing nations such as Australia, to<br />
put a view of moderation, but to put that moderate view with strength,<br />
to try and achieve agreement, to try and lessen differences where<br />
those differences occur. That is the only way ultimately,<br />
we can achieve a more secure and a safer world.<br />
I venture to say that if had not been for the involvement of<br />
some countries not directly concerned, that what was achieved at<br />
Lusaka would not have been achieved. The progress that has been<br />
made in recent weeks in London would not have been made if it<br />
were merely left to the countries who were directly concerned in<br />
the first instance. That I think is an example of where a<br />
concerned interest by others can help contribure to reaching a<br />
consensus, to reaching agreement, and hopefully to resolving one<br />
of the more difficult and intractable problems in that instance,<br />
that has bedevilled relations in Africa over a very long period.<br />
On this point, there is some cause for us to be optimistic about<br />
the ultimate result. That again, gets us back to the interests<br />
of the Pacific and of Australia and of New Zealand. There are<br />
matters that are likely to impinge upon the future and well-being<br />
of the nations of the Pacific, of New Zealand's, of our own interests.<br />
It is up to us to be involved, to do what we can, to secure a<br />
safe path-for the whole region and all the nations of the region.<br />
In that, I believe a middle-ranking country such as Australia should<br />
not write itself down. I be lieve the countries of the Pacific,<br />
Your Majesty, should not write themselves down in the influence<br />
that they can have and should have in determining their own future<br />
and what happens to the region in which they live. </p>
<p>The interdependence in the region has grown over recent years.<br />
That interdependence can be seen in the early origins of the<br />
South Pacific Commission: in 1971 the South Pacific Forum,<br />
-where the South Pacific Heads of Government meet on a regular<br />
basis to discuss problems of mutual interest and concern.<br />
I think the very principle of consensus about which I have been<br />
speaking the call for moderation is exemplified in that<br />
particular forum as one nation stands out against<br />
agreement, aqainst the consensus of the others, everything is<br />
done, by the groupsconcerned to try and overcome the<br />
difficulties,* to try and seek a moderate path, to try and seek<br />
a solution that is acceptable. Not just the majority a,<br />
solution which is ult%-imately acceptable to all the nations of<br />
the forum. That is an example small in the wider world area<br />
if you like but important to the South Pacific. It is an<br />
example of the way in which relations between nations ought<br />
to be conducted.<br />
Beyond that, there is the South Pacific Bureau for Economic<br />
Co-operation to help achieve greater economic development<br />
and co-operation between the island States of the Pacific.<br />
There are now co-operative . arrangements in relation to fisheries,<br />
shipping services, aims at rationalising air services, and<br />
there is greater co-operation in trade and telecommunications.<br />
Australia is associated, and wants to be associated, with all of<br />
co-operative arrangements. They are practical examples of the<br />
way in which nations can work together, and in this case should<br />
work together to secure their own national objectives.<br />
Greater development of trade and greater possibilities in trade,<br />
are going to be very important, Your Majesty, as I know you well<br />
understand, for the well-being and development of the Pacific nations.<br />
Negotiations have now begun to try and achieve a comprehensive,<br />
non-reciprocal trade agreement between Australia and New Zealand<br />
and the Forum island countries. I hope very much that that<br />
agreement can be brought to a successful conclusion. It has<br />
as an objective, the extension of duty free access to the<br />
Australian-New Zealand market for as wide a range of products<br />
as possible from the Pacific nations. In addition to that, we<br />
have had a trade and development mission visit the island States<br />
identifying trading opportunities from--those States to Australia,<br />
identifying opportunities for investment from Australia in the<br />
island States themselves.<br />
The South Pacific Trade Commission office has been established<br />
in Sydney which is designed to assist in gaining access<br />
to the Australian market for the products of the Pacific nations.<br />
It will operate as part of the South Pacific Bureau for Economic<br />
Co-operation.<br />
In these important areas of trade, there is clearly an intention<br />
and a willingness to make progress and to provide greater<br />
opportunities. I hope that those efforts will be successful.<br />
Your Majesty, I believe Australia and Tonga relations have<br />
always been friendly and on the best possible terms, with a<br />
warmth between our two countries. I am sure it is our joint<br />
objectives to maintain and enhance-that in future years. / 14 </p>
<p>-4<br />
We are both members of regional and international forums.<br />
In those forums we work closely together on many different<br />
issues. We are both members of the Commonwealth. We were<br />
both at the Commonwealth Heads of Government Regional Meeting<br />
which was first held last year in Sydney, which will next be<br />
held in India in 1980.<br />
I have had particular pleasure working with Prime Minister<br />
Prince Tui'Pelehake, who joined platforms with me in a<br />
number of these regional forums. There are many things in<br />
which we have a common concern. For example, at the<br />
. Commonwealth Heads of Government Regional Meeting in Sydney<br />
a concern was expressed the problems of small States.<br />
Problems of representation in the wider international theatre<br />
can be expensive and very difficult to a small island State.<br />
How can those problems be overcome? What can be done to<br />
assist to make sure that the point of view of those nations<br />
is put effectively and with adequate strength in the forums<br />
where it needs to be heard. As a result of that Sydney<br />
meeting the Commonwealth Secretariat was invited to develop<br />
proposals which might then be put to Commonwealth members<br />
generally in relation to the problems of small States. A<br />
report from the Secretary-General was put to the Lusaka meeting<br />
with a plea and a call for as many nations as possible to act<br />
upon the various recommendations within it. That is a matter<br />
that Australia will want to follow closely.<br />
Your Majesties, I think that Sydney meeting also emphasised<br />
one other matter which is important to the nations of the Pacific.<br />
At the wider Commonwealth meetings so often other matters<br />
dominate the agenda, but the matters that might well be<br />
important to Pacific nations, and some of the members of the<br />
Commonweailth, don't always get heard, aren't given enouqh time<br />
on the wider agenda of the Commonwealth. Therefore,<br />
the regional meeting has a particular relevance, has a<br />
particular concern to the smaller States, because it does<br />
enable the agenda to be properly tapered to meet their needs,<br />
their concerns, and to make sure that something can be done<br />
about their particular matters. The follow-up from the Sydney<br />
meeting has given us an indication that something<br />
useful and positive can come from that. Those matters at<br />
the Sydney meeting involved not only the one Ihave mentionedthe<br />
problems of small States but also matters of trade and<br />
progress, as I have indicated has also been made on that<br />
particular front.<br />
Your Majesty, I am pleased to ani'ounce also on this occasion,<br />
that the Foreign Minist ' er has decided that our diplomatic<br />
representation to Tonga should be upgraded with a Permanent<br />
Resident High Commission being established in Tonga. I hope<br />
that can again be taken as an instance of Australia's concern<br />
to establish the closest possible relationship, to be able<br />
to work in harmony and co-operation with the nations of the<br />
Pacific as we pursue our common objectives.<br />
Your Majesty, I would again like to welcome you very much to<br />
Australia on this occasion. I hope that your days here will<br />
be happy and successful ones, and I would now like to ask the<br />
Leader of the Opposition, Mr. Hayden, and then the Deputy<br />
Prime Minister, Mr. Anthony, to support me in this welcome.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
