<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11161</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 RADIO INTERVIEW WITH HOWARD SATTLER (6PR)                                                  SUBJECTS: Taxation reform, ACOSS response, Commonwealth/State financial                 relations, National Document of Reconciliation, Jeff Kennett, Labor                 stunts, Premiers&amp;#146; reaction; another election, ANTS public education                 campaign</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/06/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..................................................................................................</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Good morning Prime Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning Howard.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>I thought I might try and scene set a bit. Did I get it right?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh largely but I think the thing you didn't acknowledge is that the</p>
<p> deal between the Democrats and the Government delivers 85 to 90 per</p>
<p> cent of what the public endorsed last October.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>But it is not the tax package on which we voted your party into office</p>
<p> is it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's 85 to 90 per cent. And the only alternative would have</p>
<p> been for us to say to the Australian public, because we didn't get</p>
<p> the 100 per cent we wanted we are going to ask you to have yet another</p>
<p> election. Now, can I tell you the mail I was getting from the Australian</p>
<p> public was that it didn't want another election on this issue. That</p>
<p> most people I spoke to before and certainly everyone I have spoken</p>
<p> to since, without exception, no one exception, and I'd have spoken</p>
<p> to hundreds of people since and they've all said, we think you</p>
<p> are very sensible to reach an agreement with the Australian Democrats.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Were they people within your own party?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, there were people outside it. Loads and loads of people outside</p>
<p> my own party. Howard, one of the things you have got to remember is</p>
<p> that when people elect people as Prime Minister or Premier or whatever,</p>
<p> or party leaders, they do expect them by and large to solve their</p>
<p> differences. I would think in the long-term that public esteem for</p>
<p> the Leader of the Australian Democrats has gone up as a result of</p>
<p> this agreement. Whereas public esteem for the Leader of the Opposition,</p>
<p> Mr Beazley, has gone down because he just huffs and puffs and says</p>
<p> "no". He never tries to engage us in any kind of debate.</p>
<p> He took no notice of the result of the last election. I mean, even</p>
<p> if you accept his theory about split mandates you don't do it in the</p>
<p> knowledge that we were returned. I mean, he's still in Opposition</p>
<p> and I am still Prime Minister.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Yeah, but I wonder how the esteems of both of you would sit, and with</p>
<p> the Democrats, now with people like small retailers who have got this,</p>
<p> sort of, mish-mash and anomalies and all that sort of thing to contend</p>
<p> with.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Howard, not everything in this package is acceptable to everybody.</p>
<p> I understand that, but nobody gets everything. And we argued uphill</p>
<p> and down dale. We put our political bodies on the line and we won</p>
<p> the election. We couldn't get it through the Senate because the opposition</p>
<p> parties in the Senate would not agree to the plan that we put to the</p>
<p> electorate. And I sat down with Senator Lees and I negotiated and</p>
<p> I found that I could reach agreement with her on 85 to 90 per cent</p>
<p> of our plan. And I thought accepting it on that basis was infinitely</p>
<p> better than the two alternatives.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Now, you mention 85 to 90 per cent. I have been running a web poll</p>
<p> for the last few days and 87 per cent say they want to have another</p>
<p> election on it, they'd like to have a vote on it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am not for a moment casting aspersions on your web poll, certainly</p>
<p> not. But that is not the mail I am getting in my discussions with</p>
<p> people all over the country.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>What about the Premiers? I mean, Richard Court started it and others</p>
<p> have picked it up and they are saying that this is not the package</p>
<p> on which they signed off. So what is the paper on which they signed</p>
<p> off worth now?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, obviously there have been some changes but all of the additional</p>
<p> costs, and I say this very carefully, all of the additional cost as</p>
<p> a result of the agreement I made with the Democrats is being borne</p>
<p> by the Commonwealth. That's $1.4 billion in the year 2000/2001. That</p>
<p> is being borne by us. Now, nobody has got everything they wanted.</p>
<p> That is always the case with a compromise. But there comes a point</p>
<p> in public life where you have got to ask yourself whether the compromise</p>
<p> is better than the alternatives. And I came to the conclusion that</p>
<p> it was. Now, I don't like it but I am a realist. And I ask the Premiers</p>
<p> to be realistic about it. They will still be better off. We will still</p>
<p> be abolishing, albeit at a slower rate, most of the unsatisfactory</p>
<p> taxes they have at a State level. There will still be a guarantee</p>
<p> that they will be not a dollar worse off during the transitional period.</p>
<p> We will still be giving them full access to the GST revenue which</p>
<p> will over time provide them with more resources to fund government</p>
<p> schools and hospitals and police.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>So there agreement still stands does it? 87 per cent of it does or....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The fundamental elements of the agreement with the States, of course</p>
<p> it still stands. The changes relate to the need because of the reduced</p>
<p> quantum of the GST revenue because basic food has been taken out there</p>
<p> will be a delay in the removal of some of the States' indirect</p>
<p> taxes. But their financial position will still over time be much better</p>
<p> than it would have been if they had continued under the existing Commonwealth/State</p>
<p> financial arrangement. And during the transition period the guarantee</p>
<p> that we have given to the States will remain intact, in full. And</p>
<p> we are carrying on our account, we are carrying the additional cost</p>
<p> of the compensation that's been injected into the taxation plan. We</p>
<p> are not asking the States to carry that.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, would you agree it got a bit farcical this week with</p>
<p> senior Ministers and your opponents arguing over cooked whole and</p>
<p> parts of chicken, frozen peas, packaged salads, cakes, plain and cheese-topped</p>
<p> bread and even soup? I mean, it almost looked like your worst nightmare</p>
<p> was being realised.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, can I say to you, Howard, I think that is ridiculous. But that</p>
<p> line of attack was initiated by the Labor Party, by the Opposition.</p>
<p> I mean,...can I just say to Mr Beazley, waving a can of soup around</p>
<p> in front of a camera is not a tax policy. If the Labor Party had had</p>
<p> a serious well thought out alternative to what we have put forward</p>
<p> then the public would take them more seriously. The Australian Democrats</p>
<p> have demonstrated a commitment to the national interest by sitting</p>
<p> down with the Government and working out a compromise. Now, this plan</p>
<p> will deliver great economic benefits to Australia. 80 per cent of</p>
<p> Australian taxpayers will be on a top marginal rate of 30 cents in</p>
<p> the dollar. We will be reducing business costs by about $10.5 billion</p>
<p> a year. We will be taking down the cost of diesel. There's a huge</p>
<p> benefit for wheat growers in a State like Western Australia because</p>
<p> one of the new elements of the package is that diesel excise on rail</p>
<p> carriage has been totally removed. Now, that's an enormous benefit</p>
<p> to the wheat growers of Western Australia.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Sure, but for an outlet like, say, KFC, I know they're a big multinational</p>
<p> to come out and say that 24,000 jobs are at risk because there are</p>
<p> anomalies in whether or not a whole or a part of a chicken is going</p>
<p> to attract a GST. I mean, surely that's an anomaly that should be</p>
<p> cleaned up.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Howard, nobody is totally satisfied about everything, that is the</p>
<p> nature of a compromise.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>But we are talking jobs here....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am talking jobs too and the net economic benefit of this package</p>
<p> will be to add jobs in Australia not subtract them. I don't believe</p>
<p> that that claim is properly based. I believe it is an exaggeration</p>
<p> and....</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>...don't agree with the example of the whole or part chicken, one</p>
<p> part attracting a GST one not?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Now, look, I have made a compromise deal with the Australian Democrats</p>
<p> and what I am saying is that if we are so immature as a community</p>
<p> and as a group of people to focus all of our debate on the periphery</p>
<p> rather than the heart and soul and the centre of this package and</p>
<p> the enormous benefits that it delivers. I mean, I could spend the</p>
<p> next half an hour regaling you with examples of anomalies in the wholesale</p>
<p> tax system, about the difference between the taxation of toothpaste</p>
<p> and a toothbrush, the differential treatment of chocolate biscuits.</p>
<p> And I could go on for half an hour...</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>But that is why most people voted, or they voted...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And there are still far fewer anomalies, far, far fewer. I mean, to</p>
<p> start with, we have one rate. Under the wholesale sales tax there</p>
<p> were five.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>But there weren't going to be any anomalies under your new system?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that wasn't possible to be achieved, Howard. I mean, I am asking...you</p>
<p> can criticise me for doing a compromise deal....</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>No, not just you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, well, I don't mind if you just, you know,....</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Well, the Democrats....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Okay, well you can criticise it but I ask you the alternatives were</p>
<p> a) to walk away from tax reform altogether which nobody wanted or</p>
<p> have....</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>...or have another election.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Can I tell you the Australian public wants another election like a</p>
<p> hole in the head. They're fed up with elections in this country.</p>
<p> We had one 8 months ago and most Australians to whom I spoke were</p>
<p> saying to me: look, if you can get a sensible deal that delivers most</p>
<p> of what you want with the Democrats, go for it. That's what they</p>
<p> were saying to me. They were saying it to me in spades. And not just</p>
<p> people in my own party, people in the business community. I have been</p>
<p> contacted by numerous people in the business community since I made</p>
<p> the deal with the Democrats, and can I tell you Howard not one of</p>
<p> them said it was a stupid thing to do. They all said good on you.</p>
<p> You got most of what you wanted. It's still a much better package</p>
<p> than the present system. Sure we would have liked the lot but we understand</p>
<p> the realities of the Senate. Now that's been the universal reaction.</p>
<p> Even might I say from people in industries that will have to assimilate</p>
<p> some of the anomalies of which you've spoken.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Right, the Prime Minister's here and we've opened the lines.</p>
<p> If you want to give him a call you can.</p>
<p>[ad break]</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, just before the first caller, we've heard from</p>
<p> the council which is there they say for the disadvantaged in Australia,</p>
<p> ACOSS, today, your package, the package of a compromise package, they</p>
<p> say, and I suppose it wouldn't surprise you, they say is not</p>
<p> fair to low-income earners.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't agree with them and I think ACOSS is going down</p>
<p> the same path as the Australian Labor Party. They're taking themselves</p>
<p> right out of the debate.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Pretty predictable comment.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well how on Earth can a package which provides a real increase in</p>
<p> the pension of 2%, and actually increases the compensation even though</p>
<p> basic food is taken out, how can that be regarded as unfair. I just</p>
<p> think ACOSS unfortunately has got itself into a hole on this issue</p>
<p> and just can't come to terms with the reality that the agreement</p>
<p> we've struck with the Democrats is not only fair but also preserves</p>
<p> the overwhelming elements of the original plan.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Okay John's your first caller, to John. Hello John how are you?</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>[inaudible]</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>The Prime Minister's listening.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, I believed when we voted, I thought that the petrol,</p>
<p> and all these taxes are going to be eliminated like excise, and those</p>
<p> sorts of things.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there's been no changes in relation to petrol. The price</p>
<p> of petrol doesn't rise. For business purposes the prices of petrol</p>
<p> will effectively fall by 7 cents a litre.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>When we first heard the GST came out it was, to me, we were getting</p>
<p> rid of all these hidden taxes.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you're getting rid of the wholesale sales tax in full, and</p>
<p> that will go on the 1st of July in the year 2000. The financial</p>
<p> institutions duty will go a year later. The stamp duty on share transfers</p>
<p> will go as announced. There's been some delay in relation to</p>
<p> some of the State taxes, bank account debits and stamp duty on mortgages</p>
<p> and hire purchase agreements and so forth.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>But petrol stays the same?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But the petrol stays exactly the same.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>All right thanks John for your call. And Craig's next Prime Minister.</p>
<p> Good morning Craig.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p> Good morning Howard. Good morning Prime Minister, how are you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Very well indeed.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p> Mr Howard I would just like to congratulate you on your negotiations</p>
<p> of an amicable agreement between you and the Democrats. Well done.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thank you. I appreciate that very much.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>My pleasure. I just think that people have to realise that people</p>
<p> are getting older. Someone's got to pay the taxes. I only would</p>
<p> assume that income tax rates go higher if we don't this income</p>
<p> coming by taxing everybody if you like, which is a fast area tax.</p>
<p> And I find it hard to believe that businesses are going to lose turnover</p>
<p> and have to put off people because of this tax. I think people will</p>
<p> still get their bottom line if you know what I'm saying.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well they will, and the reason they'll get their bottom lines</p>
<p> is that families will be better off, they will be significantly better</p>
<p> off. Many families will be $40 to $50 a week better off because of</p>
<p> the very sizeable income tax cuts, the increase in family benefits.</p>
<p> And now that food, basic food is GST free, with the removal of the</p>
<p> hidden taxes the prices of some food items will actually come down.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Thanks for your call Craig. And Arvo joins us now. Hello Arvo.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Howard how are you?</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>I'm good. And the Prime Minister wants to hear what you have</p>
<p> to say.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p> Hello Mr Howard. Listen, mate, why don't you have another election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think the public wants another election.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Well I'm part of the public and I do.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, all right, well I respect your view. But you'll respect</p>
<p> the views of your fellow Australians. And the reaction I've had</p>
<p> from people is that they don't want another election.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>The reaction I've had from a lot of people I speak to is they'd</p>
<p> like....they would vote for this GST legislation now coming in.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there's a lot of people who voted Labor didn't vote</p>
<p> for it. No that's true.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>True true, I agree.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah sure. They're not going to change their position.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p> Well why don't you have another one?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Because it think when you can 85 to 90% of what was endorsed, it's</p>
<p> a failure of good government, a failure of leadership, and really</p>
<p> an unfair imposition on the public only 8 months after you've</p>
<p> had an election to go back to the public.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, does it now mean too that tax reform will not be an</p>
<p> issue at the next election.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I would think it will be far less of an issue because....</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Because once in it can't be reversed can it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't believe so.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>Well that's what Kim Beazley said.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't know. I mean I don't know what his position</p>
<p> is. I mean he just waves cans around.</p>
<p>SATTLER:</p>
<p>No but he said before this was introduced, he said if you allow a</p>
<p> GST in that's it, we can't reverse it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that's his position because that's having two bob each</p>
<p> way. He's saying "it's a shocking, outrageous, obscene</p>
<p> thing, but of course I can't reverse it. I'm happy to have</p>
<p> the benefit of it". I mean that</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
