<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8388</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP JOHN LAWS PROGRAM, 2UE SYDNEY 21 JANUARY 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/01/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008388.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E OE PROOF COPY ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE' PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
JOHN LAWS PROGRAM, 2UE, SYDNEY 21 JANUARY 1992<br />
PM: Good moriLng John.<br />
JL: You are running close to time.<br />
PM: I'm right on time. Never been so early.<br />
JL: Absolutely right on time. Is that part of the deal when<br />
you are Prime minister you have to be on time?<br />
PM: I generally try to run on time.<br />
JL: Tell me other ' things about being Prime Minister that<br />
come as a surprise to you.<br />
PM: I Con't thiink any of it is a surprise but it is a<br />
different job than the one I have done for a long time.<br />
You know, it has got many other bits and pieces to it<br />
policy issues which are new and varied. Above all else<br />
I think taking responsibility for the direction of the<br />
thing.<br />
JL: Yeah. Well we saw the pre-recorded, heavily edited<br />
dress rehearsal last night so let's get into the real<br />
thing now. Can you really sit there in front of me this<br />
morning and insist as you did last night and look<br />
Australia in the eye, of which you are quite capable of<br />
doing, and tell us you didn't do any deals with anybody<br />
to get the top job. </p>
<p>PM: No. I didn't do any deals with anybody. It Was a<br />
matter of choice for the Labor Party and it is like most<br />
of these t: hings, I mean you make alliances, friendships<br />
and thinga;. But they are not deals. Deals go to people<br />
getting positions and policies and what have you.<br />
JL: Are they fair dinkum friendships or are they friendships<br />
of convenience?<br />
PM: Oh well, think, you know, you do end up with a certain<br />
core group of supporters in this game and you get a few<br />
added on along the way and sometimes there is more of<br />
them or loss of them, and it just depends on the<br />
circumstances I think.<br />
JL: But you diLdn't do any deals with the left?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JL: What about: the centre left?<br />
PM: No. Nor ' the centre left. The centre left were<br />
substantial supporters of mine.<br />
JL: Not that it really matters mind you.<br />
PM: No.<br />
JL: One would expect to swing it around the way it was swung<br />
around would require a bit of engineering, a bit of<br />
manipulatiLon.<br />
PM: I understand that, but no, nothing which you would call<br />
a deal. rhey know what I generally think about things.<br />
To that exitent they needed to be sure of what I thought<br />
about things. But beyond that, no.<br />
JL: Did you have to alter you attitude to certain things in<br />
order to accommodate them.<br />
PM: I don't think so. I think that the fact that I thought<br />
the economy more recessed than maybe the official family<br />
was telling the Government, the bureaucracy was telling<br />
the Government, struck a cord with some people in the<br />
Caucus and it was that in which they were interested.<br />
And as time wore on they believed that that was true and<br />
therefore a number of groups were interested in what<br />
they thought I might do about it. But beyond those sort<br />
of generalised things, that was about the main.<br />
3L: Anyway, I imagine one of the prime requisites for the<br />
job is to be reasonably flexible. </p>
<p>PM: At least keep your mind open. I think to have an open<br />
mind about things is important. You can get a closed<br />
mind in this game I think. That is, you know,<br />
particularly when you have been the author of policies<br />
and where you are not just putting them in but defending<br />
them. You have got to know when to stop defending<br />
things and when to move on.<br />
JL: Tell me this. The general consensus at the moment seems<br />
to be, and I only came back last Thursday, that you are<br />
not yet looking comfortable in the role of Prime<br />
Minister. Do you think that is a reasonable<br />
observation, again it would be understandable.<br />
PM: I don't know. I think some of the commentators want me<br />
to come out sort of fighting every time they see me. I<br />
think they think I'm on the floor of the House of<br />
Representatives all the time at Question Time. Well<br />
you're not, you're not, and therefore to be thoughtful<br />
about what you say and to be not smothering people in<br />
argument iLs, I think, appropriate for the moment. I'm<br />
feeling my way. I'm listening. I'm trying to get a<br />
grip on where I think the place is going and that is as<br />
I think it should be at the minute.<br />
JL; You say that you are feeling your way again, that is<br />
understandable. is the whole thing a bit overwhelming?<br />
FM: Not really, no it is not overwhelming, I don't think.<br />
JL: It is just another job.<br />
PM: It is another job, but it is a different job, and it's a<br />
job where the ultimate responsibility is yours, with the<br />
direction of the place. I think it is like, the great<br />
burden of these jobs is never the hours or the time, it<br />
is always the responsibility. The responsibility is<br />
what weighs upon you. That is what I find the<br />
difference, but as far as the job, I mean a lot of<br />
people I'm sure that have had this job in the past have<br />
wondered well what should we do. Well that is really<br />
not my problem. I mean, I have got a reasonable idea of<br />
what we should do. But what I think is important is to<br />
tap other people's ideas of what we should do now.<br />
JL: That is a~ n interesting observation People say what<br />
should we do, that is really not your problem. I would<br />
have thought it was absolutely and totally your problem. </p>
<p>PM: No what we do though is our problem, but I'm saying<br />
knowing what to do, that is having an idea of what to<br />
do, and what I'm doing with these round or meeting<br />
which we have had with the business community anid the<br />
trade unions and others last week and this week is to<br />
tap into community opinion about how they see the<br />
economy and society and what they believe the remedy<br />
should : be.<br />
JL: Ok, you've got in round terms, 12 months to get the<br />
place mDving again. is it possible to do it in 12<br />
months?<br />
PM: I think so. I think that a is a possibility.<br />
JL; Only a possibility?<br />
PM: More than a possibility. Provided the Government takes<br />
the right policy steps.<br />
JL: well you are the Government, aren't you?<br />
PM: That's right. And that is why it is very important to<br />
see what people think. I mean, we tend to think that<br />
most of the various interest groups, they come our way<br />
at various times and what they have to say is pretty<br />
much on record, or pretty much been said to us a month<br />
ago or we nave some idea of it. but it is nice to hear<br />
their contemporary view and hear it direct. And you<br />
can pick things up which you haven't heard before, and<br />
I think we have done quite a bit of that in the last<br />
week.<br />
JL: Ok, well you say providing the Government takes the<br />
right steps. From that we could glean that in the past<br />
the Government hasn't taken the right steps.<br />
PM: well I think, all governments can only feel their way<br />
through a situation and with this recession, I mean we<br />
have felt our way, we rely upon the statistics as they<br />
come in, you rely upon anecdotal evidence, you are<br />
generally just trying to reel your way through.<br />
JL: Ok, well the same people got it wrong before. What<br />
kind of assurance that they won't get it wrong again?<br />
PH: Well I think the only way now is up. And therefore<br />
what the Government will do will be to take the economy<br />
up, to take the place up. So one should hope that we<br />
get the general direction right.<br />
JL: When you say the only way is up, does that mean that<br />
anybody could get it up now, it is so flat that it<br />
wouldn't matter who was there it would go up? </p>
<p>PM: Oh no, I think it will require changes to bringing it<br />
up faster than it might otherwise naturally do, and<br />
leaving it to its own natural devices, I don't think it<br />
is good enough right now. I think we have to do more<br />
and assessing what to do is what we are about now.<br />
JL; Yeah. What did you do wrong, or what did they do wrong<br />
that needs to be changed?<br />
PM: it is not they, it is me. I was the Treasurer for a<br />
long time. I think that there are two things, I mean,<br />
there was first of all the boom in 1988 had to be the<br />
spending spree and the rise in activity in imports had<br />
to be slowed down. We lifted interest rates to do it.<br />
I think we have left interest rates on probably too<br />
long, -they didn't come off quickly enough through 1990<br />
and 1991. Remember this, I took interest rates off for<br />
the first time in January 1990, exactly two years ago<br />
this month, to avoid this recession.<br />
JL: Ok, but you didn't succeed.<br />
PM: but I don't think we took them off quickly enough. And<br />
secondly there was what the Americans call the asset<br />
price overhand.<br />
JL: Let's keep away from that stuff.<br />
PM: I know, but let's off, but let's say what it is. It is<br />
a belief in inflation. A belief that if you bought a<br />
couple of shops, or you bought a flat, or you bought<br />
another house, that inflation would kick it along and<br />
over a period of time without any effort on your part<br />
you would be more wealthy. And that belief in<br />
inflation was there while inflation was high. But now<br />
inflation is low and we have seen asset prices fall it<br />
is that fall in asset prices which has knocked a lot of<br />
business confidence around and I think as properties<br />
have been tipped to the market both here and in the<br />
United States and in Britain and in Canada and<br />
countries like us. we have all got recessions now at<br />
the same time that it is that fall in asset prices<br />
which I think has really knocked confidence about at<br />
least to unemployment. When unemployment starts to<br />
rise, people then start to worry about their spending,<br />
so they cut their spending and so the thing generally<br />
winds down. So it is a combination of the two things.<br />
The interest rate rises and the speed of the decline in<br />
them and this big belief in inflation and the collapse<br />
or inflation or expectations which has seen asset<br />
prices fall and<br />
JL: Well all of that is very natural. I mean, if inflation<br />
exists you can understand people who want to invest,<br />
wanting to capitalise on the tact that inflation is<br />
there. So the public can't really be blamed for that.<br />
You say that you didn't take interest rates of f early<br />
enough, are you going to take them of f now? </p>
<p>PM: Well we have, we just took them of f another 1 per cent.<br />
JL: Are you going to do more?<br />
PM: Not at the moment. we are at 7 1/ 2 per cent and I<br />
can't remember how long it was ago that we had, if you<br />
like, bill rates at 7 1/ 2 per cent. So they are down a<br />
long way. They are down ii percentage points from<br />
1990. They are a long way down. I mean, I suppose<br />
what I'm trying to say, John, is this, that if it were<br />
not for a long running belier in inflation and asset<br />
values and the rest, the recession wouldn't be as deep<br />
and if the banks who went into a basically a very big<br />
lending spree in the late 1980s because of collapsing<br />
asset prices they've pulled their head in. They won't<br />
be lending as they were lending. And the combinations<br />
of the two has produced a recess ion of greater depth<br />
than any of us believed.<br />
JL: There are 23,000 people in this country waiting for<br />
refugee status which can take a long time. The other<br />
day some more arrived in the West as you know, claiming<br />
to be refugees and even called refugees by some, there<br />
is no guiarantee that they are in fact that. Why should<br />
we continue to allow these people to stay in our<br />
country when our country is economically unstable, it<br />
needs all the help it can get and we have unemployment<br />
running at a dangerous level and we import more people<br />
into the place that we can't employ. Now are you going<br />
to do something about that?<br />
PM: Well this is where our border was breached by a group<br />
of people who arrived by boat unannounced.<br />
JL: well so did the other 23,000.<br />
PM: Well somie of them have come in all sorts of ways. But<br />
we are now assessing those to see what their real<br />
status is.<br />
JL: And if -they are not refugees, are you going to send<br />
them back?<br />
PM: Well I will see what the report says. I don't want to<br />
pre-judge it. We have got people now up there speaking<br />
to them. But on the general point about migration<br />
which I think is what you were directing your remarks<br />
to, we ] iave seen the program change over the last half<br />
a dozen years to rise rather sharply in the late<br />
particularly when we saw a need to bring in skill sin<br />
demand, one of the things which was in evidence between<br />
1985 and 1990 was skills shortages in the economy, and<br />
we had a large complementation of skills coming from<br />
the migration program. In a slower economy, you don't<br />
need that skills supplementation and what the<br />
Government has been doing has been slowing the program </p>
<p>up, and. it has slowed rather considerably now from its<br />
peak of say about 1988.<br />
JL: Why don't you stop it until the place is right<br />
economically?<br />
PM: well I don't think that is the right thing to do. I<br />
think that you can't just turn these programs on and<br />
of f.<br />
JL: Why?<br />
PM: Well because there is a whole system of people being<br />
assessed over a period of time, being interviewed<br />
between the various categories of migration whether<br />
they be business migrants, skills in demand, family<br />
reunion. The operation of these various categories<br />
which are different than each of the other and to just<br />
simply wind the program off and try and wind it back<br />
up, you won't be able to wind it back up. And it is<br />
not very easy, and it is very harsh often to wind it<br />
right back.<br />
JL: Harsh on whom?<br />
PM: well it is harsh on. I think, the people who have been<br />
part of the process to date.<br />
JL: Well maybe it is, but surely your first responsibility<br />
and our collective first responsibility is to this<br />
country, and you know that politics is all about<br />
perception and if we are perceived to be in such a<br />
condition that we have almost I million unemployed<br />
people, it seems to some extraordinary that we continue<br />
to import people from other parts of the world who,<br />
too, ar-e likely to become unemployed.<br />
PM: Well some will, no doubt. But it has been a long term<br />
program, a long term program to complement the natural<br />
growth of our population and governments in their<br />
wisdom have increased it and decreased it as things<br />
have changed, but they have never cut it out.<br />
JL: Governments aren't always wise. Because the Government<br />
did it in its wisdom, there might be a limit to its<br />
wisdom as indicated by the situation in which this<br />
country now, finds itself.<br />
PM: But I think they have been wise, I mean it has kicked<br />
our population along, the place is a more interesting<br />
vibrant place because or the migration program.<br />
JL; Yeah, but I fail to see what value there is in having a<br />
whole lot of interesting unemployed people around the<br />
place.<br />
PM: Well it won't be all unemployed. </p>
<p>JL: But there are a lot of unemployed. There are a million<br />
unemployed people in Australian seeking work and we<br />
continue to bring people in from other parts of the<br />
world. Now the perception is that that is stupid and<br />
unfair to the people who, really are the responsibility<br />
of the Government.<br />
PM: But it is a medium term program, well it is a long term<br />
program with a medium term perspective and I think that<br />
the thing about it is, you have got to decide whether<br />
you think this country can take a share of people from<br />
abroad. Is advantaged by a more diverse and larger<br />
population and if you believe that, a program should<br />
exist, and perhaps it should change in its quality and<br />
its quantity as time goes by, but most governments have<br />
changed it at various times. We had huge numbers come<br />
into Australian and then it dropped off to much smaller<br />
numbers and it has picked up as prosperity picked up,<br />
and whEtre there have been difficult times it has<br />
dropped back. Can I say the more general point is by<br />
and large I think it has been accepted by most<br />
Australian. The migration program has been good to<br />
Australia, has made it a more interesting place, made<br />
it a more economically robust place. And it has been<br />
very important at various times to complement skills,<br />
the business migration program is now bringing quite a<br />
lot of people from various parts of the world.<br />
JL: Ah yes, we saw what a rort that was being turned into<br />
by people coming here from Hong Kong and other places<br />
buying real estate and going home, saying they were<br />
unable to make their business investment and yet that<br />
was part of the package.<br />
PM: But thEre is a lot here though, John, there is a lot<br />
here.<br />
JL: Of course there are and when you say that it has been<br />
accepted I agree with you I think that it has been<br />
accepted. I'm not sure that it is accepted now,<br />
because! it-has been accepted doesn't mean that it is<br />
going t~ o continue to be accepted.<br />
PM: Well there has always been a debate about the numbers<br />
whenever the economy goes off the boil and that is fair<br />
enough. And I think the Government has taken note of<br />
that and that is why the program has been scaled back<br />
in the last few years and we have got a review of the<br />
program underway now. And then in April, or about<br />
April, which is the normal cycle of these reviews, we<br />
will cconsider the intake again for the coming year.<br />
JL: What is your recommendation?<br />
PM: Well I will wait and see what the review turns up. </p>
<p>JL: Well assessing it at this stage, you see, you say that<br />
most people accept it. Most people that I talk to<br />
don't accept it and I think that, with respect to you,<br />
I speak: more of the population of Australia than you<br />
do.<br />
PM: You certainly speak to them, whether you speak with<br />
them I'm not sure about that.<br />
JL: Well they speak to me.<br />
PM: Well that's true, that's true.<br />
JL: They pick up the telephone and dial the number.<br />
PM: That is right. I don't doubt that you have a<br />
perception, and probably a correct one, that people<br />
think the program should respond to difficult times,<br />
and I think it should.<br />
JL: Shouldn't you respond to the people?<br />
PM: Yes, but I'm not going to pre-judge what is a<br />
reasonably sophisticated process of review every year,<br />
and then the Minister, in this case Gerry Hand, will<br />
bring a recommendation to the Cabinet.<br />
JL: But on the information you have know, what would your<br />
recommendation be?<br />
PM: Well I'm not going to make a recommendation. I won't<br />
be recommending. It will be Gerry recommending to the<br />
Government rather than me recommending to him. But the<br />
program has been coming back and I would be surprised<br />
if there was a discernible trend in any other<br />
direction.<br />
JL: But down?<br />
PM: But down? But when I say that, I don't mean down the<br />
way some of our colleagues in the Opposition mean down<br />
because I think from them we will see a repeat of what<br />
we saw in 1988 which was basically about how we<br />
shouldn't have more Asians here, we shouldn't have<br />
Asians in this country. I mean, if you scratch most of<br />
these characters what you get is a little bit of that<br />
sort of talk from them and that won't be motivating us.<br />
JL: No. Well of course it is not specifically Asians, its<br />
people that we have to employ, that is the problem, it<br />
doesn't matter where they come from.<br />
PM: I know, I understand that but from the Liberal Party's<br />
point of view the sub-plot in the late 1980s was about<br />
Asians. </p>
<p>JL: OK, prior to my going away in December, I read a story<br />
about * a pie manufacturer who warned us that the great<br />
Australian meat pie might soon ship to China, tasty<br />
products, warned that high labour costs, high taxes<br />
expensiLve food ingredients would force lots of<br />
businesses off-shore. Now it didn't seem very<br />
important at the time, but when you look into it, in<br />
china's Xnandung Province they will give you the land<br />
to build your factory. They will provide you with<br />
labour at $ A160 a month and offer a flat company tax<br />
rate of 16 per cent. Now the $ A160 a month is nonsense<br />
in this country. But why don't we consider doing<br />
things like they are doing in China. We have got<br />
plenty of land why don't we give it to people in order<br />
that they can create enterprises and businesses here.<br />
And why, don't we offer them a special company tax to<br />
come in. from other parts of the world instead of us<br />
going off-shore, bring them here give them the land we<br />
have got plenty of land?<br />
PM: Well the thing is, they are a developing country and<br />
they are re doing all the classic things which<br />
developing countries have done. you know, Korea was<br />
doing that some time ago, and now they are doing it.<br />
I'm sure it happened in Taiwan.<br />
JL: Do we ever give land away, I never heard it was giving<br />
land away?<br />
PM: No we don't, I don't think. I mean, certainly the<br />
Commonwealth doesn't. But I mean, the States have<br />
industrial parks and they let people have access to<br />
them.<br />
JL: When I say giving away, I don't mean give it away<br />
forever. Give a lease arrangement to these people, but<br />
at a proper rate to encourage business to come here,<br />
why don't we do that?<br />
PM: Well, because I think it is important to understand<br />
what we are. This is a developed place. We run a<br />
sophisticated society and public sector. services here<br />
are in evidence wherever you look, whether it be<br />
hospitals, roads, or railways, or what have you. And<br />
we finance this public sector with the second lowest<br />
rate of tax in the world bar a decimal point. We are a<br />
decimal -Point higher than Japan. We are the second<br />
lowest tax country in the 27 countries of the OECD.<br />
now you can't provide this sort of public sector with<br />
these sort of services and this standard of living with<br />
the tax rate very much below that. So if you want to<br />
give big tax breaks to developing companies, what you<br />
have got to do is put tax hikes on ordinary people. </p>
<p>JL: Why can't it be done for a short period of time?<br />
PM: Well it: all costs and once you do these things, that is<br />
it. you set a new benchmark. I mean, you can't<br />
compete with them because you see<br />
JL: Why can't you?<br />
PM: Well let me just give you an example. Now I was<br />
talking to a company last week. They went to Malaysia<br />
because it had a tax holiday for 7 years so they said<br />
we set up a business in Malaysia unfortunately they<br />
said the 7th year is up so now we are going to Sri<br />
Lanka which promises a tax holiday for 15 years. That<br />
is no tax for 15 years. Well if we try and run this<br />
country on a basis of no tax for 15 years, you won't<br />
keep this sort of society of ours together.<br />
JL: No, but this is a more attractive place to be so surely<br />
with somae sort of incentive.<br />
PM: But we don't need to do the things which those people,<br />
in other words, rely upon wage rates and labour<br />
conditions that those companies rely upon in those<br />
countries. We produce different things.<br />
JL: But we need to do something.<br />
PM: We are doing it. We literally exported our heads off<br />
all through the 1980s.<br />
JL: You can't say that because we are developed country<br />
that we don't want to continue to develop.<br />
PM: No, but -all the developed countries, we have got a<br />
corporate tax rate of 39 per cent with full dividend<br />
imputation. In other words, you don't pay tax on<br />
dividends twice. Germany has got a corporate rate in<br />
the ' 50s.. Most of the countries we compare ourselves<br />
with have got corporate rates like us, Britain, the<br />
United St~ ates, what have you. They don't have 15 per<br />
cent tax rates. Or zero tax rates as business<br />
incentivets because they are developed places and you<br />
can't runk your developed society on zero tax rates.<br />
JL: OK, well if we can't do that for people who want to<br />
create businesses from other parts of the world, what<br />
sort of incentive could we offer to the people who are<br />
one by one going to the wall, and they are one by one<br />
going to the wall, here in Australian. Surely at this<br />
time, we should be offering them some kind of incentive<br />
to keep their business instead of taking it to Sri<br />
Lanka or Singapore. </p>
<p>PM: Well the best incentive offered to them is growth, is<br />
to get back to rates of growth and that is what the<br />
point of the Economic Statement will be about. to<br />
restore growth to the economy, to get the economy out<br />
of the recession.<br />
JL: How do you do that?<br />
PM: Into recovery. Well it won't be long before you will<br />
see. EBut we are now assessing how best to do that, but<br />
one of the things which we have obviously done in the<br />
last two years is reduce interest rates, which<br />
themselves will have their effect upon the economy and<br />
we will be doing other things which we think are<br />
sensible in the short term but are also supportive, if<br />
you like, of the structure of the place over the long<br />
term.<br />
JL: Like what sort of thing?<br />
PM: Well I don't want to go through..<br />
JL: Well just give me an idea of what sort of thing?<br />
PM: Well some of the public infrastructure, for a start,<br />
which wets left to languish in the ' 80s as we cut the<br />
public sector back, and which can take the place of<br />
some of the private investment we're now not getting.<br />
In some of those areas we're looking closely now.<br />
JL: Does that mean increasing the public sector?<br />
PM: Not particularly, but it means for the moment in areas<br />
of public infrastructure where there are needs, and<br />
where they are an important part of the efficiency of<br />
the economy, then they are areas I think which we can<br />
look. But the main thing is to provide growth to the<br />
economy and that's the best thing we can give the<br />
business sector, small, medium and large. And there's<br />
not much point in saying well here's a low tax rate,<br />
but sorry there's not much growth around, because if<br />
you look at the small business community in particular,<br />
both them survive on growth.<br />
JL.-. By-growth, you-simply mean that somebody who has,<br />
they're making matchboxes, you're going to make the<br />
place so efficient that people are going to want to buy<br />
more matchboxes?<br />
PM: Well we're finding, firstly to lift activity and demand<br />
so theres a demand for product in Australia and people<br />
start hiring people again to produce product.<br />
JL: How do you do that? </p>
<p>PM: Just by lifting activity. We did it after 1983-4,<br />
JL: Well if' it was that simple why wasn't it done before?<br />
PM: Well in. 1983-84, when we came to office after that<br />
recession, we turned it around within about 12 months.<br />
And I hope that in the same way we can do that now.<br />
JL: We'll have to do it quickly because from what I hear,<br />
and correct me if I'm wrong, but from what I hear from<br />
business people we are not in a position to be able to<br />
trade competitively with other countries, we are<br />
disadvantaged here in Australia?<br />
PM: I don't think that's true. Because what is happening<br />
and has happened, we are now running a very large goods<br />
and services surplus, we are running a huge merchandise<br />
trade surplus. A lot of Australian companies I have<br />
spoken t: o in the last two weeks have said, we've made a<br />
shift, because the domestic market is down we've made a<br />
more rapid shift to exports and we'll stay in exports.<br />
Now we aire doing that because the place is largely<br />
competitive, its competitive in wage rates, its<br />
competitive by the exchange rate, its a generally<br />
competitive product that I'm will to support.<br />
JL: Well, why are we in recession?<br />
PM: Well we are in a recession in the domestic economy,<br />
while the international economy is also not doing well,<br />
the truth is we can eat a bigger share of it and that's<br />
one of the things which is at least holding employment<br />
where it is and keeping the place growing where it is<br />
is the fact that we have a thing which we never used to<br />
have called net exports. In other words we are now<br />
exporting a large part of our product, particularly in<br />
manufactures.<br />
JL: OK that's fine, and I understand it is very important<br />
but its very hard to convince people who haven't got<br />
any money and have got kids, and they haven't got any<br />
clothes and they are flat out having a house, that<br />
because somebody is selling something overseas its<br />
going to be to their advantage, its not to their<br />
advantage now. Surely the domestic economy, as you<br />
refer to it, is at this stage in your career and in the<br />
history o'f this country the most important thing?<br />
PM: Absolutely.<br />
JL: Well what do you do about that? It's all very well to<br />
talk about the exports </p>
<p>PM: Well, exports are what give you production and there<br />
would be a lot of people employed in factories out<br />
there now, probably listening to us, who are doing so<br />
for products which are going to be exported, and if<br />
they were not going to be exported their jobs wouldn't<br />
be there. So exports have filled a very large void in<br />
this cycle and that's why these export growth numbers<br />
and the merchandise trade surplus is very important to<br />
us, they are complementary to domestic growth.<br />
JL: Well its not working<br />
PM But it doesn't invalidate your point and that is that<br />
the domestic economy has to grow more, we can't have<br />
the thing, if you like, in the negative, that is<br />
contracting which is what its been. It's contracted by<br />
about three per cent in the last year and a half or so.<br />
And that:' s what's produced the angst and produced the<br />
unemploynent. We have got to get that back to positive<br />
rates of' growth.<br />
JL: OK well how do you do that domestically?<br />
PM: Well a combination of I think, a change in confidence<br />
which comes from a willingness on part the of the<br />
Government to let the economy grow. That people in the<br />
business community know now that the Government wants<br />
the economy to grow. Where in 1988 and 1989 and 1990<br />
they thought the Government wanted the economy to slow<br />
down which we did. We now want it to grow, and we have<br />
now provided one of the instruments of that growth,<br />
much lower interest rates, and we can provide a more<br />
direct stimulus to the economy coming from the<br />
Governments own policies, and that's what we are now<br />
examining with the business community as to how best to<br />
cast those so they complement, if you like, interest<br />
rate reductions. To try to induce and engender a high<br />
degree of business confidence to get people out there<br />
spending again and to pick the place up.<br />
JL: Prime Minister Paul Keating back to the subject of<br />
Australia and its immediate future domestically, and I<br />
think that you agree that that's what matters at the<br />
moment. Certainly that's what matters to the people<br />
listening to this radio program around Australia.<br />
PM: Exactly. To get back to growth and to get the place<br />
moving again, to get employment shifting and to do it<br />
as quickly as possible. That's got to be our first<br />
priority. </p>
<p>JL: OK you can understand the frustration of people and<br />
confusion of people when you can go into a supermarket<br />
and yout can buy imported canned tomatoes, I think from<br />
Italy, cheaper than you can buy the Australian product.<br />
So here! we have the dilemma of the people who are doing<br />
to tough having the opportunity to buy the product<br />
cheaply but we also have the converse situation of<br />
those producing the product here in Australia not being<br />
able to compete. Why do we import canned tomatoes?<br />
PM: I think a number of reasons. I mean it makes me<br />
furious as it does you I'm sure. It does make you<br />
furious because its just absurd but I think we really<br />
haven't developed as well as we might agriculture<br />
businesses which extend beyond the agriculture into<br />
canning and into promotion and into the efficient<br />
production of canned products often particularly in the<br />
horticulture/ agriculture sort of fruit and<br />
vegetables.<br />
JL: Is that because we are not smart?<br />
PM: Well I don't know. I think it might be the fact that a.<br />
lot of these were done through co-operatives in the<br />
past and the co-operatives flourished well enough<br />
before the trade in these things world wide, there's<br />
now a greater trade in food products and that we<br />
haven't seen the sort of efficiency and competitiveness<br />
coming from the canning of these sort of foods and<br />
their marketing.<br />
JL: OK, well what do you do about that? I mean why<br />
PM: Its a sort of breakdown of entrepreneurship. I mean<br />
there should be in that particular industry more<br />
entrepreneurship I think than there is and its a pity<br />
that people say well its not a pity you saying it but<br />
its a pity its being said, you know what can we do<br />
about the fact that we have got sort of canned tomatoes<br />
from the United States or Italy or Israel or somewhere<br />
like that and you know, I think one of the things we<br />
can do well in Australia is food and food processing.<br />
JL: In order to let us do that, and I know that this is a<br />
simplistiLc point of view but most of mine are, why<br />
can't we put some type of moratorium on non-essential<br />
imports?<br />
PM: Well beca-use what happens then is that people put a<br />
moratorium on our non-essential exports. The trading<br />
world is a very nasty place and once you get into sort<br />
of trade reprisals everybody gets into you. I mean we<br />
are still shipping great stacks of meat to the United<br />
States and Japan and if we were to say </p>
<p>JL: But why are we doing that, because Japan needs it,<br />
that's why they're buying it.<br />
PM: Yes but they can buy it from other places and<br />
JL: And because America needs it<br />
PM: But again it has got other options. I mean if we get<br />
into the trade reprisal business so will they and<br />
that's rnot a goer and the fact is we have got to do<br />
better. It's not their fault that we are not doing<br />
better, in some of these areas we have just got to do<br />
better. Now its happening. You can see it, I was<br />
talking to one chap last week in these rounds of<br />
consultations who has brought together a whole lot of<br />
food products and is now marketing them much more<br />
efficiently in Australia. These were formerly brand<br />
names which had sort of been left by the way-side,<br />
business which were not running efficiently but making<br />
largely food stuffs. Now that's changed for that<br />
particular person and his business and for those<br />
products. And that general change is what we need. In<br />
other words you see an opportunity and go and exploit<br />
it, not just to say well look we can actually import<br />
compete, compete against these imports but actually<br />
export them ourselves.<br />
JL: But are you going to encourage people to do it because<br />
the number of people that come to me directly and<br />
indirectly to tell me that they have had a wonderful<br />
idea that they've wanted to start a business doing<br />
somethin~ g here in Australia, and have been unable to<br />
get co-operation from the Government and they end up<br />
doing it: elsewhere and successfully. Now what are you<br />
going to do about that?<br />
PM: Well I think it's happening I mean you know and again<br />
another company I spoke to last week has just taken<br />
over Petersville, this is Pacific-Dunlop has just taken<br />
over Petersville which is a big food producer and that<br />
includes Edgell and all those business Edgell, you<br />
know, peas and beans and these things<br />
JL: and tomatoes<br />
PM: and hopefully now with a larger company, a greater<br />
understanding of the value of the product it produces,<br />
its capacity~ to sell into the largely growing South-<br />
East Asian market, we will see now the marketing of<br />
those products but we haven't seen enough of the export<br />
opportunities being obvious to people, investing in<br />
them, getting an existing business and making it more<br />
efficient, marketing the things better in Australia, I<br />
mean its often true of the large supermarket, they have<br />
often sa: Ld to me you can't get people to quote the </p>
<p>supply a lot of the food lines that just don't quote<br />
because they think they will get too tied up to Coles<br />
or too tired up to Woolworths so they don't quote and<br />
so what: happens they end up taking stuff from Italy or<br />
from Po'rtugal or somewhere like that.<br />
JL: Would the Government be in a position to subsidise<br />
producers of those kinds of products that have unfair<br />
competition if it is considered unfair from overseas?<br />
PM: Well, we don't subsidise agricultural produce in<br />
Australia.<br />
JL: I know we don't, but why don't we?<br />
PM: Well because when we do it becomes a cost on the rest<br />
of us. In other words, you know, I mean we are getting<br />
the very thing we are complaining about in the GATT. 1<br />
mean the reason why our wheat producers are not being<br />
able to sell now as profitably in the markets is<br />
because of subsidies from the European Commission and<br />
the Unit~ ed States. Now if we get in the same game the<br />
thing is they can outplay us at that game, theres no<br />
point in us getting in.<br />
JL: Then we can't compete?<br />
PM: We don't have a deep enough pocket to go into an export<br />
subsidy war and wouldn't want to.<br />
JL: OK well let's get back to..<br />
PM: And that's why, can I just say in the GATT in the<br />
Uruguay round, the General Agreement on Trade and<br />
Tariffs where all this is being discussed at the<br />
moment, we're saying keep the markets free from<br />
pollution, keep them open, keep them free from this<br />
export subsidies, give the honest producer a chance.<br />
Now if we were to say well look, forget all that<br />
rhetoric we didn't really mean that what we are going<br />
to do now is start subsidising canned tomatoes and<br />
canned this and something else then the whole game goes<br />
bad and I think it will work against Australia over the<br />
long terra.<br />
JL: So what do we do? Stop canning tomatoes and do<br />
something else?<br />
PM: No. Do it efficiently. What we should do is someone<br />
say look I've got a tomato here which is as good as any<br />
other tomato, I can put in a can for this price<br />
providing I have an efficient business<br />
JL: Yes but then you have difficulty doing it because of<br />
work practices and all sorts of added tariffs here </p>
<p>PM: Well the good management smooths all those things out.<br />
I mean the huge shift in productivity which we are<br />
seeing in businesses today is coming from the fact that<br />
good Managers getting rid of work practices which are<br />
bad. See, a good management which actually make any of<br />
these businesses competitive.<br />
JL: Despite the trade union movement?<br />
PM: Not despite them, with their support. I mean by and<br />
large the trade unions are knocking out restrictive<br />
work I mean if there's one thing which has come<br />
through four to three days of very intense meetings now<br />
is the almost every hour declaration by managers of<br />
major companies and small companies of the changes in<br />
enterprise bargaining and workplace reform.<br />
JL: Because the union movement is becoming more cooperative?<br />
PM: Yes absolutely because they are saying lets not only<br />
keep our jobs lets make the place better.<br />
JL: What about the 17.5% holiday loading which is a laugh,<br />
and laugrhed at all over the world?<br />
PM: Well a lot of other places in the world have got it to,<br />
its in the United States<br />
JL: Not at 17.5% its not.<br />
PM: Well its every higher I think in some places.<br />
JL: But that doesn't make it right?<br />
PM: Well you know why its there, because most people<br />
earned, often earn in their normal working week more<br />
than the standards weekly wage because they get a bit<br />
of overt: Lme<br />
JL: Some, sorme not all<br />
PM: So when t~ hey go on holidays there is a compensation.<br />
JL: Yes<br />
PM: This is a. feature of many, many economies.<br />
JL: But the mian who introduced it even says its stupid now.<br />
A bit late now but he even says its stupid now.<br />
PM: Who said that?<br />
JL: Clyde Cameron. </p>
<p>PM: Clyde, well I didn't know he said that but look the<br />
main thing is labour costs in total and labour costs in<br />
total i~ n Australia now by OECD standards are low. I<br />
mean it~ s another thing that has been said over and over<br />
again in the last three or four days in the last week<br />
by people running businesses, look this is now<br />
basically a low labour cost country. John that is the<br />
truth, this is a low labour cost country which includes<br />
holiday leave loading.<br />
JL: Well it is and that's why Japanese motor companies and<br />
others want to set up large factories here because it<br />
is becoming a low labour country.<br />
PM: And that includes the holiday leave loading on these<br />
things.<br />
JL: Yes, it would be better still if we didn't have the<br />
holiday leave loading though wouldn't it?<br />
PM: Well I don't necessarily think that's right. I mean I<br />
think, you know, if someone goes off on their annual<br />
leave they don't take a big drop in pay.<br />
JL: What abcout penalty rates on the week-end though? For<br />
working Saturday's, whoever said that Saturday is<br />
different from Friday or Thursday?<br />
PM: Well, now this is an old hobby horse one of yours I<br />
know, I know.<br />
JL: Its a good one<br />
PM: You're like a dog at a bone on these penalty rates.<br />
Look, they are changing, they are changing over time,<br />
they perhaps should change more slowly in some places I<br />
agree particularly in the hospitality industry but I<br />
think a bit of that is changing.<br />
JL: Are you going to encourage the change?<br />
PM: Well part of my job now is to make this a competitive<br />
labour cost country and I did that across the board, it<br />
was part of my job in the 1980s to get inflation down,<br />
we have now got a 3% inflation rate instead of a<br />
inflationL rate and that was in a large part<br />
accommodated by shifts in wages so its not my job to<br />
run bull-at-a-gate at one particular thing<br />
JL: But nobody wants you to do that, but could we receive<br />
some sort of guarantee that you will give your careful<br />
consideration to penalty rates?<br />
PM: Your a great one on guarantees you are. </p>
<p>JL: Yes its: very important its very important to me<br />
and penalty rates stop people getting work.<br />
PM: Well look, I can see that the structure of penalty<br />
rates are not always conducive to employment and<br />
productivity but changing them is not a simple matter<br />
the Government particularly can change overnight.<br />
JL: No but You've got friends.<br />
PM: Yes well I hope I've got a few.<br />
JL: Have a quite talk to Bill.<br />
PM: Poor old Bill, you'd get him to do everything.<br />
JL: Well I maean he is the man to do it because by having<br />
those.<br />
PM: Well you get him in, next time you get him in you put<br />
it on him.<br />
JL: OK I wil. l but in the meantime you might put in a word<br />
for me because you're keeping young people out of work<br />
and the same thing in the United States. If you want<br />
to go to a restaurant in the evening or at lunch time<br />
you drive up the to the restaurant, get out of your car<br />
somebody parks it.<br />
PM: Look the whole service sector in the United States is<br />
far more<br />
JL: Fantastic?<br />
PM: Sophisticated than here.<br />
JL: That's right.<br />
PM: And we have got to learn to be like that.<br />
JL: Ok and people are doing it Saturday nights, Sunday<br />
nights and their lunch time and they're doing it for<br />
what they get in tips. No you couldn't do that in<br />
Australia because you would have to join the Transport<br />
Workers Union before you could drive the bloody car.<br />
Now that's stupid isn't it.<br />
PM: Well I think that the proof of the pudding is in the<br />
eating. They have a service sector which is a vast<br />
employer, I mean we do to but theirs is greater and the<br />
services are more varied and more sophisticated.<br />
JL: But you see a bunch of young kids could set up valet<br />
parking as they insist on calling it in America, and be<br />
contributors to the economy but making money and </p>
<p>keeping them gainfully occupied instead of hanging<br />
around sticking needles in their arms, but they can't<br />
do it because of some stupid work practice or having to<br />
belong to some union and pay union fees.<br />
PM: Well that's not necessarily true. I mean a lot of<br />
people are working in places which are not unionised.<br />
It doesn't stop people working.<br />
JL: How long do you think it would take before the TWU<br />
wasn't down on people who set up valet parking outside<br />
restaurants? About a day and a half?<br />
PM: No, no I don't think its going to worry the TWU very<br />
much. The truth is as long as it doesn't happen<br />
because it hasn't occurred to people. I mean we Just<br />
don't have these sort of services here. I mean in the<br />
US<br />
JL: It has occurred to me.<br />
PM: I know because you travel and you experience it. But<br />
you can see there was a time when there wasn't<br />
propriety car parks, you know car parks operated as<br />
businesses in Australia that happened in the United<br />
States many, many decades ago, its been with us a<br />
couple of decades only and I think, you know, we will<br />
see a much greater sophistication in services, personal<br />
care things.<br />
JL: Ok but you can only do that with the co-operation of<br />
the trade union movement?<br />
PM: John don't underestimate the co-operation. I mean we<br />
are seeing, this is not rhetoric, we're seeing now such<br />
mammoth changes in productivity and work place reform<br />
the likes of which most businesses could not have<br />
contemplated a decade ago, could never have<br />
contemplated and it is why Toyota is coming to<br />
Australia. Toyota motor company, probably amongst the<br />
most efficient in the world and which is going to set<br />
up a $ 400M state of the art plant in this country.<br />
It's not doing it because it thinks labour relations<br />
are bad, they know that productivity is good, they know<br />
that.. the-trade unionsare . co. operating and we are<br />
making great strides.<br />
JL: That's right, but I have watched the progress of that<br />
from fairly close quarters and its been interesting to<br />
note the reaction of the trade union movement who have<br />
been more than co-operative. Now obviously they are<br />
smart because Toyota obviously are going to employ a<br />
lot of people in Australia, now that kind of cooperation<br />
is the sort of thing that will help to get<br />
the place back. But it means that the unionists, the </p>
<p>trade union movement has got to co-operate with the<br />
Government doesn't it?<br />
PM: It does and what I'm saying to you is that it has, and<br />
that's why the inflation rate is 3% and that's why<br />
interest rates are<br />
JL: Ok but tell my why.<br />
PM: If inflation was 10% interest rates would be 13/ 14.<br />
JL: Its great to have 3% inflation. One of the reasons it<br />
is three per cent is nobody is spending any money and<br />
one of the reasons is nobody's got any money.<br />
PM: The main reason is wage change in the 80s and the<br />
second reason is, in part, the deflation coming from<br />
the recession. But its only a part, a very large part,<br />
the largest part was a decline in inflation coming from<br />
wage changes.<br />
JL: Yes, but: obviously inflation is going to be low if<br />
nobody has got any money to spend.<br />
PM: Well, that's not true. We came out of the 1982-83<br />
recessio~ n flat on our backs with a 10% inflation rate.<br />
JL: That's true. What about the engineering company that<br />
can buy Australian made BHP steel cheaper in Singapore<br />
than it can buy it in Australia? That's slightly<br />
bigger than tomatoes.<br />
PM: True and I think we need competition in steel like we<br />
do in everything else and I think it is a great pity<br />
that we have to import certain varieties of steels<br />
because they are not available here.<br />
JL Yes but this is Australian made BHP steel which can be<br />
brought cheaper in Singapore $ 700 a ton in Singapore,<br />
$ 1000 a -ton here. Now how can you allow that to<br />
happen? Not-that its your direct responsibility.<br />
PM: No its not my responsibility, but look obviously, I<br />
don't know that the numbers are actually right I can<br />
only.. take.. your. word-. for.. those..<br />
JL: Well do.<br />
PM: It may be! its been part of an export deal, a package<br />
deal which BHP has done a sort of shop deal for steel<br />
to some supplier in South-East Asia which they are now<br />
supplying back. But I'd be surprised, well pretty<br />
surprised. if you could buy BHP steel cheaper abroad<br />
than you buy it here. </p>
<p>JL: Well you can, you can buy it in Singapore for $ 700 a<br />
ton as opposed to $ 1000 a ton here.<br />
PM: Well no doubt that someone in BHP will hear this<br />
conversation and give us an answer.<br />
JL: If the answer is yes that is a fact, what can you do<br />
about it?<br />
PM: Well I -think BHP would say it seeks to be competitive<br />
inside -the Australian economy and supplying product.<br />
The complaint against it is it doesn't supply enough<br />
product, enough of various types of product that it<br />
should, but there is no doubt the export markets are<br />
very competitive and if you've got people saying, well<br />
look you can have an Australian job at BHP we export<br />
steel but we've got to export it cheaper than we have<br />
been exporting it then BHP will probably taken the view<br />
that we want to keep that employment and we want to<br />
keep those exports. So its losing profitability and<br />
margin exporting but better to have the product export<br />
and have the jobs than not have it all and that's<br />
probably the position right now.<br />
JL: Yes except they are paying the price here in Australia<br />
and obviously they are going to suffer long term<br />
because people are simply bringing it back from<br />
Singapore cheaper than they can get in Australia.<br />
PM: Well look, I mean the international steel market is now<br />
becoming over supplied, it is very competitive out<br />
there and there is not there is probably price falls<br />
and theres discounting in all markets.<br />
JL: There's a dreadful expression that has come into our<br />
language and that I hope you'll never use, when people<br />
talk about a level playing field which seems to be all<br />
the go, why are we doing that with a level playing<br />
field when nobody else seems to be?<br />
PM: I don't -think we are. I mean, I think anyone who<br />
believes there's a level playing field off-shore<br />
outside of Australia is basically deluding themselves,<br />
I mean its catch as catch can out there and survival of<br />
the. fittst..-and-the . smartest . and I think that if anyone<br />
believes it is fair and reasonable and above board and<br />
level they are having themselves on.<br />
JL: Ok well we are about to run out of time and I know you<br />
have got a lot to do with your day jut to rap it up,<br />
the illegal immigrants, these boat people, apart from<br />
costing us a fortune in searching, if we find out that<br />
they are not what they claim to be will you send them<br />
home? </p>
<p>PM: Well I -don't want to pre-judge that.<br />
JL: Would that be your desire?<br />
PM: I don't want to pre-judge that let's wait and see how<br />
they interview, where they're from, what their claims<br />
are and there's a very clear process there in dealing<br />
with people who cross our borders and there is no<br />
reason -why that process won't work just as well on this<br />
occasion as on any other occasion.<br />
JL: So it would be likely that if they are not what they<br />
appear -to be that they won't stay in this country?<br />
PM: Well again that is pre-judging them and I don't want to<br />
do that because to do it in the position I hold,<br />
prejudice is their position, and the processes are such<br />
that they shouldn't be prejudiced.<br />
JL: Ok the other point, when you assess immigration in<br />
April it won't rise?<br />
PM: Well I'm not saying that<br />
JL: No I was asking.<br />
PM: The trend has been down, the trend has been down but<br />
that is not the dissimation of the program which some<br />
people wish and it won't be and it won't be motivated<br />
by crude political instincts like we have seen from the<br />
Liberal Party in the late 1980s and which we are seeing<br />
a bit of now. In other words we will be looking at the<br />
long run future of the Australian population, its<br />
growth, a contribution of the migration program and<br />
looking at the labour market and the capacity to absorb<br />
people : Ln that market, to house them and making a<br />
judgement about the intake for the following year.<br />
JL: OK but in the present circumstances being as they are,<br />
would it be reasonable to say that it is unlikely that<br />
it will rise?<br />
PM: Well it hasn't for the last couple of years. It's<br />
unlikely to rise this year.<br />
JL: Ok something else that I think we should touch upon<br />
briefly. Will you be doing something to restore<br />
confidence for the job getters in Australia quickly?<br />
PM: Well that this the whole point of what I'm doing now,<br />
that is trying to make sure whatever the Government<br />
does that is what we announce, when the statement is<br />
announced, that we have assessed as fully as we can<br />
with business and with other groups in the community </p>
<p>the likely measures to have the greatest and earliest<br />
impact upon activity and employment.<br />
JL: Will the dole rise?<br />
PM: Well that's not an issue which we are examining right<br />
now but the question I think is not a matter of the<br />
dole rising its activity rising is what we need. We<br />
need basically more people being employed and that can<br />
only come from producing more product and that means<br />
getting confidence going, getting people confident<br />
again about the economy that they think there is a<br />
future out their. We actually face a good 1990s in<br />
many respects low inflation, lot of good structural<br />
things there's no reason why this country can't get<br />
back to decent rates of growth and more satisfying<br />
levels of employment.<br />
JL: Prime Minister thank you very much for your time and<br />
let's hope we can talk again very soon.<br />
PM: Thank you John.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
