<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8515</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P.J. KEATING, MP ACCESS TO TAX INFORMATION FOR ROYAL COMMISSIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008515.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 47/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P. 3. KEATING, MP<br />
ACCESS TO TAX INFORMATION FOR ROYAL COMMISSIONS<br />
As I made clear yesterday the Commonwealth has always been<br />
prepared to make relevant taxation information available to<br />
the WA Royal Commission.<br />
However, I remain strongly of the view that such access<br />
should be limited to relevant information of a specific<br />
nature and not constitute a broad " fishing licence" approach<br />
in order to protect the right to privacy of Australians.<br />
It has been the consistent view of the Commonwealth and the<br />
Commissioner of Taxation that there is a mechanism by which<br />
relevant tax information can be obtained by the Royal<br />
Commission under Section 3E of the Tax Administration Act.<br />
The Royal Commission appears not to accept the Taxation<br />
Commissioner's interpretation of that Act.<br />
To put beyond doubt the Commonwealth's preparedness to<br />
assist the Royal Commission in seeking relevant tax<br />
information the Commonwealth will propose an amendment to<br />
Section 3E, nominating Royal Commissions as agencies which<br />
can seek such information.<br />
This would give Royal Commissions the same authority to seek<br />
tax information that is available to law enforcement<br />
agencies specified under the Act.<br />
To this end, I have asked the Treasurer, Mr Dawkins, and the<br />
Taxation Commissioner, Mr Trevor Boucher, to consult the WA<br />
Royal Commission as soon as is practicable on how best to<br />
structure the amendment to Section 3E.<br />
I trust this will satisfy the Commission's need for access<br />
to relevant tax information.<br />
Further, I seek the support of the Opposition to allow a<br />
speedy passage of the proposed amendment.<br />
CANBERRA May 15, 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
