<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>812</transcript-id>
    <title>BROADCAST ON RADIO AUSTRALIA ON THE OCCASION OF MALAYSIA DAY </title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/09/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000812.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>63/ 099<br />EROADi3T Br Til MMK XIN 18TER THE RT. RON.<br />SIR ROfRT HUIZIS ON RADIO AUITRAIJA ON TIM<br />OCCASION OF VIArAISI DAX ON 16TH SZPMEflR, 1963<br />LAdies and Gentlemen s<br />With peat plesure I convey my congratulations and<br />best wishes, to the Laesand peoples of Malaysia an this<br />very notable day in their history*<br />The esa. blishument of Malaysia Is of particular interest<br />to Australia and Australians for we have had a close and varm<br />association with you in the past and are extremely keen to come<br />oven closer to you an you develop your now nationhood,<br />I regret to say that I " e hover visited either North<br />Borneo or Sarawak butI do of course know the Leaders of Malaysia<br />and Singapore, Tw~ k% Abftl Rtabman anid Mr, Lee Mun Yew, for each<br />of Vhe I have greet respect and regard.<br />We in Australia have had a long experience in the<br />formation of a self-gorning federation out of a group of<br />* elf-@ mvrning ooloanie As you perhaps knov, all this happened<br />in Austalia ust be fore the end of the last century With the<br />result that Australian Federation somw Into existence in<br />1901. So we have had a good deal of experience in forming a<br />federation and of couse$ we have amw had 60 years of experience<br />In making hat federation work* I mention this beaue, althug%<br />today " epresents a splendid begi% 6% ningd I would not like you to<br />think it represents the and of a road IIt is really the beginning<br />of one, From now on, it is your task to ake the federatimn<br />effective strn cohesive, influential, and I an sure you<br />wil-l so aunt it La that way.<br />Now what I have just said indicates just why we are<br />deeply Interested in you and are very confident of your success,<br />We have of course some spesial personal eontacts. A number<br />of your young son and wemen hae come to Australia for educational<br />or other purposes and I believe ( and I an sure rightly) that<br />they have found great friendship awmg the Australian people.<br />Theme eontacts In addition to anl the others I need<br />not refer to, 0 will no doubt oontime and grow. They have<br />certainly produced in Australia a preat affection for, and<br />a high degree of understanding of Malaysia and Its special<br />problems, We are, of eorse you Malaysia we the IsMAMiatk<br />of Australia -Coonwealth partvers and we AaVe a stron-g Interest,<br />an enduring Interest In peace and in the ecoomic advanowment<br />of South last Asia* I emphasise this because I 3sgard the<br />Malaysia creation as a great step forward in the forwarding of<br />peace and the forwarding of ecoomic development.<br />We must all veyk together think togather., be willing<br />to understanid each other and to help each other. ) y Minister<br />for External Affairs, Sir Garfield Barvick, Is personally<br />representing the Australian Government and Its peple at your<br />imngeral celebrations and I do not roed to toll you that be<br />bears with his the good wishes of everybody In Australia. 0 .&amp; 00</p>
<p>-2-<br />I an suw that yar no w dty winI briag i<br />Its train the strength that wi oumrm a great fiture<br />for Malaysias That in ertainly what I vish, that is<br />ortainiy what the people of Autralia wish, and therefore<br />it is the wish we oaL you on this oonsion in your history,<br />rou have the wtmsat exprssions of podvill<br />free my oouatry and its people*</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
