<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1122</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: EXTRACT FROM OPENING ADDRESS TO THE ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE AUSTRALIAN COUNTRY PARTY (N.S.W.) JUNE 23, AT WAGGA BY THE RT. HON. J. MCEWEN, ACTING PRIME MINISTER, MINISTER OF TRADE AND INDUSRTY, LEADER OF THE AUSTRALIAN COUNTRY PARTY</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/06/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001122_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 655.<br />
Extract from opening address to the annual<br />
conference of the Australian Country Party June<br />
23, at Wagga by the Rt. Hon. J. McEwen, Acting Prime<br />
Minister, Minister for Trade and Industry, Leader of the<br />
Australian Country Party<br />
VIETNAM There 13 controversy as to whether Australian<br />
troops should be in South Vietnam.<br />
This is a free, independent country recognised<br />
by the United Nations.<br />
Australia had hoped that the United Nations<br />
would be an organis'tion cxpable and willing to protect free<br />
countries at least small free countries.<br />
We will work towards the United Nations becoming<br />
such an Authority, but at this stage we have to face the fact<br />
that it has no such power or will at present.<br />
Today the United Nations is unable, and many<br />
of its member States unwilling, to protect South Vietnam from<br />
falling victim to the Communists of North Vietnam and<br />
Communist China. The United States is not engaged in South<br />
Vietnam to protect American soil or American interests.<br />
She is there to defend the freedom of a small<br />
nation freedom from domina. tion by Communism.<br />
For Australia, far more so than for the United<br />
States, this is not just a conflict of ideologies.<br />
Vietnam is the only fighting front in the<br />
world today where the forces of freedom are actually fighting<br />
the Communists. Every Australi. n must note that this, the only<br />
fighting front, is dangerously close to our front door.<br />
Some assert that this is a war wvich can't be won.<br />
The argument goes that even if the United States<br />
wants to persevere in this struggle, Australia should not<br />
become militarily involved.<br />
To me, this line of argument ignores the plain,<br />
hard facts of our defence situation.<br />
There are too many episodes of recent history,<br />
to justify any confidence that any country with a small<br />
population can safely work on the principle that if we mind<br />
our own business, the rest of the world v; ill let us dwell in<br />
peace. Incident after incident shows this to be<br />
a completely unreal and dangerous approach to our defence<br />
, nd security. </p>
<p>Nor can a country with our limited population<br />
and present resources, geogro
realisticilly think that vie can, by our own enceavours, take<br />
care of all contingencies which might arise, invrlving our<br />
security. In a1n age when v. a. ons and military equipment<br />
require great resources, and higLhly-developed technology,<br />
only the greatest of industrial powers, can alo 1e really<br />
indeprenlent military powcre in their own right.<br />
Unable to depend on the United Nations, what<br />
is the courseof safety to us?<br />
There is only one. The crea. tion and maintenance<br />
of alliances wiith po erful and reliable friendos.<br />
This must be the simile basis of our ap. roach<br />
to defence. We have forimed alliances.<br />
f course, v. with Britain, and New Zealand, with<br />
whom we have a long and, proud history of standing together<br />
in military affairs, for better or for worse.<br />
And also w-ith t1e createst military and industrial<br />
power there is the United States.<br />
The United States, under ANZUS, is pledged to<br />
defend us to safeguard our security.<br />
But like any alliance, ours with the United<br />
States must also be a two-ay alliance, for bettcr rr for worse.<br />
You can't make alliances, you certainly can't<br />
keep them, if you are going to take the view that:<br />
" We want to be looked after in any event, but<br />
wve'll pick aznd chloose when we'll support our<br />
partner. Te won't esupport him unless we are<br />
sure he's . ign to win.<br />
This is the answer to those who say we should<br />
not be in Vietnam because they think that in the circumstances<br />
the United States can't win a clear-cu. t victory in that<br />
troubled country. To merit thle NiJ re ty commitment of the<br />
United States, vital to Australia not -uet for today or<br />
tomorrow, but for years, pCerhapr generations in the future,<br />
, ustralia must support our great and powverful ally in the task<br />
she has assumed, of prcvcntinc further encroachment by the<br />
ommunists in South :' ast Asia.<br />
This is a stru-gle which could affect the<br />
safety, even the survival, of our own country.<br />
If Vietnam fall, . hat are the prospects for<br />
peace, and for freedom, in Le in Thailand in alayysia?<br />
What are the prospeats for utrl1ia 11 million<br />
eople holding an i-mmense countr, with tremendous resources<br />
nly now beginning to be e-ploitel, </p>
<p>A country in Australia's position cannot<br />
afford the luxury of doing only uwhat is comfortable? doing<br />
only that which does not involvo rieks.<br />
Our conduct today must ansure we merit the<br />
unhesitating support of our a. llies wen their support is<br />
needed. Of course, we detest r: ar, but notso much as<br />
we detest the thought of lms of our froedom to Communism.<br />
Of course, we w: o ul---! ork with the British and<br />
Americans to restore peace.<br />
But I mean peace which preserves the freedom<br />
of South Vietnam not a Deace which le-.~ s to Communist<br />
victory by Treaty. As I said before, Vietnam is the only fighting<br />
front in the world today " here the forces of freedom are<br />
actually fighting the ComiLiunists.<br />
Every Australian must note that this, the only<br />
fighting front, is dangerously close to our front door.<br />
Australia hel-ped the British, New, Zealanders<br />
and . Malayans to stamp out the Communist terrorists in Malaya.<br />
Today they are finished there.<br />
We put them out by fighting them not by<br />
signing a treaty with them.<br />
Co .: mun-ism is here in Australia. I believe that<br />
never before have Australians had such real ~ round to<br />
recognise the da4nger to our freedom from Communisrm.<br />
The Country Party w, as the first, and for a<br />
time, the ONLY political Party in Australia declaring that<br />
ommunism should be banned.<br />
Let us again lead the fight against this<br />
pernicious menace,<br />
7, V A year ago Australia held reserves in foreign<br />
exchange of œ 854 million next week at the end of this<br />
Einancial year our reserves jwill have fillen to œ 680 million.<br />
Having re~.: rd to all of the factors which<br />
nfluence Australia's balance of payments, it would not be<br />
n unreasonabl-guesstiimate that in a year's time our<br />
eserves may have fallen by as much ag. in.<br />
' Phis estimate pays some regoard, but not an<br />
unduly pessimistic regard, to the U. S. A. U. K. policies of<br />
minimising capital outflow.<br />
So one of Australia's greatest needs xIill<br />
ontinue to be, to increase export earnings to pay for the<br />
mports of capital equipment : and raw mnterials, which provides<br />
he , iuscles and sinews for the industry 3so essential for our<br />
rowth. </p>
<p>-4<br />
This year Australia will buy no less than œ 1,400<br />
illion worth of imports, œ 500 million more than 5 years ago<br />
hen imports were controlled at somewhere about œ 900 million a<br />
ear. There is nothing wrong with dipping into reserves<br />
to pay for these imports. That is what reserves are for.<br />
But neither a business nor a country can go on<br />
iving on its savings.<br />
If Australia is to maintain continuously a high<br />
evel of imports, then more anid more foreign exchange, must<br />
e earned by our exports, by exporting more, by exporting<br />
ifferent products, by getting better prices for our exports.<br />
If prices had remained at the levels of 1963-64 on<br />
hese 3 commodities alone, Australia would have earned an<br />
additional œ 135 million export income in the financial year<br />
nor closing. If prices of ALL export commodities had returned<br />
to the more reasonable levels of 1952-53, Australia's export<br />
i come would have been œ 300 million higher this financial<br />
y ar. There must be fought a constant battle to improve<br />
A stralia's earnings from exports. More in quantity! better<br />
p ices. Australia has now entered a new phase of export<br />
o gigantic quantities of crude minerals iron ore, coal, and<br />
b uxit e. It is a. matter of great interest that, to date,<br />
t ese sales and prospects of sale are almost in their entirety<br />
td Japan. The historic Australia-Japan Trade Treaty of 1957<br />
h -4s transformed the trading relationship between Australia and<br />
J pan and, perhaps more important, transformed relationships<br />
b tween the governments and the people of our two countries<br />
alel counts this is good beyond c ofculation.<br />
However, I have said on earlier occasions that<br />
A1 stralia is not to be exploited only as a quarry. It is time<br />
nn for us to see a growing development of the sale of these<br />
ra materials after somie processing.<br />
WAH A T Australia knows that historically wheat has been<br />
pr duced in surplus to the co. mnercial market.<br />
In recent years most of this surplus has been taken<br />
of the commercial market and disposed of on concessional<br />
te ms to the needy countries.<br />
Part of the Australian proposal now is to deal with<br />
wh at, surplus to commercial demand.<br />
We concede that the country which produces wheat<br />
su'plus to its commercial opportunities ought to be prepared<br />
to sell some of that wheat at less than the commercial price<br />
to the needy ought not to be the responsibility only of those<br />
couhtries which produce wheat in export quantities. </p>
<p>That, in short, all the more affluent countries<br />
whether wheat exporters or wheat importers should make a<br />
money contribution to a fund which would be used to buy surplus<br />
wheat at less than the going commercial price, and provide it<br />
on concessional -terms to the needy.<br />
That, in broad terms, is the Australijn approach.<br />
DROUGHT It is proper that governments should concern<br />
themselves with the problems of drought. The industries<br />
affected by drought are essential to the national well-being,<br />
and much that could be done to alleviate the consequences of<br />
drought can be done only by governments.<br />
In the livestock industries, drought is primarily<br />
i problem of feed and water, but in practical terms transport<br />
acilities and transport costs become a major part of the<br />
roblem. I am hopeful that the present drought may bring all<br />
Australian Governments collectively to face the fact that<br />
irought is a recurring phenomenon of the Australian environment.<br />
Not only does great personal hardship occur with tremendous<br />
uffering to livestock, but the whole economy of a country sunh<br />
as Australia is set back when a major drought occurs.<br />
Clearly there is opportunity for more water<br />
conservation by governments and, in very many cases, need for<br />
more water conservation by the landowner.<br />
It is quite practicable to-day to hold reserve<br />
tocks of grain for feed without the risks that applied in<br />
arlier times, of destruction by pests.<br />
I believe there should be special consideration of<br />
redit policies to enable farmers to hlve better reserves of<br />
ater and of fodder.<br />
In drought transport needs to be adequate and<br />
inexpensive. It is not easy to mitigate the consequences of<br />
drought for the grain grower, but the certainty that he will<br />
have recurring experiences of loss of production through<br />
drought and indeed, recurring experiences of failure to be<br />
able to plant his crop in many districts through excess rain<br />
must be sufficiently taken into account in assessing his costs<br />
for the purpose of stabilisation schemes.<br />
Over the whole field of drought consideration, the<br />
assistance of the scientist and the extension worker must be<br />
fally invoked. Most important work in relation to the drought<br />
f eding of sheep has been done, but I very much doubt whether<br />
tae result of this work has penetrated all sheepowners'<br />
uaderstanding. In a comprehensively organised approach to mitigation<br />
oC drought consequences, I believe the Commonwealth Government<br />
w uld co-operate with State Governments.<br />
This whole subject of drought is one on which the<br />
c) untry voice must be heard. 4 5/ 6 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
