<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4397</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004397.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Broadcast 3HA 15 May<br />
Embargoed until 7.00 p. m. 3YB 19 May<br />
U S T LIA&amp;<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 15 MAY 1977<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Good evening ladies and gentlemen. This past week has been an<br />
important week for Australia. It has been a week where Australians<br />
have focused on two separate but fundamentally important issues.<br />
The issue with the most immediate impact and the one that has<br />
taken the newspaper headlines has been the strike by the air<br />
traffic controllers. The Government made a stand that I believe<br />
was supported by millions of Australians. We made a conscious<br />
decision to put the interests of this community before the self<br />
interest of a small and elite group. We made responsible decisions.<br />
We made decisions in the national interest.<br />
I am pleased that the air controllers have finally agreed to go<br />
back to work, so their case can be heard by the highest arbitral<br />
tribunal in the land. The Government will support the decision of<br />
this tribunal. I hope the men will be unequivocal in the support<br />
of the umpire's decision.<br />
The other issue of fundamental and basic importance to the good<br />
government of our country is the referendum proposals to reform<br />
our constitution. It has not made dramatic headlines but in<br />
many ways this is understandable because the issues before the<br />
people are not dramatic issues. They are simply aimed at tidying<br />
up the constitution to meet the needs of Australia at this moment.<br />
This past week I have visited Melbourne, Sydney, Brisbane, Hobart,<br />
Launceston, Adelaide and Perth, explaining the benefits of the<br />
four proposals. I have been greatly encouraged by the response<br />
so far. I have no doubt that all four proposals will pass in<br />
every state. I am confident that they will receive overwhelming<br />
support.<br />
Some people have suggested that either or each of Queensland,<br />
Tasmania and Western Australia would reject the proposal that the<br />
Senate and the House of Representatives elections be held at the<br />
same time. I am convinced that the basic logic and common sense<br />
behind this proposal will make sure it is passed in these three<br />
states, as well as in New South Wales, Victoria and South Australia.<br />
I believe our arguments arguments put by every member of the<br />
House of Representatives and the great majority of Senators are<br />
getting through to those people who want to decide the merit of<br />
each proposal with an open mind. / Our arguments </p>
<p>-2<br />
Our arguments are being accepted. -' arid-they are being accepted<br />
because of their fairness, logic and plain Australian common sense.<br />
I believe that men and women are applying what I call the ' common<br />
sense test' to each questii. Is it common sense to allow people<br />
in the A. C. T. and Northern Territoryx to be counted in any referendum<br />
vote? Is it common sense for-judges-to\ retire at 70 years of age?<br />
Is it common sense to hold elect4, gns for the House of Representatives<br />
and Senate on the same day? Is-. it mmon sense to replace a Senator<br />
with a Senator from the same part-0, ' Surely the answer in each case<br />
is a clear ' yes'.<br />
It is significant that since ( We began on the ' yes' campaign, support<br />
for each of the four questions has steadily risen. This support<br />
will continue as the argument\ S .* continue to be put before the<br />
community. So far, I'and other Parkiamentarians putting our case<br />
have spent many hours on radio~ and,. t l'evis ion programmes talking<br />
directly to men and women who have sh ! own a real concern for<br />
constitutional reform. Their concern and their wish for reform<br />
in this important area has been demonstrated by the seriousness of<br />
their questioning. This concern is most heartening and refreshing<br />
because constitutional reform is essential if we want to maintain<br />
the real role of our democratic institutions.<br />
If by some chance these proposals are rejected by the community,<br />
I believe the future of our constitutional conventions will be<br />
in jeopardy. These proposals were overwhelmingly-supported by<br />
all political parties at all levels of Government at the last<br />
constitutional convention. Those proposals are the same proposals<br />
as we are now putting to Austr,-lians. It is for that reason that I<br />
am a little disappointed in the attitude of a couple of Premiers to<br />
the simultaneous election proposal. There was no dissent on this<br />
proposal at the convention. In fact, statements of support were<br />
issued. I<br />
This coming week, following a Cabinet meeting in Melbourne that<br />
will attend to normal Government business, we will continue to<br />
put our views plainly and directly. I have no doubt that Australians<br />
will see our arguments for what they are and that is plain common<br />
sense. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
