<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>559</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMONWEALTH BANKING CORPORATION GOLDEN JUBILEE DINNER HELD IN SYDNEY ON 16TH JULY, 1962 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000559_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
S COMMONWEALTH BANKING CORPORATION GOLDEN JUBILEE<br />
DINNER HELD IN SYDNEY ON 16TH JIULY 1<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt, Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
Mr, Chairman, Your Grace, My Lord Bishop, Parliamrentary<br />
colleagues and Gentlemen<br />
You will be delighted to know that I am making a<br />
very short speech tonight because, for some reason or other<br />
I haven't been too good today. I mean physically ( Laughter)<br />
and I therefore found mysalf bringing myself here with a little<br />
bit of reluctance this evening. Butt anyhow, Warren McDonald<br />
haa agreed that I need not make one of those forty-minute<br />
talks which are supposed to come so easily from political lips.<br />
As a matter of fact, I have had a very interesting<br />
weekend. I saw a Rugby League match on Saturday; ( Laughter)<br />
I read the rules the night before, ( Laughter) not being<br />
familiar with this strange game, and when I arrived at the<br />
Sydney Cricket Grcund, I said to my hosts, " Well, I read the<br />
rules last night. There are some points in them I don't fully<br />
understand" and they at once offered to make me a referee,<br />
( Laughter) ( Applause) Anyhow, we wcn ( Laughter) That gave<br />
me e great deal of pleasure,<br />
Yesterday morning, just in case I had become a<br />
little elevated by the inspiring events of Saturday afternoon,<br />
I had to go and read the Lesson in the Presbyterian Kirk, and<br />
the Lesson included the Ten Comnandments, No document could<br />
be more disturbing to a practising politician ( Laughter) than<br />
the Ten Commandments; unless, Your Grace, it is the Sermon<br />
on the Mount, That, really, some of my colleagues find<br />
impossible. Anyhow, all I wanted to say to you tonight was that<br />
I can remember in my youth the uproar that attended the<br />
establishment of the Commonwealth Bank. I think it is quite<br />
safe to say that of those who established it few if any, could<br />
foresee its future, Few, if any, could have understood either<br />
the fact or the reasons why it would become some day, in one<br />
of its manifestations, the Federal Reserve Bank of Australiao<br />
Central banking was not very much talked about or very much<br />
understood fifty years ago, It is now talked about a great<br />
deal. ( Laughter) But, Sir, right through the history, this fifty<br />
years of very distinguished history, there has been from time<br />
to time controversy. First of ally the Bank itself established<br />
under a Governor whose picture you will see here on this golden<br />
programme Look at him] He lonks exactly like a staunch<br />
supporter of the Liberal Party ( Laughter) And yet he was<br />
appointed by a Labor Prime Minister, It shows how broadminded,<br />
Arthur, they were in those days. ( Laughter) ( Applause)<br />
This is something you must remember after the next election<br />
( Laughter) And then it went on for a long time. It went on<br />
through the First World War,, It developed, perforce, a<br />
tremendous extent of activity and a variety of activity. It<br />
is a very curious thing that amid all the horrors they produce,<br />
these two Great Wars have produced other things and, in the<br />
case of Australia, brought us measurably nearer to central<br />
banking, Just as in the field of science, the developments<br />
under t. he pressures of war, both times, have been almost fabulous.<br />
8 a ** 000o </p>
<p>0 2.<br />
Then in 1921a Board of Directors, That produced a<br />
great argument, and a great uproar. And then later on, that<br />
disappeared and then later on, my own Government re-established<br />
it; and on each occasion arguments broke out which were full<br />
of heat and occasionally had gleams of lignt. But, at any<br />
rate, they were full of heat. There were misunderstandings,<br />
there were threats, there were fears. Never, I suppose, has<br />
a great institution passed through such a chequered career in<br />
so relatively short a time. And I believe that today there is,<br />
in the banking world, a higher level of mutual understanding<br />
than we have known for a long, long time. I believe that there<br />
is, right through the banking world of Australia, a warm appreciation<br />
of the significance of the Central Bank, the Reserve Bank<br />
and, equally, a recognition of the skill with which the Commonwealth<br />
Trading Bank, the Development Bank, the Savings Bank are<br />
carried on.<br />
All this, I believe, has brought about an era of good<br />
relations and good relations in the banking world are immensely<br />
important Good relations between banker and customer, yes;<br />
but good relations between bank and bank, And this of course,<br />
could not have happened in the middle of all the political<br />
disputes and the fiery eloquence at Canberra, unless these<br />
Banks had had men of singular talent engaged in directing and<br />
serving them,<br />
I would like to take the opportunity, because at one<br />
stage he was regarded as a controversial figure, of paying a<br />
wholehearted tribute to Dr. Coombs as the Governor of the<br />
Bank, ( Applause) Throughout the whole of my long association<br />
with him now, I have cone to regard him as a man of immense<br />
ability and of the most impeccable integrity. ( Hear, hear)<br />
( Applause) While, of course, on the trading side, subject to<br />
a little interruption occasionally by Warren McDonald, the<br />
show seems to me to be very well run, ( Laughter) He has<br />
referred to Mr. Armstrong who is by common consent, a very<br />
great trading bankero ( Applause, And in the result, I believe<br />
that we have now a pattern of banking, arrived at after almost<br />
the whole of the fifty years have gone, which is calculated to<br />
serve the interests of the people of Australia.<br />
Indeed Sir, tho one general observation that I wanted<br />
to make is this: We, in Australia, have developed when you<br />
come to think of it, a habit of mind on certain matters which<br />
Y believe has proved extraordinarily usefulø We have not<br />
been doctrinaire and said, " That's something that the Government<br />
ought to run and that nobody else ought to run." Nor have we<br />
carried our views on the other extreme to a doctrinaire limit.<br />
The result is, in broadcasting we have a dual system. The<br />
Government stations and private enterprise. In television,<br />
we have the dual system, except at Canberra ( Laughter) where<br />
the Government station has not yet arrived, but is understood<br />
to be on the way. But its very interesting isn't it,<br />
Radio the dual system; television the dual system;<br />
banking the dual system. And when we look back on it and<br />
know these things have been argued about and hammered out<br />
over many, many yeors I thldn most of us, irrespective of<br />
political views, would be disposed to say that this kind of<br />
compromise has been a happy one, because it has given full<br />
scope for the authority of government and adequate scope to<br />
the ingenuity and enterprise of the private citizen. ( Applause)<br />
And none of these things were in the minds of the founders of<br />
the Commonwealth Bank, I think; I don't think that many of<br />
them, although he was a man of ability, could have been in the<br />
mind of the first Governoro 00o 0 </p>
<p>3.<br />
I was sent by kind permission of Mr. Richardson an<br />
excerpt from a newspaper called the " Sydney Morning Herald".<br />
( Laughter) Not a recent number. That would have been an<br />
unkind thing to do; but quite an old one, fifty years ago<br />
in fact, and it contained an account of how Denison Miller<br />
was appointed. There it was, Very interesting pjce of<br />
history in the bank; and on the left-hand column, there was<br />
a vivid description of a game of poloo Polo, That's a<br />
very aristocratic game, they tell me, Ard on the other<br />
column, a vivid description of some of the great cricketers<br />
at work George Bonner and Charlie Macartney and the like.<br />
And I thought, " Well, now that must be a good newspaper<br />
polo, an account of the foundations of the Commonwealth Bank,<br />
and a lovely account of a cricket match, and I will remember<br />
it in my prayers, in future," ( Laughter)<br />
But, Sir, the real reason i referred to it I must<br />
not perpetuate these old reticences of mine, but the reason<br />
I referred to it was that here was the beginning of great<br />
events. After all, nobody could deny the massive size and<br />
quality and extent of the Banks we are celebrating tonight.<br />
Nobody. And yet here is the very beginning. A little<br />
letter from Andrew Fisher " Dear Mr. Miller. I would like<br />
to know whether you would be interested to accept a post in<br />
the service of' the Commonwealth of Australia, etc, etc."<br />
All done with true Andrew Fisher caution. Nothing committed,<br />
a little Scots reserve, very proper ( Laughter), and the answer<br />
is there. It is of a similar character, and in the upshot,<br />
there is an Order in Council, and that; man becomes the Governor<br />
of a Bank non-existent up to that time, not a person on the<br />
staff, not a skerrick of furniture, not a building to work in.<br />
That is how the Bank began and in fifty years, we have seen<br />
its development, its ramifications, its authority and we<br />
have, if I may particularly refer to its Reserve Bank functions,<br />
seen it as one of the great and respected Central Banks of<br />
the world, ( Applause)<br />
Sir, you may have noticed that it is not uncommon<br />
for the Leader of the Opposition at Canberra, ( I don't know<br />
what happens in Sydney) to disagree with the Prime Minister.<br />
I seem to remember doing it myself, when I was Leader of<br />
the Opposition ( Laughter) but tonight though he may express<br />
different reasons, I am happy to say that I am going to be<br />
supported in the presentation of this Toast by Arthur Calwell<br />
who is my devoted political enemy ( Laughter) but, I don't<br />
mind admitting, my personal friend. Now, Arthur. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
