<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18979</transcript-id>
    <title>Federal Financial Assistance to Help Tasmanians Get Back on Their Feet</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/01/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Sydney</p>
<p>Australian Government Disaster Recovery Payments (AGDRP) are now available to residents in the southeast and east of Tasmania covering the affected Local Government Areas of Sorell, Tasman and Glamorgan-Spring Bay.</p>
<p>Eligible people affected by the recent bushfires that commenced on 3 and 4 January in southeast and east Tasmania will be able to claim payments of $1,000 for each adult and $400 for each child.</p>
<p>These bushfires have had a devastating impact on some communities.</p>
<p>This is a very difficult time for many Tasmanians and these payments will assist individuals and families to get back on their feet.</p>
<p>People directly affected by the bushfires are urged to take advantage of this assistance.</p>
<p>Centrelink has deployed officers to recovery centres in Tasmania to assist with the claims process.</p>
<p>Claim forms will be available online later today at <a href="http://www.humanservices.gov.au/disaster">www.humanservices.gov.au/disaster</a>. The easiest way to lodge a claim is by calling the Australian Government Information Line on 180 22 66 from 8am to 8pm or in person at a disaster recovery centre.</p>
<p>This assistance is over and above the support to be provided by the Australian and Tasmanian Governments under the jointly funded Natural Disaster Relief and Recovery Arrangements (NDRRA) in coming days.</p>
<p>Affected residents may also be eligible for personal hardship and distress assistance, including a range of grants administered by the Tasmanian Government.</p>
<p>Further information on Australian Government assistance is available online at <a href="http://www.disasterassist.gov.au">www.disasterassist.gov.au</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
