<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8646</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP, INTERVIEW WITH MAXINE MCKEW, &quot;TALKS WITH THE PRIME MINISTERS&quot; SERIES, ABC &quot;AM&quot;, RECORDED 3 SEPTEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/09/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008646.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I. TRANSCRIPT OF THlE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEAING MP,<br />
INTERVIEW WITH MAXINE MCKEW, " TALKS WITH THE PRIME<br />
MINISTERS" SERIES, ABC " AM RECORDED 3 SEPTEMBER 1992<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
MM: Primc Minister in 1967 when we were listening to rcports about Vietnam,<br />
when we were singing songs like " Light My Fire" and " Friday on My<br />
Mind", you were 23 years old, you were two years away from a career in<br />
Canberra, what was on your mind in those days?<br />
PM: I was then at that stagc pretty well devoted to securing myself a scat in<br />
Parliament, but I was as mutch a product of the ' 60s as most other people<br />
were at the time. I was interested in the popular music you spcak about, we<br />
had this debilitating war going on in Vietnam which was an upsetting<br />
background fcature to most people's lives, they didn't quite understand all<br />
the issues involved. But for my part I was at that stage very heavily<br />
committed to coming to the H-ouse of Representatives.<br />
MM: What was i t in your background that propelled you towards a political<br />
career?<br />
PM: Public life offered a smorgasbord of things that so many things could be<br />
achicved if one could A: know what should be donc and B3: how to operate<br />
the system to do it.<br />
MM: What was it you wanted to do? Was it an ambition for yourself, did you<br />
have an idcal, a combination of both? </p>
<p>PM: It was a combination of both, I think most people who come into public life<br />
are well motivated, are altruistic, I certainly was. A lot of people have<br />
asked about the influences on my political life, what excited me, thc only<br />
two people that ever excited me in history was primarily Churchill and<br />
followed a close second by Roosevelt, they were the two that I thought well<br />
if that's the business they're in, that's the business I should be in.<br />
MM: What is it about those two historic figures that excites you?<br />
PM: lust that they would take positions and do things and they had that sense of<br />
leadership about them where they would not always take the safe position,<br />
not do the conventional thing and they had breadth about them and while<br />
each made mistakes they were always exciting.<br />
MM: It's interesting, you nominate two foreign leaders and you have said, of<br />
course, that you feel Australia has never produced a great leader. Do you<br />
still stand by that?<br />
PM: I'm not sure the occasions arc there where one might have come through. I<br />
made the point a couple of years ago in the United States they seem to come<br />
through at the right time for them, with Washington at the time of the<br />
Revolution, with Lincoln during the Civil War, with Roosevelt during the<br />
collapse of robber Baron capitalism re-establishing the. social and economic<br />
order and that leadership told on the United States, it became a very great<br />
country as a result of those important turning points. We've never had a<br />
Civil War and all those social stresses so I suppose the conditions produce<br />
the people.<br />
MM: If you haven't any local heroes you certainly had some..<br />
PM: No, there were people I was interested in and had a great abiding interest in<br />
and affection for like Theodorc and Curtin and Lang and people like that.<br />
MM: Lang was an important early mentor was he not, or is that overstated<br />
somewhat?<br />
PM: It is very much overstated. I knew him well, very well in fact, but he was at<br />
Henry Parkcs' rallies and he would give you a pen sketch of their<br />
personalities, Parkes, Latham, Holman, Storey, Isaac Isaacs.<br />
MM: Is that why you sought out his company? He was some sort of connection<br />
to the past and you wanted to know about that? </p>
<p>PM: Yes and he was intcrested in young people. He would always open himself<br />
up to young people and hc gavc me a tremendous amount of lime, but he<br />
used to think I was unimpressed with his economic and social views and by<br />
and large I was, but he was always so good spirited and he could teach you a<br />
lot. And so you felt you knew all these char acters, or you had some real<br />
feeling about them.<br />
MM: Has that been important to you throughout your career, that sense of being<br />
connected to Labor's past?<br />
PM: It gives you bearings, it gives you bearings throughout the nation so<br />
certainly in the history of the Federation it gives you bearings.<br />
MM: You came to Canberra in 1969 which was an election that Labor nearly won<br />
and you came here I suppose as a pretty young impatient young man and<br />
you came to..<br />
PM: I wasn't that impatient, I like to think I was canny enough not to be<br />
impatient.<br />
MM, But you came to a parliamentary party that had a lot of older men who were<br />
used to waiting for government. How did that strike you?<br />
PM: Yes, that was a pity, the two forces which play against the Labor Party was<br />
the First World War and communism. The First World War, Gallipoli,<br />
Flanders snuffcd out a lot of the social experimentation and nationalism<br />
which caused us to federate, where we formed the Labor Party and where<br />
we did so many novel, social things in the first fifteen or so years of the<br />
century and the conservatives wrapped the flag around it all and then made<br />
quite a radical thing, young men walking off the land and serving abroad,<br />
turned quite a radical thing and a conservative thing and of course a very<br />
divisive thing for the Labor Party. The belief that communism in some way<br />
centrally planned economics and the problems of the depression that<br />
communism hcld out some sort of option which was taken up by the<br />
intellectual Left in Britain, Australia and other places produced a lot of<br />
division in the Labor Party as thc polarities of the party shifted towards<br />
central planning as distinct from open markets and market operated<br />
economies. And the Cold War, the expression of all that in the Cold War<br />
and the stretched loyalties there were instnimental in Menzies having such a<br />
free nin wvith the DLP to keep us out of office for a quarter of a century.<br />
Without either Australia would have been a much more prosperous, more </p>
<p>united place, a more progressive place and Labor probably would havc been<br />
the dominating party throughout the history of the Federation.<br />
MM: Did you find though that there were some people here in ' 69 who still had<br />
paralysing views about the past?<br />
PM: A lot of people here were here twenty years at that stage, came in ' 49, had<br />
no office and were very jaded, not all of course, some were terrific, but<br />
many were jaded and disappointed, but they used their opportunity and did<br />
their best, just that they lacked that experience which would have come with<br />
a more natural party of government, one that had been around more often.<br />
MM: You came here with an immediate interest in economics which is very<br />
unusual for the time.<br />
PM: It wasn't, I wouldn't be too haughty about it Maxine, I wouldn't say it was an<br />
interest where I had all the economic theories at my fingertips, but I was<br />
intercsted in economic issues and in the creation of national wealth and I<br />
always saw the creation of national wealth as the passport to most<br />
Australians getting their share of income and all the other things. So my<br />
focus when T arrived, just about everyone in the parliamentary party was<br />
interested in foreign policy, the Foreign Affairs Committee was everyone in<br />
the Caucus bar about two or three and in social policy.* I remember Gough<br />
Whitlamn saying in the late ' 60s our job is basically to distribute the<br />
abundance, that is to carve up the wealth and that was a pretty reasonable<br />
view given the history of the ' 50s and the<br />
MM: But would you say the problem was no one talked about creating the<br />
wealth?<br />
PM: T'hc basis of the wealth was falling apart, hut it was not apparent to people,<br />
that is the terms of tradc post War had turned sharply against us, but it was<br />
not apparent. It was only apparent in thc ' 70s and that's when of course, the<br />
remedy should have been undcrtaken. As it turns out they were left until the<br />
so it is very easy to say at this point with this hindsight, but back there<br />
in 1969-70 ' 71-72 you had to be very perceptive to see the terms of trade<br />
shifting so markedly, that is the former dependence upon commodities<br />
being in a position to let us down.<br />
MM: How did Gough Whitlam trcat you in those days, did he dismiss you<br />
because you didn't have a tertiary education? </p>
<p>PM: Yes, Gough and I have been on and off over the years. I liked him because<br />
he was interesting, he understood that Australia had become a backwater<br />
and that we were too much a derivative society and we needed to break out<br />
of it and that's what really " Its Time" thing was about, but he said to me one<br />
day I judge a man by the number of questions he puts on the Notice Paper<br />
and I thought God, I'm going to fail here for sure because politically I<br />
thought it was never a political thing to do to ask your opponent questions,<br />
because they mostly give you the wrong answers.<br />
MM: You were pretty socially conservative when you came to this place, your<br />
maiden speech talked about the view of the family, women staying at home.<br />
PM: That's the sort of society, the part of Australian life I grew up in and in the<br />
quarter century that's passed, I've changed my views about that and not only<br />
that, in the last decadc played, I think, I hope anyway a reasonable role in<br />
facilitating some of that change.<br />
MM: You think there'-, now a much broader role for women?<br />
PM: One of the great changes in the last twenty five years since " AM" first<br />
began is the role of women in Australian society. Today relations between<br />
women and men are different than they were in 1967.<br />
MM: Better?<br />
PM: Absolutely, the sheer mode of address one would undertake at a political<br />
meeting or a gathering then and now is totally different.<br />
MM: It sometimes seems to many people though that men and women are at war<br />
with each other.<br />
PM: It's takcn some years for women to adjust to their new role, their greater<br />
opportunities in society, in education, in thc work place and it's taken men<br />
some years later to adjust to that. But it's a happy adjustment, I'm not saying<br />
it is without friction, but the end result is a pleasing one.<br />
MM: Have you consciously reinvented yourself over the years?<br />
PM: In what sense do you mean? </p>
<p>MM: Are we seeing something of a metamorphosis now from someone who<br />
believed in classical economics to someone who perhaps could be<br />
characterised as a born again Whitlamite?<br />
PM: No, I've always believed that the ' 80s was the decade that finished off<br />
communism and monetarism, it put them both asunder, that is the belief that<br />
private initiative, private reward, chasing moncy supply targets and these<br />
things were the salvation of everybody, no one believes that now anymore<br />
than they..<br />
MM: Didn't you embrace that to a certain extcnt?<br />
PM: No, never and if you look at communism that the state and central planning<br />
was thc answer is no longer an answer either. It has bcen the triumph of the<br />
thoughts of the social democracies, the social democratic parties which I<br />
think have emerged from the ' 80s best, that is what we've done; construct an<br />
open market economy, but where a social policy has been stitched into it in<br />
such things as access for health, which we began in 1983 or more equal<br />
access to education which we began about the same time or better aged care<br />
or child care to give women some freedom in life to pursue the things they<br />
want to pursue, All those sorts of things occupational supcranntuation with<br />
the work force, these are all early to mid ' 80s things. In talking about them<br />
now, we're talking about them in the context that the great change of the<br />
that Labor presided over and that I was involved with was employment, the<br />
huge ratc of employment with a work force today 26 per cent larger than it<br />
was in ' 83. It's in the context of unemployment that we arc focussing on the<br />
social policy and in the context of the John Hewson view of the world that<br />
you socially impoverish the place and thcn as I said a day or so ago a whole<br />
lot of little Hewsons will rise from the ashcs; God help you if you don't rise.<br />
And we're saying there's got to be something better than that, that is you<br />
don't tear up cherished institutions and cherished institutional arr angements,<br />
you don't sacrifice those things part of a country's soul and progress is<br />
these social changes and we should keep them.<br />
MM: Has there not been some evolutionary changes though in yourself? Gough<br />
Whitlam earlier this week suggested that after you stopped being Treasurer<br />
you took a long period to do some reflecting and you emerged with quite a<br />
differcnt perspective. Isn't that correct?<br />
PM: Only moderately, I haven't changed my tune much in my basic view of<br />
things since I first came to the House of Representatives. I'm smarter and<br />
wiser for the experience I hope, I've been just simply living through a lot of </p>
<p>these changes has bccn important, but I think if you've got time you do<br />
reflect on things. You and I wcrc just speaking about thc role of women,<br />
but two of thc other great influences of the last twenty five years, certainly<br />
the last ten years has been the education of the trade unions. Their role in<br />
Australian society in thc last decade has been an exemplary one, that is in<br />
making the place more competitive and being at the lcading edge of training<br />
and productivity of social change, of getting up social programs; things like<br />
the Family Allowance Supplement or occupational superannuation and the<br />
leaders of the trade union movement can take great pridc in that. Another<br />
thing which upon reflection makes apparent is that we are now investing in<br />
our most valuable resource, if you look at the resources boom mentality of<br />
the 170s, the most valuable resources of course our childrcn and we're now<br />
being certain that seven in ten complete secondary school, 40 per cent go on<br />
to universities, we're hoping that will soon be nine in ten; a decade ago it<br />
was threc in ten.<br />
MM: Having raised the trade union question and having talked to all the Prime<br />
Ministers this week one can't help but look at this question and that is that if<br />
Bill Kelty had behaved during the ' 80s with the H-awke Government in the<br />
way that perhaps Bob Hawke behaved towards the Whitlam Government<br />
when Mr Hawke was ACrU chief, things would have been very different.<br />
PM: I think the unions were greatly dehilitated by the late ' 70s experience. The<br />
profit share had been smashed to pieces, and with it investment and<br />
employment, and they came to the conclusion that chasing nominal wages<br />
growth was really leading to unemployment. And like a lot of very honest<br />
people, when one honestly understands a fact one responds to it. And they<br />
did en masse, and their leadership took the responsibility of telling them and<br />
teaching them that. So, wc can he grateful that someone as conscientious<br />
and as Australian, if I can say that, as Bill Kelty came along because I think<br />
he had the intellectual grasp and the leadership and the courage to pull the<br />
thing the right way. But again, even he couldn't have done that I don't think<br />
in the 1970s. It needed that cathartic experience of the late ' 70s, that wage<br />
explosion and the rest, to bring them along. But they have been, as an<br />
institution, one of the leading institutional forces for change.<br />
MM: Gough Whitlam made the point this week that the only thing that Bob<br />
Hawke had going for him was the Accord, and beyond that he only had one<br />
ambition, to be Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Well I think that's unfair to Bob. H-e has understood more about the basis of<br />
the importance of wealth and letting the economy be efficient, and to get out </p>
<p>there and take our share in the post-war trade in goods and services which<br />
passed Australia by. That was the terrible thing of the ' 60s, that we believed<br />
in thc commodities absolutely. It was wheat and wool and minerals and that<br />
was it. But the trade which made Japan strong and Germany strong had<br />
passed us by, not just In goods but in services. And as a result our kids and<br />
our people didn't have the interesting jobs thcy could have had. And<br />
changing Australia to undertake that huge odyssey out into the world<br />
economy was what the ' 80s was about. And I think Bob understood that, he<br />
had a lot of helpers but hy and large he had enough wisdom about him to<br />
understand that.<br />
MM: Now that you're in the job, what is it do you think that defines good<br />
leadership?_<br />
PM: Leadership has always been about being out in front, striking out, and trying<br />
to bring up support behind you if you're the Icader, making judgements and<br />
taking risks, and encouraging people, exciting people to do things.<br />
MM: Do you think the question of changing the flag is an illustration, though, that<br />
you can't be too risky, you can't afford to get too far ahcad of public<br />
opinion?<br />
PM: All the more reason to just to make the point, truths are absolute. We can<br />
never be so tricky that we move away firom truths. When you get around as<br />
a country with the flag of another country in the corner of your flag, you are<br />
not representing yourself as best you can. Now what that means in terms of<br />
the attachment people have to existing emblems and the methodology and<br />
the mode of changing them, that's a different matter. But I think it's<br />
important for lcaders to speak about these things.<br />
MM: Are you still committed to changing the flag?<br />
PM: I've said it should only change with a plebiscite. I don't think any<br />
government has got the right to just impress its vicw on the whole nation<br />
about emblematic or constitutional things. But it's important to know, we<br />
had this very day a Minister in the Thai Government saying if Australians<br />
are more clcar about themselves, if they want to do business with Asia, if<br />
they wish to he part of the regional community, we will welcome them with<br />
open arms. I mean, wc'vc really been waiting for it. I think the important<br />
thing is being certain about who you are and what you are. </p>
<p>MM: Do you think that's one of our problems, we are too ambivalent, too many of<br />
us love the country but it also drives us crazy? Arc you a hit like that, you<br />
get frustrated with the place?<br />
PM: I think you get frustrated with all every country has got its problems, but<br />
MM: We do seem to have a particular identity problem, don't we?<br />
PM: This was a derivative place, and still to some extent is, and shaking that off<br />
has been what the last quarter of a century has been about. But migration,<br />
multiculturalism, doing something new here in world terms with this<br />
community, taking more pride in our own intrinsic worth and value and<br />
what our own culture means and stands for, reflecting the fact that we are<br />
living on the oldest land mass on the face of the earth in a continent, a<br />
continent which was inherited by black people, coming to tcrnms with that<br />
and them, is all part of making tip Australia and Australians. And we're<br />
now much more clear ahout that, aren't wc? I mean, everybody is.<br />
MM: If we are to know who we are and be confident about that, we need a new<br />
flag, we need a republic?<br />
PM: We need In the first instance to know that it is important to be yourself.<br />
Now that is not universally known or accepted in Australia. It's important to<br />
be yourself, to be proud of what you are and to be better than what you are.<br />
MM: Any timetable?<br />
PM: Let me just say this. Thc neighbourhood of this area, where we've got very<br />
large societies, and old socicties, Malaysia and younger ones, Singapore,<br />
and the rest there's a great opportunity for Australia. But taking the view<br />
that they're the places we fly over to somewhere else and you look at Jakarta<br />
from 35,000 fcet is not, I don't think, an option for Australia.<br />
MM: Prime Minister, as we're reflecting historically, do you think we're still<br />
bedevilled by the fact that wc tend to celebrate losers in this country, we<br />
celebrate losers and losses?<br />
PM: Yes, there's a great underdog syndrome in the place, which is a nice thing in<br />
some respects, as long as it doesn't overtake us so that the best people are<br />
draggcd down by it. And there's too much of that in Australia, there's too<br />
much of the tall poppy problem, tall poppy syndrome. People think it's </p>
<p>elitist and elitism is frowned upon. Well the elite people encourage others<br />
and give them heart and inspiration. Look at this young group of<br />
Olympians, some of who I met last night returning again to some of the<br />
celebrations, and they will all be inspiration to Australian young people in<br />
sport, and in many other respects, for years to come. And whether it be in<br />
the arts, or business, or where ever it might be, we've got to get over this<br />
notion that we drag people down, we hop into them because they've got<br />
talent so let's nail them, this sort of view.<br />
MM: You referred, last weekend at the 20th Anniversary of the Whitlam<br />
Government at thc dinner, you said that what Gough Whitlam understood<br />
was thc need to lift the national spirit and to excite people. We could do<br />
with a bit of that now, couldn't we?<br />
PM: Yes, you can always do with it I think. But thcre I was reflccting upon that<br />
which I said to you a few moments ago, that the thing is in the ' 60s the place<br />
was still very much a derivative place and we were not making declarations<br />
about ourselves and what it was like to be an Australian or Australia playing<br />
a more independent role for itself in the world, and I think Gough was very<br />
much'associated with that ' coming out' after the 25 years of Menzies, the<br />
Menzian age. And it was exciting. The ' 80s were cxciting too, for different<br />
reasons. It was, I think, one of the most exciting decades. No doubt a lot of<br />
silly things were done, but it was very exc iting as well.<br />
MM: What silly things were done?<br />
PM: Spreading money around, 20 per cent credit growth a year, and all that sort<br />
of thing which was rather debilitating in the final analysis. But, still you<br />
look at Australia comparing the end of the ' 80s to the beginning of the<br />
and it is really to bc compared as a more exciting place, a more exciting<br />
country. Tourism, for instance, didn't exist at the beginning of the<br />
financial services, educational services, all of these various things we were<br />
doing, films. There's always a place for excitement, but the problem we've<br />
had recently is unemployment produces a pall over the economy and over<br />
society and it's a bit hard to even if it was one's want to suggest to people<br />
to throw that off and look beyond it, as I think there's a very exciting future<br />
in the 1990s for Australia. For the moment people are dealing with our<br />
condition with the gravity it deserves.<br />
MM: So one can't be inspirational, particularly in 1992, it's a lot harder? </p>
<p>PM: One can be inspirational, but one can't be I don't think frivolous, and<br />
frivolity had its place in the scheme of things in the<br />
MM: When you became Prime Minister you said it was a humbling experience,<br />
and other Primc Ministers this week have referred to the constraints of<br />
office. How have you found it?<br />
PM: Constraints of office are obvious to any practitioners of this place. We all<br />
know the li mitations of it. In terms of it being humbling, I think it is<br />
humbling because in thc Prime Ministership is invested, in some respects,<br />
the ideal of the nation and its aspirations, and that's quite a lot to invest in<br />
any one office or person. And if you happen to be the person in the office, I<br />
think it's humbling.<br />
MM: Bob Hawke also said this week when you come to the job you lose your<br />
private life, but you of course insist on a private life.<br />
PM: Well one can never insist upon it, of course we have journos who upset it.<br />
MM: Do you resent that?<br />
PM: In a sort of good natured kind of way I suppose I do. I think you can have it<br />
if you wish, or remain a sort of normal person. I still get about the place, no<br />
matter where I am I always walk around by myself, or I go into shops or<br />
buildings or into cinemas or into theatres, or whatever it might be.<br />
MM: You don't feel self conscious about that?<br />
PM: No, I think if you move about freely it tends to be accepted, but if you<br />
believe that onc should not move without an centourage and what have you<br />
then you're a victim of your own circumstances. I think it's very<br />
encouraging for Australians to think that the people who are managing their<br />
affairs are normal, live normal lives.<br />
MM: Do you ever feel that in projecting yourself, as you have to do in this job,<br />
that there's a fine line you tread? There's a public persona and there's the<br />
private man, are you worried about the tendency towards, I suppose,<br />
phoniness that might bc involved in that?<br />
PM: YCS, I can't stand phoniness or humbug, I can't stand it. And that, in some<br />
respects, tells against me. I won't do the tricks and stunts that perhaps those </p>
<p>who've been more cynically advised might do. I can't naturally do them and<br />
feel comfortable with them. If it's not real I'm not in it-<br />
MM: Are you're minders telling you to do certain things that go against the grain?<br />
PM: All minders will encourage you to do things which go against the grain, and<br />
not that they are encouraging me or have they ever to do things which are<br />
unnatural or which are phoney. I think you tend to attract the staff that<br />
share your values. But every now and again you find yourself doing things<br />
that you might not otherwise do.<br />
MM: Such as?<br />
PM: Whether it be..<br />
MM: Tripping over the odd camera cable at the shopping mall?<br />
PM: No, well I don't do that you see. If I go to a shopping mall I go there to<br />
shop, I don't go there to accost shoppers.<br />
MM: You must rcgret you came to the job as late as you did, that you didn't have<br />
long to establish yourself before thc-election..<br />
PM: Yes, I think that people should not try to stay on the stage too long. I think<br />
there's a certain amount of perceptions, energy, horsepower, perspicacity, all<br />
thcsc things that stay at the burn rate of this kind of change. Let's make this<br />
clear, Australia has been through a decade of just phenomenal change, the<br />
pace of change has been phenomenal. Anyone who had lived in the ' 70s or<br />
knows that. In public life the burn rate is very high. And I think the<br />
public also get disenchanted with the same personalitics doing the same<br />
things, and they are right. They are right in saying look, we want you on the<br />
stage for a while and give us your best and please quietly leave, hut a lot of<br />
them want to hang on too long, and I think that's a shame.<br />
MM: Would you leave if you lost the next election?<br />
PM: Well I don't think I will ( lose), I don't think Australia is about to turn the<br />
country over to somebody that doesn't really have any sort of institutional<br />
respect for Australia for its institutions, its social fabric or its values. This<br />
sort of hard hearted view that John Hcwson is proposing, that as I said<br />
before, you socially Impoverish the place and In more spartan conditions<br />
where economic athletes rise from the ashes, is; not I don't think acceptable </p>
<p>to Australians. That sort of view, or if you're in large business you're a<br />
bloated illegitimate bureaucracy, if you're not self made you're no good.<br />
This sort of thing. It's immature and I think Australians will spot the<br />
phoniness of that, the immaturity of it.<br />
MM: Finally Prime Minister, as it's our birthday I wonder if I could ask you if you<br />
wouldn't mind telling us a bit of a story against yourself about a particular<br />
morning whcn I happened to know you didn't listen to AM.<br />
PM: Well I'm not an AM listcner. I used to be, but I think waking up to the<br />
Weetbix with a bus being hit in Jerusalem or something else, tends to shake<br />
you too quickly out of your slumber. I like to start on the newspapers and<br />
gradually if I see a story I don't like I turn the next page and gradually move<br />
into it, rather than the shock therapy you get with AM. When I was young I<br />
could stand it, I can't thcsc days. But the day you're talking about was the<br />
stock markct crash of 1.987.<br />
MM: That's right.<br />
PM: And I came into Parliament House, and the day before, that's right, on the<br />
Friday thcrc had bccn a bit of a shake in the markets, and I walked in<br />
Monday morning and the journalists said to me, well what do you think<br />
about the stock market, which had collapsed over night and I didn't hear it, I<br />
didn't know. And I said ' it's a correction, it's not to be I don't think one<br />
should be fazed by this', or words to that cffect. And of course AM had<br />
carried the story because it was an over night story. So I missed it.<br />
Therefore thcre may be an omen in all that, or a moral in all that, that is<br />
listen to AM.<br />
MM: I do hope so. Prime Minister, thank you for your time.<br />
PM: Thank you Maxine.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
