<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19093</transcript-id>
    <title>New Q20 Group To Maximise G20 Benefits For Queensland</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/02/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Brisbane</p>
<p>The Gillard Government is pleased to announce the formation of the Queensland 20 (Q20) - a new peak group of Queensland business leaders to ensure the state reaps the maximum benefit from next year's G20 Leaders' Meeting.</p>
<p>The Q20 will be chaired by Ms Catherine Tanna, Chairman of resources group BG Australia, based in Brisbane.</p>
<p>Queensland's role as host state for the summit in Brisbane and a G20 Finance Ministers and Central Bank Governors' meeting in Cairns provides an opportunity to showcase not only these locations, but the entire Sunshine State.</p>
<p>The G20 brings together leaders, finance ministers and central bank governors from major emerging and advanced economies to address the critical economic and financial challenges facing the world. </p>
<p>It is expected to attract 25 world leaders, 4,000 delegates and up to 3,000 members of the world's media. </p>
<p>It is the premier forum for global economic co-operation and decision-making and its member nations account for more than 85 per cent of global economic output.</p>
<p>There are enormous benefits that will flow to Australia and Queensland from hosting this global event, both now and into the future.</p>
<p>Led by Ms Tanna, the Q20 will help make sure that the whole of Queensland reaps the benefits of this tremendous opportunity.</p>
<p>The Q20 will work to ensure that all of Queensland can make the most of hosting the G20 by highlighting the state's diverse economy, including the resources, construction, education, agriculture and tourism sectors. It will highlight Queensland as a great place to visit, learn and do business.</p>
<p>It will help Queensland business to directly engage and work with the B20 - the advisory body headed by Mr Richard Goyder AO to lead business engagement for the G20 - to help facilitate the significant contribution Queensland business can make.  </p>
<p>Ms Tanna brings invaluable experience to the role. Raised in Gladstone, Queensland, Ms Tanna has forged a successful career as a leader in the resources industry.</p>
<p>Ms Tanna joined BG Group in 2009 after a long career with Shell and BHP Billiton. Ms Tanna has been a member of the Reserve Bank of Australia Board since 2011 and is a member of the 2018 Commonwealth Games Board.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
