<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10726</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                DOORSTOP                KIRRIBILLI HOUSE , SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/02/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>Good afternoon. Well ladies and gentlemen I have called this news</p>
<p> conference to announce that I have decided to postpone my visit to</p>
<p> Malaysia and Papua New Guinea and the reason for that is that it has</p>
<p> become quite obvious to me that crucial decisions about the possible</p>
<p> involvement of Australian forces in military action against Iraq might</p>
<p> need to be taken during the next week and I would not want the possibility</p>
<p> to arise of those decisions being required during my absence from</p>
<p> Australia.</p>
<p>This does not mean any weakening of my hopes that there will be a</p>
<p> peaceful settlement and that Saddam Hussein will see the reason in</p>
<p> the mission of the Secretary General of the United Nations to Iraq.</p>
<p> I rang the Malaysian Prime Minister a short while ago and informed</p>
<p> him directly of my decision. Although disappointed that my visit would</p>
<p> not be taking place now, he does understand the reasons why I have</p>
<p> taken this decision.</p>
<p>I have endeavoured, over the past little while, to get in touch with</p>
<p> the Prime Minister of Papua New Guinea and that has not been successful</p>
<p> but, I have conveyed a message and my regrets, to one of his officers.</p>
<p>I particularly regret the fact that I am not going to Malaysia because,</p>
<p> amongst other things, I would have wanted to personally convey to</p>
<p> Dr Mahathir and the Malaysian Government the confidence that the Australian</p>
<p> Government feels in the efforts being undertaken by the Malaysian</p>
<p> Government to cope with the very severe economic difficulties which</p>
<p> have buffeted that country.</p>
<p>However, we both agreed that this afternoon's decision was a</p>
<p> postponement and not a cancellation and we are already searching for</p>
<p> an alternative date and I hope that that visit can take place then.</p>
<p>Returning to the first of my comments, I remain hopeful that Kofi</p>
<p> Annan's visit can yield results. The whole world would want bloodshed</p>
<p> to be avoided, but if that mission fails, it will not be through a</p>
<p> lack of good-will on the part of the United Nations, on the part of</p>
<p> the United States, or on the part of Australia, it will rest entirely</p>
<p> upon the head of Saddam Hussein. And it is clearly my responsibility</p>
<p> to be in Australia dealing with the situation as it evolves and as</p>
<p> it proceeds over the next week.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>(Inaudible)...the situation in the Gulf...(inaudible)?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The situation in the Gulf has been delicate for some time but it has</p>
<p> become apparent to me over the past few days that the time for taking</p>
<p> decisions, both in relation to whether or not the peace mission is</p>
<p> being successful, or otherwise, could possibly - and I repeat - possibly</p>
<p> arise, during the time that I might have been away. And I don't</p>
<p> think it is appropriate for the Prime Minister of this country to</p>
<p> be out of Australia when decisions are taken that could directly lead</p>
<p> to the involvement of Australian forces in military action. That is</p>
<p> absolutely not acceptable to me and I don't think it would be</p>
<p> acceptable to the Australian public and that is the reason why I have</p>
<p> decided to postpone the visit.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>(Inaudible).</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>People are aware that if the peace mission fails, then military action</p>
<p> is the only alternative. I hope the peace mission succeeds, I really</p>
<p> do, I fervently hope the peace mission succeeds, but if it doesn't,</p>
<p> then a number of decisions must be taken. The first decision is a</p>
<p> decision that further peace efforts are going to be pointless and</p>
<p> the second of course, could be the involvement of Australian forces</p>
<p> in military action.</p>
<p>At present the authority of the Australian forces is the authority</p>
<p> to deploy, not the authority to involve themselves in military action</p>
<p> and it is imperative that, as Prime Minister, I be around when those</p>
<p> decision are taken.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Have you spoken to Mr Clinton in recent days?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. I have not spoken to President Clinton since the Cabinet decided</p>
<p> to deploy forces to the Gulf. I rang him then, and if necessary, we</p>
<p> will talk again, but there has been no necessity for us to talk over</p>
<p> the past few days.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What will be the role of Defence Minister McLachlan if you are going</p>
<p> to stay back..(inaudible)?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>He will be playing the appropriate full role of the Defence Minister.</p>
<p> These are whole of Government decisions and it follows from that,</p>
<p> that the presence of the Prime Minister is always essential. Its committing</p>
<p> Australian forces to military action is the most significant decision</p>
<p> that any Government and any Prime Minister of this country can take.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>(Inaudible).</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is obvious from a number of circumstances, including the nature</p>
<p> of Kofi Annan's visit to Baghdad, that it could possibly be that</p>
<p> one or two of those crucial decisions will need to be taken during</p>
<p> the time that I would have otherwise been away. I want to emphasise,</p>
<p> however, that I have not received any information in the past few</p>
<p> hours which indicates that the prospects for success of that mission,</p>
<p> by the Secretary General, have been altered.</p>
<p>I still remain hopeful, and I can't put it any more strongly</p>
<p> than that, that the mission will be successful. We all hope that the</p>
<p> mission will be successful. Nobody wants war, nobody wants bloodshed,</p>
<p> nobody wants the necessity of a military strike. The person standing</p>
<p> between the realisation of that hope, and the possibility that that</p>
<p> hope will be dashed, is Saddam Hussein.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>When were you leaving..(inaudible)..and how long was that going to</p>
<p> be?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I was going tomorrow, around about lunch time, and I was going to</p>
<p> be away until Thursday or Friday of next week. I should emphasise,</p>
<p> that this decision of mine, does not alter the plans I currently have</p>
<p> to visit the Northern Territory, which, of course is not affected</p>
<p> by the requirement of my being in Australia.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>(Inaudible).</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We are a peaceful, democratic country and people have the right to</p>
<p> lawfully and peacefully demonstrate and lawfully and peacefully dissent.</p>
<p> That's one of the great things about being an Australian and</p>
<p> that is why we take stands in international fora and that is why we</p>
<p> are prepared to put our country's reputation on the line to defend</p>
<p> liberty. We believe that people should have the right of free expression,</p>
<p> Saddam Hussein doesn't.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you believe that most Australians still support sending our troops?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I believe that most Australians do support what we have done.</p>
<p> No Australians want war, I don't, none of my colleagues do, we hate</p>
<p> the very idea of it, but it may become necessary to use military force,</p>
<p> and if it is, I have no doubt that the Australian service personnel</p>
<p> will distinguish themselves as they always have in the past. But I</p>
<p> hope and pray that that doesn't become necessary.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, do you see..(inaudible)?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We both agreed that our officials would get together immediately to</p>
<p> find an alternative date. I want to visit Malaysia, he wants me to</p>
<p> come. He was very appreciative of the fact that I had rung him personally</p>
<p> and had not informed him of my decision through the normal diplomatic</p>
<p> channels. He understands the position although he is disappointed,</p>
<p> as I am, but we both appreciate that in these circumstances my first</p>
<p> duty is to be in Australia.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
