<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10692</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  DOORSTOP INTERVIEW - FRANKSTON, VICTORIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................</p>
<p>  Well, ladies and gentlemen, no doubt you'll have some questions</p>
<p>   but I just thought I'd open by saying that now, more than ever</p>
<p>   is not the time to change economic course. It is very, very clear</p>
<p>   that only the Coalition Government can offer Australia economic</p>
<p>   security, safety and stability against the background of the economic</p>
<p>   turmoil in Asia. If my Government had not taken the measures it</p>
<p>   did over the last two and a quarter years Australia would now be</p>
<p>   weaker and more vulnerable economically than what it is.</p>
<p>  Now is not the time to turn back to the Labor Party which gave us</p>
<p>   huge debts and huge deficits and tried to stop the Coalition taking</p>
<p>   the measures that were necessary to strengthen and protect the Australian</p>
<p>   economy and to deliver us the strongest economic foundations for</p>
<p>   25 years. And it will mean that although we are not untouched by</p>
<p>   the Asian economic turmoil, we will weather the storm effectively.</p>
<p>   Nor is it the time to turn to the experimentational policies of</p>
<p>   One Nation which would chase away foreign investment, threaten our</p>
<p>   export industries and, as a consequence, endanger the jobs of many</p>
<p>   tens of thousands of Australians. It is not an occasion to turn</p>
<p>   back to the failed policies of the past, nor is it a time to experiment</p>
<p>   with other policies which could have disastrous consequences for</p>
<p>   employment levels, particularly in regional Australia.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  It also not a good time to introduce a GST, Mr Howard.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  We need tax reform. The fact that we are facing economic challenges</p>
<p>   around the world in fact makes it more necessary to reform Australia's</p>
<p>   taxation system. One of the great advantages of a broad based, indirect</p>
<p>   tax or a goods and services tax rather than the existing indirect</p>
<p>   taxation system is that it would make our exports more competitive.</p>
<p>   So if people are worried about our export performance, if they want</p>
<p>   more jobs in our export industries, they should support tax reform,</p>
<p>   not oppose it. The people who oppose tax reform are opposing the</p>
<p>   growth of our export industries.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  (Inaudible)</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well as Prime Minister I never pick sides when it comes to locations</p>
<p>   in different parts of Australia but speaking generally, on behalf</p>
<p>   of the entire country, let me make it perfectly clear that foreign</p>
<p>   investment in this country, in accordance with our longstanding</p>
<p>   and successful foreign investment policy, is always welcome. Foreign</p>
<p>   investment has generated tens of thousands of jobs over the years</p>
<p>   and I think the talk which is going on about this company is a timely</p>
<p>   reminder to everybody that Australia is not the only part of the</p>
<p>   world in which foreigners can invest and if we give the impression</p>
<p>   that we don't want foreign investment, if people start mouthing</p>
<p>   policies which discourage foreign investment, what they are doing</p>
<p>   is chasing jobs out of Australia. Because in a globalised economy,</p>
<p>   if foreign investment doesn't come to Australia it will go</p>
<p>   somewhere else and so will the jobs.</p>
<p>  The idea that you can have the jobs without the foreign investment</p>
<p>   is wrong. The idea that you can say foreign investment is not welcome</p>
<p>   and not pay a price is wrong. The idea that you can have it both</p>
<p>   ways, as some people would, is wrong. And I think this is a timely</p>
<p>   reminder and a timely warning how dangerous and silly and short-sighted</p>
<p>   it is to sound unfriendly towards foreign investment because foreign</p>
<p>   investment has lifted the living standards of Australia and generated</p>
<p>   hundreds of thousands of jobs over the years and that would be at</p>
<p>   risk if we say in a globalised economy that foreign investment is</p>
<p>   not welcome.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Will you be able to respond to the call of Jewish business leaders</p>
<p>   to try and persuade the Liberal Party to put One Nation last?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well I've said before that that's something that will</p>
<p>   be decided by the State divisions and some of them have already</p>
<p>   indicated publicly, like the Victorian division, that that will</p>
<p>   occur. That is something for our party organisation and it always</p>
<p>   has been.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, the world bank boss has (inaudible) heading for</p>
<p>   a depression. Does that put more pressure on you to go to an early</p>
<p>   election, do you think (inaudible)</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well I am not going to underwrite the views of one individual. I</p>
<p>   thought talk of a depression was somewhat exaggerated. There is</p>
<p>   no doubt that Asia is going through a difficult economic time, and</p>
<p>   there's no doubt that if we had not taken action to strengthen</p>
<p>   our economy we would be hurting a lot more now, and it's equally</p>
<p>   the case that if we go back to the deficit debt policies of Labor</p>
<p>   or we play around with the experimental policies of One Nation we'll</p>
<p>   get hurt even more. As for the timing of the election, well, nothing</p>
<p>   has really changed. I've read a lot about the timing of the</p>
<p>   election and what form it will take. Can I say that nothing has</p>
<p>   changed. I will decide, I will decide the election date, as all</p>
<p>   Prime Ministers have done in the past, at the right time.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  What about (inaudible) the Deputy Prime Minister?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I haven't the faintest idea what anybody has...</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  ....that you are obliged to go to the polls if there is no resolution</p>
<p>   of your Wik plan by the end of this Parliamentary sitting?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  The election date will be decided by me in the normal way.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, if the Wik bill is not passed within a fortnight, will</p>
<p>   you use that as a trigger to hold an immediate double dissolution?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  It's already a trigger.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  ... on whether you will go to a d.d.?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Good try Fleur, good try.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Brian Harradine has said that he is willing to revisit the Wik issue.</p>
<p>   Would you like to meet with him before Parliament resumes to see</p>
<p>   whether there is scope?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well if Senator Harradine, who I respect on many issues, but disagree</p>
<p>   with on others, including Native Title, so far, if Senator Harradine</p>
<p>   wishes to speak to me and put a proposition to me, I'm always</p>
<p>   ready to do so. But our position hasn't changed. It is in Australia's</p>
<p>   interests that the Native Title issue be sorted out. Our Bill is</p>
<p>   a fair Bill. It's already a compromise. We've accommodated</p>
<p>   all interests and the idea that there can just be further compromised</p>
<p>   to the detriment of the national interest is misplaced. It is in</p>
<p>   the interest of the economies, particularly of Queensland and Western</p>
<p>   Australia, that this issue be sorted out, and it really must be</p>
<p>   sorted out. People lose sight of the fact that this is a national</p>
<p>   interest issue. I'm not pushing the Native Title Bill to score</p>
<p>   some ideological point or to have a double dissolution for the sake</p>
<p>   thereof. I want the Native Title issue sorted out.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Do you agree with Mr Fischer's assessment yesterday of how</p>
<p>   that needs to be done, in terms of an obligation (inaudible)?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I'm not saying anything additional to what I've already</p>
<p>   said on the timing of elections. You're just wasting your time.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Are you disappointed that Mr Fischer has been so forthright?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  That's an interesting variation on the theme, David. Good try.</p>
<p>   Two more and then I must go.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Are you obliged to go to a double dissolution on Wik if the Parliament</p>
<p>   doesn't (inaudible)?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  What's the next question?</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  If you could take your time, and surely (inaudible)?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  That's an even higher decibel rating.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  What's your message to those Taiwanese (inaudible) One Nation?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well my message to all foreign investors is that you are welcome</p>
<p>   in Australia. We have a foreign investment policy which protects</p>
<p>   the national interest but encourages foreign investment and my Government</p>
<p>   will guarantee a receptive climate for foreign investment because</p>
<p>   that generates Australian jobs and generates higher living standards</p>
<p>   in this country. If we had not received foreign investment over</p>
<p>   the years we would be a poorer country, we would have higher unemployment</p>
<p>   and our living standards would be lower. And I say it again, you</p>
<p>   can't have it both ways. You can't say that you are in</p>
<p>   favour of Australian jobs yet chase foreign investment out of Australia</p>
<p>   which means you're chasing jobs out of Australia. And the point</p>
<p>   people have got to understand in a global economy is that investment</p>
<p>   is footloose.</p>
<p>  If it's not welcome in one part of the world it will go somewhere</p>
<p>   else and it will take the jobs that would have been employed in</p>
<p>   that first part of the world with it and that's the message</p>
<p>   for Australians who may think there's some easy solution in</p>
<p>   saying no to foreign investment. If you say no to foreign investment,</p>
<p>   you're saying no to Australian jobs, and by the tens of thousands,</p>
<p>   and that would be a very tragic outcome for this country. Thank</p>
<p>   you.</p>
<p>   [ENDS]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
