<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7525</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPENING OF THE CYPRUS COMMUNITY CLUB OF NSW STANMORE - 12 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007525.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING OF THE CYPRUS COMMUNITY CLUB OF NSW<br />
STANMORE 12 MARCH 1989<br />
Mr President,<br />
Distinguished Guests,<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen.<br />
Tonight's ceremony marks the sixtieth anniversary of your<br />
club. Looking around your new club premises, I see the evidence of<br />
the determination of the Cypriot-Australian community to<br />
make the very best of life in this great country.<br />
So in celebrating that landmark we are celebrating not just<br />
an achievement by the Cypriot community of New South Wales<br />
but indeed a genuinely Australian success story.<br />
Australians and Cypriots have been in friendly contact for<br />
many years now.<br />
The first Cypriots attracted to Australia arrived in the<br />
gold rush days of the 1850s.<br />
In the sixty years this club has been in existence the size<br />
of the Greek Cypriot population in Australia has grown<br />
substantially.<br />
There are now very strong and very respected Cypriot<br />
communities here in Sydney, in Melbourne and in the other<br />
capital cities of Australia.<br />
Indeed Australia is now the home of the world's second<br />
largest Cypriot community outside Cyprus itself.<br />
Many members of this community have made their mark as<br />
entrepreneurs in business.<br />
You have provided leaders in public affairs, most notably<br />
Andrew and Theo Theophanous, who represent the Australian<br />
Labor Party in respectively the Federal and Victorian<br />
Parliaments. You can be proud in particular of Andrew Theophanous' work<br />
as Chairman of the ALP Caucus Committee on Immigration and<br />
Ethnic Affairs. </p>
<p>The role of community organisations like yours in Australia<br />
is sometimes understated.<br />
But you provide a crucial meeting place for<br />
Cypriot-Australians.<br />
The growth and popularity of the Cyprus Community Club is<br />
testimony to your community's desire to maintain your<br />
cultural heritage, as part of your new life in a new land.<br />
At the same time, your generous donations each year to aid<br />
cancer research clearly manifest a commitment to and<br />
identification with the broader community.<br />
I recall with pleasure my own visit to Cyprus in 1987 and<br />
the talks I held with the then President Kyprianou.<br />
Indeed it was a happy coincidence, in view of the large<br />
Cypriot-Australian community, that as part of a longer visit<br />
to the Middle East and Switzerland in late January and early<br />
February 1987, my visit to Larnaca fell on January 26<br />
Australia Day.<br />
I also recall the const'ructive meeting I held in Canberra<br />
last May with a delegation of Cypriot MPs led by Dr Vassos<br />
Lyssarides, President of the House of Representatives.<br />
And it is always a pleasure to meet Cypriot representatives<br />
at Commonwealth meetings.<br />
I share with you a deep concern for the situation in Cyprus.<br />
The Australian Government continues to recognise the<br />
Government of Cyprus as the sole legitimate Government in<br />
Cyprus and has consistently and strongly supported the<br />
sovereignty, independence, unity and non-aligned status of<br />
Cyprus. The Australian Government has condemned vigorously the<br />
Turkish invasion of Cyprus and is committed to pursuing a<br />
peaceful resolution to the conflict and issues affecting the<br />
people of Cyprus.<br />
We remain willing to help, in particular though our<br />
contribution to the United Nations' Peacekeeping Forces in<br />
Cyprus. We are strongly of the view that the problems of Cyprus can<br />
only be resolved through negotiations and dialogue.<br />
While the Government regrets the circumstances that have<br />
forced many people to leave Cyprus, we have never regretted<br />
that you chose Australia as your new home.<br />
Cypriots, and millions of other people from all parts of the<br />
globe, have come to Australia to build a new home here. </p>
<p>Your efforts, dedication and commitment to your new home<br />
have been vital to the foundation and maintenance of our<br />
national prosperity.<br />
It is largely in recognition of this vital contribution that<br />
my Government so strongly supports the principles of<br />
mult i cult u rali sin.<br />
It is a source of great strength for our society that we<br />
acknowledge and respect the cultural diversity of our nation<br />
as well as accept the economic benefits which arise from the<br />
immigration program.<br />
In keeping with this commitment, my Government is developing<br />
the National Agenda for a Multicultural Australia, a package<br />
of principles and policy initiatives that will give tangible<br />
expression and long-term direction to our commitment to<br />
multiculturali sm.<br />
When we release the National Agenda for a Multicultural<br />
Australia later this year, the issues it addresses will set<br />
a direction of lasting benefit for all Australians as we<br />
approach the year 2000.<br />
My Government will not retreat from its commitment to<br />
multiculturalism. To do so as some of our opponents have done would be to<br />
disown and offend all those Australians who have come here<br />
from overseas and whose loyalty and commitment to this<br />
country have never been questioned by me or my Government.<br />
We are committed to making better use of immigrants' skills,<br />
education and entrepreneurial drive.<br />
We are committed to maintaining and developing our language<br />
resources in order to advance Australia's trade, tourism and<br />
diplomatic interests.<br />
And we are closely examining the manner by which overseas<br />
qualifications are recognised to ensure that the skills of<br />
immigrants are more fully and more effectively utilised.<br />
We intend to ensure that all eligible people have access to<br />
Government services that barriers of language and cultural<br />
difference are no longer sources of inequality and<br />
injustice.<br />
While we are intent on breaking down barriers to Government<br />
services, so that no cultural group will be disadvantaged,<br />
let me also make clear that, in Australia, social rights are<br />
balanced by responsibilities.<br />
And in saying this let me address quite directly the<br />
concerns about multiculturalism that have been expressed<br />
following certain recent highly publicised events in this<br />
country. </p>
<p>Angry demonstrations against visiting Heads of Government or<br />
State, such as Prime Minister Thatcher and President<br />
Sartzetakis; incitement to religious bigotry, such as that<br />
recently directed at Jewish Australians; violent reactions<br />
to protests at consulates; and threatened violence against<br />
authors and booksellers events such as these have been<br />
perceived or alleged to be somehow a consequence of<br />
Australia's policy of multiculturalism.<br />
Let me say at the outset that such events are thoroughly<br />
unacceptable to me and to the Government. They are<br />
repugnant and in a clear sense of the word, they are<br />
un-Australian.<br />
People are right to be concerned if they apprehend that<br />
multiculturalism means that the conflicts of another<br />
continent and another age can be imported, perpetuated and<br />
pursued in this country. We do not ask people to forget<br />
their past, but we do require them to express their concerns<br />
within an Australian framework of law and tolerance.<br />
Therefore I want to set the record straight for the benefit<br />
of those who misunderstand or misrepresent multiculturalism.<br />
Let me say it quite unequivocally and unambiguously:<br />
multiculturalism is not a licence to stray beyond the law,<br />
least of all to threaten the property or life of any other<br />
human being, be they Australian, British or any other<br />
nationality. Let us recognise the regrettable truth that cultural<br />
conflict and ethnic rivalry, not infrequently accompanied by<br />
violence, is a fact of Australian history. It existed long<br />
before the word multiculturalism was heard and indeed long<br />
before the era of post-war immigration. I need refer only<br />
to the experience of Aborigines, the Chinese, the Irish and<br />
the Jews during the first 150 years after European<br />
settlement. Now, as then, the use or threatened use of violence remains<br />
anathema to the very concept of the rule of law and the<br />
right of the individual to its protection. It is also<br />
totally unacceptable in terms of multiculturalism which,<br />
above all else, espouses the virtues of tolerance.<br />
The right to the free expression of opinion, within the<br />
constraints of the law, works both ways. Freedom of<br />
expression is founded on the same principle as the right to<br />
disagree with what is expressed. As I said in Parliament<br />
last week, Australia sets the highest value on the rights of<br />
individuals to express their views freely and without fear<br />
of recrimination providing all parties stay within the<br />
limits imposed by the laws of this country. </p>
<p>At its core, multiculturalism is about tolerance tolerance<br />
of diversity, of individuality, of difference. Tolerance<br />
means nothing if it is confined to opinions with which one<br />
agrees. Multiculturalism is the enemy of intolerance it<br />
is the natural ally of those of us who cherish freedom and<br />
individuality, the right to be different, the right to a<br />
fair go, the idea of Jack being as good as his master in<br />
other words, the very core of what it means to be an<br />
Australian. I had not intended to inject a partisan note into this<br />
event, but I cannot let pass without comment a recent<br />
statement by-the Opposition Leader, Mr Howard.<br />
In a radio interview on Friday, Mr Howard has, apparently<br />
mischievously, distorted an important element of the<br />
Parliamentary statement I made on the important issue of The<br />
Satanic Verses.<br />
In Parliament last week, I said:<br />
" this Government was not one which was demanding<br />
adherence to one set of values. That is not the sort of<br />
society Australia is. But that does not mean that there<br />
are not values to which we have the strongest commitment<br />
and, in particular, we have the commitment to the right<br />
to speak freely without fear of violent reprisal or<br />
threat."<br />
I would have thought those words were beyond<br />
misunderstanding. Indeed I said at the time that I thought<br />
both sides of Parliament held that value as fundamentally<br />
important. But to my astonishment, I find Mr Howard has decided to<br />
pretend that what I said was that " we don't require any<br />
basic set of values in this country". He actually claimed<br />
in this interview that " the thinking behind [ my] answer was,<br />
we don't really require certain basic things"<br />
I can't believe Mr Howard misheard the full comments I made<br />
in Parliament. After all, he sits only a few feet away from<br />
me. He had the opportunity, then, to dissent but, as one<br />
would indeed expect, all the indications from the Opposition<br />
were of agreement with what I said.<br />
So I have to conclude that this later distortion of what I<br />
said is a deliberate attempt to make it seem I stand on the<br />
side of those who advocate violence in Australia. And I<br />
conclude too that it is a foolish attempt by Mr Howard to<br />
throw fuel onto the fire of this regrettable affair of The<br />
Satanic Verses. It is not only foolish it is utterly<br />
contemptible. So let me repeat, at least for Mr Howard's benefit, what I<br />
have said before as to the limits that exist on<br />
multiculturalism. </p>
<p>First, all Australians must accept the basic structures of<br />
Australian society that includes the rule of law,<br />
Parliamentary democracy, and English as our national<br />
language. Second, the right to express one's own culture and beliefs<br />
within this framework involves a reciprocal responsibility<br />
to accept the right of others to express their views and<br />
values. Third, multiculturalism assumes an overriding and unifying<br />
commitment to Australia, to its interest and future. This<br />
means, in part, that the conflicts and rivalries of the old<br />
world must yield, in the final analysis, to our common<br />
identity and our common loyalty as Australians first and<br />
foremost.<br />
Within these limits, all Australians are free to express,<br />
preserve, develop or share such of their individual heritage<br />
and experience as they wish. Indeed, it is this freedom,<br />
and the tolerance it presumes, that is one of the most<br />
potent sources of loyalty to this great country of ours. It<br />
is the very basis of our social cohesion. Those who would<br />
circumscribe or compromise that freedom whatever side of<br />
the religious or political fence they come from do this<br />
country, and themselves, a great disservice.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Cypriots who have made their home in Australia have<br />
certainly made good their commitment to Australia.<br />
Tonight's function is a gathering of Australians who share a<br />
common commitment to the future of Australia.<br />
This new club is a just reward for what you have achieved<br />
and will serve as a reminder to you all of the significant<br />
contribution you have already made and will continue to make<br />
to Australia.<br />
I congratulate everyone involved with the organisation of<br />
this evening's celebration.<br />
I have much pleasure in declaring these new club rooms open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
