<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5211</transcript-id>
    <title>LOAN COUNCIL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/12/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005211.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIMINEIST E<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 7 DECEMBER 1979<br />
LOAN COUNCIL<br />
Commonwealth and State Governments' meeting today as Loan Council,<br />
approved nine new projects under the special financing programme<br />
designed to accelerate the national development.<br />
It has been the concern of the Commonwealth for some time that<br />
national development should not be impeded because of inadequate<br />
supporting capital facilities whether they be power generating<br />
plants, roads, coal loaders, or ports.<br />
The Loan Council endorsed the provisions of $ 489 million for<br />
electricity power generation; $ 182 million for rail electrification;<br />
$ 53 million for conversion away from oil fired generation; and<br />
million for provision of other infrastructure facilities.<br />
The $ 800 million programme agreed to, will expedite the development<br />
of energy reserves which are alternatives to liquid fuels.<br />
It will increase the national capacity for the export of these<br />
reserves. It will increase the extent to which these reserves can be used<br />
on the domestic market.<br />
It will provide an unprecedented coal-fired power base for mining<br />
and manufacturing investment in Australia including the<br />
domestic processing of our own raw materials.<br />
As part of this programme for national development and consistent<br />
with our initiatives in liquid fuel conservation, the Commonwealth<br />
today sought Loan Council approval for 3 projects of its own, the<br />
chief of which is the electrification of the Sydney to Melbourne<br />
Rail Link. / 2 </p>
<p>The Commonwealth has, subject to the agreement of the<br />
States, agreed to support this project in principle.<br />
Having regard to increasing oil prices and the effect<br />
this will have on various surface transport costs,<br />
the Commonwealth has taken the view that, because of<br />
the lead times involved, it is now appropriate to seek firm<br />
proposals and detailed technical advice on the works that<br />
would be involved in electrifying'the Sydney to Melbourne<br />
Railway. Preliminary investigations and planning will be carried<br />
out by private consultants in liaison with the NSW<br />
and Victorian Railway Authorities. The Commonwealth has<br />
undertaken to meet the costs of such a feasibility study,<br />
including consultancy fees, with a view to a report being<br />
presented to the June 1980 Meeting of the Premiers' Conference.<br />
on the basis of this report firm decisions for the project<br />
should then be taken, but precise terms of reference for<br />
the study will be agreed upon with the States and announced<br />
next week.<br />
In conjunction with this initiative agreement has been reached<br />
between the Commonwealth, all States, and the Northern Territory,<br />
on the suggestion of Sir Charles Court, for the establishment of<br />
a separate joint study of the practicality of electrification of<br />
the Government railway systems of Australia.<br />
This study is designed toiassess<br />
the economies of such a proposal including railway<br />
upgrading requirements which would be necessary<br />
to promote efficiencies in electric rail transport<br />
the impact of rail electrification on consumption<br />
of liquid fuels / 3 </p>
<p>any needs for expanded capacities for electricity<br />
generation and supply, and consequent requirements<br />
that electrification would make<br />
assessment of the impact of increased demand on<br />
facilities for coal production and shipment<br />
the timetable and programme needed to optimize<br />
economic returns from electrification of rail links.<br />
A preliminary report indicating the scope and approach to be taken<br />
in the joint study made to the Governments by 1st June, -1980.<br />
This will enable Governments to consider relative priorities<br />
and give further guidance.<br />
The joint study will be assisted by private consultants but full<br />
use will be made of Government railway authorities and their<br />
considerable knowledge of railway factors.<br />
As part of the expanding development prog ramme the Commonwealth<br />
today sought the co-operation of the New South Wales and<br />
Queensland governme nts in a study to determine the requirements<br />
which will facilitate the expanding trade in export of steaming<br />
coal.<br />
Exports-. of steaming coal are anticipated to rise from 6 million<br />
tonnes per year to approximately -100 million tonnes by the end<br />
of the century. Concern has been expressed about the<br />
availability of proper facilities to cope with this enormous<br />
increase in exports of steam ' ing coal from Australian mines<br />
to overseas power stations, cement works and steel mills.<br />
This increase will require significant expansion of existing<br />
facilities. The Commonwealth is anxious that such facilities<br />
should exist to allow Australia to take full advantage of the<br />
trading opportunities which seem likely to arise as a result<br />
of our extensive reserves of steaming coal. / 4 </p>
<p>All this development is now possible because in the last four<br />
years the fundamentals of the Australian economy have been<br />
restored. Australia's inflation rate is now below that of the O. E. C. D.<br />
average and well below some of our major trading partners.<br />
Development projects announced today take advantage of three<br />
major strengths in our national economy--our new international<br />
competitiveness; our abundance of raw materials and energy<br />
resources in a world hungry for both; and the quality and<br />
calibre of our human resources.<br />
The need for development has given new urgency as a result<br />
of the deteriorating international energy position.<br />
This makes it imperative that our drive towards<br />
alternatives to liquid fuels must continue and accelerate.<br />
But at the same time, the international energy crisis has<br />
created -unique opportunities for Australia, and today's<br />
announcements place us advantageously to capitalise on<br />
these opportunities.<br />
The development of alternative energy sources and the use of<br />
our coal-fired energy reserves will give a thrust to<br />
national development in the 80' s which will strengthen the<br />
economy and its capacity to provide the right opportunity<br />
for new employment and investment.<br />
These opportunities have been clearly seen by private<br />
enterprise and were evident from the involvement of overseas<br />
and domestic capital in development projects for Australia.<br />
The Government has its part to play.<br />
It has already created the economic climate in which<br />
this development can profitably take place. </p>
<p>This new determination to see that capital works which<br />
are needed to provide the structure for private<br />
enterprise are able to proceed with urgency.<br />
Because of this, at a historic mneeting last November, the<br />
Loan Council approved a new borrowing programme to finance<br />
provisions for future development.<br />
our emphasis then was on creation of an adequate supply<br />
of coal-fired energy to meet our needs during the next<br />
decade. At that-meeting the Commonwealth approved twelve projects<br />
estimated at a total of $ 1.7 billion ( in June 1978 prices).<br />
The. actual borrowings in the last financial year amounted<br />
to $ 149 million and the June Loan Council meeting approved<br />
a further $ 393 million for those projects in 1979-80.<br />
Consistent with our plan for national development the<br />
allocation of approvals was as follows:-<br />
electricity generation $ 869 million<br />
coal loaders $ 164 million<br />
other resources development $ 643 million<br />
other projects $ 91 million<br />
The projects approved today represent a continuation of the<br />
significant initiative begun last year.<br />
Since November. 1978, however, when the first series of<br />
projects were announced, the world energy situation has<br />
further deteriorated.<br />
Consequently, in assessing projects, particular<br />
attention has been given to those coal-based energy projects<br />
which fit into our over-all energy policy.<br />
These are projects which specifically encourage either<br />
the conservation of oil, or alternatives to its use. </p>
<p>The major projects announced today relate to the provision<br />
of electricity generation capacity.<br />
Three of them,. for which a total of $ 489 million has been<br />
approved, are to provide additional generating capacity<br />
using Australia's abundant coal resources.<br />
These projects are:<br />
The B'ayswater Electricity Project in New South' Wal'es<br />
$ 142 million has been approved for this project near<br />
Musswellbrook in the Hunter Valley.<br />
The first stage will involve the consideration of<br />
2 x 660 Mw -units and the development of associated<br />
coal and water supplies.<br />
The advancement of the Tarong* Power Station in Queensland<br />
$ 202 million has been approved to bring the first 350 Mw<br />
unit on-stream in May 1984 rather than the planned<br />
October 1985.<br />
The Northern Power Station in South Australia<br />
$ 145 million has been approved for this programme.<br />
This provides for construction of a coal-fired power<br />
station at Port Augusta and further development of the<br />
Leigh Creek coal field, including re-location of existing<br />
township.<br />
Two other electricity projects, while not aimed at providing<br />
additional capacity, will conserve fuel oil by partially<br />
converting power stations to other forms of fuel. / 7 </p>
<p>The Kwinana Power Station in Western Australia<br />
Approval has been granted of $ 28.5 million for this project.<br />
It will provide a further two generating units converted<br />
from oil to dual coal/ oil, reducing the station's<br />
dependance on oil to the point where less than 3% of its<br />
capacity will be dependant totally on oil fule.<br />
The Hydro-Electric Commission Fuel Oil Conservation Project<br />
in Tasmania<br />
For this project $ 25 million has been approved.<br />
It is designed to increase the capacity and flexibility<br />
of the Commission's hydro power generating system and<br />
to reduce the use of the oil-fired thermal station at<br />
Bell Bay.<br />
North West Shelf Infrastructure<br />
One further project is closely related to major<br />
private resource development.<br />
Approval was given last November to special infrastructure<br />
borrowing for the Dampier-Perth Gas Pipeline.<br />
An integral part of the massive North-West Shelf project.<br />
Approval has now been given for further infrastructure<br />
financing associated with the North-West Shelf.<br />
A total of $ 45 million has been approved to meet<br />
essential needs in the form of water supply, airport,<br />
social and civic facilities, and the acceleration of the<br />
development of the pipeline. </p>
<p>RAIL ELECTRIFICATION<br />
The increased cost of fuel oil means that the electrification<br />
of major rail links has assumed a new significance.<br />
Electrification will result in savings in diesel fuel<br />
consumption sales providing a range of operating and<br />
economic benefits.<br />
I have already indicated the details of the Commonwealth<br />
initiative in relation to the electrification of the<br />
Melbourne to Sydney railway link. However, borrowings<br />
for two major rail electrification projects, proposed<br />
by the States, have now been approved under the infrastructure<br />
guidelines. Brisbane Railway Electrification in Queensland<br />
For this $ 68 million has been approved. Approval in<br />
principle had been given in June 1979. This provides for<br />
the upgrading of public transport in Brisbane involving<br />
rail electrification and the intergration of car, bus<br />
and rail traffic.<br />
The Gosford to Newcastle Rail Electrification Project<br />
in New South Wales<br />
For this $ 114 million has been approved involving the<br />
electrification of 90k of double track railway line between<br />
Gosford and Newcastle.<br />
These initiatives evidence the determination of national<br />
transport development must be based on alternatives to<br />
liquid fuels. / 9<br />
L7-</p>
<p>COMMONWEALTH PROJECTS<br />
At the first meeting for which the Loan Council gave special<br />
borrowing approvals all projects were proposed by State Governments.<br />
At today's Loan Council meeting the Commonwealth proposed three<br />
projects under the infrastructure guidelines.<br />
One of these was the electrification of the Melbourne-Sydney<br />
rail link.<br />
The other two projects are as follows<br />
1. The Telecommunications Rural Sector Network<br />
For this, $ 30 million has been approved.<br />
It is for the acceleration of the programme to<br />
convert most of the telecommunications rural<br />
sector network to automatic exchanges by 1985.<br />
2. Adelaide-Crystal Brook Standard Gauge Rail Link<br />
The Loan Council has approved in principle the<br />
Commonwealth's proposal for borrowing to finance<br />
the construction of this link. A detailed proposal<br />
will be put to the Loan Council by the Commonwealth<br />
incorporating spending for the year of $ 62 million.<br />
ALTERNATIVE FUNDING<br />
Two other projects proposed by the States were viewed by the<br />
Loan Council as being more appropriately suited to be funded<br />
in specific Commonwealth programmes. These were<br />
1. WURDEE BOLUC PIPELINE IN VICTORIA<br />
A special borrowing of $ 12 million has been sought<br />
to increase the water supply of Geelong and<br />
Bellarine Peninsulars. Consideration will be<br />
given to this project under the National Water<br />
Resources Programme.<br />
2. THE NORTH EAST CORRIDOR TRANSIT PROJECT SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
$ 27 million was sought for this project for an electrically<br />
powered light rapid transit system in suburban Adelaide.<br />
This project will be considered in the Urban Public<br />
Transport Programme. </p>
<p>PORTLAND VICTORIA<br />
At the June, 1979 Loan Council Meeting, approval in principle was<br />
recommended for inclusion under the infrastructure programme and<br />
finance for the provision of power supply associated with the<br />
development of an alumina smelter in Portland, Victoria.<br />
It is expected that this proposal involving estimated borrowings<br />
of $ 120 million will be formally considered in 1980.<br />
It can be seen that the heavy emphasis in the total plan for<br />
national development has been placed on projects which<br />
facilitate electricity generation.<br />
on-going programmes amounting to $ 869 million ( at June 1978 prices)<br />
were approved in November 1978 out of a total borrowing approval<br />
of $ 1.7 billion.<br />
Electricity generation projects account for $ 489 million out<br />
of the additional $ 800 million which was approved by Loan Council<br />
today. However, in addition to projects already approved, the Commonwealth<br />
has invited Premiers to submit further proposals under the<br />
infrastructure programme for the development of further electricity<br />
generation projects.<br />
This initiative by the Commonwealth has been motivated by the<br />
worsening international energy position in conjunction with the<br />
availability of Australia's reserves of coal.<br />
This highlights Australia's potential for development of energyintensive,<br />
export-oriented industries, and it is the Commonwealth's<br />
concern that these should not be inhibited by the unavailability<br />
of adequate electricity reserves. </p>
<p>11.<br />
The Commonwealth is gratified by the positive response<br />
of the States to the development programme who have indicated<br />
that they will be proposing further projects designed to<br />
improve the electricity generation programme.<br />
These will be considered at future meetings of the Loan Council.<br />
000---</p>
<p>ATTACHMENT 1<br />
SPECIAL ADDITIONS TO STATE SEMI-GOVERNMENT BORROWING PROGRAMS UNDER<br />
INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING GUIDELINES AMOUNTS AND PHASING IN<br />
JUNE 1978 PRICES TOTAL 1978-79 1979-80 1979-80 1 1980-81 1981-82 1982-83 1983-84 1984-85 1985-8<br />
SPECIAL Approved Approved<br />
ADDITION in Nov in June<br />
1978 1979<br />
June ' 78 June ' 79<br />
prices prices<br />
$ m $ m $ m $ m $ m $ m $ m $ m $ m $ m<br />
NSW Coal Loaders 89 24 32 35.0 33<br />
Eraring Electricity 210 55 80 81.0 75<br />
Vici VIC Loy Yang Electricity 343 35 88 96.5 37 119 64<br />
World Trade Centre 56 10 24 17.3 20 2<br />
QLD Hay Pt Coal Loaders 75 40 44.0 35<br />
Electricity Projects 130 70 76.0 60<br />
SA Redcliff 186 11 70 96 4 4<br />
WA Dampier-Perth Pipeline 416 133 263 17 3<br />
Pilbara Electricity 111 -5 4.5 11 15 16 16 27 21<br />
Worsley Rail and Water 41 9( a) 20 14.9 12 1<br />
TAS Hydro-electric power 75 15 15 16.5 15 15 15<br />
Water supply projects 35 10 8 7.0 8 5 4<br />
1,767158393392.7316313236283<br />
In the event no borrowings were undertaken for this project in 1978-79. </p>
<p>ATTACHMENT 2<br />
SPECIAL ADDITIONS TO STATE SEMI-GOVERNMENT BORROWING PROGRAMS UNDER INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING GUIDELINES<br />
AMOUNTS PHASING ( At June 1979 prices unless otherwise indicated)<br />
State Project TOTAL Special 1979/ 80 1980/ 81 1981/ 82 1982/ 83 1983/ 84 1984/ 85 1985/ 86 1986/<br />
Addition<br />
N. S. W. Bayswater Electricity 142 12 38 92<br />
Gosford-Newcastle<br />
Rail Electrification 114 18 36 41 19<br />
QLD Brisbane Railway<br />
Electrification 68 8 20 22 18<br />
Power Stations:<br />
Advancement of Tarong 202 0 32 78 92<br />
S. A. Northern Power Station 145 10 13 17 19 26 25 19 18<br />
W. A. North West Shelf Gas:<br />
Infrastructure 45 1 21 .2 11 12<br />
Kwinana Power Station.. 28.5 2.4 5 14 6.4 0.7<br />
Conversion ( c)<br />
TAS Hydro-Electric Commission:<br />
Fuel Oil Conservation 25 4.5 6.8 8.6 5.1<br />
CTH Telecommunications Rural<br />
Sector Network 30 30<br />
TOTAL: 799.5 85.9 172.0 283.6 171.5 26.7 24 19 18<br />
December 1979 prices<br />
January 1979 prices<br />
current prices<br />
current prices with provision made for inflation </p>
<p>A'i" I'ACH 9MNT 3<br />
INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING<br />
SUMMARY OF PROJECTS APPROVED BY LOAN COUNCIL<br />
7 December 1979 </p>
<p>BAYSWATER ELECTRICITY PROJECT ( NSW)<br />
Brief Description<br />
The Bayswater Power Station near Muswellbrook in the<br />
Hunter Valley is required to meet load growths arising from<br />
the development of large, new electricity intensive<br />
industries. The project, the first stage of the station,<br />
involves the construction of 2 x 660 miW units and development<br />
of associated coal and water supplies.<br />
Funding Arrangements<br />
Total cost is estimated at 590m in June 1979 prices.<br />
Total funding arrangements cannot be specified currently.<br />
However funds from the Electricity Commissions sources for<br />
the 3 years from 1979/ 80 are fully committed to other<br />
projects and funding in full by special infrastructure additions<br />
totalling $ 142m in June 1979 prices is required with further<br />
requirements beyond 1981-82 possible.<br />
Phasing Special additions required in the 3 years commencing<br />
1979/ 80 are $ 12, $ 38 and 892 million in June 1979 prices.<br />
Very little flexibility exists in these timings if the<br />
units are to be phased in as planned for the winters of<br />
1985 and 1986.<br />
General Comments<br />
The project is essential for provision of adequate<br />
electrical energy in N. S. W. from 1985 onwards. This is<br />
particularly important in the light of oil supply problems<br />
and expected transfer of many domestic and industrial<br />
loads to electricity.<br />
Proposed aluminium. refining developments could not<br />
be supplied without clear indications that Bayswater will<br />
be in commercial operation in 1985.<br />
Benefits for non metropolitan employment: 1,200<br />
workers will be employed during the construction phase<br />
and 315 will be required to operate the plant:-in addition<br />
there will be increased coal production with possible<br />
employment increases. </p>
<p>GOSFORD NEWCASTLE RAIL ELECTRIFICATION PROJECT<br />
Brief Description The electrification of 90 km of double track<br />
railway line . between Gosford and Newcastle together with<br />
of sidings, crossovers etc. The cost includes<br />
provision for electric locomotives and interurban electric<br />
cars, construction works, electrical equipment and the<br />
raising or replacement of more than 30 over bridges.<br />
Funding Arrangements Estimated total cost is $ 114m in June 1979 prices.<br />
As funds available for the Public Transport Commission for<br />
the 4 years 1979/ 80 to 1982/ 83 inclusive are fully committed<br />
to other projects funding in full from special infrastructure<br />
additions is required.<br />
Phasing Special additions required are $ 18m in 1979/ 80 and<br />
$ 36, $ 41 and $ 19 million in the following 3 years.<br />
The project should be comoleted as quickly as<br />
possible to take advantage of operating economies and the<br />
chance to conserve oil fuel.<br />
General comments Electrification of the Gosford Newcastle line will<br />
further reduce the Public Transport Commissions reliance on<br />
liquid fuel as a prime energy source. At present<br />
approximately 15% of the Commissions annual liquid fuel<br />
consumption is used between Sydney and Newcastle. </p>
<p>BRISBANE RAILWAY ELECTRIFICATION ( QLD)<br />
Brief Description Upgrading of public transport in Brisbane with the aim<br />
of providing an integrated passenger transport system involving<br />
rail electrification the provision of modern rail and bus<br />
rolling stock and the integration of car, bus and rail traffic<br />
through interchanges.<br />
Funding Arrangements<br />
The total cost of the completion of the upgrading<br />
program is estimated at $ 248m ( at current prices) of which<br />
$ 151m will be required over the 4 years ending 1982/ 83. The<br />
current States Grants ( Urban Public Transport) Act under<br />
which $ 48.6m will be contributed to the program also ends<br />
at that date. Two thirds of the remainder of the program<br />
$ 68m will be funded from special infrastructure additions.<br />
Phasing Sm<br />
1979-80 8<br />
1980-81<br />
1981-82 22<br />
1982-83 18 68m<br />
General Comments<br />
While the project may not directly contribute to<br />
development it will result in the more rational utilisation<br />
of Australia's natural resources. Electrification will<br />
brinq about a 3% drop in Queensland railway oil consumption<br />
equal to 100,000 barrels of crude oil per annum. </p>
<p>ADVANCEMENT OF TARONG POWER STATION (. QLD).<br />
Brief De'scription Advancement of the construction of the Tarong<br />
Power Station program to bring the first 350 MW unit on<br />
stream in May 1984, rather than the planned October 1985,<br />
to ensure sufficient power generation in 1984 to allow the<br />
development of three planned aluminium smelters.<br />
Three further 350 MW units will be in service<br />
by the end of 1986, rather than 1988 as planned.<br />
Funding Arrangements The total Tarong project will cost $ 812 million<br />
( Dec 1979 prices) Expenditure on the accelerated project<br />
will amount to $ 480 million over the period 1979-80 to<br />
1982-83 or an increase of $ 202 million over the present<br />
development program.<br />
Queensland is already in receipt of special<br />
infrastructure additions for power station projects and<br />
there is no scope for raising the $ 202 million required<br />
for advancing the Tarong Project from State Government or<br />
State Electricity Commission of Queensland sources.<br />
Phasing The lead time associated with tiae construction of<br />
power stations is such that funding must be approved now<br />
and expenditure committed although additional funds will<br />
not be required until 1980-81 as follows:-<br />
1980-81 $ 32 million ( in December 1979 prices)<br />
1981-82 $ 78 million<br />
1932-83 $ 92 million<br />
General Comments As a result of three new aluminium smelter projects<br />
up to 600MW of electr-icity in excess of available supply will<br />
be required by 1984. The State Electricity Commission<br />
investigated the options available for providing additional<br />
generating capacity and concluded that the most realistic<br />
course was to accelerate the Tarong Power Station Project.<br />
The construction of the power station and associated<br />
works will provide employment for approximately 1,000 men<br />
( peaking at 1,1400) for up to 7 years. The permanent<br />
work force for the stations operation will be 300. Further<br />
jobs will be created by the development of the associated<br />
mines;* Additional employment opportunitie ' s will be<br />
generated by the planned aluminium smelters.. </p>
<p>NORTHERN POWER STATION ( SA)<br />
Brief Description The project comprises construction of a coal-fired<br />
power station at Port Agusta, the first stage of which is<br />
the installation of two 250 MW units, and further development<br />
of the Leigh Creek coalfield including relocation of the<br />
existing township and purchase of additional mining equipment.<br />
The first generating unit will come on stream<br />
towards the end of 1983 and the second a year later.<br />
Funding Arrangements The total cost of the project is estimated at<br />
$ 263 m in June 1979 prices. The Electricity Trust of<br />
South Australia requires special additions for its borrowing<br />
program of $ 145m ( at June 1979 prices) to assist financing<br />
of the project.<br />
Phasing: $ m at June 1979 prices<br />
1979-80<br />
1980-81 13<br />
1981-82 17<br />
1982-83 19<br />
1983 -84 26<br />
1984-85 24<br />
1985-86 19<br />
1986-87 18<br />
$ 145 m<br />
Construction of the power station has been in<br />
progress for 12 months approximately and site preparation<br />
work for the new township of Leigh Creek South is in progress.<br />
A number of major contracts have been left.<br />
General Comments The power station and its associated Works are<br />
essential to ensure adequate power supplies are available<br />
for industrial and general consumers in the Adelaide<br />
metropolitan area by the late 1980' s. The expansion of<br />
existing industry and the development of new industry is<br />
dependent on assured and economic power supplies.<br />
The project will also reduce the dependence of<br />
the State's electricty supply or natural gas from the<br />
Cooper Basin. During the construction phase 400 workers will<br />
be employed on the power station while 250 will be employed<br />
in building the new township and additional facilities at<br />
Leigh Creek. </p>
<p>NORTH WEST SHELF GAS PROJECT SOCiAL, CIVIC<br />
AND ECONOMIC. INFRASTRUCTURE<br />
Brief Description Essential infrastructure needs in the form of<br />
water supply, airport, general purpose berth and social<br />
and civic facilities to meet the requirements arising<br />
from the development project and the projected doubling<br />
of Karratha's population.<br />
Funding Arrangements Estimated total expenditure on the relevant<br />
infrastructure works is $ 73.1 m ( in Jan 1979 prices) of<br />
which $ 45m is sought as a special addition. The remainder<br />
of the cost of projects will be bourne by the State, various<br />
State authorities, the joint venturers-and in some cases will<br />
be partly funded through Commonwealth-State assistance programs.<br />
An in-principle agreement to a special addition<br />
for the second stage of the water supply upgrading was reached.<br />
Phasing $ m ( in January 1979 prices)<br />
1979-80 1<br />
1980-81 21<br />
1981-82 11<br />
1982-83 12<br />
General Comments The infrastructure elements are essential components<br />
of the gas project which in total will make a major<br />
contribution to Australian resource development and mineral<br />
export proqgram. The operational workforce on the N. W. She&amp; lf<br />
project will be approximately 200 off-shore, 500 on-shore<br />
and 50 on the gas pipeline. However during the construction<br />
phase available jobs will rise to 10,450 in 1983 falling to<br />
about 4,000 in 1985. </p>
<p>KWINANA POWER STATION CONVERSION<br />
Brief Descriptionl Conversion of a further two generating units at<br />
the Kwinana Power Station from oil to dual coal/ oil<br />
firing. Twounits have already been converted. These<br />
additional conversion would reduce the stations' dependence<br />
on oil to the point where less than 30% of its capacity<br />
would be dependent totally on oil fuel.<br />
Funding Arrangements The total cost of the project is $ 28.5m at current<br />
prices. The State Electricity Commissions other capital<br />
works commitments necessitate the total funding of the<br />
conversion from special additions.<br />
Phasing $ m ( at current prices)<br />
1979-80 2.4<br />
1980-81<br />
1981-82 14.0<br />
1982-83 6.4<br />
1983-84 0.7<br />
28<br />
This phasing ensures that the reliablity of the power<br />
system will not be jeopardised while the units being<br />
converted are not operative for about a year.<br />
General Comments The continued development of Western Australia's<br />
natural resources and its mineral exporting industry<br />
require a stable and economic electricity supply.<br />
The conversion of oil fired units to coal will<br />
contribute to the future reliability and economy of the<br />
State electricity supply system. </p>
<p>HYDRO-ELECTRIC COMMISSION FUEL OIL CONSERVATION<br />
PROJECT ( TAS)<br />
Brief Description The object of the proposal is to increase the<br />
capacity and flexibility of the Commission's hydro-power<br />
generating system and to reduce the use of the oil<br />
fired thermal station at Bell Bay. There are two components;<br />
the raising of the existing Great Lake Dam and the<br />
acceleration of the Pieman River power development to bring<br />
the Rosebery and Lower Pieman stations on stream 6 months<br />
earlier than currently programmed.<br />
Funding Arrangements The total estimated cost of the project at June<br />
1979 prices is $ 25m the whole of which is sought as a<br />
special addition because the Commission is already committed<br />
to a peak capital development program over the next 5 years.<br />
Phasing $ m ( at June 1979 prices)<br />
1979-80<br />
1980-81 6.8<br />
1981-82 8.6<br />
1982-83 5.1<br />
General Comments The project will make use of Tasmania' s abundent<br />
water resources, will contribute to industry development<br />
and to employment both in the short-term, through the<br />
creation of 170 construction jobs, and in the long term.<br />
The project has indirect implications for the<br />
balance of payments through the reductions in the use of<br />
imported fuel oil that can be achieved. Significant<br />
direct savings will also be achieved through the reduction<br />
of oil fuel use. </p>
<p>TELECOMMUNICATIONS RURAL SECTOR<br />
NETWORK ( COMMONWEALTH)<br />
Brief Description An accelerated program to convert most of the<br />
telecommunications rural sector network to automatic<br />
exchanges by 1985, including associated upgrading of<br />
telephone lines.<br />
Funding Arrangements<br />
The total cost of Telecom Australia's program to<br />
complete rural upgrading by 1985 is estimated at $ 300m<br />
in June 1979 prices. Telecom plans to finance not<br />
less than half the costs of the program from internal<br />
sources and the balance from external borrowings.<br />
The special addition of $ 30m is to finance approximately<br />
half of the estimated expenditure in 1979-80.<br />
Phasing A special addition for 1979-80 only has been<br />
provided. General Comments<br />
In the absence of special funding arrangements the<br />
program would proceed but would not he completed until<br />
1990. The program is planned to reduce the number of<br />
subscribers On manual exchanges from 91,000 in 1979<br />
to about 10,000 in 1985.<br />
The program will greatly improve the. services to<br />
remote areas, make telecommunication available in areas<br />
where it is not yet available, assist the development of<br />
the pastoral and mining industries, stimulate employment<br />
in those industries<br />
7-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
