<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10352</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP SPEECH TO RYDE BUSINESS FORUM, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/05/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010352.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
21 May 1997 U<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
SPEECH TO RYDE BUSINESS FORUM, SYDNEY<br />
E O E<br />
Thank you very much Ian for those very warm words of introduction and to Cath<br />
King, to Jim Hull, the Mayor of the city of Ryde, other very well known and<br />
distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen, it's a great pleasure to be back at the Ryde<br />
Business Forum wearing my new hat and carrying my new responsibilities. Some<br />
things of course go on from year to year and one of those is the dedication of John<br />
Booth to the community of Ryde and I want to congratulate John and TWT on its antiunemployment<br />
initiative. The more small businesses that can do that, the better. The<br />
more small businesses who commit themselves out of a sense of social obligation and<br />
civic pride to reducing unemployment the better.<br />
Of course it would help ladies and gentlemen if we could even further reform the unfair<br />
dismissal laws which have acted as a barrier for a long time against small business<br />
employing more people and if I can say at this stage one of the small business<br />
initiatives of which I was particularly proud after we were elected was the<br />
implementation of our commitment to reform the unfair dismissal laws that we had<br />
inherited from the former Government, laws which actually worked as a disincentive<br />
against small business taking on staff We reformed them a lot and then a few weeks<br />
ago when I announced a package of measure for small business we decided to go even<br />
further and to completely exempt all small firms employing fewer than 15 people in<br />
relation to staff they'd had for less than 12 months, a proposal that I think every man<br />
and woman in this room who runs a small business would see the great common sense<br />
of and something that would make it easier for you to take a punt about employing one<br />
or two more people in your business, and as you all know, the solution really to<br />
Australia's unemployment problem lies more in the small businesses employing three<br />
and four, making that five and six than in any sort of expectation that the large<br />
corporations of Australia that are still into downsizing are going to pick up the<br />
unemployment slack.<br />
The only problem is that our political enemies in the Senate say they are going to<br />
disallow the regulations to bring in that under 15 rule and I have to say that if that<br />
regulation is disallowed then we will roll it back in the form of a bill and it's an<br />
illustration of some of the road blocks that lie along the path to economic reform and<br />
change in Australia.<br />
But John, again congratulations on the TWT initiative. It's a great example of a public<br />
spirited commitment to things that really matter about the community of Ryde and also<br />
the broader community of Australia. I am delighted to be here today to say a few<br />
things about the business climate, not only here but throughout Australia and also<br />
about some of the responses to the Federal budget. Can I say, I hope without any real </p>
<p>hyperbole but a natural tone of optimism that I believe general business conditions in<br />
Australia now are good and they are strengthening. If you look at the fundamentals<br />
we do have a much lower rate of inflation than we've had for many years. We do have<br />
significantly lower interest rates although they are not as low for small business as they<br />
are for housing and I know that's something that is in the minds of many people in<br />
small business all around Australia.<br />
What is more we have the prospect of maintaining low inflationary conditions in this<br />
country for some time into the future. I don't think it's an exaggeration to say that we<br />
appear as a community in common with other industrialised countries, we appear to<br />
have turned the corner and moved away from those years when we seem to have<br />
entrenched in our system high inflation and high inflationary expectations.<br />
We do have by world standards a very high level of economic growth. The Economist<br />
will argue about it. It's 3.5 Some will say it's 3 and a quarter. The best advice<br />
we have is that by year's end in budget terms we will be looking at a rate of about 4%.<br />
Now historically, that's very good. We're into the sixth year, I think, perhaps the fifth<br />
of recovery out of a very deep and a very damaging recession. The omens<br />
internationally are strong. The Asia Pacific region where we send most of our exports<br />
is still growing at a very strong rate. The American economy is very strong indeed and<br />
the news this morning that the Federal Reserve had decided not to increase interest<br />
rates in the United States has given a great deal of confidence to not only the markets<br />
in the United States but also the markets here in Australia. And the rate of growth in<br />
the US is good. Japan is not growing as strongly but certainly better than was the<br />
situation several years ago. The scene in Europe is more mixed, with the British<br />
economy being by far in gross terms, in inflation terms and unemployment terms the<br />
strongest of all the major European economies.<br />
Now I paint that international picture to put the point across that the general climate is<br />
quite conducive. There are of course a number of areas where there are still major<br />
concerns. Unemployment in this country remains high, and unacceptably high and the<br />
focus of policy must remain on unemployment and every time we think of reform,<br />
every time we think of change, we have to ask ourselves, will it make a contribution<br />
towards reducing Australia's level of unemployment? Generally speaking, it is a good,<br />
positive, optimistic climate for business. Now I don't deny that in some areas of the<br />
Australian economy, particularly in the small business sector, it's a mixed scene. I talk<br />
to a lot of men and women in small business and I get a different feedback. I wandered<br />
around today. Just about every second person I spoke to, I said how's business, and I<br />
got a mixed reaction, some very positive, some doing all right but it's tough, others not<br />
so good. Now I understand that and one of the great values of a gathering like this is<br />
to actually hear people making those comments and to feel that you are in touch with<br />
what they're saying and what are their concerns.<br />
The Budget, ladies and gentlemen, was designed to reinforce the fairly positive<br />
optimistic outlook for business. It wasn't a budget that went for gimmicks and rabbit<br />
out of a hat tricks. We didn't need in this budget, because of the expenditure<br />
reductions that we had made in the first budget, we didn't need to repeat that. I mean,<br />
there has always got to be a purpose to economic change. There's no such thing as<br />
economic reform being an end in itself You don't change the industrial relations<br />
system to make yourself feel better. You don't change the tax system to make yourself </p>
<p>feel better. You change it for a purpose and the purpose of economic policy is always<br />
to generate jobs, to improve the competitiveness of the Australian economy and to lift<br />
the living standards of the Australian people.<br />
Now they're the three things that you should judge every measure against. Does it<br />
help to generate jobs? Does it improve the competitiveness of the Australian economy<br />
and does it build the living standards of the Australian people? Now the greatest thing<br />
that I think the budget that Peter Costello brought down last week did, the greatest<br />
thing it did was to lay down a pathway to this country being back in the black at the<br />
end of the third year of the first term of my Government. I mean, we did inherit a<br />
deficit of $ 10.5 billion and by year three of my Government's first term, we will have a<br />
surplus of $ 1.6 billion and of all of the, and as I went around the business community,<br />
whether it was big or small, before the last election they had a lot of advice to give me.<br />
I always get advice and I understand that it goes with the territory and I don't object<br />
to it. I welcome it but one of the things that I was always told before the last election<br />
is that we can't live beyond our means. There's a limit and somebody bells the cat on<br />
us and so it ought to be with the Government. In 1995 just under 20% of the annual<br />
wealth generated by Australia each year, just under 20% of our gross domestic product<br />
was represented by the accumulated national debt of this country and that is all the<br />
money that over earlier years governments have borrowed to make up the difference<br />
between what they have raised through taxation and what they have spent on the<br />
various responsibilities of government and in 1995 if you said our GDP was something<br />
like, you know, let us say, for example, I can't hold myself to the exact figure, if it was<br />
$ 400 billion, then 20% of that would be, what, $ 80 billion this year, roughly what the<br />
debt was.<br />
Now the message I bring you today is that by the year 2000 that almost 20% will have<br />
been reduced to 10% and in proportionate terms it would be exactly half of what it<br />
was in 1995. Now that is not the sort of thing that gets people dancing in the streets.<br />
It's not the sort of thing that gets people popping the corks out of the champagne. It's<br />
not the sort of thing that gets people absolutely lyrically but in the long run it does<br />
more for stability and it does more for a prosperous, stable Australian future than just<br />
about anything else that a Government can do. I mean, your first responsibility as a<br />
Government is to make sure that the accounts of the nation are in order because<br />
without that you can't help people. I mean, you can't help pensioners. You can't help<br />
the underprivileged. You can't attack the fundamental problems of say, Aboriginal<br />
health unless you've got the wherewithal to do it and you don't have the wherewithal<br />
to do it unless you are living within your means so I am very proud of the fact that we<br />
did that and I would defend on that ground alone the enormous contribution this<br />
budget has made to the future economic stability of this country and I am very happy<br />
to say that by the turn of the century on present projections we will have the spending<br />
levels of the present government back to what they were in proportional terms in the<br />
early 1 970s, just after the Whitlam Government came to power and given the added<br />
responsibilities of Government through higher levels of unemployment and greater<br />
social and family disintegration than was the case 25 years ago I think that's a quite<br />
remarkable achievement.<br />
I am also very proud of the fact that the Federal Budget contains something that the<br />
rest of the Australian community, as well as the business community have been asking<br />
for for years and that is an incentive to save. I mean, I listen to the radio, I go around </p>
<p>the community and over the last 20 years people have been saying to me year after<br />
year, meeting after meeting, lunch after lunch, lecture after lecture, they've been saying<br />
to me, why don't you do something to relieve the double taxation on savings? They've<br />
been saying to me, it's ridiculous, I pay tax when I earn my money, I put it in the bank<br />
or I do something else with it and I pay tax on the interest. That's double taxation.<br />
Now people have been saying that to me for years and for the first time we've got a<br />
government that's actually done something about it and it's not limited to savings.<br />
If you make a personal contribution to superannuation you can claim the 15% on that.<br />
If you get a rental return from a business investment you can claim the 15% on that<br />
and so the list goes on. It's an across the board, comprehensive savings initiative and<br />
for the first time you've had a government that's nailed its colours to the mast and said<br />
we believe in savings, we believe in encouraging and procuring a savings culture and<br />
that is why we've done it.<br />
And in another area that I'm particularly proud of, that this budget has looked to the<br />
future and that is the establishment of the Federation Fund. One of the things that I<br />
recognise both in my present position and in past positions, one of the things I have<br />
recognised for a long time is that some of the basic infrastructure of the Australian<br />
community is starting to wear out. We do need some more capital investment and one<br />
of the responsibilities of government is to make certain that we have a strong level of<br />
basic infrastructure and that is why we have established a Federation Fund which in the<br />
lead up to the centenary of federation will make available about $ 1 billion for major<br />
capital projects.<br />
It's not going to be a slush fund for a thousand provincial and municipal obelisks.<br />
Now I am sorry, there may be some people in this room who are disappointed about<br />
that but I have got to tell you, this is a fund about large projects. This is a fund which<br />
is meant to support major projects that are going to change some of the basic<br />
infrastructure services of the Australian community.<br />
So I speak to you today therefore ladies and gentlemen as somebody well pleased with<br />
the important job that the budget has done. It has put us in the pathway to being back<br />
in the black. It has turned around a $ 10.5 billion deficit into a $ 1.6 billion surplus by<br />
year three, and that's a monumental achievement by any measure. Yet at long last has<br />
broken through in relation to giving a broadly based savings initiative. And also it will<br />
look to the future particularly to the centenary of the federation of our nation in<br />
recognising the need for additional infrastructure support and infrastructure spending.<br />
I am of course somebody who has spent a lot of years of his political life campaigning<br />
for the cause of small business. I came out of a small business environment and one of<br />
the things I learnt as a child was the belief in the importance of small business and the<br />
notion that there's nothing you can do more nobly in your life than to start with<br />
absolutely nothing and build up a business through the efforts and entrepreneurial flair<br />
that you might have.<br />
I do want to share with you for a moment some of the important initiatives that we<br />
have introduced for the small business community. Our industrial relations changes are<br />
very valuable to small business. They significantly reduce the role, the compulsory role<br />
of the trade union movement in the negotiation of workplace contracts. They have </p>
<p>encouraged the development of workplace and enterprise agreements and contracts<br />
which are far more amenable to the average small business enterprise than the more<br />
complicated and cumbersome awards system. We have reformed the unfair dismissal<br />
laws. We would like to go a lot further if only the Senate would allow us to do so.<br />
From the 1 st of July we will introduce, from the I1st of July this year that's only a<br />
little over two months, indeed only a little over one month we will introduce what is<br />
the biggest single change to the capital gains tax system since it was introduced in<br />
1985. And this is a provision that will give enormous rollover relief to every small<br />
business in Australia. And under this provision if you sell your small business you can<br />
invest the proceeds of that sale up to a maximum of $ 5 million, up to a maximum of<br />
million in the purchase of another business, it doesn't have to be the same kind of<br />
business. In other words you can sell a computer software company and buy a<br />
newsagency or buy a little manufacturing business, whatever you like. And up to<br />
milIlion of the proceeds of sale will be completely exempt from the payment of capital<br />
gains tax.<br />
Now that will over time, it will completely alter the attraction for investment into small<br />
business. What it effectively means is that in some many areas of small business there<br />
can be an indefinite deferral of capital gains tax liabilities. And on top of that we have<br />
a more modest but nonetheless valuable measure that says when you retire up to<br />
$ 500 000 in relation to the sale of the business will be completely exempt from any<br />
kind of capital gains tax.<br />
Now that fulfils, more than fulfils the commitment we made before the election about<br />
what we were going to do in the area of capital gains tax We have through<br />
responding to the recommendations of the Bell Report, we have bought about major<br />
reductions in the paperwork burden, particularly in the area of fringe benefits tax<br />
where from a date soon, any firm that has less than $ 5000 of fringe benefits will not<br />
have any obligation to keep any records at all and we are exempting another number of<br />
areas completely from any obligation in relation to fringe benefits tax.<br />
We have of course in the small business area implemented a number of other changes<br />
and reforms including our commitment in relation to the provisional tax uplift factor<br />
back to where we reduced it from 8 per cent to 6 per cent in relation to last year and<br />
this year.<br />
So I go over those things ladies and gentlemen, some of you would be aware of them,<br />
I hope many of you are, some of you would not be aware of them. But they do in a<br />
period of 14 months tell a very strong story and represent a very solid list of<br />
achievements in the area of small business. And when you add to that those who have<br />
received the benefit of reductions in official interest rates of about 1.5 per cent over<br />
that period of time. All of those things are together will be very valuable to small<br />
business. And in the last budget we announced as from the 1 st of July next year, we<br />
will be extending up to a period of three months the time in which small businesses<br />
may remit the proceeds of deductions in relation to PAYE tax payments and other<br />
payments of a similar kind. And in cashflow terms that will be of very great benefit to<br />
small business. I think the period of time now is less than a month and it will go to<br />
three months from the 1 st of July 1998. </p>
<p>We are trying at every point, we are trying to make changes that are of benefit to the<br />
small business community, because I remain very strongly of the belief, ladies and<br />
gentlemen, that energising small business, giving small business more initiatives, taking<br />
the paperwork burdens away from them, reducing where you can the taxation burdens,<br />
all of those things will contribute to the capacity of small business to employ people.<br />
And going back to what I said a few moments ago, it is all about measuring what you<br />
do against the benchmarks, the three benchmarks, the first and most important of<br />
which is job generation.<br />
Now ladies and gentlemen in the last few days there's been a little bit of debate about<br />
taxation reform in Australia. And I make no apology for talking about and recognising<br />
the need for taxation reform in Australia. I'm very proud of the reforms that we have<br />
already implemented. The capital gains tax reforms in the area of small business. The<br />
$ 1 billion family tax package that gave a great deal more justice to low and middle<br />
income families brought in on the 1 st of July. The personal tax incentives for private<br />
health insurance that will come in operation on the 1 st of July this year. And oh what a<br />
shame it is that those incentives weren't brought in 5 or 6 years ago when we had<br />
about 40 to 41 per cent of the Australian population holding private health insurance.<br />
It is now because of the lack of incentive for people to take out private health<br />
insurance to climb to a figure of about 34 per cent. Now I believe that those measures<br />
will be begin to turn that around and they'll be highly beneficial and they'll provide a<br />
very strong incentive.<br />
But it's an enormous pity and an indictment on my predecessors that the advice of the<br />
former Labor health minister, Senator Richardson, in 1990 that something should be<br />
done about giving people incentives to go into private health insurance wasn't taken up<br />
on that particular occasion.<br />
I don't think anybody would argue that we have a perfect taxation system in this<br />
country. I've not met anybody in business or in the professions who believe that. We<br />
have made some improvements and some reforms. And if we are thinking forward, if<br />
we are to be a forward thinking nation, if we are to be truly competitive, if we are to<br />
maximise the incentives for job generation in this country well you can't leave out of<br />
that examination or leave out of that picture a taxation reform.<br />
Now I made certain commitments about particular taxes before the last election and I<br />
intend to honour those commitments in full. But I do believe that we need as a nation<br />
to talk about and to think about and to debate the desirability of tax reform and the<br />
form that that should take. And in doing so, we should always remember those three<br />
benchmarks. We should ask ourselves will the reforms help to generate jobs? Will the<br />
reform improve the competitiveness of the Australian economy and will the reforms<br />
contribute to an increase of the living standards of the Australian people?<br />
Tax reform in its own right is not a goal. What is a goal is reform to the taxation<br />
system that matches those three benchmarks. We need a tax system that makes it<br />
easier to create jobs. We need a tax system that improves the competitiveness of the<br />
Australian economy and we need a taxation system that improves the living standards<br />
of the Australian people. Now what we do on this issue in the years ahead will be<br />
judged against those three benchmarks. I think it's profoundly disappointing that the<br />
reaction of the Labor Party on this issue has been so negative and backward looking. </p>
<p>People who say there is no need for any taxation reform in Australia are indicting<br />
themselves as yesterday's men chained to yesterday's taxation system. Because<br />
anybody who understands the competitive pressures that are weighing in on the<br />
Australian economy, despite all the changes that we have made, and others that are in<br />
the pipeline must recognise that if you are to compete effectively in an increasingly<br />
global economy, you must be absolutely certain that the taxation system that we have<br />
is adequate to that task. And that is why I have quite openly and deliberately<br />
embraced and talked about the need for debate on the future of Australia's taxation<br />
system. And I invite people whether they're in the business community, whether<br />
they're in the welfare sector, as private citizens, those in academia and those in the<br />
government service, and I invite all of them to participate in a very important debate.<br />
We do have to be sufficiently courageous and mature as a nation to recognise that<br />
although we have come a long way in the reform area, and although by in comparison<br />
with the rest of the world we are very richly endowed nation, that if we are to maintain<br />
that position we must be willing to examine and where necessary change some of the<br />
economic structures of our country. But don't change it out of some kind of blind<br />
commitment to ideology. I'm not interested in that. I'm not interested in an<br />
econometric model of an Australian taxation system, I'm interested in a people's and<br />
job generating model of an Australian taxation system. And if we can design over the<br />
years ahead a system that matches those three great benchmarks then I think we will be<br />
doing ourselves, the future of our nation and the future generations of Australian<br />
people a very great service.<br />
It is the role of the Government, it is the role of those who have been elected to<br />
leadership positions to combine a patient understanding of the concerns of the<br />
Australian community with a need on occasions to point a goal and point to an end<br />
direction to which the community should strive and aspire. And I believe we do need a<br />
debate on this issue and I invite people who are concerned about a positive future for<br />
Australia instead of a negative, backward looking, smug, complacent, ' she's all right'<br />
approach, of complete lack of realism. I invite people to join in that debate.<br />
And finally ladies and gentlemen, can I say as the Member for Bennelong how pleased<br />
I am to be here, how pleased I am to share a few thoughts about the budget and about<br />
the future of the Australian economy with people who represent the commercial and<br />
small heart of my electorate. I mean this is a cross section of what small and medium<br />
size business in Australia is all about and it's a great privilege to be amongst you again.<br />
I wish you well. I congratulate the Ryde Business Forum on what it's achieved and<br />
what it's doing to represent the small business and commercial aspirations of the City<br />
of Ryde.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
