<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9901</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DINNER GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF MALAYSIA, KUALA LUMPUR, 15 JANUARY 1996</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009901.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Is<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DINNER GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF MALAYSIA,<br />
KUALA LUMPUR, 15 JANUARY 1996<br />
Prime Minister, thank you for the honour you do me and my country with this<br />
dinner and this visit, the fIrst by an Australian Prime Minister since 1984.<br />
The friendship between our two countries Is old and runs deep,<br />
50,000 Australian servicemen and women have served in Malaysia, and many<br />
lie burled In Malaysian soil. 120,000 Malaysians have studied In. Australia.<br />
200,000 Malaysians and Australians come and go between our two countries<br />
each year.<br />
Prime Minister, I know Australians hold your country In warm regard. I know<br />
they want Australia's relationship with Malaysia and the Malaysian people to<br />
thrive. And it should thrive. Our shared past provides a strong foundation,<br />
but increasingly the strength of our relationship derives from the future we<br />
share. Whatever the benefits of our relationship In years gone by, there are<br />
more many more to be gained in the years head.<br />
The past can no longer be the primary source of understanding between us.<br />
We must work hard to understand the modern face of our two countries.<br />
Consistent with the changes being made In both countries, and with the fluid<br />
International environment In which both countries live, Australia and Malaysia<br />
need a fresh, contemporary appreciation of each other.<br />
Change Is something we have In common. It Is fundamental to our<br />
contemporary existence as undeniable as any fact In our history.<br />
Under your leadership, Prime Minister, Malaysia has set Itself the goal of<br />
becoming a developed country by 2020. And anyone who has watched your<br />
progress In recent times will be In little doubt that you will succeed.<br />
Malaysia Is now one of Asia's most rapidly growing economies, with a rate of<br />
growth consistently better than 8 per per cent, and this year at 9.5 per cent.<br />
Your country Is a dynamic force for prosperity in the region, and this modem<br />
city of Kuala Lumpur Is emerging as a major regional business centre. </p>
<p>It is a quite remarkable economic transformation, a remarkable national<br />
achievement and, Prime Minister, It Is, Indelibly, a remarkable tribute to your<br />
personal vision, leadership and energy..<br />
Malaysia's economic revolution is watched with admiration in Australia, where<br />
the necessity for economic change and the rewards and difficulties which<br />
accompany It, are well understood. The process has been different In Australia,<br />
but the ambition has been the same. We recognisedmore than a decade ago<br />
that our future depended upon sweeping economic change.<br />
The changes we made turned Australia Into one of the most open economies<br />
in the world: open, Innovative and diverse, forty. per cent more competitive than<br />
it was a decade ago and growing consistently.<br />
Our mining and rural industries remain great strengths and continue to<br />
complement the needs of rapidly developing countries in the region, including<br />
Malaysia. But our fastest growing exports are manufactures and services, and<br />
elaborately transformed manufactures are growing faster than anything else.<br />
This is why we say, Prime Minister, that we understand the need for change<br />
and the realilis of it.<br />
And because this change In our economy has been made contemporaneously<br />
with the new dynamic growth In countries like your own. we also say that this<br />
Is the region where Australia's future lies.<br />
The facts speak for themselves. Sixty per cent of all our exports go to the<br />
countries of Asia. Forty per cent of our Imports now come from those<br />
countries. By the end of this year all of our top ten export markets will very likely be In the<br />
Asia-Pacific region.<br />
The level of our engagement with Asia Is unprecedented and I believe<br />
Irreversible. And not just In economic terms. We now seek our security In the<br />
region not from the region.<br />
We continue to participate in the Five Power Defence Arrangements, which<br />
contribute directly to the defence of Malaysia and Singapore. We are an active<br />
participant in the ASEAN Regional Forum. We have just signed an historic<br />
security agreement with Indonesia, which signals the complete confidence<br />
each of us has In the strategic intentions of the other. And our alliance with the<br />
United States constitutes a dependable pillar of security In the region. </p>
<p>Our cultural links with the countries of the region go back a surprisingly long<br />
way. Australia has long been one of the " universities of Asia" and that tradition<br />
continues with nearly 70,000 Asian students around 10 per cent of the<br />
Australian student population now studying in Australia.<br />
At the same time, Australians are increasingly learning from Asia. . In no other<br />
country in the world, in fact, is such a high proportion of the population studying<br />
the languages of Asia as second languages. And in ten years' time we aim to<br />
have 60 per cent of Australian school students studying an Asian language.<br />
At a less formal level, the last decade and a half has seen an extraordinary<br />
growth in our awareness of Asian countries and their cultures. Travelling In<br />
Asia is much more common. For many young Australians, the countries of<br />
Asia have replaced Europe as the place to go and see and learn.<br />
At the same time, of course, Asian migration to Australia has radically<br />
increased our understanding of Asian cultures and values. And with Asians<br />
comprising the largest proportion of new migrants each year, this Is a pattern<br />
which Is bound to continue.<br />
Prime Minister4 none of this is to say that we are In the process of becoming<br />
" Asian". Weocinnot be Asian any more than we can be European, American or<br />
African. What we can be, and what we are determined to become, Is a society<br />
which is rare In Its cultural diversity, richness and tolerance, and a country<br />
which Is strong and Integrated with the region around It.<br />
Prime Minister, there are almost limitless opportunities to develop what Is<br />
already a very healthy relationship between our two countries... Last-year trade<br />
between Malaysia-and Australia increased by 22 per cent. Tomorrow, when I<br />
talk to business people from both countries, it will be with a view to Increasing<br />
that growth still further.<br />
Technology and research, including environmental technology which you and<br />
I have talked about in the past, Is one important new area for cooperation<br />
between us. Education will be another: the finalsatlon of your new<br />
Education Act will broaden the range of our cooperation enabling the<br />
establishment of twinning arrangements between Australian and Malaysian<br />
Institutions, and the opening of Australian campuses In Malaysia. Of course,<br />
as I have said before, I sincerely hope that even with these changes students<br />
from each country will still have the opportunity to live and study In the other.<br />
As Malaysia prepares for the Commonwealth Games In 1998 we are preparing<br />
for the Olympic Games two years later. The conjunction obviously creates the<br />
potential for cooperation on matters relating to sport by which I mean<br />
everything from youth development to building infrastructure. </p>
<p>For these and many other reasons, I believe the last few years of this century<br />
hold out the chance to deepen and expand the relationship between our two<br />
countries. In addition, we can continue to work together in a multilateral environment: in<br />
APEC and in the development of links between AFTA and the<br />
Australian/ New Zealand Closer Economic Relations agreement.<br />
We have common views about the world. We agree that the end of the<br />
Cold War creates a unique opportunity to address the threat of nuclear<br />
weapons. We welcomed the signature of the South East Asia Nuclear<br />
Weapons Free Zone treaty at the ASEAN Summit last-December. And next<br />
week we will welcome Datuk Ronald McCoy from Malaysia when he joins a<br />
group of outstanding international statesmen, scientists and military strategists<br />
In the Canberra Commission on the Elimination of Nuclear Weapons.<br />
Prime Minister, we have great Interests In common and we share great<br />
opportunities commercial opportunities, opportunities In science and<br />
technology, education, tourism and much else. Above all, * we have the<br />
opportunity to create a new level of mutual understanding between--the peoples<br />
of Australia a id Malaysia, and to forge a rich and rewarding friendship which<br />
will endure ihitb the 21st century.<br />
Prime Minister, I believe you will agree with me when I say that these are<br />
opportunities we cannot afford to let pass.<br />
I thank you once again for the honour of this visit and this dinner, the. warm<br />
welcome and the gracious hospitality you have extended to me,. my wife and<br />
my party. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
