<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1947</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT THE PRESENTATION OF A GOLD COIN COMMEMORATING THE DEDICATION OF THE ANZAC MEMORIAL AND FOREST IN ISRAEL, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/10/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001947.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRESENTATION OF A GOLD COIN COMMEMORATING THE DEDICATION OF THE ANZAC MEMORIAL AND FOREST IN ISRAEL</p>
<p><br />MELBOURNE, VIC. 29 OCTOBER 1968</p>
<p><br />Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton.</p>
<p><br />Mr. President, Your Excellency:</p>
<p><br />I understand that at some later stage in these proceedings there will be a presentation of a memento, and I wish now to take this opportunity of saying how much I value the opportunity to appear before you and how honoured I am that the Government of Israel has made this occasion possible. I would like, Mr. ' President, through you,. and also Your S Excellency, through you, to express to the Government of Israel my own deep gtatitude and appreciation.</p>
<p><br />W The Anzac Memorial Forest must, in a sense, be unique.<br />There it is, part of a programme of transforming unproductive land to<br />productive land, and yet at the same time a memorial to the 17, 000<br />Australians who were in Palestine as it then was in the First World<br />War and to the 70, 000 who were there in the Second World War.<br />Australians who on both occasions rode, if they were Light Horsemen,<br />knee to knee with citizens of Australia of Jewish extraction and were<br />helped by those of Jewish extraction in that country a memorial to<br />shared efforts, to shared dangers, to shared hardships so long ago.<br />I have not seen this forest, but I can in my mind imagine<br />it a vast stretch of eucalypts, bearing witness to those things which<br />were together done, and reminding us of battles long ago. This must<br />serve to draw closer and closer the ties between our two countries which<br />are I think already as close as the ties between any two countries I know.<br />There is in some ways a remarkable parallel between the<br />State of Israel and the nation of Australia. Both have got to develop and<br />have developed in a harsh environment where nature is not kind, where<br />there is no smiling way of developing, of growing, of building, but where<br />what has to be attained has to be attained only by great effort and by<br />wresting from ; that harsh environment the requirements for growth.<br />Both of us are, in the councils of the world, comparatively<br />new, comparatively small, and yet I think both of us are, by applying<br />scientific knowledge, by applying technology, showing what can be done<br />in arid country, showing what can be done if effort is put in. And both<br />of us require, and Israel particularly has required over the years,<br />assistance from outside in the form of capital to enable the building of<br />industrial muscles, the provision of a better life for its citizens to go ahead.</p>
<p>-2<br />ICertainly the area of your land is smaller than the area<br />of ours. Probably, I think, the amount of good land that we have is<br />perhaps greater than the amount in Israel, but having said that, still<br />there are these shared problems, still there are these requirements<br />for overcoming them, and that is something else we have in common.<br />That is not all. Though we in Australia and though you<br />Australians have not ever had to bear the direct impact of total itar ianfs m,<br />yet those of your faith have seen what can happen when people are prepared<br />to give away their freedom, when people are prepared to allow an allpowerful<br />dictator to decide their fates and their lives. You know it,<br />perhaps at first hand, perhaps from stories from relatives, or friends,<br />certainly you know it, and while we have not had to experience it, yet<br />we know it too. There is, I think, again a shared determination by the<br />State of Israel and by the nation of Australia to see that there will never<br />develop in our countries that kind of totalitarianism, and to seek to do as<br />much as within our compass lies to see that it does not develop any further,<br />that it does not spread any further. We have seen what happens to<br />individuals when one accepts the doctrine which you and we do not accept<br />that the citizen exists to serve the state and not the state to serve the<br />0 citizen. We have seen what can happen when religious bigotry or<br />political bigotry, or racial bigotry is allowed to run riot, and that can<br />only run riot if totalitarianism is in existence. That again is something<br />I believe we have in common.<br />Of course you have difficulties in Israel, Sir, that we don't<br />have. We do not have to plough our land with a rifle within arm's reach,<br />we do not have to go to bed at night and bar and lock the doors or be careful<br />that the lights don't so shine that a sniper may take advantage of it. We can<br />use ploughshares alone. In Israel it must be ploughshares and arms. But<br />we have as a nation, I believe, a feeling and a knowledge of what this might<br />be like. We have an admiration for what has been achieved on the<br />developmental and the economic and the defensive front in Israel. We<br />have this shared determination of which I have previcu sly spoken.<br />Now, Sir, may I add this. I believe that we in Australia<br />have reason to be grateful to the Jewish community of Australians because<br />they have helped in my view to foster the knowledge of Israel in Australia<br />and draw closer the bonds between Israel and Australia, leading to that<br />kind of genuinely friendly feeling which I believe exists between our two<br />countries. The rebirth of Israel after 2, 000 years though it was not-easy<br />has been, because of heffsofte Jesh _ 6mmrnity in this and other<br />countries, something in which we can take some joy as well as those of<br />Jewfish extraction. so / 3</p>
<p>3-<br />We look forward as a government and as a people to the<br />time when true peace will be restored in that area in which Israel lies.<br />I haven't heard many people saying " Let us sit down and talk. Let us<br />sit down and discuss" though I know, Sir, your own government wants<br />this to happen. When it does and when the foundations of true peace are<br />laid and when no longer is there a need for a rifle or a grenade to be<br />within the reach of somebody ploughing a field in Israel, then how much<br />better it will be for the human race as a whole, how much brighter and<br />easier the'future will be for a country like Israel so close in affinity, in<br />its difficulties, in its desires, in its aims to Australia.<br />For these reasons, Sir, for the admiration we have, for<br />the problems that we share in common, for the aspirations and ideals<br />which I think are the same between Australians and Israelis, I am doubly<br />honoured that today you have asked me to come here and talk to you. To<br />you, Sir, the representative of the Government of Israel, and to all of<br />you, who are not Israelis, but Australians of the Jewish faith, I thank you<br />for the opportunity and express my gratitude to you.<br />7T</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
