<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10827</transcript-id>
    <title>QUEENSLAND ELECTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>+</p>
<p>The result of the Queensland election will not be known for some days,</p>
<p> perhaps longer.</p>
<p>Irrespective of the outcome it would be foolish for either the Coalition</p>
<p> or the Labor Party to ignore the very strong showing of One Nation.</p>
<p>There are clear lessons to be learnt from the result. These include</p>
<p> the genuine sense of vulnerability felt by many Australians during</p>
<p> times of economic and social change.</p>
<p>Now that it has won seats in the Queensland Parliament One Nation</p>
<p> must be made fully accountable for its policies. Glib one line responses</p>
<p> might work when a party is an outsider in an election campaign but</p>
<p> not once it holds seats in a Parliament.</p>
<p>There are, in truth, no simple solutions to Australia's challenges.</p>
<p> Like all other parties One Nation is about to learn this.</p>
<p>It is always an error to fully translate a State election result to</p>
<p> the Federal arena.</p>
<p>The Queensland result is no reason for the Federal Government to abandon</p>
<p> or modify such things as taxation reform, which are sorely needed</p>
<p> to strengthen the Australian economy and improve opportunities for</p>
<p> the Australian people.</p>
<p>It would appear that One Nation has the same negative approach to</p>
<p> taxation reform as the Australian Labor Party.</p>
<p>It is also essential that the Government's Native Title Amendment</p>
<p> Bill be passed into law.</p>
<p>Suggestions that the Government should further compromise on this</p>
<p> issue are totally misplaced. Not only would that be a betrayal of</p>
<p> the legitimate interests of farmers and others it would also allow</p>
<p> the Coalition's critics to argue that it was no longer prepared</p>
<p> to fight for the interests of rural Australians.</p>
<p> 14 June 1998</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
