<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>722</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: 33/1963 - AUSTRALIA&#039;S WEDDING GIFT TO HER ROYAL HIGHNESS PRINCESS ALEXANDRA OF KENT AND THE HON. ANGUS OGILVY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/04/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000722.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
No. AV961<br />
AUBSTRLUA 1 WEDDING oT TO IR ROYAL HIGIIESS<br />
PRINCESS ALEXANDRA OF X[ UT AND THE HON* ANGUS<br />
OGILVY.<br />
Statm n I hr he EPUrM initr2 1 the It-a irO rt Ibnies<br />
Australia's gift to Hew r yal Higha ss<br />
Prinoess Alexandra of Kent and the Honourable Angu Ogl3vy,<br />
on the ooasion of tbher maria g, vill be a set of eight<br />
candflestiks = de froma Astralian silver, the Prim. Minister<br />
anoueed today. The oandlestiks are east and hand-chased in<br />
silver, being w. epSrouetions of a set Mad in the " ism of<br />
GOorgo III, about Uwyear 1761. Each candlestick is in<br />
the shape of a fluted Cornthian coluom with a square<br />
stopped base engraved with the Australian 0oat-o-Arus.<br />
Tby are l1i inches over all.<br />
The e&amp; nMlesticks are being made h the firm<br />
of Hannll Sons Limited of Iondon ad the gift will<br />
berented to the Prinoess and her huxbaad-tobe bO the<br />
Austtlian High Osmissioner in leadon, Sir Bria Harrison.<br />
The candlesticks will be contained in a p'sntation asse<br />
and a silver plate on the ontside, of the gase bears the<br />
inscription upnated to e Ucyal Higbaess Princess<br />
Alexandra of Kent and The Honourable Angus Ogilvy with<br />
warmest good wishes fro the Oovewent and people of<br />
Australia. 2i4th April, 1963. w<br />
The s. t of candlesticks is being made to<br />
order t a design known to be favxmred bq Princess<br />
Alexandra, The sot has not yet been completed and therefore<br />
no photogphs are available* It is expected that the<br />
presetation wil be ade a few weeks after 24th April and<br />
photographs w4il be obtained for distribution tn..<br />
CANURRA, 21st April, 1963. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
