<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1180</transcript-id>
    <title>RHODESIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/10/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001180.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
RHODESIA 7 w<br />
The Prime Minister, Sir Robert Manzie -ree<br />
Rhodesian situation today in reply t-a question in e -ouse of<br />
Representatives from Mr. Nicholls ( Bonython, For your<br />
information, the text of the question and answer follows:-<br />
Queation: " I ask the Prime Minister a question. A week has<br />
elapsed since the right honourable gentleman was asked a<br />
question about Rhodesia. In that time, the Prime Ministers<br />
: f Britain and Rhodesia are reported to have referred to the<br />
role that the right honourable gentleman might play in<br />
settling the differences between those countries. Will the<br />
Prime Minister state the Government's attitude on this matter<br />
which not only can affect the peace of Rhodesia and the major<br />
African States but the standing in the world of the entire<br />
British Cmmonwealth?"<br />
Answer: " The h. nourable member may take it that this is a preblem<br />
that we have approached with a proper realisation of its very<br />
grave importance. " Some days ago, the Prime Minister of Great Britain,<br />
his discussions in London having failed to produce an agreement,<br />
rang me and promoted to me an idea that there might be a<br />
Cmmnwealth mission to Rhodesia which, if it were to be<br />
useful, should include, say, two f the African leaders one<br />
from Asia and myself. This presented me with a very Aifficult<br />
problem. Mr. Nilson followed up his call that night with a<br />
cable repeating his request.<br />
" I di not need to tell the honour-ble member that this<br />
presented me with some political difficulties, but I gave the<br />
matter a lot of thought. I concluded that I ought nt to<br />
stand in the way if the sending of a Commonwealth mission<br />
because slight though the hspe might be, there might be same<br />
hope of arriving at a composition. So, after great and<br />
anxious thought, I sdd that I would be willing to go. I<br />
showed to the Leider of the Opposition for his information my<br />
cable and my reasons.<br />
" In the result, as we now know, the Prime Minister Lf<br />
Rhodesia has rejected the missivn idea. He has said that he<br />
does not want a mission and that he will not receive it.<br />
This means that the whole position goes back into a state of<br />
deadlock. It loaks as though one cannot be positive<br />
however this deadlcck is to be resolved by the Gcvernment<br />
df Southern Rhodesia declaring its independence unilaterally<br />
in nther words, illegally. Th~ t may not be the situation but<br />
at the present momen,, this seems to be the case.<br />
" Mossages have been exchanged, I gather between Mr.<br />
Wilson and Mr. S. iith. I h:-ve n
messages. I have had no further ccmmunications. Even at the<br />
last moment we all hope that better counsels will prevail and,<br />
to say nothing else, that there may be some process of delay<br />
in which heat can go down and in which people can accommodate<br />
themselves to new ideas.<br />
" I do not think there are many people, even among<br />
African leaders, who have strong views en this matter, who<br />
would demand an instantaneous creation of adult suffrage in<br />
Rhodesia. I think most people looking at the situation hope<br />
to see steady progress a phasing in of the ultimate majority<br />
rights of the native people. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
" That has been my own view. It-s a vd avocated in<br />
London and which indeed I pressed to Mr, Smithin a long letter to<br />
him when he was in London for these discussions. This view<br />
appears to be imacceptable to the Government of Rhodesia and it<br />
looks as if we will ave some extremely difficult problems<br />
presented to us. Of course, none of us would fail to understand<br />
something of the position of the European settlers, if I may so<br />
call them, chiefly the British settlers, in Southern Rhodesia.<br />
They have made an enormous contribution to the country. They<br />
have rights which everybody would want to protect. 3o the matter<br />
is not utterly simple.<br />
" What will be done in the event of a unilateral declaration<br />
of inaependence will be decided, in the first place, I have no<br />
doubt, by the Government of Great Britain, which is the colonial<br />
power an which by common agreement amongst all of us, has the<br />
responsibility or dealing with the Government of Rhodesia.<br />
This is a matter between the two of them. In due course, we will<br />
learn what the Government of Great Britain proposes and we will,<br />
as a Government have to give earnest thought to what we will<br />
present to the Parliament as the policy of the Government. That<br />
is as far as I , ant to go at present; but one thing is certain:<br />
If there is a unilateral declaration of independence, there can<br />
be Lo diplomatic reconition by the Australian Government cf a<br />
government so formed.<br />
CANBERRA, 21st October, 1965. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
