<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17579</transcript-id>
    <title>Kings Park to host CHOGM Retreat</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/01/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Perth</p>
<p>The Prime Minister, Julia Gillard and the Premier of Western Australia, Colin Barnett today announced that Kings Park in Perth would be the Retreat location for leaders attending the next Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting (CHOGM).</p>
<p>CHOGM will be held from 28-30 October 2011 and is expected to attract as many as 3000 delegates from more than 50 nations.</p>
<p>The existing facility at Kings Park will be significantly expanded to accommodate the Retreat, which will be the centrepiece venue for world leaders to discuss key issues in a private, informal atmosphere.</p>
<p>The Retreat will involve the construction of a new high quality reception centre on top the existing complex where the temporary marquee currently exists - offering visitors exceptional facilities and views of Perth.</p>
<p>The construction by the Western Australian Government is anticipated to be completed well in advance of the October meeting.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government has worked closely with the Western Australian Government to identify the best possible venue for the Retreat.</p>
<p>CHOGM 2011 will be the biggest international event ever held in Perth and is a unique opportunity to showcase Perth and Western Australia as modern, world class destinations.</p>
<p>Kings Park is a magnificent location which will offer visiting Commonwealth leaders a valuable opportunity for informal discussions and the exchange of ideas.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth Secretary-General Kamalesh Sharma was consulted and supported the selection of Kings Park as the Retreat venue.</p>
<p>Around 1,000 representatives from the media are also expected to cover the event.</p>
<p>For more information visit the CHOGM 2011 website: <a href="http://www.chogm2011.org">www.chogm2011.org</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
