<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18076</transcript-id>
    <title>Vietnam Veterans&#039; Remembrance Day, Canberra </title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/08/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Their Excellencies Ms Quentin Bryce, Governor-Generalof the Commonwealth of Australia and Mr Michael Bryce.</p>
<p>Former Governor-General Michael Jeffrey.</p>
<p>His Excellency, Major General Martyn Dunne, High Commissioner for New Zealand.</p>
<p>Mr Jason Hyland, Representing the Ambassador of the United States.</p>
<p>The Hon. Warren Snowdon, Minister for Veterans' Affairs and Minister for Defence Science and Personnel.</p>
<p>Leader of the Opposition, Chief Minister and other parliamentary colleagues.</p>
<p>General David Hurley, Chief of the Australian Defence Force, your distinguished predecessor Sir Phillip Bennett and fellow Service representatives</p>
<p>Chaplain Geoff Webb.</p>
<p>And above all, to every Vietnam Veteran and your representatives who have come to this sacred place; we are honoured by your presence today.</p>
<p>Friends, the Australian historian Paul Ham wrote a few years ago that “the last act of war is to grieve.”</p>
<p>Grief  -  and its sister emotion, remembrance  -  are what is left when the guns are put away and the gaze of history turns to other stories and other events.</p>
<p>It's a long time since anyone fought in Vietnam or indeed protested against its waging.</p>
<p>The chief actors  -  John Kennedy, Robert McNamara, Ho Chi Minh, Lyndon Johnson, Richard Nixon, Bob Menzies, William Westmoreland, General Giap  -  are all gone.</p>
<p>And the very Cold War which gave rise to the conflict is itself now just a page in the history books.</p>
<p>And yet here, on a very cold winter's morning, we gather.</p>
<p>In fact, we gather in growing strength and numbers.</p>
<p>We gather with a renewed sense of this day's value among the anniversaries our nation's calendar.</p>
<p>And why?</p>
<p>To perform that last and most noble act of war:</p>
<p>To grieve.</p>
<p>And to remember.</p>
<p>Repeating it often never diminishes the power of saying that in this nation, we do not glorify war.</p>
<p>If any nation had earned the right to do so, it would be us:</p>
<p>The nation of Villers-Bretonneux and Milne Bay, Kapyong and Long Tan.</p>
<p>The nation that brings forth men like those of D Company, 6 RAR  -  rightly honoured with a unit citation this day.</p>
<p>We honour  -  but we do not glorify.</p>
<p>We who have never served suspect it.</p>
<p>Those who have been there know it.</p>
<p>Michael Jeffrey said as much on this anniversary five years ago when he remarked that:</p>
<p>“War is a dirty, frightening and totally unpleasant business and never to be glorified as such.”</p>
<p>For that reason, our days of commemoration are solemn, not triumphant.</p>
<p>We wear rosemary, to prompt remembrance.</p>
<p>The Ode cautions against forgetting.</p>
<p>And our chief shrine is a tomb to a nameless soldier plucked from the mudof northern France.</p>
<p>We do not glorify war.</p>
<p>But we do remember.</p>
<p>Friends, we remember that eighteen of our personnel died at Long Tan;  521 in Vietnam as a whole.</p>
<p>We remember each of them, and judge that they made the ‘supreme sacrifice'  -  because that is what it is.</p>
<p>Parents and siblings, girlfriends and wives, children and mates  -  grieving then and grieving still.</p>
<p>Long lives and brilliant careers and happy retirements cut short and never known.</p>
<p>And so we remember.</p>
<p>This was Australia's longest war yet we treated the returning veterans with shame.</p>
<p>And so we remember.</p>
<p>Three thousand of our own fellow citizens were wounded in body and spirit.</p>
<p>And so we remember.</p>
<p>Sixty thousand served, many against their will and by the casting of lots.</p>
<p>And so we remember.</p>
<p>Her Excellency's predecessor, Paul Hasluck proclaimed our nation's involvement in Vietnam at an end on the 11th of January 1973.</p>
<p>And yet, for many of the 60,000 Australians who went there, the Vietnam War will never end.</p>
<p>As another wise Governor-General once reminded us:</p>
<p>“The past is never fully gone.It stays to shape what we are and what we do.”</p>
<p>We are a different nation because of Vietnam.</p>
<p>We are a different nation than if those men had stayed at home and workedand married and built their lives.</p>
<p>But we don't always get to choose.</p>
<p>History and circumstance sometimes choose for us.</p>
<p>What counts is our response.</p>
<p>Our response as reflected in the qualities and character of those who go  - </p>
<p>What Michael Jeffrey in that same 2006 speech called the “courage, compassion and professional skill” of the Australian personnel who served in Vietnam.</p>
<p>And also the qualities and character of those of us who stay behind:</p>
<p>Our willingness to understand what it is for men to go to war.</p>
<p>To accept that some will return broken or changed, and some will not come back at all.</p>
<p>That is Vietnam.</p>
<p>That is war.</p>
<p>And so we gather.</p>
<p>And so we remember. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
