<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7350</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007350.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
' 4<br />
,, 4usMA L I<br />
PRIME MINISTER 4 JULY 1988<br />
Four new members have recently been appointed<br />
Planning Advisory Council. to the Economic<br />
Last year, following a review of tripartite consultation<br />
arrangements by the Government, it was announced that the<br />
Advisory Committee on Prices and Incomes would be abolished and<br />
that EPAC would be responsible for monitoring prices and incomes<br />
policy matters as they affect Australia's growth performance. in<br />
line with its new responsibilities, it was decided that EPAC<br />
would be expanded by two members selected after consultation with<br />
organisations representative of the professions and the<br />
Australian Council of Trade unions. Enabling legislation was<br />
passed in June 1988.<br />
The two new members are Mr G A ( Gerry) Murphy, Am, President of<br />
the Australian Council of Professions and Mr Ian Watson, Senior<br />
Research Assistant, ACTU.<br />
Two other non-Government appointments to EPAC have recently been<br />
made following the resignations from the Council of Ms Jan Marsh<br />
and Mr Bryan Kelman, both of whom were founding members of EPAC<br />
and made strong contributions toward establishing the Council as<br />
an effective forum for economic policy consideration and<br />
community consultation. Ms Marsh has been replaced by Mr Laurie<br />
Carmichael, Assistant Secretary, ACTU, and Mr Kelman by Mr Eric<br />
Mayer, Managing-Director, National Mutual Life Association of<br />
Australasia and Chairman of the Business Council of Australia's<br />
Taxation Committee.<br />
1463 FOR MEDIA C<br />
21: mft' </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
