<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7521</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 9 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007521.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-r29 / aci<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 9 MARCH<br />
1989 E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke what were the factors that caused..<br />
to state your concerns about the Protocols?<br />
PM: let me make clear what the Protocol 1 of the Geneva<br />
Convention does. It relates to the treatment of civilians<br />
and civilian targets in war time and it's designed to<br />
prevent attacks on them. The decision to sign it was taken<br />
by the previous Liberal Government. This Government took a<br />
decision in principle to ratify some time ago but we delayed<br />
a final decision pending very extensive consultations with<br />
our friends in the United States. Six NATO countries have<br />
already ratified it and others a-re expected to. We expect<br />
to make an explanatory statement at the time of ratification<br />
to clear up any possible residual problems on<br />
interoperability. Our military advisers are confident, I'm<br />
advised, that Australia's adherence to the Protocol will not<br />
adversely effect interoperability and they strongly endorse<br />
ratification. I think if you consider each of those points<br />
you'll see why we've adopted the position we have.<br />
JOURNALIST: What do they mean by interoperability?<br />
PM: What do they mean by interoperability? It's not a<br />
complex -I mean I must confess Milton that at times when we<br />
get into the area of military strategic discussion I have to<br />
think a bit about some of the terms, they get rather<br />
esoteric. But interoperability is not a difficult one, it<br />
doesn't come into that category. It means the way in which<br />
the forces of one type of the alliance actually operate in<br />
war with another.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well isn't that a matter of major concern to<br />
Australia? PM: If it hadn't been a matter of major concern as to the<br />
possible impact upon it then we wouldn't have had all these<br />
discussions. I guess if it was a matter of such concern<br />
that it made it questionable as to whether you could have<br />
effective interoperability I guess 6 NATO countries wouldn't<br />
have signed. I guess if it had been a fact that it would<br />
have adverse impacts on interoperability our Defence Force<br />
people wouldn't have been in favour of signing it. They<br />
are. JOURNALIST: inaudible </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM: There's not much more in that one is there.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you concerned at all Mr Hawke about the way<br />
your Minister, Mr Punch, has handled the Sydney Airport<br />
issue, and do you think that there has been at least some<br />
scope for improvement in his performance?<br />
PM: No the only criticism I would have is of what would've<br />
appeared at one stage in public, not in the Parliament, to<br />
have been a pre-emption of a consideration by the Cabinet of<br />
all the options. Now that was the only criticism and I've<br />
mentioned that to him as I thought it was not wise to have<br />
conveyed an impression that all the options wouldn't be on<br />
the table. But apart from that no I have no reason to<br />
question his performance. I have confidence in him. I<br />
thought he handled himself very well in Parliament<br />
yesterday. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke what is you view on third runway<br />
PM: It will be expressed in the Cabinet.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will that decision be finalised today?<br />
PM: I don't know whether it will be finalised today<br />
Michelle. It is an extremely I mean there won't be any<br />
argument about this, it's an extremely complex issue. It's<br />
one which I want to allow to all my ministers a full<br />
opportunity for discussion and consideration. If I judged<br />
that there hasn't been enough time by the end of this<br />
evening when we will be considering it tonight in the<br />
Cabinet then more time will be given. But I can assure<br />
you and the Australian public that the decision will be made<br />
in the very near future. If it's not made this evening it<br />
will be made within the week.<br />
JOURNALIST: that the Government here is driven by<br />
politics rather than considerations of national interest?<br />
PM: I repudiate it completely. It is an obscenity of an<br />
argument because with a thing like this there is no way I<br />
or would I allow any of my ministers to make a decision<br />
simply on political grounds. I mean all decisions that<br />
governments make it would be dishonest to say that some<br />
elements of political considerations don't come into it of<br />
course they will. But as far as I'm concerned the decision<br />
will be made on the basis of what is best for this country<br />
and I can assure you that in regard to this issue those who<br />
would seek to paint it as one which is made simply in terms<br />
of which decision offends the least people or gets the most<br />
kudos from others, are completely on the wrong runway.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was it not unwise to put Mr Punch in that job? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM: of course it was not unwise to put him in that job. I<br />
was conscious when I was allocating the portfolios that his<br />
interests and involvement in this area and I referred to<br />
it at the time and indicated that all these things had to<br />
be handled according to their merits. Now the fact that he<br />
has a view will have nothing to do with the decision of the<br />
Cabinet I think Laurie that you appreciate the political<br />
realities of knowing the make-up of the Cabinet. I don't<br />
think you would believe that the Cabinet and the people in<br />
the Cabinet would have their position determined by the<br />
attitude of Mr Punch.<br />
JOURNALIST: vested interest than a view?<br />
PM: Well he obviously has an interest from his own<br />
particular point of view as a member It would be stupid<br />
to deny that. But this submission has been prepared by and<br />
will be presented to the Cabinet by Mr Willis. As a member<br />
of the portfolio Mr Punch will be in the Cabinet but he will<br />
not be making a decision on this. Mr Willis has the<br />
carriage of it in the Cabinet.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is the third runway still an option?<br />
PM: Well let me put it this way. It is an option which I<br />
insisted there was no problem about insisting on it<br />
we've accepted that that's the way it had to be. But I want<br />
every option and the arguments for and against before the<br />
Cabinet. There is no way that this matter will be decided<br />
on the basis of simply saying " well someone has a preference<br />
for one and doesn't like the other so only the one will be<br />
there". All the options, as I say, with all the pros and<br />
cons will be there.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you believe Badgerys Creek can be built in<br />
four years or three years or whatever<br />
PM: If you have some doubt let there be no doubt as to<br />
what's been said. No-one is saying that from the point of<br />
decision that Badgerys Creek could be built in three years.<br />
No-one is or has said that. It could not be.<br />
JOURNALIST: You'd be well aware of the history of the whole<br />
thing PM: But make it also clear nor could the third runway.<br />
JOURNALIST: But you'd be well aware of the history of the<br />
whole episode going back at least to the Whitlam Government<br />
in considering<br />
PM: And before, yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you concede that this decision should've<br />
been made actually a long time ago? </p>
<p>PM: It should've been made before this Government came into<br />
office. Let it be said this is the first government which<br />
has made a relevant decision in respect of the expansion of<br />
airport facilities to meet the needs of Sydney. That is by<br />
the decision that we have taken and which we've already<br />
acted upon to acquire land at Badgerys Creek. A decision<br />
like that should've been taken before hand. Because<br />
remember this, it seems to be overlooked and it certainly<br />
was overlooked in the discussion and debate and observations<br />
of the Parliament yesterday, no-one, no-one involved in this<br />
discussion and debate is arguing that you will not need to<br />
have Badgerys Creek. The arguments are simply whether it is<br />
a third runway plus Badgerys Creek at some time. It was<br />
this Government which was the first and should've been done<br />
before hand by previous governments, to take some steps to<br />
acquire the additional land for additional capacity.<br />
Because no-one and I repeat no-one is arguing that Badgerys<br />
Creek will not at some stage have to be built. It will.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke if neither of those options can be<br />
done quickly is there anything that you can do in the<br />
interim PM: Yes there are some things that will be done and they'll<br />
be announced.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can Sydney afford and indeed Australia<br />
afford the economic cost of waiting until Badgerys Creek is<br />
ready when a third runway at Sydney must be a quicker<br />
option? PM: Well on what do you base that? There is no evidence<br />
whatsoever. I mean that's nice to say and I don't intend to<br />
be in saying this. But one of the unfortunate things in<br />
this discussion has been the mindless, uninformed<br />
assumptions that are made by many people, and that's on both<br />
sides of the argument. The mindlessness hasn't been<br />
confined to one side. Now there is no evidence available to<br />
support the assumption that the third runway can be built<br />
quicker than a facility at Badgerys Creek. Because you've<br />
got to take into account the period and quite considerable<br />
period that would be involved in an environmental impact<br />
statement in regard to a third runway at Kingsford-Smith. I<br />
repeat there is no basis for the assumption which seems to<br />
be explicit or implicit in so many positions on this. The<br />
third runway at Kingsford-Smith, click you fingers, there it<br />
is, Badgerys Creek much longer. It's not accurate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can the Government afford to fast track<br />
Badgerys Creek?<br />
PM: There are ways, I believe, in which this would be<br />
capable of being done. But it involves questions not only<br />
of government but there's a limit to how far obviously I can<br />
go in all of this discussion. I mean I don't want to be not<br />
forthcoming in regard to your questions. As you can see I<br />
have been responding to your questions. But an amount of </p>
<p>( PM cont) the detail which is involved in that particular<br />
question but I'm not prepared to go to it in any detail.<br />
But let me simply say this in regard to fast tracking,<br />
that's one element that's on the table.<br />
JOURNALIST: On another subject Prime Minister. What's the<br />
Government going to do about militant Muslims that are<br />
threatening Australians in Australia?<br />
PM: The position let me repeat the position Laurie. If<br />
any Australian citizen or group of Australian citizens<br />
infringes the law in terms of their atttides to others in<br />
the position of my Government and I'm sure it would be the<br />
postion of the State Governments and it does seem to have<br />
arisen more particularly in Sydney, I'm sure it would be the<br />
attitide of Mr Greiner and his Government, but if any<br />
citizen or group of citizens infringes the law then the law<br />
should take its course. You have the difficult and fine<br />
line position which I think you'll appreciate Laurie and<br />
this is in the sense at the heart of the Rushdie affair<br />
itself that what distinguishes our country from others,<br />
including Iran for that matter, is our total commitment to<br />
the right of free expression, and that expression of oral<br />
and written, provided as I say it's not infringing the law.<br />
Now provided that individual groups express their view on<br />
this issue without infringing the law then an essential part<br />
of our position is that that should be allowed.<br />
JOURNALIST: What about the comments of Mr Javed Chaudry<br />
last night? How do you react to those<br />
PM: Well I must say I was offended by them, reading them<br />
this morning. It would be a question however of the law.<br />
Simply because I'm offended by what someone says is not a<br />
basis for action. After all, if that was the case, half of<br />
you wouldn't be here because you've offended me at times.<br />
But to be offended is not a cause for legal action. I mean<br />
God where would we finish up?<br />
JOURNALIST: Is there clause to protect the booksellers who<br />
have been threatened by<br />
PM: Well look Laurie, I mean there's obviously the legal<br />
question involved here. I can't pretend just standing here<br />
at the forum in answer to a very legitimate question that<br />
you put, to answer whether there has been an infringement of<br />
law, it ought to be looked at. If there is an infringement<br />
of law, action ought to be taken.<br />
JOURNALIST: But there has been a threat. Are you going to </p>
<p>PM: Well obvio * usly in the area involved here it is more<br />
probably a matter of State jurisdiction and that's not said<br />
to avoid the issue. If there is any infringement of a<br />
Federal law which could involve Federal action, then that<br />
should be taken. I'll obviously, when these things happen,<br />
I get reports coming to me. There'll be a report to me<br />
today no doubt and I can say to you quite clearly, if I was<br />
advised that there is an infringement of Federal law then I<br />
would expect action to be taken. Similarly, Laurie, I would<br />
expect that if there is an infringement of a State law, I<br />
would expect action to be taken. We are in this area of<br />
fine line where expressions of view are not necessarily an<br />
infringement of the law. I mean probably you it may not<br />
have happened in your case but you at times may have said<br />
things which of course thump you in the bloody nose.<br />
I'd be surprised if they had because you're such a<br />
reasonable bloke in what you say. But threats can be made<br />
which don't necessarily involve a breaking of the law. But<br />
I repeat, because this is a matter of fundamental<br />
importance, the right of Australians themselves to have, to<br />
be able to speak freely, to write freely and to disseminate<br />
freely. I mean that is something that I regard as<br />
fundamental. If anything has happened against the law in<br />
that respect then I would want action to be taken.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just looking beyond the law for a moment to the<br />
immigration program are you concerned at all that you may be<br />
recruiting people to come to this country who have very very<br />
different sets of values and that this may pose some sort of<br />
problem? PM: Well the question of different sets of values of course<br />
of itself is a difficult thing because this country is not<br />
going to become one under this Government in which we are<br />
demanding adherence to one set of values. I mean, the<br />
majority of people in this country would be adherents to the<br />
Judean-Christian ethic and practice and beliefs. A very<br />
significant proportion of this country have either none or<br />
different so we are not going to have uniformity. The<br />
critical test Paul is this, that if there was an evidence of<br />
recruitment of people committed to the processes of<br />
violence, then that would not be * acceptable. If I had such<br />
evidence I would require action to be taken to see that that<br />
sort was stopped.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister would you adopt Mr Saunderson's<br />
suggestion that in anticipation of any ruling by the ABC<br />
next week about transition legislation to the Bond network?<br />
PM: No this Government hasn't operated on the basis of<br />
moving legislation following speeches made by backbenchers.<br />
That's not the way we go about forming legislation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could it be a problem though Sir if Mr<br />
PM: Well that's a different question. It's a hypothetical<br />
one which I'm not going </p>
<p>-7-<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister you've had a chance now to<br />
Senate report on the ATSIC legislation, will the Government<br />
go ahead with that body, do you anticipate the changes that<br />
will be made to the Bill to be major changes or minor<br />
changes and when do you think those decisions will be taken?<br />
PM: I have had a chance to have a preliminary look, but I<br />
still to have discussions in detail with the Minister,<br />
Michelle, and I am not going to make any statement or<br />
foreshadow any positions until I've had that opportunity of<br />
both discussing it with him and with other Ministers. But<br />
let me say this, it would be my presumption and intention<br />
that the legisation should proceed with whatever amendments<br />
we, as a Government, decide are appropriate in the<br />
circumstances. After whatever consultation may in the<br />
circumstances, further consultation, it may be necessary<br />
with the Aboriginal community.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think another major round may be<br />
necessary? PM: I'm not sure at this stage. I simply repeat I haven't<br />
yet had detailed discussions with the Minister and I can't<br />
answer that until I've done that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you concerned about the very strong<br />
criticism in the majority report about the lack of adequate<br />
consultation? PM: Yes, one must be concerned. I must say that on the<br />
basis of my knowledge the consultations were extensive. I<br />
mean the minister reported to me on a number of occasions,<br />
both on the number and the nature of the consultations and I<br />
certainly form the impression from those discussions and<br />
from the comments of others who are involved in them that<br />
they had been extensive. There does seem to be some<br />
difference of view on this but I find it very difficult, on<br />
the basis of my knowledge, to be critical of the Minister as<br />
to the extent and nature of the consultations on the<br />
knowledge that I have. They were both extensive and, as far<br />
as I could judge, effective.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you see any need for consultation with the<br />
States on this legislation?<br />
PM: Well there has been forms of consultation. The<br />
Minister discussed a whole range of matters with his<br />
counterparts in the States. As to whether further<br />
consultation is necessary that would be something that I<br />
would need to,...... conclusion which I'd need to come on the<br />
basis of further discussions with him. I can't answer the<br />
question, authoritatively, until I have discussed the matter<br />
with the minister.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you told Paul Keating not to dispute<br />
rulings by the Speaker? </p>
<p>PM: No I haven't told Paul Keating how to behave himself in<br />
the Parliament.<br />
JOURNALIST: If there was a situation such as the Cope<br />
situation and one of your Ministers was named, would you<br />
back the Speaker?<br />
PM: That seems to me, just prima facie, to be a very, very<br />
hypothetical question Laurie.<br />
JOURNALIST: Not too hypothetical after yesterday is it<br />
Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Well I don't know. Let me just, as yesterday's events<br />
have been raised, let me just make this point which I think<br />
is appreciated by those of you who have watched the affairs<br />
of this Parliament now over some period of time. The<br />
fundamental point that has to be understood is that by<br />
deliberate decision, by deliberate decision, the Opposition<br />
has decided to attempt to create a different form of<br />
Parliamentary proceedings. I am not a member of the<br />
Parliament for an extraordinarily long time, others are, but<br />
I have been a close follower, listener to Parliamentary<br />
proceedings for a very long time, and to the best of my<br />
knowledge there has never been a situation as that which the<br />
Opposition has attempted to create. They are totally<br />
incapable of handling Question Time as all preceeding<br />
oppositions have been capable of handling it. That is that<br />
all preceeding oppositions have been able to use Question<br />
Time effectively to probe Ministers by asking questions<br />
about policies based upon the fact that they themselves have<br />
policy positions. Oppositions have said ' well here's our<br />
position, there's the Government position, we're going to<br />
hammer the Government on questions of policy from a basis of<br />
our own policy position'. Now that's been the basis of the<br />
way in which Question Time has operated in this place from<br />
Sday one. But now we have, for the first time, an Opposition<br />
which has demonstrably proved itself incapable of operating<br />
as every other opposition before it has. Why? The simple<br />
reason is, it has no policy positions. None. Let's look at<br />
the existing critically important area of economic policy.<br />
What's the essence of economic policy? When you get down to<br />
the guts of it, it's a question of what's your fiscal<br />
policy, what are you going to raise from the public either<br />
for personal tax, company tax or other forms of tax and how<br />
are you going to spend it and how are you going to adjust<br />
the relationship between the two? That's the very guts of<br />
Government. Now on that critical area, not only do you have<br />
no policy on the part of the Opposition, but more<br />
importantly than that you have now exposed a fundamental<br />
difference of view within the Opposition. You have the<br />
Shadow Treasurer who seems to be really a Shadow, Shadow,<br />
Shadow Treasurer because you have Hewson, the Shadow Finance<br />
Minister saying ' well we' with the obvious compliance of his<br />
leader, ' we probably won't really reach our position, final<br />
position on tax or on what we do on the outlay side. We'll </p>
<p>-9-<br />
( PM cont) probably leave all that in some sort of a limbo<br />
until after the election'. But the Shadow Treasurer who<br />
presumably in these matters should have the real running,<br />
saying ' well that's not right, don't talk to Hewson, talk to<br />
me'. So there you have the public indication of their<br />
unreadiness, their lack of preparation, compare it with what<br />
was being said last year, both by their leader and by their<br />
external Party President Elliott. Unequivocal commitments<br />
last year to have their positions publicly stated by August<br />
of last year, August of 1988. We're now March of 1989, no<br />
further down the track. Indeed, regressed because now<br />
saying ' well we mightn't have our policies prepared at all<br />
before the election'. So there is the core of the problem<br />
which differentiates this Opposition from every previous<br />
opposition. Having no policy position themselves, they have<br />
no basis, no basis whatsoever to do what every previous<br />
opposition has done. To question the Government from their<br />
policy position, probe weaknesses. What have they decided<br />
to put in its place? For the first time ever, they have<br />
decided to put in place, not being able to do or perform the<br />
traditional function of an opposition, organised<br />
pandemonium. Ministers can hardly start an answer before<br />
the cacophony of hee-haws and mindless laughter, giggles<br />
based on ignorance start. Points of order, manifestly not<br />
wellfounded. Now obviously that position places strains on<br />
the rest of the organisation and not least upon Madam<br />
Speaker. I accept that our behaviour in six years of<br />
Government hasn't been perfect and you know I'm always<br />
prepared to say that we're not perfect, we make mistakes.<br />
We have made mistakes including myself, but what I want to<br />
say is that those mistakes are made within an historically<br />
unique situation and may I say, I want to say in regard to<br />
the Speaker that I feel very sorry for her that she is, in a<br />
sense, the victim of the basic inadequacy, incompetence and<br />
historically unrivalled incompetence and unprincipled nature<br />
of this Opposition.<br />
JOURNALIST: I'm not trying to do a Tuckey and harp on<br />
relevance but you haven't really answered the question.<br />
Will you give a guarantee that you will back the Speaker<br />
even if she felt it necessary to discipline one of your<br />
ministers? PM: I believe that that would be the appropriate course of<br />
action. JOURNALIST: That's a guarantee?<br />
PM: I don't in advance Laurie answer hypothetical questions<br />
and I don't really think that you would expect me to. I<br />
would need to know every circumstance that was involved at<br />
the time but certainly what you put is what I would expect<br />
to happen. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, did your Government receive<br />
representations from either Mr Kelty or Justice Maddern<br />
about Justice Staples and if judges of the Industrial<br />
Relations Commission aren't really judges as you said last<br />
week are you still going to continue to pay them the same<br />
salary and allowance as Federal Court judges?<br />
PM: I didn't receive any submissions from Kelty or the<br />
Commission about Staples. I don't know whether any of my<br />
Ministers did, I certainly personally didn't receive any.<br />
Let's make it quite clear, don't let's have the discussion<br />
muddied in any way Milton by the use of the word ' judge'<br />
implying that he held a judicial position. He didn't, and<br />
he doesn't, never held a judicial position, not a judicial<br />
body. So don't let's muddy the waters by reference to<br />
judicial positions. Secondly let's make it clear, the fact<br />
that Staples was, as it were, unemployed was not a decision<br />
of this Government or of the previous government. It was as<br />
a result of successive decisions by successive presidents of<br />
the tribunal. It was their decision and as you know and as<br />
I said in my answer in the Parliament, the previous<br />
government had not only acknowledged but facilitated these<br />
positions, first of all by sending him off on some overseas<br />
trip and then secondly by an amendment of the legislation to<br />
facilitate the action of the president of the commission in<br />
making the decisions affecting Staples. So those are the<br />
facts. Not judicial and not action of the Government<br />
decisions of the Commission. In those circumstances we took<br />
the legislative action that's been involved and out of which<br />
comes this controversy. Now in those circumstances the<br />
results are automatic.<br />
JOURNALIST: The others aren't judges either that follows<br />
from what you said. Will you continue to pay them the same<br />
rate of pay as Federal Court judges?<br />
PM: The question of the remuneration of High Court judges,<br />
Federal Court judges and members of these other tribunals is<br />
something that will be decided by the Cabinet in the<br />
relatively near future.<br />
JOURNALIST: You've emphasised Mr Hawke that your tax<br />
package is particularly directed at families. Is it<br />
possible that you could look at, in this context, family<br />
allowances as well as the tax structure itself?<br />
PM: Yes, it's conceivable it will have to be looked at<br />
Michelle but I'm obviously not going to say in advance what<br />
it is we're going to do. But the answer to your question is<br />
yes it's conceivable that that can be looked at as well.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you had a chance to look at yet and do you<br />
have an opinion on the Industrial Relations blueprint<br />
released last Friday by the Greiner government? </p>
<p>-11-<br />
PM: No, it probably doesn't come as any surprise to you<br />
Paul that in the massive material that I have to read that<br />
decisions of the Greiner government don't come very high on<br />
the list and it hasn't quite got onto the agenda yet.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you accept that the self government system<br />
that your Government has put in place in Canberra has now<br />
become a joke?<br />
PM: The which?<br />
JOURNALIST: The self government system here. Do you accept<br />
it's now a joke. Is there anything that can be done about<br />
it?<br />
PM: I don't accept that it's a joke. I must say it's<br />
becoming rather difficult to foretell the outcome of the<br />
electoral processes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will you do anything about it?<br />
PM: No, I don't think that point's been reached. Let's<br />
wait until you get the outcome of the vote and the<br />
discussions between the parties and non-parties. going<br />
to happen.<br />
JOURNALIST: On another parliamentary question Prime<br />
Minister, how soon can the television audiences of Australia<br />
expect to see what you say in Parliament as well as hear?<br />
PM: I don't know the answer to that question. I haven't<br />
got anything before me at the moment, any proposals before<br />
me on this issue. Just expressing a personal view and<br />
that's all I'm doing, not a Government view<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you like us to give you a proposal?<br />
PM: I'm not quite sure what Cabinet Laurie but I'd be<br />
more than happy to receive one but I'm expressing a<br />
personal view. I think it would make sense for it to be<br />
televised but not imposed. If people want to watch us in<br />
action, and I think there are probably a lot of people who<br />
would like to, then that's a decision which stations ought<br />
to be free to take. This is purely a personal view but I<br />
don't think it's something that ought to be imposed on an<br />
unwilling public.<br />
JOURNALIST: What do you think of yesterday's Senate<br />
Education report that most Australians don't know how this<br />
place works, and does it matter so long as they're kept in<br />
touch with the issues? </p>
<p>-12-<br />
PM': That doesn't distinguish them from some people who are<br />
here all the time. I mean when I read some of the things<br />
that some of you reporters say about what has happened,<br />
which hasn't happened, what hope is there? The answer to<br />
your question is it's disappointing but I have no doubt that<br />
you've seen material in regard to the United States, the<br />
lack of knowledge in the United States about their<br />
governmental processes, the institutions, even names of<br />
presidents and senior positions like this. It just does<br />
seem to be a feature of political life in most countries<br />
that the people don't attach the same importance to us as we<br />
attach to ourselves.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just getting back to the Speaker Mr Hawke, when<br />
you said the Government has made some mistakes in the<br />
Parliament over the last six years, has Mrs Child also made<br />
some mistakes and have you and other members of the<br />
Government ever had any doubts about her ability to handle<br />
the position?<br />
PM: Mrs Child would admit she's made some mistakes. I<br />
suppose she would be upset that on a particular occasion she<br />
hasn't readily identified a member and his constituency, his<br />
or her constituency. I don't think that that's something to<br />
get terribly excited about but she may regard it as a<br />
mistake. No, in regard to Mrs Child I've regarded her as a<br />
good Speaker.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think there's a case to follow the<br />
British system where the Speaker is removed from a political<br />
role and doesn't need to belong to the party or go to Caucus<br />
meetings or whatever to politically neutralise the role?<br />
PM: It sounds good, easier to do in a House of Commons of<br />
the best part of 600 members. Not so easy to do in<br />
Australia I would think. Conceptually it sounds attractive<br />
but I doubt given the relatively much smaller size of our<br />
House of Representatives that parties would be able to come<br />
to an accommodation on it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was it premature to disallow Japanese<br />
involvement in the Woolloomooloo Bay redevelopment project?<br />
PM: There wasn't a disallowance of Japanese investment as<br />
such. It was a disallowance made on environmental grounds.<br />
I'm glad you asked that question because it gives me the<br />
opportunity of affirming once again my own and the<br />
Government's very strong position. We will not be party to<br />
any discrimination in investment on grounds of race or of<br />
nation and it wasn't the case in the particular project to<br />
which you refer. It was a decision on environmental<br />
grounds. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
