<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3454</transcript-id>
    <title>PLAGUE LOCUSTS - 14 NOVEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003454.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 368<br />
14 November, 1974<br />
PLAGUE LOCUSTS<br />
The Prime Minister today released the text of a<br />
letter of appreciation from the Queensland Graingrowers<br />
Association. This follows Mr. Whitlam's announcement on Monday<br />
that the Australian Government would participate on a<br />
dollar for dollar basis in a $ 720,000 scheme for locust<br />
control in Queensland.<br />
The letter reads as follows:<br />
Dear Mr. Whitlam,<br />
On behalf of the Grain Industry in Queensland I wish to<br />
express appreciation for your Government's offer of financial<br />
assistance to aid locust control in Queensland.<br />
The control programme proposed by the Queensland Goverrnent<br />
is a most realistic plan and we feel that it is a good chance<br />
of achieving effective control over our very serious locust<br />
infestations this summer. Your Government's financial<br />
commitment to assist this plan is most welcome and will make<br />
a really constructive control effort possible.<br />
My association looks forward to working with the Queensland<br />
Department of Primary Industries in making the best possible<br />
use of available funds.<br />
The Central Highlands Locust De-. truction Committee and the<br />
Near South West Region Locust Co-ordinating Committee have<br />
asked me to express their thanks also for the significant<br />
assistance effort by your Government.<br />
L. V. Price,<br />
General President,<br />
Queensland Graingrowers Association.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said he was pleased to have such a<br />
response from an organisation so much affected by the locust<br />
problem. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
He said he was surpresed that the Queensland Premier had not<br />
yet responded to the Australian Government's offer to set up<br />
an Australian Plague Locust Commnission as recommended by the<br />
Australian Agricultural Council.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said that his letter to Mr. Bjelke-<br />
Petersen on the matter had outlined proposed funding for such<br />
a Commission. The Australian Government was prepared to<br />
provide 50% and had suggested that Queensland's share of the<br />
remaining 50% should be only 2<br />
Mr. Whitlam said he could not understand the Queensland<br />
Premier's delay in responding to this initiative which was<br />
clearly of great potential benefit to Queensland's grain<br />
growers. CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
