<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7557</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 6 APRIL 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/04/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007557.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 6 APRIL<br />
1989 E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: I wanted to take this opportunity of announcing the<br />
important decision that the Cabinet made earlier this week<br />
in regard to the Greenhouse effect. We have decided that<br />
there must be acceleration of work in this country on this<br />
very important issue.<br />
Before I just mention briefly the decision that we've taken<br />
it may serve to put the importance of this issue in<br />
perspective. I'll just give you one or two statistics. It<br />
is the case that in the last 10,000 years the variation in<br />
climate temperature has been between the order of one and<br />
two degrees. It is estimated that in the next 50 years with<br />
the estimated 30 percent increase in the further release of<br />
carbon dioxide, that by the year 2030 there could be an<br />
increase in temperature of between 1.5 and 4.5 degrees. In<br />
other . words, the estimate is that in this period, there<br />
could be, within 50 years, a greater and perhaps a<br />
significantly greater increase in the earth's temperature<br />
than in the whole of recorded human history.<br />
Of course the potential impacts of that are almost<br />
immeasurable at this stage. We are facing the situation<br />
therefore where the whole pattern of life and of industry,<br />
of nations and people, may be totally changed within one<br />
lifetime. It's against that background that we have made the decision<br />
that Australia is going to be at the forefront of action in<br />
this area.<br />
we have decided that an amount of $ 7.8 million will be<br />
provided between now and 30 June 1990 for the first stage of<br />
developing Greenhouse research and policy support in this<br />
country.<br />
We will establish a National Greenhouse Advisory Committee,<br />
six experts will be appointed to that. They will have the<br />
immediate responsibility to provide advice on priority areas<br />
for further Greenhouse research and to set objectives for a<br />
dedicated research grant scheme. </p>
<p>So I want to make it clear that in this area of the<br />
Greenhouse effect and in the associated important area of<br />
the depletion of the ozone layer, Australia intends to be at<br />
the forefront of research. We will work not only in our own<br />
country, as you know, I've also promised support to<br />
countries in the Pacific region. That support will be<br />
provided.<br />
We intend to cooperate at every possible level of<br />
international research, work in consultation on this issue.<br />
It's particularly important that Australia do this because<br />
most of the work to this stage has been concentrated in the<br />
northern hemisphere area, it's important that Australia with<br />
our capacities and resources should see that there is<br />
introduced as much as possible into the international work<br />
that's being done, a consideration of the impact and<br />
implications of these important matters for the southern<br />
hemisphere. So this is a first and significant stage and I give the<br />
commitment to the people of Australia that all necessary<br />
resources will be made available to ensure that the work<br />
that can be done within Australia will be done to the best<br />
possible effect and that we will be fully involved in all<br />
international work in this important area of human affairs<br />
which, as I say, has the capacity clearly to change<br />
dramatically the economies, the lifestyles and indeed the<br />
very viability of certain areas of the world.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what are the preliminary assessments<br />
in how Greenhouse will change the way we live and work? Did<br />
Cabinet PM: Well, associated with the submission was some very<br />
interesting documentation which essentially came from the<br />
United Nations Environmental Program work and what it sets<br />
out is that there is hardly any aspect of life that will not<br />
be effected. Let's look at agriculture for instance, just<br />
for a start. It is suggested that if the developments that<br />
are associated, already identified, with the Greenhouse<br />
effect, go on in the way they are, then you'll have the<br />
possibility of a total change in the pattern of agricultural<br />
production in the world, that the areas available for the<br />
growing of crops will push more towards the Poles. If that<br />
takes place in areas where the soil is poor, then yields<br />
will be down. So you are going to have massive changes<br />
possibly in the patterns of agricultural production. It<br />
will effect, as well as the patterns of agricultural<br />
production, it will effect the natural eco-systems, your<br />
forests, deserts. There will be increased, the word is<br />
increased desertification as a result of the Greenhouse<br />
effect. That will impact upon problems such as soil erosion<br />
and with all that means. It can have a significant effect<br />
on urban infrastructure. It could make some cities </p>
<p>-3-<br />
( PM cont): unbearably hot and obviously a warmer or a dryer<br />
climate can effect basically questions of water use and<br />
longterm planning, perhaps making some large reservoirs or<br />
other projects which are in contemplation, useless before<br />
the normal 50 year timespan that's involved in the planning<br />
and the contemplation of the useful lifestyle. Obviously it<br />
can effect ports and coastal communities. The estimate is<br />
that approximately one third of the world's population lives<br />
within 60 kilometres of the coastline. Now with the rise in<br />
ocean levels that can be associated with the warming of the<br />
earth's climate, you could have a situation where, for a<br />
significant portion of the world's population, you are going<br />
to have the possibility of inundation and the requirement<br />
for change of location therefore. So when you, I mean,<br />
that's just going to some of the things. Some of the basics<br />
and why, for instance just taking that latter point, at the<br />
last meeting of the South Pacific Forum I made the offer<br />
there that we would provide assistance to some of the<br />
smaller states in the South Pacific because if you take a<br />
place like Kiribati, Tuvalu, which are virtually at sea<br />
level, any relatively small rise in the ocean level simply<br />
means that their countries cease to exist. It is, as I say,<br />
almost impossible to, I think, exaggerate the significance<br />
and implications of this issue with which we are dealing.<br />
JOURNALIST:' Would it have, or do you know what significance<br />
it would have in particular to Australian coastal cities?<br />
PM: well, by definition, it's going to, if you take the<br />
worst possible scenarios which could involve in the period<br />
of the next 50 years or so, quite significant rises in ocean<br />
levels it could, for parts of Australia, have manifestly<br />
disastrous impacts. That's why it's important that there be<br />
a public understanding of the signficance of what we're<br />
talking about. May I say as part of the expenditure of this<br />
near $ 8 million that we've set down for this period up until<br />
June 1990, there will be provision for a public awareness<br />
campaign. This is an issue which manifestly goes beyond<br />
Party, Government considerations, it's something which we<br />
want the community as a whole to be aware of so that as a<br />
community we can both plan and make the sort of contribution<br />
that we're able to make to countries in the region. Indeed<br />
one of the features of my recent Asian visit was to indicate<br />
to countries in the region that, in the associated area of<br />
ozone depletion and the impact of CFCs on the ozone layer<br />
that we had developed here in Australia and, as a result of<br />
cooperation between manufacturers, consumers and<br />
Governments, technology which is relevant in the question of<br />
recycling the offensive chemicals and we've undertaken to<br />
cooperate with them in the use of that, and transfer of that<br />
technology. They welcome that. What I'm saying is that<br />
it's something that we, as a nation, have to give increasing<br />
emphasis to. As I say, to cooperate with others not only in<br />
the region but I repeat also it's very important that </p>
<p>( PM cont): Australia plays a large role in the<br />
international work that's being done because to this stage<br />
of course most of that research and planning has a northern<br />
hemisphere bias.<br />
JOURNALIST: Inaudible<br />
PM: Just a minute, I'll come to that.<br />
JOURNALIST: From what we know now of the problem, do you<br />
anticipate that if this is to be slowed down and hopefully<br />
ultimately reversed, that Australians and many other<br />
countries are going to have to have massive changes to their<br />
way of life?<br />
PM: Let me put it this way. It is the case that if you<br />
look at the industrialised countries, one can identify in<br />
the period since the industrial revolution, if you take the<br />
period roughly of the last 125 years, the estimate is that<br />
in that period there's been approximately 0.5 percent<br />
increase in the temperature in that period. Now as a<br />
result of that industrial revolution it is the case that<br />
developed societies have developed industries and lifestyles<br />
which have locked us into this increasing generation of the<br />
Greenhouse gases. So it follows, as a matter of logic, that<br />
if we are going to arrest the imminence of disaster<br />
associated with a continuation of those patterns, it follows<br />
as a matter of logic then we have to give serious<br />
consideration to changing those patterns of behaviour.<br />
Otherwise we are guaranteeing for future generations,<br />
universal disaster. That gives some point to the question<br />
that was asked here. It gives, I believe, added emphasis to<br />
the need to try and ensure in the area of power generation<br />
that for those countries that have made the decision to use<br />
nuclear power for peaceful purpose of the generation of<br />
power, that every effort be made to ensure the maximum of<br />
safety of such processes because it is the case that one of<br />
the fundamental elements in the Greenhouse effect has been<br />
the burning of fossil fuels. This is not a matter for<br />
argument, it is a fact. So it's not only a question of<br />
nuclear power, but mankind is going to have to examine the<br />
whole question of power generation to try and ensure that,<br />
as a concerned and intelligent world, global community, we<br />
produce the power that we need in a way which is not going<br />
ultimately to destroy civilisation. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Does that mean Australia will have to consider<br />
nuclear power to replace our present fossil fuels?<br />
PM: I don't think it needs to be on our agenda at this<br />
stage. In the total global picture of the generation of<br />
Greenhouse gases the estimate is that Australia generates<br />
less than one per cent of that. But I don't think we should<br />
be approaching as members of the international community<br />
the global community we ought to be approaching these<br />
issues with prejudices or assumptions as to what we can or<br />
cannot do. I mean what we've got to do is first of all to<br />
look at the evidence which is increasingly compelling and<br />
then I believe to cooperate fully with all the international<br />
programs and that includes most particularly the United<br />
Nations Environmental Program. Within Australia what I want<br />
to see happen and what I've insisted in the Cabinet will<br />
happen and which I have the support of my colleagues, is<br />
that we're not going to be looking at this question in terms<br />
of financial restraint. We've done a survey of the areas<br />
within the Australian community where research is being done<br />
but most research has been done within the CSIRO and in the<br />
Bureau of Meteorology. So what I'm insisting is that they<br />
be provided with the resources that they've indicated they<br />
need to further their work, that's involved in the $ 8M that<br />
we're making available. What I want to see happen then is<br />
that the Greenhouse Advisory Committee will, from an expert<br />
point of view, then tell us what the further areas of<br />
research are, how we will best acquire the predictive<br />
capacity which is necessary for us to be able to make<br />
sensible planning decisions. Now I think that we've got to<br />
approach these things with an open mind and on the evidence<br />
of all the research available to me and which I've taken a<br />
fair bit of time now to try and assimilate I think that<br />
the approach on these issues has got to just over-ride<br />
political partisan boudaries and any areas of prejudice.<br />
We're in the fortunate position environmentally that because<br />
of the size of our country and the dispersion opportunities<br />
that that involves, that we don't face so many of the<br />
environmental problems of others. But we are in a position<br />
I think to make a very significant contribution to world<br />
research in this and will do so.<br />
JOURNALIST: On the basis of the research and evidence so<br />
far, which parts of Australia will be first effected?<br />
PM: You would have to say if you look at the I mean the<br />
answer is obvious in this sense that to the extent that we<br />
contemplate the possibility of the rising ocean level there<br />
are those parts of Australia which are the most low lying,<br />
the ones that would be most likely to be adversely effected.<br />
But I make the point that I made at the beginning in<br />
answering your question, " what's the range of<br />
implications?". If we have a situation where the whole<br />
pattern of agricultural production is going to be changed<br />
and adversely effected then that effects all Australians and<br />
obviously it has a potentially adverse effect in regard to<br />
certain of our minerals industry. I mean if the world were </p>
<p>-6-<br />
( PM cont) as a result of the work that's done here and<br />
internationally, to accellerate a move away from the burning<br />
of fossil fuels that has implications for our coal mining<br />
industry and it's a point I mean I could stand up here and<br />
try and dodge that and say well I don't want to talk about<br />
the possible deleterious effect on our mining industry. I'm<br />
not going to do that. I think that as I said earlier we've<br />
just got to face these issues squarely and honestly and<br />
understand that it has implications for everyone in<br />
Australia, everyone. That's why I've insisted that we<br />
approach this matter dramatically now and effectively.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just on that question Mr Hawke about the fossil<br />
fuels. If it does have an adverse effect say on steaming<br />
coal exports, the of that is that it would be a<br />
yellow cake exports. You mentioned earlier about overcoming<br />
prejudices. Do you think this is a justification for the<br />
Labor Party re-examining its attitude to uranium?<br />
PM: Well let me say this. Firstly as you know the Party<br />
has a committee which is examining the whole attitude on<br />
uranium policy. Let me secondly make this point, that I've<br />
had discussions not calculated ones but in the<br />
course of meeting people it's been interesting to me not<br />
only in this country but overseas that people in the<br />
environmental movement have had an attitude in regard to<br />
uranium and the use of uranium for the generation of power<br />
have been saying well they need to look at that to some<br />
extent again in the light of the developing evidence of<br />
deleterious impact of the Greenhouse effect which has the<br />
large single contributor, the burning of fossil fuel. But I<br />
don't say that with any sense of saying, well now you've got<br />
to therefore change your position. What I'm simply saying<br />
is that given the magnitude, the dimension of the issues<br />
that we're talking about, I think it anyone to go<br />
walking into that discussion and that analysis and carry<br />
into it any prejudices of the past. I think you've got to<br />
say, well the evidence here is overwhelming, it's near<br />
universal in its acceptance in the scientific community, I<br />
mean obviously there are degrees of emphasis, we haven't got<br />
a position where people are universal in their measurements<br />
and timetable in regard to the problem. But there is<br />
virtually universal scientific acceptance that the world has<br />
a very significant problem on its hands. Now when you've<br />
got problems of that dimension I mean it's silly to be<br />
trying to score political points or you know to carry<br />
prejudices, I mean it just is too big for that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Apart from the fact that we might be able to<br />
make money out of uranium exports, we are in fact the<br />
highest per capita user of energy, we rank quite highly in<br />
the world, and although the country is large and therefore<br />
we should not the problem as perceived by people living<br />
in Australia we contribute per capita more than most or as<br />
much as anybody to the Greenhouse effect. we could be<br />
considering switching to nuclear power generation? </p>
<p>-7-<br />
PM: You could be, I'm not. I made the aggregate point a<br />
while ago that in terms of the global release of Greenhouse<br />
gases it's estimated that we're less than 1% in that area.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just a year ago Cabinet knocked back a<br />
submission from Senator Richardson for just $ 1M for research<br />
into the Greenhouse effect. What's happened in the meantime<br />
to cause you to change your mind and why couldn't this<br />
research already be underway?<br />
PM: There is research underway already. I mean there is<br />
significant research being done by the CSIRO and the Bureau<br />
of Mineral Resources. They have diverted some resources<br />
from other areas of activity towards this area. But I think<br />
the simple fact is that there is a dramatic explosion of<br />
awareness which is evidenced in a number of ways. We've had<br />
S just recently two large international conferences that<br />
which was called by Mrs Thatcher in March in London and the<br />
conference in the Hague. I think it is the case that as a<br />
result of the very good work that's been done by the United<br />
Nations and by people in particular countries that there has<br />
in the last twelve months or so been as I say an explosion<br />
of awareness. As far as I'm concerned I have become totally<br />
convinced of the urgency of this matter and I give the<br />
Australian people my unqualified assurance that financial<br />
considerations are not going to stand in the way of any<br />
decisions that we can take as a Government both in terms of<br />
what we can do to accelerate research and create the<br />
appropriate predictive capacity in this country and also to<br />
participate in all relevant areas of international work on<br />
the issue.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible<br />
PM: Just a minute I think Geoff asked a question, what<br />
does the Finance Minister think about that? Let me say in<br />
fairness to a man who is too often maligned as only having a<br />
calculus for a mind, that Senator Walsh shares our concerns<br />
on this issue.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke there are also implications for the<br />
preservation of our forests.<br />
PM: I beg your pardon.<br />
JOURNALIST: There are implications<br />
PM: There are indeed.<br />
JOURNALIST: For the preservation of our forests and I<br />
believe that related to this the negotiations on Wesley Vale<br />
are resuming again. What's the situation there? </p>
<p>-8-<br />
PM: Well I'm not aware of negotiations resuming on Wesley<br />
Vale. I've heard some indications that there may be some<br />
residual interest at least on the part of the local partner<br />
here. So if there is an attempt to resume negotiations<br />
either with the existing local enterprise or with others I<br />
simply make the point that my Government will insist on the<br />
strictest of guidelines as distinct from the Leader of the<br />
opposition who wanted to race in and endorse Wesley Vale<br />
despite the clear warnings and strict injunctions, if I can<br />
put it that way, from the CSIRO. Well Mr Howard and the<br />
Liberals can be developers at any cost beggar future<br />
generations. We're not going to do that.<br />
JOURNALIST: guidelines by May 2..<br />
PM: I beg your pardon?<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard's proposing that you..<br />
PM: Mr?<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, the Leader of the opposition, is<br />
proposing that you set out your timetable<br />
PM: I mean I wasn't trying to be smart about I just<br />
didn't catch the word, I'm sorry.<br />
JOURNALIST: By May 2, set out national guidelines for the<br />
environmental requirements for these pulp mills. Will you<br />
go along with that? would you try and set<br />
PM: The day when I make decisions about the future welfare<br />
of this country according to the opportunism of the Leader<br />
of the opposition will be the day this country starts going<br />
backwards. He can embrace his opportunism in his desperate<br />
attempt to retain the leadership of the Liberal Party and<br />
0 he's very much under seige there. Principles mean nothing<br />
to him. The ecological safety of this country, the<br />
preservation of this environment for future generations<br />
don't figure on his agenda. They do on mine. I won't be<br />
bullied into any artificial timetable by this Leader under<br />
seige of the conservatives. As far as I'm concerned it's<br />
almost a contradiction in terms to have a strictly national<br />
set of guidelines because what may be appropriate in one<br />
physical environment is not necessarily appropriate in<br />
another. And let me make the point in regard to Wesley<br />
Vale. There is no way in which I or this Government is<br />
going to tolerate a situation where 13 tonnes per day of<br />
chlorides are pumped into the ocean. So Mr Howard can<br />
abandon his principles, will not have any, the deregulator<br />
can be seen in this extraordinarily unbecoming exercise he's<br />
having with the National Party in regard to issues of the<br />
deregulation of the wheat industry, he can go on and have<br />
all his problems and deadlines that he wants to impose upon<br />
others or upon himself. They will have absolutely no impact<br />
upon me or on the Government because if you're looking for<br />
principles and if you're looking for concerns about the </p>
<p>-9-<br />
( PM cont) welfare of this country in terms of present and<br />
future generations don't waste your time looking in the<br />
direction of John Howard.<br />
JOURNALIST: I take it that you also have the same view of<br />
the merit of the Leader of the Opposition's proposal of a<br />
joint Federal/ Victorian Royal Commission into the NSC, do<br />
you see any merit in the idea at all?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: I was asking, $ 8 million, will it be enough to<br />
get the CSIRO back to where it was five or six years ago<br />
before the cuts started?<br />
PM: As far as the CSIRO is concerned on this issue we<br />
believe that this will be sufficient. It will involve a<br />
very significant addition in staff for them and resources<br />
for them to enable them to do the work which they believe<br />
they can do in this period. I want to emphasise that this<br />
is a first and preliminary stage for them to be determining<br />
what are the substantial priority areas of research to<br />
develop in that period from the middle of the 1990s. So we<br />
want them to be working further on the areas that they've<br />
already initiated but under the recommendations that we get<br />
from the Greenhouse Advisory Committee and the work will be<br />
done, the further work will be done by the CSIRO and with<br />
the Bureau of Meteorology. We expect then to have an<br />
indication to us of what further funding requirements<br />
there'll be. I repeat that as far as I'm concerned and this<br />
Government is concerned, no reasonable requests will be<br />
refused. Anything that we can do will be done.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard today revealed that senior<br />
businessmen have expressed concern to him about the<br />
politicisation of the Treasury in the Reserve Bank. Have<br />
those concerns been expressed to you by businessmen as well?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, on the NSCA, should the very<br />
important business of search and rescue with the<br />
implications for public safety be in the hands of groups<br />
such as the NSCA or specifically the preserve of the Defence<br />
forces?<br />
PM: It's hard to say it should be specifically the reserve<br />
of the Defence forces although historically and currently<br />
they've had and have a significant role to play. I think<br />
that we want to try and put these things in perspective.<br />
Obviously there has been a disastrous misuse of funds in the<br />
operations of the NSC. Now that needs to be examined, it<br />
needs to be cleared up. But it seems to me that if you look<br />
at the history of this country we've had a history where<br />
there's been co-operation between organisations of that type<br />
and between the Defence forces. We're going to have to get </p>
<p>PM ( cant): the right balance but we're certainly going to<br />
have to see a situation where as a result of the enquiries<br />
by the appropriate authorities, which are essentially State<br />
ones, that the mess of the NSC be cleared up. But I don't<br />
think you'll reach a situation in this country where<br />
exclusively these sorts of functions will be in the hands of<br />
the Defence forces.<br />
JOURNALIST: What's your view of the action of the air<br />
traffic controllers in Sydney and do you see any threat to<br />
the wage/ tax trade off from the current industrial activity<br />
on their front and the threat from the Telecom employees?<br />
PM: No, if you look back over the last six years Geoff<br />
you'll find that wherever we've had these negotiations<br />
there've been one or two unions who've made noises and said<br />
' well we're not going to cop it' and right through those<br />
periods we've had questions like the one you raise will<br />
the action of this union break the system down? I've given<br />
the answer consistently, no it won't. I was right then and<br />
I believe I'll be proved right again in saying no, the<br />
action of one or two particular unions is not going to break<br />
down what I believe will be the emergence of an appropriate<br />
outcome on this occasion.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can I put a question on Kampuchea?<br />
PM: Yes, then I think we better get going.<br />
JOURNALIST: Vietnam has announced it will unconditionally<br />
pull out by September. Are you hopeful for some internal<br />
resolution in Kampuchea between the factions? Do you see<br />
Australia having any role, any control or peacekeeping force<br />
and will we resume aid to Vietnam?<br />
PM: Let me say, first of all, I welcome the statements that<br />
have been made that unequivocally the Vietnamese forces are<br />
going to be withdrawn from Kampuchea by September of this<br />
year. That's consistent with indications that I'd been<br />
given on my recent visit to Asia and certainly, in<br />
particular, when I've been talking with the Prime Minister<br />
of Thailand he was confident that this would be the case.<br />
So I believe that the fact that this announcement has been<br />
made would suggest that there have been some understandings<br />
at other levels and I would think particularly in<br />
discussions between the Soviet Union and China. Now, as you<br />
rightly say, what needs to occur is a resolution of the<br />
other externalities and of the internal problem. When I<br />
refer to the other externalities of course I specifically<br />
mean the provision of assistance from outside to factions<br />
within Kampuchea and particularly provision of assistance by<br />
China to the Khmer Rouge. I would assume that Vietnam<br />
wouldn't have made the decision that it has announced, in a<br />
sense reannounced, if it were not satisfied that there were<br />
going to be appropriate responses from China in that regard.<br />
Now, the other element that we must note is that Prince </p>
<p>-11-<br />
PM ( cont): Sihanouk has resumed his Chairmanship of the<br />
coalition and is agreeing to meet Hun Sen and I would hope<br />
and expect that the unequivocal nature of the decision that<br />
his been announced by the Vietnamese now will act as an<br />
impetus to the resolution of these internal problems. I<br />
mean, they are complex. One shouldn't underestimate the<br />
complexity of the issues that are involved. Without being<br />
exhaustive about them, let me refer to them. The issues<br />
that have bogged down the negotiations to the JIM meeting so<br />
far and in other discussions that have taken place, there is<br />
the question of what will be the nature of the internal<br />
regime in the period up to the time of the election. What<br />
place can there be for the coalition factions together with<br />
the Hun Sen regime in that lead-up period which will be such<br />
as they will have confidence in the preparations for the<br />
election. That is a critically important issue. Without<br />
being exhaustive, there are others. Now I think that the<br />
time that's available, it means we're now in relatively<br />
early April, they announced they're going to withdraw by<br />
September. I think, given the environment that's been<br />
created by that decision, given the assumption I make that<br />
there are basic understandings between the Soviet Union and<br />
China, given the resumption of the leadership of the<br />
coalition by Sihanouk, I think we have grounds for a<br />
considerable degree of optimism that these issues can be<br />
resolved in the time available.<br />
JOURNALIST: Unemployment Mr Hawke, could we have a quick<br />
comment on the big drop in the unemployment<br />
PM: Well, I was wondering whether you'd ever get there.<br />
We're very pleased with the fact that the unemployment rate<br />
is now down to 6.2 per cent and that has been associated<br />
with some fall in employment, but a fall in the<br />
participation rate and an increase in employment over the<br />
period since, twelve months ago of over 3 per cent, 3.2 per<br />
cent in fact. So it's a very substantial increase in<br />
employment. I'm very pleased with the result.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, just the end of my question<br />
about the peacekeeping force, you didn't respond to that.<br />
Whether Australia would<br />
PM: Yes, I'm sorry. Yes, I just repeat on that what I've<br />
said overseas and here. We have an historical involvement<br />
and interest in this issue. I've made it clear in my<br />
discussions with the Prime Minister of Thailand, as has my<br />
Foreign Minister, Senator Evans, that Australia stands ready<br />
if requested by the parties principle and those associated<br />
with this. By that I mean particularly the ASEAN countries.<br />
If they want an Australian involvement, we are prepared to<br />
be involved. We have expressed the view that we would hope<br />
that there is no need for an armed peacekeeping force, but<br />
more of a monitoring role. But if that more extensive<br />
peacekeeping type arrangement were contemplated, then we<br />
would be prepared to look at that. It is a matter of some </p>
<p>-12-<br />
PM ( cont): satisfaction to me that the countries directly<br />
involved, countries like Thailand, seem to take the view<br />
that it is appropriate that Australia should be involved.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
