<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8368</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, PAUL KEATING, - DOOR STOP 22 DECEMBER 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/12/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008368.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, PAUL KEATING, DOORSTOP<br />
22 DECEMBER 1991<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: When will you be announcing the new Ministry?<br />
PM: As soon as I can, but I want a chance to talk to my<br />
colleagues and that will be afforded to me in the next few<br />
days.<br />
J: Do you plan big changes?<br />
PM: There's no point in speculating about it let's just wait<br />
and see. But between Christmas and New Year, I'd say at<br />
the latest.<br />
J: Who'd make the best Treasurer?<br />
PM: Well that's something the whole Ministry will be<br />
announced at once.<br />
J: Will people see a return to high airfares now that Compass<br />
has dropped out of the race, Mr Keating?<br />
PM: I think you're going to see a competitive airline system.<br />
I'm not sure whether the Compass targets could have been<br />
sustained. It looks as though probably they couldn't have.<br />
But we will see a competitive airline system, which we<br />
never had in the old days of regulation.<br />
J: And what about Mr Grey? He's blaming the Federal<br />
Government.<br />
PM: Well I think that's unfair, but our principle interest now<br />
is the Compass passengers and their families. And we've<br />
arranged now for, I think, another seven or eight thousand<br />
Compass passengers to be taken up today by the two airlines<br />
which have now chartered new capacity. Qantas is also<br />
involved in a 767 charter, and Ansett and Australian<br />
Airlines have chartered large aircraft from Qantas, and<br />
we've got the Airforce's 707s on standby if we need them.<br />
But we think that most passengers will be able to be<br />
lifted, -and if they are taken to their destination before<br />
the 15th of January, we pretty well guarantee they'll be<br />
taken back at the same deep discounts.<br />
J: Just on another issue, are you happy at the level of<br />
pressure that Senator Evans put on the Indonesians on his<br />
visit thiLs week? </p>
<p>2<br />
PM: Well I have got to speak to Senator Evans. I did have a<br />
brief conversation with him the other day, and before I<br />
comment on that I'd prefer to speak to him directly.<br />
J: Can we expect a bit of a reshuffle at the top level of the<br />
public service, as well as the Cabinet?<br />
PM: I'm looking at the Departmental structures as well as the<br />
Ministry.<br />
J: When do we expect an economic statement?<br />
PM: Well, that you'll have to wait for. We've got to decide<br />
our schedule on that. Thank you.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
