<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9195</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP URUGUAY ROUND</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/04/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009195.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 15. Apr. 94 16: 42 No. 017 P.( 1202<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRJME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATIYG MP<br />
URUGUAY ROUND<br />
The signing today in Marrakesh, Morocco, of the " Final Act" of the Uruguay Round<br />
marks the formal end of these multilateral trade negotiations. Over 120 countries will<br />
be represented, with Senator McMullan signing on behalf of Australia.<br />
Signing of the final act represents the culmination of over 8 years of sustained and<br />
intensive effort by Australia, including through our leadership of the Cairns Group, but<br />
also our active role in services and other negotiations.<br />
The benefits of the Round outcome are widely acknowledged. It represents the largest<br />
trade agreement ever in terms of countries involved, products covered and<br />
liberalisation achieved. Se: veral studies have now confirmed world trade could be<br />
boosted by as much as $ 1,000 billion when the full effects flow through. Australia<br />
could gain up to $ 5 billion in export revenue and $ 4 billion to GDP over the next<br />
years, with benefits across the full spectrum of Australian exporters.<br />
Since the Uruguay Round deal was struck in December last year, we have already seen<br />
a restoration in world business confidence and a rallying of a number of world<br />
coimnodity markets of importance to Australia.<br />
I hope that countries will now move quickly so that the new World Trade Ozganisation<br />
can be in place from 1 January 1995. The creation of this body will bring new vigour<br />
to the world trading system. Strong multilateral trading rules remain crucially<br />
important for Australia and other medium and small sized trading'nations.<br />
Australia will continue efforts in the WTO to pursue liberalisation in world markets<br />
and to ensure our voice is heard in future discussions on issues such as trade and the<br />
environment, and trade and competition policy.<br />
The Uruguay Round aclhievement also provides a good basis for seeking further trade<br />
liberalisation in the Asia-Pacific region. I am pleased that APEC trade ministers met in<br />
Marrakesh to take forward the direction from Leaders that APEC undertake work<br />
aimed at deepening and broadening the Uruguay Round in our region.<br />
April 15, 1994<br />
CANBERRA </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
