<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1983</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM. NO. 5/1969 - MESSAGES TO THE U.S. PRESIDENT AND THE PRESIDENT-ELECT</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/01/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001983.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS, PM. No. 5/ 1969<br />
MESSAGES TO THE U. S. PRESIDENT AND THE<br />
PRESIDENT-ELECT<br />
Following is the text of messages sent by the Acting Prime<br />
Minister, Mr John McEwen to President Johnsou and the incoming President,<br />
Mr Richard Nixon<br />
To President Johnson AS YOU LEAVE THE GREAT OFFICE OF<br />
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES, I CONVEY TO YOU ON<br />
BEHALF OF THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE<br />
AND OF MYSELF, OUR WARMEST GOOD WISHES FOR THE<br />
FUTURE. YOUR FAR-SIGHTED CONCEtIION OF THE<br />
INTERESTS OF YOUR COUNTRY AND YOUR DEVOTION ' O THE<br />
CAUSE OF PEACE AND JUSTICE HAVE EARNED YOU AN<br />
ENDURING PLACE IN HISTORY. YOUR CLOSE INTEREST IN,<br />
AND THE PERSONAL VISITS YOU HAVE PAID TO, AUSTRAIJA HAVE<br />
GIVEN YOU A SPECIAL PLACE IN THE HEARTS OF ALL<br />
AUSTRALIANS. WITH EVERY WARM REGARD,<br />
j. McE -en, Acting Prime Minister.<br />
To President Nixon I OFFER THE SINCERE BEST WISHES OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE ON YOUR ASS[ MPFION<br />
OF THE GREAT AND EXACTING OFFICE OF PRESIDENT OF THE<br />
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. WE ARE CONFIDENT THAT<br />
UNDER YOUR WISE LEADERSHIP THE AMERICAN PEOPLE<br />
WILL CONTINUE TO PROSPER AND WORLD PEACE BE FOSTlERFD.<br />
AUSTRALIANS AND AMERICANS HAVE A VERY WARM REGARD<br />
FOR ONE ANOTHER. THE MANY VALUES AND INTERESTS<br />
THAT THEY SHARE PROVIDE A FIRM BASIS FOR ESPECIALLY<br />
CLOSE AND FRIENDLY RELATIONS BETWEEN THE TWO<br />
COUNTRIES, WHICH I AM SURE WILL EXPAND AND DEEPEN<br />
DURING THE PERIOD YOU HOLD OFFICE.<br />
J. McEwen, Acting Prime Minister."<br />
CANBERRA, 19 January 1969 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
