<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2686</transcript-id>
    <title>MACQUARIE NETWORK WEEKLY BROADCASST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP - FOREIGN TAKEOVERS - UNEMPLOYMENT - 5 OCTOBER 1972 - INTERVIEWER: PAUL LYNCH</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/10/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002686.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO NOT FOR PUBLI TIL 6.30 PM ( EST)<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
1ACQUARIE NETWORK WEEKLY BROADCAST<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON.<br />
WILLIAJ Mc1AHON, CH, MP.<br />
FOREIGN TAKEOVERS<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT 5 OCTOBER 1972<br />
Interviewer: Paul Lynch<br />
Q. Prime Minister, last week you spoke to us about your<br />
plans to control foreign takeovers. What has happened in<br />
the week since then?<br />
PM: Immediately after I madethe statement, I gave directions<br />
to my Department to prepare a bill relating to the creation<br />
of an independent authority to vet takeover proposals for<br />
Australian companies. The bill has been completed now, and<br />
I put the final touches on it yesterday with the technical<br />
experts, nd I very much hope I will be able to introduce<br />
it into the House in the coming week. In other words, the<br />
newspaper reports that you have read that the bill won't be<br />
put on the table of the House are wrong. And what we will<br />
do is to have this independent authority that will have<br />
guidelines set down, and unless it can be proved that the<br />
takeover is in the public interest, then a recommendation<br />
can be made by the independent authority, submitted to the<br />
Government and it is up to the Government to make up its<br />
mind what it will do. But it will be an independent authority<br />
with people outside the Government analysing the facts and<br />
making reoresentations to the Government about them.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, have you received any representations<br />
from foreign interests at all about your proposals to affect<br />
the way they can invest in Australia since you first announced<br />
this last week?<br />
PM: No, I have not had any. But I have read comments in<br />
the newspapers a. nd those comments seem to indicate that they<br />
were accepted by the internatimalcorporations. In any event,<br />
it doesn't matter whether they are accepted or not. The<br />
simole fact is that they are going into law. We are going<br />
to protect Australia's interests. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Q. Prime Mlinister, when would you hope that this au4Jaarity<br />
could be set up and--could pass on foreign -takeove-s-nd also<br />
inflow of capital investment?-<br />
PM: Very soon, but the time factor is not of a great amount<br />
of importance for thase reasons that I did say in my statement<br />
to the House that we would have an interim authority<br />
comprised of civil servants within the Commonwealth Government,<br />
and they will act in the same way as the independent authority<br />
will act when it is created. So already we have got the<br />
Departmental authorities working. They can make recommondations<br />
either to me or to the Cabinet and we will decide what<br />
action should be taken either to prevent or to permit<br />
foreign takeovers. All in all, it is going to be a very<br />
difficult project for the so-called international conglomerates<br />
to get their hands on Australian companies. They will have to<br />
submit very strict proof that it is in Australia's national<br />
interest to permit it to happen.<br />
Q. Do you consider this in any sense interim legislation,<br />
or do you feel that it is so tight and so clear-cut that it<br />
will make future guidelines under any government for foreign<br />
takeover p,. roposals?<br />
PM: At least it is the outline of what my Government will<br />
follow in the future. We may refine it a bit but the essentials<br />
are there. what a government of a Jifferent texture would<br />
do I don't ' know, but they will find it very difficult to<br />
get away from our decisions. And in any event, I believe we<br />
will be there to administer it.<br />
Q. Turning to another matter, Prime Minister unemployment.<br />
In a matter of a few days, the September unemployment figures<br />
will come out. There has been a certain amount of discontent<br />
in the Press and elsewhere about the fact that the previous<br />
set of unemployment figures showed higher unemployment. Do<br />
you have anything to say about that?<br />
PM: Well, there are two things that have to be said. The<br />
first one is, without any doubt at all) that there was a<br />
reduction in unemployment in the month before last. In fact,<br />
there was a drop of about 4,500. But we also have what I<br />
regard as a somewhat complicated system called seasonally<br />
adjusted figures. Now those seasonally adjusted ficures<br />
over-emphasise the degree of unemPoloyment and even the<br />
Government Statistician warns whenever he issues the figures<br />
that they must not be taken as definitive. They are only<br />
there for the purpose of scientific analysis and they must<br />
not take the place of scientific analysis, and if you do, you<br />
are bound to be wrong. So that puts the matter in perspective.<br />
There will be, I believe, and I have talked to my colleague,<br />
the Minister for Labour and National Service about this, there<br />
will be a quite substantial reduction in unemployment for the<br />
month of September and that will be published quite soon. It<br />
will be, I believe, a bigger reduction than normally takes place.<br />
I am looking forward with a little bit of anxiety but<br />
nonetheless with, I believe, a great deal of confidence that<br />
' when the figures come out, even those who want to misrepresent<br />
them will be hard pittto to do so.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, thank you very much. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
