<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4956</transcript-id>
    <title>&#039;EXPORT NOW&#039; CAMPAIGN</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/02/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004956.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PIMiE MINIST-R.<br />
FOR PRESS. 19 FEBRUARY, 1979<br />
" EXPORT NOW" CAMPAIGN<br />
It's a great pleasure to address this conference and to<br />
launch the " Export Now" Campaign.<br />
Some people might say that the first thing we should export<br />
are our politicians. But in all fairness I must warn you that<br />
such action would be viewed by our trading partners as an<br />
act of war and in breach of the international conventions<br />
against cruel and inhuman weapons. Nevertheless, we must<br />
export our goods and services for it's largely by selling<br />
what we have that we can get what we want.<br />
What we all want for Australia is economic growth, rising<br />
living standards, and greater employment opportunities.<br />
This national export campaign concerns all Australians,<br />
so it is fitting that there are representatives of all<br />
sections of our nation here today. Your presence here is<br />
clear evidence of a determination to help Australia<br />
" lext ort now". Your leadership is crucial to the success<br />
of campaign.<br />
In t~ ne 1960' s we had the highly successful " Export Action"<br />
campaign and now, as then, we rely on export earnings to<br />
pay for our imports and keep the Australian dollar strong.<br />
Now, as then, we rely on exports to develop our industries<br />
and emplo y more Australians. Now, as then, the need<br />
for exports is compelling, but Australia has changed<br />
enormously over the last 20 years.<br />
Just look at our language twenty years ago " to be<br />
busted" meant you were out of money; " to be a swinger"<br />
meant that you liked jazz and " to be gay" was simply a<br />
mood. Australian exports have also changed dramatically.<br />
In 1952/ 53 our major'exports comprised 5 percent manufactures,<br />
7 percent minerals, and 83 percent farm products. By last<br />
year those proportions had been transformed to 21 percent<br />
manufactures, 31 percent minerals and farm products were<br />
only 43 percent although we're hoping that this will be<br />
up a bit this year.<br />
The markets in which Australia trades have also changed. our<br />
traditional market was the United Kingdom. In 1953 more than<br />
one third of our exports went there and there were only a<br />
dozen countries to which Australia exported more than<br />
million worth of goods. Today, the U. K. takes barely / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
four percent of our exports; 64 countries take more<br />
than $ 10 million worth of our exports; and 22 countries<br />
take over $ 100 million. It is now Japan that takes<br />
a third of our products. China is now our fourth largest<br />
export market.<br />
ASEAN is now a major customer our exports to ASEAN<br />
countries have risen 260 percent from $ 329 million in<br />
1971/ 72 to $ 853 million in 1977/ 78. And, in turn, even<br />
in the sensitive areas such as footwear, textiles and<br />
clothing, we are a large importer of ASEAN products.<br />
If the United States, the E. E. C. and Japan took the same<br />
per capita quantity of these items from ASEAN as we do,<br />
ASEAN would be selling $ 1,000 million more.<br />
On anyv reasonable comparative basis which must include<br />
embargoes, quantitative restrictionsand subsidies as<br />
well as tariffs we have an open trading policy. While<br />
percent of our exports face significant non-tariff<br />
barriers in some world markets less than 7 percent of<br />
our own imports are subject to non-tariff barriers.<br />
Even in the case of the imports upon which we impose<br />
restraint a considerable part of the Australian market<br />
is available for overseas goods. For example, in the<br />
case of motor vehicles, 20 percent of the Australian market<br />
is available for imported cars although I believe that the.<br />
quality of Australian cars will make it hard for foreign<br />
makes to sell in Australia. But if we consider the position<br />
in Europe despite the advantage their manufacturers have<br />
market access is much more restricted. Furthermore, our<br />
agricultural goods are almost totally excluded from<br />
important world markets like the E. E. C.<br />
A large part of our trading future lies in Asia but to<br />
ignore other markets in Europe would be to compr6mise the<br />
national interest. Europe is one of the world's largest<br />
and most affluent markets. It is important to us. We<br />
object to our efficient producers being unfairly excluded<br />
from many parts of that market. And it is not just a<br />
question of access to Europe.<br />
Australia's sales in other overseas markets are undercut<br />
by European agricultural and wage subsidies which on<br />
some counts run as high as $ 25 billion. We can spend years<br />
developing a market in Asia only to have it taken away from<br />
us by subsidised European products. There is no way that<br />
a country with 14 million can compete with the subsidies<br />
financed by 260 million Europeans. We cannot ignore<br />
European policies it is not just a question of access,<br />
it is also a question of the disruption of other markets in<br />
which we sell. As a trading nation we must be concerned<br />
with Europe and its policies. And as a trading nation we<br />
have to become more competitive. We have to get out and<br />
sell; we have to do better than our competitors; we<br />
have to get a larger share of markets in Australia and overseas.<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Australia is a great raw materials exporter but<br />
we cannot be satisfied with that. We have abundant<br />
cheap energy and we want to process more materials.<br />
Together with the States we are examining how this<br />
can be done.<br />
We must diversify our markets overdependence on any one<br />
buyer is not good business sense and it is not good<br />
export sense. We must diversify our exports. Traditionally<br />
Australia has relied on primary industry, minerals and<br />
on some manufactures for its export earnings. Australia<br />
will be stronger if our exports are more diverse.<br />
We must exploit our advantages in abundant resources;<br />
our highly skilled labour force; our management and<br />
productEion talents.<br />
We need to embrace, not reject, the new technology.<br />
By doing so new industries will develop, new products<br />
will be sold, and more people will be employed.<br />
During part of the 1970' s there were reasons why our<br />
manufacturing exports did not increase as fast as we<br />
hoped. Inflation eroded our competitiveness. Costs<br />
in Australia sky-rocketed. Average weekly earnings in Australia<br />
increased by 45 percent over the two years 1972/ 73 to<br />
19741/ 75. The investment allowance was discontinued.<br />
Uncertainty delayed investment decisions. So it was<br />
perhaps understandable that Australian manufacturers<br />
lagged behind in world markets.<br />
But -we are now in a position where Australian industry<br />
can compete. We are more competitive than at any time<br />
during the last seven years. Contracts are being written<br />
for zroducts and in markets that would have seemed beyond<br />
reach only a few years ago. But it is up to Australian<br />
manufacturers and of course our traditional exporters<br />
as well to take full advantage of the opportunities<br />
we have in world markets.<br />
The timing of the " Export Now" campaign is no accident.<br />
It has been made possible by Australia's success in<br />
lowering inflation. Lower inflation creates confidence and<br />
is a vital stimulus for our exporters.<br />
The Government has also introduced a package of measures<br />
to assist exporters, although I cannot think of a better<br />
incentive than having a lower inflation rate than that<br />
in your competitor's country. There is: the expanded<br />
Export Market Development Scheme, which assists exporters<br />
to develop new markets; the Export Expansion Grants Scheme<br />
to encourage exporters to expand their markets; the<br />
Australian Overseas Projects Corporation to assist Australians<br />
with large-scale projects overseas; and the Export Finance<br />
Insurance Corporation which now has an expanded charter to<br />
allow it to provide export credit, and limit some of the<br />
risks of overseas ventures. The recently established $ 50 million<br />
credit line to China is an excellent example of the way in<br />
which E. F. I. C. funds can back Australian exporters entering<br />
new and expanding markets. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Australia's trading opportunities are vast. One need<br />
only look at the Middle East to see the possibilities<br />
for our exporters of foodstuffs, materials, manufactures,<br />
consultancy services and know-how.<br />
Australia is already capitalising on this new market.<br />
In the five years to 1977/ 78 our exports to the Middle<br />
East grew at an annual rate of 41 percent. That is only<br />
a beginning and the outlook for oil revenues suggests<br />
further massive increases in the wealth of some countries<br />
in this ar-ea.<br />
The opening up of the China market presents further<br />
exciting opportunities for Australian traders.<br />
Our export sales to China have been increasing at<br />
over 40 percent a year. We are a technologically<br />
and industrially developed middle power. We can<br />
contribute to China's modernisation and, because of<br />
our geograpThy, because we are a middle power, we<br />
are better placed than many to take advantage of the<br />
new opoortunities opening in China.<br />
In the region of -the East and South East Asia many countries<br />
are rapidly industrialising and real incomes are growing<br />
at a rat. e faster than more advanced economies.<br />
Singapore, Hong Kong and South Korea are prime examples<br />
all offer excellent prospects for Australian exporters.<br />
India has a real interest in obtaining long term and<br />
reliable supplies of hard coking coal from Australia.<br />
Thelre -is no shortage of opportunities the time has come<br />
for a united effort by all Australians to take<br />
advantage of them.<br />
The success of this campaign is important. It will require<br />
determined, sustained effort, marketing flair, and ability<br />
to perform when contracts are won.<br />
Shortly the three winners of the Governor-General's<br />
award -for export excellence will be announced, but there<br />
are many more organisations which have achieved notable<br />
export successes. A Melbourne-based company has won a<br />
multi-million dollar contract to supply and erect a number<br />
of motel units in China complete with cars! Wormald<br />
International sold the Chinese a fire protection system<br />
for a power station.<br />
We have companies exporting plastic kitchenware to Japan,<br />
door knobs to the United States that should open some<br />
other markets, concrete pipe making technology to the<br />
visual education equipment to Africa and<br />
South America, Analog computers to many countries, and<br />
fishing boats, quarrying and mining equipment to<br />
South East Asia. Many other examples could be given of<br />
Australian companies some even labour intensive<br />
exporting effectively. </p>
<p>5<br />
"'" These " export experts" have shown the enterprise that<br />
Australia needs. There is a world of opportunity awaiting<br />
them and companies like them and the Government has shown<br />
its determination to provide the backing to support<br />
their efforts.<br />
It is vital for Australia that our companies make<br />
export part of a long term strategy for growth. A strong<br />
and growing export sector is a prerequisite to a strong<br />
and growing Australia. It deserves the highest rating<br />
in our priorities.<br />
It is through our own efforts that we will be able to<br />
export more and create more jobs. To achieve export<br />
growthi we need to act now we must " export now".<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, I have great pleasure in opening<br />
this conference and launching the " Export Now" campaign.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
