<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5427</transcript-id>
    <title>HMAS DIAMANTINA - GIFT TO QUEENSLAND MARITIME MUSEUM</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/08/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005427.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA WEDNESDAY, 27 AUGUST, 1980<br />
HMAS DIAMANTINA GIFT TO QUEENSLAND MARITIMNE MUSEUM<br />
The Commonwealth Government is to make a gift of the frigate,<br />
HMAS Diamantina, to the Queensland Maritime Museum Association.<br />
As the frigate was built in Queensland ( by Walkers Ltd. at<br />
Maryborough), is named after the wife of Queensland's first<br />
Governor ( Sir George Bowen) and carries the same name as one<br />
of Queensland's major rivers, it is fitting that Queensland<br />
should be the final home for the Diamantina.<br />
HMAS Diamantina, first commissioned in April, 1945, is the last<br />
surviving World War II vessel of the R. A. N. and was the scene<br />
for the acceptance of the surrender of the Japanese at Nauru<br />
and Ocean Island. She was the research platform from which was<br />
conducted the investigation of many oceanographic phenomena<br />
( including the Diamantina Trench off Western Australia, the<br />
deepest known trench in the Indian Ocean).<br />
Her transfer to the Queensland Maritime Museum Association is<br />
supported by the Naval Historical Society of Australia.<br />
The Queensland Maritime Museum Association plans to extend its<br />
Maritime Museum to preserve and exhibit items of historical<br />
interest pertaining to ships and the sea, and the Diamantina<br />
will be installed as a permanently dry-berthed exhibit within<br />
the old Graving Dock at South Brisbane.<br />
I wish the Association every success with the restoration and<br />
exhibition of the Diamantina, which will be handed over at a<br />
ceremony to be arranged in the near future.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
