<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2649</transcript-id>
    <title>BUSINESS AND PROFESSIONAL MEN&#039;S DINNER - ADELAIDE - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP - 24 JULY 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/07/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002649_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
3USINESS AND _ PP. CFSSIO17AL MEIV S DTNNMR<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, r'nc -It Flon. William Mcilahon, CH!, NIP.<br />
24 July. 1972<br />
Dir Macklin, Parliamentary Colicagues, Ge ntlemen:.<br />
I cartehere toniciht zprimarily t'-o -talk to ' iou about a technical<br />
subject that I know is v ry dear to most of you anai certainly<br />
dear to my friend in. the Chamb-tr of !-. anuf-c-tures sitting inranediately<br />
to my right. And t hat subject I wanted -to talk about wa:) s the subject<br />
of tarif fs and its preoccupation with t;-c manuf acturing -: nd the<br />
conuercjat industries of ti-. is country.<br />
I also wanted to say somothIng to you a bout the state of<br />
the economy, not too muc.. i ecause w) e have got a Budget comi ng aLong in<br />
three or four weeks time, and I am one of the believers in the oldfashioned<br />
British custom~ of Budget solidarity and abov" all, of Budget<br />
secrecy. Not only bc&amp; c~ I think that you can kc: 2r ' jour secrets<br />
to yourse-lf and you ca-, have -the surpnris~ oiemont when the Treasurer<br />
delivers the Budget th~ en you will got infinitely better public<br />
reaction and public resrpanse thian ," ou will if therc-are leaks, and<br />
when the Cday comes, the Treasure r has nothing else to do but reci. toc<br />
the taxation proposals and the wa-y t~ o bring disapproval by those whlo<br />
have to pay thc7, m.<br />
Tonight, seeing that thei gatharing is as great and<br />
distinguishf2s as it is, I still beivdI had to go along with my<br />
irmediate intentin But af-ta ng to your President, I al! so<br />
felt th~ at, tima wil ling anC you ar~ cir. n to be intarc-sted and my<br />
pra'yers rz usually answered -that I might say something to you on<br />
a mucn morc+. Lnt:: resting subje-ct and thiat is my recent visit t"-o !,, uala<br />
Lumpur, Singaporce and Djakarta. Pocause it was a momorable triP and<br />
believe ou-r de-: stins to a zosdrhecxtc~ nt and our future<br />
developmont are wra-) p d up itll tho dCrvc,: br-mient of those cou. ntties. We<br />
are the ones w'no can raost+ benof it-froti close association with them;<br />
from, their inchastri al developmeont; and from our capaci. ty f or trade with<br />
thM. 11T But may I nowj, Mr ' lacklin, get on with the subje-ct. The<br />
two subjzlcts that I want to speak to you about tonight. I want to<br />
a ' ssure you, as one who has been Treasurer for some time, and enjoyed<br />
the nortfoi i mens. y thnit I bolieve? I had a pretty glood comm~ a-nd<br />
of Trcasury problems arnd kept the econony reasonably healthy, prohably<br />
as healthy as It ') as ever heen. So I have the % nowledg-e and the ability<br />
for quick adaptation and chango Lthat I think is so essential and<br />
imoortant to a2 Treasurer and rarticularly to a Head of Gove-rnment when<br />
we are looking at Cur economic problems. ./ 2 </p>
<p>I believe there are very sound grounds for thinking the<br />
economy will significantly improve in the future, in both the short and<br />
long term. There has never been any doubt about the long term, because<br />
over the years we have continuously built this economy of ours on a<br />
broader basis, much more variable, much more basically sound and with<br />
inherent strength. And our record of two decades of growth has been<br />
a tribute to the kind of policy that we have been able to adopt.<br />
We are all aare that most of the problems which hav.? captured<br />
the headlines in the past year or so have not been long term but short<br />
term problems. It is true, too, that we have had setbacks. The unemoloyment<br />
problems have been stubborn, somewhat too stubborn, and the oresent<br />
level while low by standards of other countries is still certainly<br />
not acceptable to me. As you know, and here I come back to that word<br />
" flexible" again because we have considered it desirable since September<br />
of last year we have taken positive measures to reduce the number of<br />
unemployed. Even taking specific action of a kind that hitherto we had<br />
not taken. We have also taken other measures on a broad basis, particularly<br />
the mini-Budget and the assistance we gave to the Premiers. I<br />
think I can say to you that as these measures work their way through<br />
the economy, conditions most certainly will improve steadily. Encouraging<br />
indicators are now showing.<br />
The latest of these is the slowdown in price inflation<br />
reflected in the consumer price index figures last weze. The increase<br />
of point nine of one per cent is the lowest quarterly increase for<br />
nearly two years, although I have to admit there were some special<br />
problems or special influences that were involved thers. A little over<br />
seven months ago we felt that in the June quarter we would be extremely<br />
lucky if we could keep the consumer index at very much less than 2 per<br />
cent and probably a little higher.<br />
So that you can take it that we were delighted when these<br />
figures of point nine of one per cent came about because it gave one<br />
of the indications that inflation, one of the most difficult and intractable<br />
nroblems that we have had to solve and one that could easily cost<br />
us out of international markets, did show some kind of improvement. I<br />
don't want to go overboard about them because the results affect only<br />
one month. I will say it is pretty good, or satisfactory anyhow, and<br />
I hope we can keep up this kind of record in the months to come.<br />
I don't want you to think that I'm arguing that inflation<br />
has been solved. It has not. Together, you and I as manufacturers,<br />
people in the commercial world, and recole in the other sections of the<br />
economy and in the Goverrment have .1l got to exercise our combined<br />
skill and our energies to contain it.<br />
Providing we can do this and make our contribution, and<br />
providing only we can keep wages closer to the increases in productivity,<br />
then the better the chance we have t First to conquer this problem;<br />
and then to get the economy moving along at a growth rate of at least<br />
per cent. Let me emphasise too, that c nsm. r demand has obviously<br />
been far too subdued. I admit that and tlr'-t is the reason why we took<br />
action at two successive Premiers' Conforeccs and in the mini-Budget,<br />
and through the banking system to give at least the incentive and the<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>intucement for consumer demand to improve. And through that means to<br />
be able to get the order books full and when the order books became full,<br />
for it to work back into the basic industries. So I emphasise to you<br />
that the community has been too cautious in its spending. But with<br />
increasing confidence and I believe confidence is improving, and<br />
there's evidence of it; there would be greater evidence of it still,<br />
if industrial lawlessness were reduced to a minimum, and we were able<br />
to reduce the uncertainty that has been caused by the difficult conditions<br />
created by some sections of the Trade Union movement; cur record<br />
must improve. What I can say in positive terms, and it has been emphasised,<br />
and emphasised very well in the Treasury Annual Review, is that the<br />
goals of national growth for this year are much higher than for the<br />
financial year just ended.<br />
Now to achieve our growth I believe we need four ingredients.<br />
The first one undoubtedly is confidence; a little more confidence; a<br />
little more willingness to spend can, I believe, achieve miracles.<br />
We can increase consumer spending and I have just mentioned that; we<br />
need greater industrial stability and we need less industrial lawlessness.<br />
I believe as you look at all these oroblems you must make this concession,<br />
particularly if you understand what my Government has done; that we have<br />
acted in both a responsible, and I believe a comprehensive way.<br />
I know it is a Government of decision. WJhen major decisions<br />
have to be made, we have handled them. Only a few moments ago, talking<br />
to my colleague on my right hand side, I was able to mention to him that<br />
never in 72 years of Federation had any government had the courage to<br />
introduce into the civil service the rule of ho work, no pay' despite<br />
the year after year recommendations that were made. This year we introduced<br />
the amendment, and I don't like to be boastful because that's not<br />
my way but at least I can say that since that time we have not had a<br />
strike or a threat of a strike on the Commonwealth Civil Service.<br />
Let me give you two exampls of the kind of action we have taken.<br />
First we have introduced into conciliation and arbitration a new system<br />
which will be proclaimed shortly if it hasn't been proclaimed today. I<br />
believe it is the most extensive reform of the conciliation and arbitrationi<br />
system that has been carried out for a little over a quarter of a<br />
century. We have in that review strengthened the sanction provisions of<br />
the conciliation and arbitration act.<br />
The second point I want to make is that we have, and we will<br />
continue to intervene before the arbitration commission in wage claims<br />
whenever we have considered it to be in the public interest. Never has<br />
a case gone by where a. sharp increase in wages is demanded by the unions,<br />
unless I have immediately asked my colleagues to have a lpok at the problem<br />
and to see whether in the public interest, in the interest of keeping<br />
inflation low and demand high, we should intervene.<br />
I now move on to the subject I really wanted to speak about<br />
tonight and that is tariffs, and I hope to explain what we are doing,<br />
the reasons for our actions and if I can, to remove some of the indecision<br />
and lac of certainty that might be in the minds of manufacturers<br />
and producers of raw materials. My Government's policy was clearly<br />
set out by my colleague, Doug Anthony, the Minister for Trade and Industry,<br />
in a statement that he made to Parliament in April of last year. I can<br />
assure you that we as a Government have not, and we will not, depart<br />
from that policy. / 4<br />
L </p>
<p>Before I get on to policy explanation, may I say something<br />
to you to put the issue in context. I want to emphasise in the strongest<br />
terms the vitally important role that manufacturing industry and<br />
the private enterprise system in general plays in the development and<br />
pr-ogress of this country.<br />
This, of course, includes transport and other areas of<br />
commerce. I want to emphasise this because we are a great country<br />
with a great performance per head of population. Those who travel<br />
overseas as I do, come back delighted with the respect and admiration<br />
that there is for us and the performance of the Australian people. And<br />
a. Ll those achievements, or mcit of them anyhow, are by private enterp3ise.<br />
The manufacturing and mining industries particularly are now<br />
playing a magnificent part in development, and in our ability to expand<br />
our trade and to play our part and make our contribution to the development<br />
of the countries immediately to our North.<br />
We, as a Government, do recognise that a sound, profitable<br />
and growing manufacturing sector is of fundamental importance. Its<br />
g:: owth must be fostered and the economic climate created to ensure that<br />
manufacturing industry assumes an even greater and more important role<br />
in our eeonomy as it does in the other higher industrialised communities.<br />
In this context, I want to discuss tariff policy and I want<br />
to make three points. As an essential condition of growth and progress,<br />
we must encourage the best and the most efficient allocation and use of<br />
our resources whether Australian, or those which are attracted here<br />
by the inducements of the ratural resources and the economic climate of<br />
tills country. Historically, in the two decades after the war, successive<br />
governments consciously pursued policies directed towards a high and<br />
sustained growth rate and the optimum employmentcf resources. This,<br />
as I said, but I repeat it now in somewhat different language this<br />
d: iversification of industry turned us into the broadly based industrial<br />
economy that we have today. In more recent years, as our economy has<br />
become more sophisticated, the need for greater selectivity in industrial<br />
development has become more desirable. To achieve this we needed policies<br />
designed and attuned to the times.<br />
As I said last year, to the Chamber of Manufactures of New<br />
South Wales, we cannot accept uncritically and without reservations the<br />
use of our national re. urces in activities which require very high<br />
levels of protection, because, prima facie, such activities are less<br />
suited to the Australian economic cnvironm~ it than industries requiring<br />
more moderate levels of protection.<br />
The second main pQint I want to stress is that low tariffs<br />
b:: ing benefits as well as costs. The benefits to the community which a<br />
government must consider in making a judgment on the level of protection<br />
include the direct marketing relationships which one Australian industry<br />
may have withaiother, and the effect of one industry's costs on another<br />
industry's prices. I assure you they go wider than that. For example,<br />
an industry may be employing special classes of labour, which we what<br />
to encourage. It may also be developing special skills and technology.<br />
In the same way, there can be highly significant non-economic benefits<br />
for us such as defence.<br />
You will see, therefore, that when these factors are involved<br />
in tariff decisions, the Government and I want to emphasise those<br />
words must play a crucial role. I personally assure you my Government<br />
gives and will continue togive very close attention to these aspects of<br />
tariff administration when Tariff Board reports are before us. </p>
<p>The third point I want to make! is that decisions are made<br />
only after considering the capital investment in the industry concerned<br />
and the employment which that industry creates. I want to emphasise<br />
these ingredients of policy and also one other points.<br />
In cases where, according to the recommendatbn of the Tariff<br />
Board, it has been considered desirable to encourage the transfer of<br />
resources from one industry to another, the Government has frequently<br />
decided that the transfer should be a gradual process. And I can assure<br />
you that in the implementation of this policy of gradualness, I have<br />
taken an interested, and I believe on occasions, a decisive role. We<br />
have done this, for example, in the case of woven and knitted shirts.<br />
We did this to achieve an orderly transition to a lower level of protection.<br />
We decided that the existing level would be maintained for a<br />
longer, much longer period than recommended by the Board.<br />
In the meantime, the Government is negotiating for voluntary<br />
restraint arrangements with low-cost overseas countries in order to<br />
ensure protection to Australian manufacturers.<br />
Today, one of the greatest leaders in Australian industry<br />
is in Japan, trying to and he will undoubtedly succeed ensum<br />
some kind of restriction is imposed voluntarily by the countries that<br />
are exporting to Australia. In the same way, protection given to<br />
malleable cast iron pipe fittings is being reduced in three stages over<br />
five years. More recently, as uith another case in which I was deeply<br />
involved, the Government has provided the local shipbuilding industry<br />
with a longer period for gradual change than the Board recommended.<br />
So let me say to you now without reservation that if tariff action<br />
ware considered likely to lead to phasing out of any segment of<br />
manufacturing industry firms would not be expected to adjust overnight<br />
anid, of course, the interest of manufacturers and emikbyees would be<br />
protected. I emphasise again to you that special care will be taken<br />
relating to changes that might have the effect of putting job opportunities<br />
for Australia at risk.<br />
Turning to another aspect of tariffs, as you know, a compreheansive<br />
review of the tariff is now taking place. I have learnt a great<br />
deal about it from my friend, Mr Pascoe, during the course of the last<br />
hour. In fact it has been one of the most informative lectures I<br />
have had since my university days.<br />
I am aware that some sectors of manufacturers are feeling<br />
apprehensive about the outcome of this review. I want to assure you<br />
that the review is not in any sense an exercise against a policy of<br />
adequate protection for economic, efficient and desirable Australian<br />
industry. On the contrary, the Government's intention is that it should<br />
work in the long run, for the benefit of our manufacturing industries.<br />
The review will be completed in about six years. And, of<br />
course, I want to emphasise that if ever you feel you are having unexpectac<br />
difficulties which have to be solved immediately, then you have recourse<br />
a~ s an immediate court of appeal to the Special Advisory Body.<br />
There is a second point that I want to teake and I want to<br />
make it now again because of the discussion I have been having with<br />
y' colleague on my right hand side, Mr Pascoe. He has mentioned that<br />
in this large-scale revie'w, there should be some kind of a timetable<br />
drawn up so that industry itself will have a degree of certainty reintroduced<br />
into the manufacturing industries and a degree of predictability<br />
that they do not have at the moment. ./ 6 </p>
<p>I can assure you that when I go back tc Canberra tomorrow<br />
night or when I arrive there on Wednesday, it will be one of the first<br />
problems I will take up either with Mr MacKay of the Department of Trade<br />
and Industry or, if necessary, with Mr Anthony. I can assure you that<br />
it is one of the problems that has worried me and I am glad that you<br />
have driven home this point effectively tonight.<br />
As each review report is reviewed, it will be considered by<br />
the Government, and we and here I want to emphasise this point and<br />
keep on emphasising it if I can we, as a Government, and no-one else,<br />
will decide what action should be taken. The Government needs and expects<br />
the Tariff Board in its report to give as clear and comprehensive advice<br />
as it can on both the reasons for its recommendations and the likely<br />
consequence of adopting them. The fact is, however, that there are<br />
larger areas of the tariff which have not been looked at for very many<br />
years and some tariffs have never been reviewed since their inception.<br />
In these circumstances-there are bound to be some tariffs which provide<br />
protection far in excess of the amount required. Of course excess<br />
protection of this kind adds unnecessarily to our cost structure, and<br />
cost inflation. And you must know this is not in the interests either<br />
of the manufacturing industry or of the community.<br />
The existing economic climate and timing are, of course,<br />
also imporant and must increasingly be taken into consideration in the<br />
decision-making process. We also take note of the protection policies<br />
of other countries where, in addition to tariffs arrangements or other<br />
devices like quotas, import licensing and export schemes are used. We<br />
are concerned entirely with the practical and beneficial effects of<br />
tariff changes on individual industries and the economy as a whole.<br />
So you will see and I hope I can convince you on this point we are not<br />
and we will never be influenced by abstract theories.<br />
Particularly, Mr Chairman, I want to emphasise that the<br />
Government makes the decisions in all cases on tariff matters. We have<br />
a very strong tariff committee of the Cabinet, and in major cases such<br />
as the chemicals review or the shipbuilding industrv or of woven garments,<br />
we take those into the Cabinet itself and if variations have to be made<br />
based on the grounds that I have mentioned, we are not only willing but<br />
happy to make changes we believe desirable in the interest of Australian<br />
manufacturing industry and above all, the country itself. Now, the<br />
Board is a highly exoert body but it is an advisory one only, and its<br />
recommendations are not automatically accented by the Government ( as I<br />
have already pointed out).<br />
Gentlemen, tariff nolicy is -art of our overall policy<br />
towards manufacturing industry and the free enterprise economy. That<br />
rolicy I want to repeat is to give all the support we can towards the<br />
development of a soundly growing and confident manufacturing industry<br />
in Australia. I want to sum un to you in this way:-Confidence is<br />
catching If we all . have confidence, talk with confidence, and above<br />
all, act with confidence, we will, I am sure, and of this I can give you<br />
great reassurance, get ahead faster and much futther this year than we<br />
did last year. This must give our longer-term development programmes an<br />
added stimulus for the good of the country, for iegood of manufacturers<br />
and for the benefit of the consumers of all kinds. If we can give<br />
these benefits to the consumers, I believe we inspire confidence to get<br />
back in the market place and buy to let those who sell to the market<br />
place get their order books full, and in time, as it works back to the<br />
/ 7 </p>
<p>manufacturers and the producers of base materials, to ensure that they<br />
are fully employed, that our growth rate continues and each and everyone<br />
of us can make our contribution to the development and to the standards<br />
of living and the values of life that I believe every person here tonight<br />
holds dear. Mr Chairman, that was what I wanted to say to you on an cfficial<br />
level. As time is passing and as you wanted me to speak for a somewhat<br />
longer period than I intended, I thought I'd say something to you about<br />
my recent mission overseas to Indonesia, Singapore and Malaysia. I<br />
must confess that I went with some trepidation based on advice given<br />
to me that there might be perhaps some doubt or disenchantment in these<br />
countries with Australia. As Foreign Minister I had the good fortune<br />
to make the acquaintance more than that a valuable friendship with<br />
Lee Kuan Yew, the Prime Minister of Singapore, and Tun Razak, the Prime<br />
Minister of Malaysia.<br />
I had also been able to establish a valuable friendship with<br />
President Seeharto of Indonesia. What did interest me was the fact that<br />
these people trust us; they hnow that we want to trade with them; they<br />
know we want to make our contiibution to their duvelopment; they know<br />
wevent to help them remove poverty and to assist them with the development<br />
of their abundant natural resources. They believe that as a people<br />
they can rely on the people of this country in whom they have the<br />
greatest confidence. I addressed their Parliament. The welcome was<br />
outstanding. And I can express this with certainty as they grow<br />
wealthier and I know they will we will be the beneficiary, the main<br />
beneficiary because they will want the kind of materials and the<br />
finished products, the manufactured products, that we in Australia by<br />
that time will be able to produce.<br />
So it was not only a mission of goodwill but it was educational<br />
in this sense. I realise the many opportunities that are open for<br />
us and the way in which we can trade with them. This must be to our<br />
mutual development. Particularly as they develop and we develop economically,<br />
so too will our ability to ensure peace in this area, and in the<br />
long run, if I can repeat those words again to be able to make our<br />
contribution to the peace of the whole of the South-East Asian area.<br />
Indonesia is a wonderful country! it is well worthwhile visiting; they<br />
like us and I believe Australians should go there more frequently and<br />
find out what the trading p:--ssbi1. ities are.<br />
I then went to Singa~ oe to talk to the Prime Minister, Lee Kuan<br />
Yew, who is a friend of ours. Of course, Singapore is developing quickly.<br />
It is now trying to change its economy from a cottage economy or the<br />
development of fabrics and textiles and things of that kind, into a<br />
manufacturing industry that will produce the medium range, high quality<br />
products such as television sets, radios and consumer durables of a<br />
similar kind. Here you find a dynamic wholesome society. Again you found that<br />
they trusted us and I think the spoech Lee Kuan Yew made on the night<br />
that he gave me a dinner was memorable in the sense that while I left<br />
Australia feeling a degree of hesitation and doubt, after hearing his<br />
speech I realised how much he valuod us as partners and friends and how<br />
much he wanted us to retain our armed forces in Singanore. Not only<br />
because, as he put it in his own inimitable way, it was of benefit to<br />
him, but it brought a feeling of confidonce and filled a vacuum which<br />
if we were not there would be filed by somebody else, probably more<br />
powerful and more intimidatory than we or they would want.ø. 48. </p>
<p>Then on to Kuala Lump~ ur to meet an old friend, Prime Minister<br />
Tun Razak. I was able to go up to Butterworth and see our Air Force<br />
at the airfield which we've made a c-ontribution towards doveloping.<br />
We provided Miragcs and other tV,. es of aircraft for the integrated<br />
air-defence system there. Again, I believc we have stationcd something<br />
like two squadrons of Mirages to be part of the Commonwealth Air Defence<br />
System in the aroa. If you want to see efficiency developed over a<br />
period of little less than two years if you want to feel proud of our<br />
ability to make our contribution to the. welfare and the defence of othersthen<br />
you should find out a little more about Butterworth. It was really<br />
heartening to see the way in which their air defence system was working.<br />
Not so long ago the Malaysians had little or no knowledge of the vast<br />
techniques of direction-finding, of radar detection and the other<br />
components of air defence systems. I think you. can now take it that thy<br />
are pretty compotent and effective, and making a significant contribution<br />
to the defence arrangements.<br />
Up there and I want to drive this home because it's not<br />
always adequately reported in the pre-ss not only are the trade<br />
opportunities great because of incroasing stability, and they will<br />
expand as the time goes by, but each of these realises that if<br />
South-East Asia is to remain free, then it is desirable that we should<br />
keep our forces, our armed forces of the three Services in Singapore<br />
and the Air Defence System in Malaysia. We should be able to assist<br />
Indonesia to build up a capacity tc develop a more ef f~ ctive Army, and<br />
a more effective way of ensuring that if a threat does emerge from<br />
outside, they will, with our help, and probably Ait help from other<br />
countries, be able not only to defend themselves but also to make<br />
their contribution to the defence of other South-East Asian countries.<br />
The point I want to make and drive home is that if eva'r there<br />
is a country that ought to be proud of what it is capable of doin~ g,<br />
and in fact does do, it is ours. For that reason, thank you Mr<br />
Chairman, forasking me to come. Above all, I have, come and I can,-<br />
assure you it has givon me an enormous amount of pleasure to be with<br />
Australians, to know what you are capable of doing.<br />
May I express the hope that I will have the good fortune to<br />
be qiven the chance to provide continued leadership. There could be<br />
no greater honour than providing leadership to the kind of people I<br />
see sitting in front of me tonight. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
