<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3386</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. E.G. WHITLAM, Q.C., M.P., AT PENRITH CIVIC RECEPTION 11 SEPTEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/09/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003386_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON.* E. G. WHITLAM,<br />
AT PENRITH CIVIC RECEPTION*.-<br />
11 SEPTEMBER 1974<br />
THE PROBLEMS AND CHALLENGES OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
HAVE NATIONAL IMPLICATIONS QUITE DISTINCT FROM THE-IR<br />
RELEVANCE TO PARTICULAR LOCALITIES. WHEN THE<br />
INSTITUTE OF MUNICIPAL ADMINISTRATION WAS ESTABLISHED<br />
' IN 1952 ON A FEDERAL BASIS IT REALISED THAT " WHILE<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT IS LOCAL AND, IN FACT, DERIVES ITS<br />
FUNCTIONS'FROM EACH RESPECTIVE STATE, THE DEVELOPMENT<br />
, AND STRENGTH OF-IT IS A MATTER OF NATIONAL IMPORTANCE<br />
AND OF NATIONAL CONCERN. 1<br />
IT WAS TWENTY YEARS BEFORE A NATIONAL<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WAS PREPARED TO TAKE A SIMILAR<br />
ATTITUDE. ONLY SINCE LABOR WAS ELECTED IN DECEMBER 1972<br />
HAS ANY ATTEMPT BEEN MADE TO GIVE PRACTICAL HELP TO<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT IN MEETING THE INCREASING DEMANDS<br />
MADE UPON IT. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Nr KNOWS BETTER THAN THOSE INVOLVED IN<br />
LOCAL GOVER'. MENT THE LONG YEARS OF NEGLECT AND<br />
INDIFFERENCE FROM WHICH IT HAS SUFFERED AND THE<br />
ATMOSPHERE OF PERPETUAL FINANCIAL CRISIS THAT<br />
SURROUNDS IT FOR GENERATIONS. I HAVE OFTEN MARVELLED<br />
AT THE DEDICATION AND FORTITUDE OF MEN AND WOMEN WHO<br />
HAVE CONTINUED TO SERVE LOCAL'GOVERNMENT IN THE FACE<br />
OF SUCH ODDS. NOW THE PROSPECTS ARE CHANGING.<br />
THE RECENT GRANTS TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT COUNCILS ALL OVER<br />
AUSTRALIA'-WITH THE LION'S SHARE COMING TO NEW SOUTH<br />
WALES ARE THE BEGINNING OF THE END OF THE INEQUALITY<br />
BETWEEN ' COUNCILS AND BETWEEN REGIONS THAT HAS BEDEVILLED<br />
' THE GROWTH OF RESPONSIBLE AND RESPONSIVE LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
IN AUSTRALIA. ALL MY GOVERNMENT'S POLICIES HAVE BEEN DIRECTED<br />
TO ELEVATING THE STATUS AND IMPORTANCE OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
WITHIN THE FEDERAL SYSTEM, AND ESPECIALLY HAVE THEY BEEN<br />
DIRECTED TO GIVING LOCAL GOVERNMENT ACCESS TO THE RESOURCES<br />
TO DO ITS JOB. WE SHOULD NEVER FORGET THE DISGRACEFUL<br />
WAY LOCAL GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN NEGLECTED AND DOWNGRADED SINCE<br />
THE VERY BEGINNINGS OF OUR FEDERATION, .1/ 3 </p>
<p>THE ø' ZBTS OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND SEMI-GOVERNMENT<br />
AUTHORITIES HAVE MULTIPLIED MORE THAN TWELVE TIMES SINCE<br />
THE WAR, STATE DEBTS SIX TIMES, UP TO LAST YEAR LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES WERE BORROWING MORE EACH YEAR THAN<br />
THE TOTAL AMOUNT OF THEIR OUTSTANDING DEBT OVER 20 YEARS<br />
OR SO AGO, AT THE SAME TIME THERE HAVE BEEN ACCELERATING<br />
DEMANDS QUITE NATURAL AND PREDICTABLE DEMANDS ON<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT SERVICES, YET NOTHING WAS DONE TO<br />
REDRESS THESE DEFICIENCIES; NOTHING WAS DONE TO CORRECT<br />
A SYSTEM THAT ALLOWED THEM TO WORSEN YEAR BY YEAR.<br />
THERE WAS NO SHORTAGE OF EVIDENCE ABOUT THE NEEDS OF<br />
LOCAL GOVERNMENT, THE BARNETT REPORT ON LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
" AREAS AND ADMINISTRATION IN NEW SOUTH WALES REPORTED LAST<br />
YEAR THAT IN THE VIEW OF MOST SHIRE COUNCILS IN NEW SOUTH<br />
WALES " THEIR AREAS COULD NOT SURVIVE WITHOUT A CONTINUANCE<br />
, OF LARGE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT GRANTS AND, WITHOUT EXCEPTION,<br />
COUNCILS BELIEVED THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S INVOLVEMENT<br />
IN FINANCING LOCAL GOVERNMENT WAS ESSENTIAL."<br />
THE RECENT GRANTS COMMISSION RECOMMENDATIONS REFLECT<br />
MY GOVERNMENT'S COMMITMENT TO SUCH NECESSARY ASSISTANCE TO<br />
THAT PART OF GOVERNMENT WHICH IS CLOSEST TO THE PEOPLE,<br />
LET ME REMIND YOU OF HOW THOSE GRANTS CAME ABOUT, ,/ 4 </p>
<p>WYf"! N SIX MONTHS OF LABOR'S ELECTION TO<br />
GOVERNMENT ri DECEMBER 19721 THE AUSTRALIAN PARLIAMENT<br />
PASSED A NEW GRANTS COMMISSION ACT AUTHORISING THAT<br />
BODY TO INQUIRE INTO APPLICATIONS FOR ASSISTANCE BY<br />
REGIONAL ORGANISATIONS OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT. ANY<br />
ASSISTANCE RECOMMENDED BY THE COMMISSION AND APPROVED<br />
BY THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WAS TO BE PAID TO THE STATES<br />
UNDER SECTION 96 OF THE CONSTITUTION ON CONDITION THAT<br />
IT BE PASSED ON TO THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT COUNCILS CONCERNED$<br />
ADDITIONAL MEMBERS WERE APPOINTED TO THE COMMISSION AND<br />
ITS STAFF WAS EXPANDED TO ENABLE IT TO DEAL WITH THIS<br />
LARGE NEW RESPONSIBILITY. FROM NOW ON, THE COMMIS. SION<br />
IS TO PLAY THE SAME ROLE IN REDUCING INEQUALITIES BETWEEN<br />
REGIONS AS IT HAS BETWEEN THE STATES SINCE 19331<br />
LAST MONTH MY GOVERNMENT APPROVED ALLOCATIONS. OF<br />
$ 56,345,000 TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT ORGANISATIONS THROUGHOUT<br />
AUSTRALIA. OF THISI $ 21,359,1000 CAME TO* NEW SOUTH WALES.<br />
WE ACCEPTED THE GRANTS COMMISSION'S RECOMMENDATION THAT NO<br />
CONDITIONS BE ATTACHED TO THE WAY IN WHICH LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
BODIES SPEND THESE, THEIR FIRST ALLOCATIONS UNDER THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN LABOR GOVERNMENT'S NEW SCHEME TO HELP REDUCE<br />
INEQUALITIES BETWEEN REGIONS THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA. THE<br />
SYDNEY WESTERN REGION WILL RECEIVE A TOTAL OF $ 3,380,0004,<br />
OF WHICH PENRITH CITY COUNCIL IS TO GET $ 330,000.' 111/ 5 </p>
<p>A .0ON AS THE GRANTS COMMISSION REPORT WAS<br />
TABLED IN ' E HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, I SENT<br />
TELEGRAMS TO ALL COUNCILS INFORMING THEM CF THEIR<br />
INDIVIDUAL GRANTS, I TRUST THAT THE MAJORITY OF<br />
COUNCILS DERIVED AS MUCH PLEASURE FROM RECEIVING THEM<br />
AS I HAD IN SENDING THEM, IT IS ALWAYS EXHILARATING TO<br />
BE ABLE TO DELIVER THE GOODS, I TRUST YOU WILL ENJOY<br />
THE PROCESS OF TYING UP THE PACKAGE AS YOUR COUNCIL<br />
DELIBERATIONS DICTATE, SINCE WE ATTACHED NO STRINGS<br />
TO OUR LONG-AWAITED PRESENT,<br />
OUR SECOND GREAT INITIATIVE LAST YEARWAS TO SEEK<br />
A VOICE AND A VOTE FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT ON THE LoAN COUNCIL,<br />
OUR PURPOSE WAS, AND STILL IS, TO ADMIT REPRESENTATIVES OF<br />
ALDERMEN AND COUNCILLORS FROM EACH STATE AND ENABLE THE<br />
., COMMONWEALTH, ON REQUEST, TO RAISE APPROVED LOANS RAISED<br />
BY THE COMMONWEALTH ON BEHALF OF THE STATES, I NEED HARDLY<br />
REMIND YOU OF THE RESULTS OF* THAT SPECIAL PREMIERS CONFERENCE<br />
IN OCTOBER LAST YEAR WHICH TURNED OUR PROPOSALS DOWN,<br />
WHEN THE PREMIERS REJECTED THESE PROPOSALS TO BALANCE THE<br />
FUNCTIONS AND FINANCES OF THE THREE TIERS OF GOVERNMENT<br />
TO ENSURE ADEQUATE SERVICES AND DEVELOPMENT OF RESOURCES,<br />
WE HAD NO ALTERNATIVE BUT TO PROCEED WITH A REFERENDUM, </p>
<p>-6-<br />
THAT REFERENDUM WAS CARRIED IN NEW SOUTH WALES,<br />
LARGELY BEC'JASE SO MANY LOCAL GOVERNMENT PEOPLE SUPPORTED<br />
IT IN THE FACE OF STRONG OPPOSITION FROM THE STATE<br />
PREMIER AND THE FEDERAL OPPOSITION PARTIES WHO TRIED TO<br />
SCARE THE PEOPLE AWAY FROM IT. I BELIEVE THAT YOU<br />
SUPPORTED THAT REFERENDUM BECAUSE YOU REALISED WHERE<br />
YOUR HOPE FOR SURVIVAL LAY, THE PEOPLE OF NEW SOUTH WALES<br />
SUPPORTED IT BECAUSE RESPONSIBLE LOCAL GOVERNMENT BODIES<br />
ENCOURAGED THEM TO DO SO.<br />
WHAT OF THE FEAR OF A FEDERAL TAKEOVER OF LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT? IT IS A GHOST WHICH MUST BE LAID TO REST.<br />
FOR MY PART I HAVE NO WISH TO SEE LOCAL GOVERNMENT BECOME<br />
AN APPENDAGE OF THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT ANY MORE THAN I<br />
WANT IT TO REMAIN AN APPENDAGE OF THE STATE GOVERNMENTS.<br />
BUT I DO WANT IT TO HAVE ADEQUATE AND REASONABLE ACCESS<br />
TO THE NATION'S FINANCIAL RESOURCES. IT MUST BE ELEVATED TO<br />
ITS PROPER PLACE IN AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY AND GIVEN THE MEANS<br />
TO CARRY OUT ITS WORK FOR THE LASTING BENEFITS OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE, THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
SHOWN THE WAY. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
