<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1139</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 60/1965 - MALAYSIA AND SINGAPORE - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/08/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001139.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. 1M. No. 6o/ 1965<br />
MALAYSIA AND SINGAPORE<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
Details of the separation arrangements being now<br />
available, Ministers have today been studying the implications<br />
of the establishment of Singapore as a State separate from and<br />
independent of Malaysia.<br />
I feel that I need to say at the outset that no<br />
prior consultation or discussion with the Australian Government<br />
took place. But the separation having occurred, we fully<br />
accept it, and direct ourselves to the future.<br />
The changes that have taken place flow from<br />
considerations of internal political relationships between<br />
Singapore and Kuala Lumpur. It was recognised in the negotiations<br />
preceding the establishment of Malaysia that special<br />
arrangements were necessary for the incorporation of Singapore<br />
in the Federation. The structural changes now agreed upon<br />
reflect an assessment on the part of the parties concerned that<br />
those special arrangements have proved unworkable. We regret<br />
deeply that it was not found possible to make a full success<br />
of the Federation as established in 1963, but at the same time<br />
we are glad that thae new arrangement recognises that the two<br />
entities must continue to work together in close association.<br />
We, for our part, apply ourselves with all goodwill to co-operation<br />
with both Malaysia and Singapore for their future security<br />
and welfare, since we believe? as they do, that this separation<br />
should be regarded as the beginning of a new approach to the<br />
task of working together to forward their common interests.<br />
Various aspects of the separation will require<br />
examination in some detail by the Australian Government and,<br />
no doubt, in some instances, consultation with other Governments,<br />
including the Governments of Singapore and Malaysia will take<br />
pla ce, A central and most important matter is the continued<br />
and combined defence of the region. Malaysia and Singapore face<br />
the same defence problems, and Singapore's facilities are<br />
involved in the defence of both. We welcome the agreement of<br />
the two Governments to establish machirmry for ensuring a<br />
common defence effort. We hope that this will be set up with<br />
speed, and that it will be effective. The particular Australian<br />
association with this common defence will require study in the<br />
light of the new circumstances. But we are determined to play<br />
our part with all the other countries concerned in continuing<br />
a common resistance to attacks upon the Malaysian area, an area<br />
which will still include Singapore, though it is no longer part<br />
of the Federation of Malaysia.<br />
I have today sent messages to the Prime Ministers<br />
of Singapore and Malaysia expressing our satisfaction in that the<br />
new arrangements provide for continued co-operation between the<br />
two States in many fields, including economic affairs as well as<br />
defence. 0000 / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Australian Government has recognised the<br />
State of Singapore and I have informed the Singapore Prime<br />
Minister that we will be happy to establish full diplomatic<br />
relations with Singapore at the level of High Commissioner,<br />
and that we wish Singapore well in its new sovereignty and<br />
look forward to a continuance of close and friendly relations<br />
with the new State and with Malaysia.<br />
CANBERRA August, 1965. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
