<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8848</transcript-id>
    <title>PHILIPPA SMITH TO BE NEW OMBUDSMAN </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/04/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008848.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
T2EL1:. Apr. 93 9: 58 No. 001 P. 01/ 01<br />
4C<br />
PRIME MINISTERI<br />
STATEMENT BY THlE PRIME MIINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
PHILIPPA SMIITHI TO BE NEW OMBUDSMAN<br />
I am pleased to announce that I will he recommending to the Governor-General that<br />
he appoint Ms Philippa Smith to be thc next Cornmonwcalth and Defence Force<br />
Omibudsman. I will propose that Ms Smith's appointment be for 5 years, commencin&amp;<br />
on 17 May 1993.<br />
Ms Smith is the first woman to be appointed as Commonwealth Ombudsman. She<br />
brings to the Office an enormous range of experience in the public and private sector.<br />
Shc has held senior positions in the Australian Council of Social Services, the<br />
Australian Consumers Association and thc NSW Department of Health. At present,<br />
she is a consultant with Issues Australia, where she has worked on complaint<br />
procedures in a varicty of organisahions and also a part-time member of thc<br />
Commonwealth Admiinistrative Appeals Tribunal. Her career has been directed at<br />
ensuring that individual Australians are treated fairly.<br />
I believe that Ms Smith is well-equipped to lead the Ombudsman's Office through the<br />
changes that may occur during the 1990s. Her predecessor, Mr Alan Cameron, was an<br />
important force for change and grcater efficiency in the way the Ombudsman's Office<br />
dealt with its task and the way it was perceivcd by the public and I am confident that<br />
Ms Smith will show the same leadership.<br />
I would also express my appreciation to Ms Lindsay Shaw, who has acted as<br />
Ombudsman following Mfr Camcron's resignation, and to the other staff of the Office<br />
who have ensured that the Office Ms Smith takes over is able to meet the challenges of<br />
the future.<br />
CANBERRA 21 April 1993 TEL: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
