<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23026</transcript-id>
    <title>Attendance at APEC Economic Leaders&#039; Meeting and East Asia Summit</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/10/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Today, I will travel to the APEC Economic Leaders’ Meeting which will take place in Bali, Indonesia.</p>
<p>From October 6-9, I will have a series of bilateral meetings to discuss our regional priorities including trade and investment.</p>
<p>Australia has a long record of engagement at APEC, as a founding member in 1989 and APEC host in 2007.</p>
<p>APEC’s 21 member economies represent 56 per cent of the world’s GDP and $437.8 billion, or over 70 per cent, of Australia’s trade in goods and services.</p>
<p>Economic engagement with our region is a priority for the Government and APEC is the leading regional forum for promoting trade liberalisation and economic integration.</p>
<p>The APEC Leaders’ Meeting will help set the priorities for APEC’s work programme across the coming year.</p>
<p>At the conclusion of APEC’s official programme, I will participate in the Trans-Pacific Partnership (TPP) trade negotiations. Australia is committed to progressing the negotiations as a way of strengthening trade and investment ties in the region to deliver better export opportunities for Australian farmers, manufacturers and service suppliers.</p>
<p>Following the APEC Economic Leaders’ Meeting, I will attend the 8th East Asia Summit (EAS) in Brunei from 9-10 October.</p>
<p>The EAS is an annual gathering of the 10 member countries of ASEAN, plus Australia, China, India, Japan, the Republic of Korea, New Zealand, Russia and the United States.</p>
<p>Together, EAS member countries make up 54.9 per cent of the world’s population and 54.2 per cent of the world’s GDP.</p>
<p>EAS member countries are crucial to Australia’s prosperity: 68 per cent of our total two-way trade is with EAS countries, and nine of Australia’s top ten trading partners are EAS members.</p>
<p>The EAS provides a platform for the region to discuss important security and economic challenges.</p>
<p>6 October 2013</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
