<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>469</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 26/1962 - COMMONWEALTH FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE - GRANTS TO STATES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/02/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000469_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PM. No 26/1962</strong></p>
<p>At the Premiers' Conference today, the Premiers accepted a Commonwealth offer to pay financial assistance grants to the States in the present financial year as follows:</p>
<p>New South Wales œ 99,2499000<br />Victoria 73,01, 000<br />Queensland 43,730,000<br />South Australia ' 3,225,000<br />Western Australia 30,085,000<br />Tasmania _ 12 83 o<br />œ 292,140,000</p>
<p>These grants include special payments to Victoria<br />C1,024,000); Western Australia (œ 339,000) and Tasmania (œ 97,000),<br />These amounts represent the difference between the grants those<br />States expected to receive on the basis of estimates of their<br />population before the census results were known, and the<br />Statistician's official determination of the grants payable for<br />this year on the basis of the census results. The Commonwealth,<br />in offering to make up those amounts this year, took account of<br />the fact that these States had based their Budgets for the current<br />financial year on the estimated, and not the finally determined<br />figureos Under the Statistician's final determination, the other<br />three States receive more than the grants estimated in relation to<br />them at the beginning of the current financial year, as follows<br />New South Wales œ 175,000<br />Queensland œ 1,003,000<br />South Australia 43,000<br />In effect, the Commonwealth's offer was on a " no loss"<br />principle, each State being offered either the full amount of its<br />now entitlement under the cunsus results, or its full expectation<br />under the earlier estimated population figures.<br />The States regarded this offer as eminently fair,<br />As the census result showed that estimates of Victoria's<br />population had been considerably overstated, the application of<br />the Statistician's final determination for 1961-62 to the formula<br />grant for Victoria over the remaining three years of the 1959<br />Agreement would have caused a considerable reduction in the<br />grants payable to that State for those years. It was agreed that,<br />for the purpose of calculating Victoria's grant for the next<br />three years, a new " base amount" of œ 72,730,000 should be<br />adopted. CANBERRA,<br />16th February, 1962.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
