<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3046</transcript-id>
    <title>UNITED NATIONS DAY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/10/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003046.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
11/ 149 24 October 1973<br />
UITI,' D NATIONS DAY<br />
On the occasion of United Nations Day, the Prime Minister<br />
Minister for Foreign Affairs, M,' r Whitlam, re-affirmed Australia's<br />
adherence to the principles and purposes of the UN Charter and the<br />
Importance Australia attaches to the work of the United Nations<br />
Organisation. le recalled that the U11 Charter came into force on<br />
24 October 1945 and on the anniversary of that event it was<br />
appropriate for the individual member countries of the world community<br />
to focus attention on the activities of the United Nations and its<br />
Specialized Agencies.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that for Australia, the United Nations<br />
continued to be the most important international instrument in<br />
man's quest for an international order based on peace and racial<br />
equality, mutual respect and the elimination of poverty and<br />
illiteracy. He emphasised that Australia had all along maintained<br />
that the Security Council should be actively involved in finding<br />
a way out of the tragic struggle in the Middle East.<br />
Mr Whitlam pointed out that some of the most significant<br />
a'chievements of the United Nations had been in the social and<br />
economic fields. He noted in particular that the guiding principles<br />
for United Nations activities 4n these areas ,; ere contained in the<br />
Charter and in such instruments as the Universal Declaration of Human<br />
R-. ghts which has been one of the most enlightened achievements of<br />
the Organisation. On 10 December this year, the United Nations will<br />
celebrate the 25th anniversary of the adoption of the Declaration<br />
ir 1948. Mr Whitlam said the work of the United Nations in these<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
fields had been a source of encouragement for the Australian<br />
Government in the promotion of economic and social justice in our own<br />
society as well as internationally. The Government has an Pctive policy<br />
of giving effect to all relevant international instruments concerned<br />
with the protection and enhancement of human rights.<br />
11I Whitlam said that the UN Charter is aimed at promoting<br />
the dignity and well-being of the ordinary man and woman and is not<br />
an abstract document concerned only with the political interests 0<br />
and objectives of Governments. Australia's part~ icip~ ation in the<br />
United Nations is intended to further our concern that all peoples<br />
should have the right to determine and pursue freely their political,*<br />
social, cultura~ l and economic development.<br />
The Prime Minister noted that this year the United Nations<br />
is emphasizing international development and that today has also<br />
been designated as World Development Informiation day. Hie said that<br />
this was an appropriate time to assess Australia's commitment to<br />
the development goals of the United Nntions.<br />
Mr Whitlam recalled that the Government intended to expand<br />
present assistance programs in Asia, Africa and the Pacific, and<br />
to work towards an official aid target of 0.7 per cent of gross0<br />
domestic product by the nd of the present decade, in keeping with<br />
the principal aim of the International Strategy for the Second<br />
Development Decade. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
