<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1612</transcript-id>
    <title>SYDNEY, N.S.W - PRESS, RADIO AND TELEVISION CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT ON HIS RETURN  22ND JUNE, 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/06/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001612.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VISIT TO US, CAN ADA UK SYDNEY, N S. V,;<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT ON HIS RETURN 22nd JUNE, 1967<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't propose to make a lengthy comment this morning<br />
because there will be opportunities in the next few days to deal with<br />
particular matters and for the same reason, I don't propose to discuss<br />
domestic issues which have developed while I have been away. Again, I<br />
shall, no doubt, comment -on some of these as we go along. But I would<br />
like to give a general comment about what has been a most concentrat-ed<br />
journey overseas. I don't think any Australian Prime Minister could have<br />
been treated with more regard, more concern given to his views and I have<br />
had the most remarkable reception, wherever I have gone, from each Head<br />
of Government I have spoken to. I think it is a mark of Australia's growing<br />
international stature and the place we occupy in this area of the world<br />
a significant place that we should have so much consideration given to our<br />
views as was shown to me by the Heads of all the Governments I visited on<br />
this occasion. It is not easy for me at this point of time to give you a<br />
great deal of detail about the results of the journey. I have no doubt myself<br />
that it has been a very valuable and fruitful journey, but some of the most<br />
important matters I had to discuss are still the subject of consideration by<br />
the Governments concerned In respect of British dispositions East of Suez,<br />
for example, as you will know, there are to be talks with Prime Minister<br />
Lee Kuan Yew and Prime Minister Tunku Abdul Rahman and we can't<br />
expect any definite United Kingdom statement until those have been completed<br />
and Cabinet has been able to consider in the United Kingdom all the views<br />
which have been put to us by representatives of the Commonwealth countries<br />
concerned, and indeed by the United States which has a very lively interest<br />
in this matter also. But it is my anticipation that they will be indicating<br />
their general attitude on these matters before the end of next month.<br />
I do feel, however, that the views we were able to put<br />
which I left behind in rather more precise form by way of a letter to Prime<br />
Minister V~' lson have been received with every consideration and I am<br />
confident myself although only a later formal decision will confirm this<br />
that the United Kingdom will maintain a continuing role in that area of the<br />
world. just what form this will take remains to be determined by them, but<br />
I feel confident that they do not intend to turn their backs on an area of the<br />
world which to us and I believe in the long term to them will have such<br />
great significance. In my talks in the United States with the President on a<br />
number of trade and financial matters, we made, I believe, very good<br />
progress, although here again the outcome has yet to be resolved in final<br />
terms. I am bringing some proposals b ack to the Cabinet for consideration,<br />
and there will be consideration given by various Departments of the United<br />
States to the views we have put on a number of matters. This can be stated<br />
quite emphatically: That in the President himself Australia has a staunch<br />
friend who brings a sympathetic outlook to the problems that we place before / 2 </p>
<p>him. I am sure that it would be his wish that the Administration does what<br />
it can within its political and administrative limits to assist Australia in<br />
the problems we have raised with him.<br />
Some of the results of a journey such as this will later be<br />
expressed in tangible form. Perhaps some of the no less important<br />
consequences are of an intangible kind and I refer in particular to the very<br />
warm and friendly discussions I had in Canada with Frime Minister Lester<br />
Pearson. I believe we laid together, both privately and in our public<br />
statements, a foundation there for a growing Australian/ Canadian co-operation<br />
in relation to international questions generally and in particular to the<br />
growing interest I think we will be finding in Canada in what occurs around<br />
the Pacific basin. That country has, for most of its history, been oriented<br />
to the North Atlantic or to North America, but British Columbia, fcr<br />
example, is very conscious of the opportunities which are developing across<br />
the Pacific and I feel confident that, increasingly, the Canadian Government<br />
as a whole and the Canadian people will find a growing interest and display<br />
an increasing activity in this area of the world.<br />
There were, of course, a multitude of other discussions, and the<br />
programme was, I repeat, a very concentrated one. In the countries<br />
visited, I made, as you may recall, a number of speeches which I think could<br />
be classed as significant speeches, in United States, making Australia's<br />
views known; the World Affairs Council in Los Angeles, the Foreign Affairs<br />
Council, the Far East America Council, the American / Aistralian<br />
Association, the Pilgrims Society, " Meet the Press'%. This is a very widelyviewed<br />
programme in the United States and produced a very good reaction<br />
from all the accounts which reached me. So in these ways, Australia's views<br />
were placed before a wide audience throughout the United States.<br />
In the United Kingdom, we had talks with Senior Cab inet<br />
Ministers concerned with our problems, and again in America, not only<br />
were the trade matters under discussion but Viet Nam, the crisis in the<br />
Middle East, the British troop dispositions East of Suez and a variety of<br />
other matters occupi el our attention. Even the concluding function of<br />
yesterday, in Honolulu the formation there of an A merican/ Australian<br />
Association was not without some % lue for us. It has been launched by<br />
the leading figures in the life of Hawaii, which plays a useful role as a<br />
geographical bridge between Australia and the mainland of the United States, of<br />
which country it now forms, of course, a part. And when I learned that<br />
some 800, CO Americans visit Hawaii each year from the mainland, and we<br />
only get something like 20, 00CC of them down here, there is clearly scope<br />
for co-operation in matters such as tourism and other matters which are<br />
of mutual interest to us in our affairs in the Pacific region.<br />
On both visits there, I had valuable talks there with Admiral<br />
Sharp the Commander-in-Chief of the Pacific Command, and after a very<br />
good briefing on my way through, he was able to refresh me on developments<br />
in military activities as I came through this time.<br />
I am very glad to be back home, even to experience a little cool<br />
weather again after a spate of summer days wherever we have gone, and I<br />
come back confident of Australia's place in the world, and a growing<br />
prosperity which I think is assured from the great interest shown towards<br />
us in so many quarters through which I passed on my way. And it is good<br />
to be back again in the country which still seems to me to be the best<br />
country one can find on earth. / 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
MR. EGGLETON VWill you take a few questions please Prime Mi4nister?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
Q. Mr. Holt, was there any request by President Johnson for<br />
Australia to increase its commitment in Vietnam?<br />
PM: Well, if I answer that question by " no comment", you read<br />
something into it. If I say there wasn't, you read into that that he was<br />
indifferent as to whether we have more people there or not. I will say<br />
explicitly this matter was not raised with me, but I am not implying from<br />
that an indifference as to whether there should be an increase in Australian<br />
forces. But the President is well aware that we review our situation from<br />
time to time. Usually we study the Defence Vote at Budget time, The<br />
changing position in relation to S1ingapore and Malaysia is, of course, new<br />
element in our calculations. But I don't want to give any impression that we<br />
are under pressure on this matter or that others are indifferent as to what<br />
we do about it.<br />
Q. Indifference on whose part, Sir, yours or President Johnson' s?<br />
PM: VWell, we are not indifferent, of course, to what we do in<br />
relation to Vietnam, but what is recognised is Australia is now providing<br />
close to 5 per cent. of its gross national product for the Defence Vote, that<br />
we have commitments and obligations in various other areas and the<br />
proportion of our people who are there in a fighting capacity ( because we<br />
dont' have the same logistics component' is higher than the mere figures<br />
would suggest.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, you showed an acute awareness of the<br />
crisis for the world of the Middle East trouble by suggesting that Australia<br />
would take some of the Arab refugees. I would like you to amplify your<br />
statements regarding this and also to tell us of your concern.<br />
Q. W-ell a great deal of emphasis appeared to be given out here<br />
to this particular aspect, but of course Australia's interest in peace in the<br />
Middle East goes far beyond that particular point. One element in the Middle<br />
East problem is the number of refugees Arab refugees which have not<br />
been satisfactorily dealt with for a considerable time, and I am afraid they<br />
become the pawn of Middle East politics. Clearly there has to be a solution<br />
of this problem and what I was indicating was an Australian willingness to<br />
play a part in company with other members of the United Nations if there<br />
would be value in their settlement around the world, or where they did choose<br />
to settle, in some financial assistance to enable them to settle in the place<br />
of their choice. I have been interested to note that in the " Financial Times"<br />
which I read only last night on the plane, Mr. Pearson in Canada has made<br />
almost precisely the same suggestion, talking about Canada taking its share<br />
of those who might wish to settle there, or else providing some financial<br />
assistance to contribute towards a solution of the problem.<br />
Q. hen do you expect to hear from President Johnson on the<br />
wool tariff? Wle have only got until June 30th<br />
PM: Vliell, there have been some proposals on this which I have<br />
to take to my own Cabinet first. Whether or not these will prove acceptable<br />
to us remains to be seen, but we are conscious that there is a time factor. / 4 </p>
<p>PM ( Contd)<br />
I think it is not necessarily bound to that date. This is the impression we<br />
gained in our discussion with them. The matter was capable of being dealt<br />
with separately but it would be, I thinkc, to everyone's advantage 4f we could<br />
get some decision on the matter quite speedily.<br />
Q. Do you expect to get anything before June<br />
PM: Well, I can't be precise because I don't know now just how<br />
long it will take our own people to weigh the c wunter -proposal which is<br />
being put to us. It relates to tobacco and this may take a little study<br />
before we can get a firm reply to them on this particular matter.<br />
C: Sir, can you give us any details of Britain's defence plans<br />
East of Suez?<br />
FM: No, I have made it quite clear that final decisions will not be<br />
taken on these matters, certainly until there have been talks with the other<br />
two Prime Ministers, . Mr Lee is in London at this moment. I understand<br />
that Tunku Abdul Rahman will be there next month. But in the House of<br />
Commons, if my recollection is correct, Mr. Grossman, replying to a<br />
question, said they expected to give an answer before the end of July.<br />
Q. just going back to the Middle East crisis, Sir, your statement<br />
. that the Middle East affair was at one stage " huffing and puffing" came<br />
in for some criticism. K'ere you quoted out of context or could this now be<br />
construed as an error of judgment?<br />
PM: Well, where did I make the statement? This is the question<br />
I think is fair to ask.<br />
Q. In the United States a few days before<br />
PM: V/ here, though, will you tell me?<br />
Q. I am afraid you are testing my memory<br />
FM: You are testing my statement. In point of fact no such<br />
statement was ever made by me publicly and certainly not ma-: de in context<br />
but Tony Eggleton in good faith, with his usu al capable care of what i s<br />
said at these background briefings, referring to the situation between the<br />
two major powers who clearly did not want to come to a clash themselves<br />
on this matter, and having heard me comment along those lines at an earlier<br />
point of time, did use this phrase in his press briefing. Now, I am not<br />
critical of Tony for that, but we do rely on the good sense of the pressmen<br />
who are getting the press briefing not to try to make in shorthand terms an<br />
over -complicated situation out of what I think was clearly known to be the<br />
intention of the statement. Once you have the tinder-like situation which had<br />
developed as between the Arabs and the Israelis, then no-one could predict<br />
with certainty what would come out as between those two. But we were<br />
confident in our own minds that neither the United States nor the Russians<br />
wanted this to develop into a Big Fower conflict.<br />
Q. Getting back to the troops in Vietnam, Sir. Reading between<br />
the lines, I suspect you think there might be a need for us to send more troops<br />
to Malaya and Singapore? </p>
<p>PM: Vieli, we are not making decisiorson this matter at this point<br />
of time. The M-ister for Defence is still overseas. We have our Budget<br />
provision for Defence yet to be considered. Australia does what it can<br />
within its capacity from time to time, and I don't want to be pressed on it.<br />
Q. Mr. Frme Minister, the world spotlight is of course on<br />
New York at the moment. You have just come from the United States and<br />
we know you share the concern of President Johnson and also Mr. Iilson<br />
Wie notice today that the British Government has suggested that Israel should<br />
withdraw from Jordanian territory. How do you feel about this and what do<br />
you think the prospects are of a lasting settlement?<br />
PM: Yes, well, I don't propose to make any off-the-cuff<br />
statement on this. My own colleague will have been kept more closely<br />
in touch with the developments and views of other Governments. I will be<br />
talking this over with him, no doubt, quite early when I get to ' Canberra, but<br />
I am not making a detailed statement on Middle East policy at this point of<br />
time.<br />
MR. EGGLETON: Sir, you have an aircraft wIting to take you to % C,: nberra.<br />
Perhaps just one more question if there is anyone with a pressing one you<br />
want to raise<br />
Q. In a lighter vein, Mr. Prime Minister, did you actually lose<br />
your pants while swimming? ( Laughter<br />
PM: W~ ell, you know, the last time I came back, one of the<br />
cartoonists had a statement about the President and myself having a frank<br />
exchange of poems. I suppose this time it could be said we had a frank<br />
exchange of films. ' lie didn't have an exchange of pants, but my luggage not<br />
having arrived, and the day being veay hot and lunch about to be served<br />
around the pool, I mentioned a little wistfully how much I would like a swim.<br />
The President very kindly made these trunks available. I am not implying that<br />
he is a stouter man than I am he's a very much taller man, and what would<br />
sit quite gracefully on his figure was a little ample for mine. Having dived<br />
off the board it is a fact they couldn't stand the impact as well as tb'ey might<br />
have. I don't think any harm was done as I was managing to keep underwater<br />
at the time and I was able to restore the situation without too much<br />
em barrassment. In Honolulu at the dinner after the wind-up of the<br />
A mcrican/ Auntral-an Association function, they presented me with a-pair<br />
about this big ( indicating tiny size). I am hoping they will fit the<br />
grandson. They said if I could ever get into them I would never fall out of<br />
them. ( Laughter"<br />
MR. EGGLETON Thank you, gentlemen. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
