<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>58</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS RELEASE - COMMONWEALTH EDUCATION CONFERENCE OXFORD, ENGLAND - 15-29TH JULY 1959 - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/03/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000058.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS RELEASE<br />
NOT TO BE RELEASED BEFORE 3AM<br />
WEDNESDAY 25TH MARCH<br />
COMMONW'EALTH EDUCATION CONFERENCE<br />
OXFORD, ENGLAND 15TH-29TH JULY,<br />
( STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER)<br />
The United Kingdom Government released the following<br />
statement this morning<br />
" All the Governments of ti-, e Common-wealth have now<br />
accepted an invitation from the United Kingdom Government<br />
to attend a Commonwealth Education Conference in Oxford.<br />
from the 15th to 29th July. The principal Colonial<br />
territories will also send representatives. Delegations<br />
will be composed of officials and representatives of<br />
educational interests including the universities.<br />
Lord Halifax Chancellor of the University of Oxford<br />
will be President of the Conference and Sir Philip Morris<br />
Vice-Chancellor of Bristol Univei-sity will be Chairman.<br />
The United Kingdom Government have invited delegates<br />
to spend the week before the Conference visiting educational<br />
establishments in the United Kingdom. They will be guests<br />
of the United Kingdom Government for the whole period of<br />
three weeks.<br />
This Conference stems from a decision of the Commonwealth<br />
Ministers at the Commonwealth Tr., tde and Economic<br />
Conference held at Montreal in September 1958 that a meeting<br />
should be convened by the United K0ingdom during 1959 to<br />
formulate a new programme of Commonwealth Scholarships and<br />
Fellowships and to review the existing arrangements for cooperation<br />
between Commonwealth countries on all aspects of<br />
education.<br />
Prime Minister's Comment:<br />
Mr. Menzies, in commenting on this announcement, confirmed<br />
that Australia has accepted the invitation of the United Kingdom<br />
Government to send a delegation to the Education Conference in Oxford<br />
next July. He added that the composition of the delegation is now<br />
being discussed with State Premiers and various interested<br />
authorities. </p>
<p>rI STRICT EMBARGO. Not for publication, broadcasting or cabling<br />
Defore f~ rn AW~ eme. nntse. aSs, T2a. hy, M . r h2,59h9 Mrch,, 159, NO. 9 / 195 9<br />
CABINET DISCUSSION ON PARLIAMENTARY SALARIES REPORT<br />
STATEMENT BY THlE PRIME MINISTER<br />
Ministers have today considered and discussed the<br />
report on salaries and allowances of Members of the Commonwealth<br />
Parliament made by Sir Frank Richardson, Mr. G. E. Fitzgerald<br />
and Mr. N. L. Cowper.<br />
After an elaborate discussion, we have decided to adopt<br />
the recommendations of the report without amendment, and will<br />
introduce legislation accordingly.<br />
As we are anxious that the Report should be care fully<br />
considered as a whole, since it provides a great deal of important<br />
material I do not propose to make any long comment upon it.<br />
I say this because I hope that everybody interested will obtain<br />
a full copy of the Report and study it. But four particular<br />
matters deserve mention:<br />
1, There is sometimes a complaint that Members of Parliament<br />
" fix their own pay". The fact is that they are bound to<br />
do so under the Constitution which provides Parliamentary<br />
Allowances on a certain scale " until the Parliament<br />
otherwise provides". As the Committee says: " It was,<br />
therefore, clearly contemplated that the remuneration<br />
of Members could be altered from time to time, and it<br />
was laid down that any alteration should be made by<br />
Parliament itself".,<br />
My own Government has introduced, for the third<br />
time now, the practice of referring the problem for<br />
independent advice by an outside committee, making its<br />
report after investigation from Parliamentary and non-<br />
Parliamentary sources.<br />
2. We have stated our policy that a review of these matters<br />
should be made early in the life of each new Parliament<br />
and that, subject only to quite abnormal circumstances, the<br />
conditions then determined should apply unchanged<br />
throughout the life of the Parliament. This, we believe,<br />
is a sensible provision.<br />
3. The 1951 Committee covered the whole field, including<br />
the salaries and allowances of Ministers. The 1955<br />
Committee was specifically asked not to deal with the<br />
salaries and allowances of Ministers, or of Parliamentary<br />
office-bearers, or of retiring allowances. The position<br />
is, therefore, that these matters have remained untouched<br />
and unconsidered for over 7 years.<br />
4e. In view of constant misrepresentation, I should again<br />
point out that the so-called " allowances" paid to<br />
Ministers and private Members do not form in the ordinary<br />
acceptation of the term, part of their salary. They<br />
represent amounts which, if paid out by way of political<br />
expenses, are then deductable. Nobody dreams of adding<br />
to the salary of some business executive the amount of<br />
expenses which he incurs in the business of his company.<br />
Yet it has not been uncommon to find some commentators<br />
adding to the salary of a Minister or Member an allowance<br />
for political expenses which represents no nett gain to<br />
himself. This is a matter which I urge people to keep<br />
in mind when considering this important document. </p>
<p>t<br />
.1 0 0 </p>
<p>2.<br />
The RePort sets out in close detail the nature of<br />
the expenditure of a non-private kind which a Member of<br />
Parliament is bound under modern circumstances to incur. I<br />
would, therefore, urge that the closest attention should be given<br />
to the reasoning of the Report. I am sure that, if it is<br />
carefully considered, the general public feeling would be that<br />
what has been recommended pays proper attention to the labours<br />
and responsibilities of Members of Parliament and their wives,<br />
and will help to give effect to the Committee's view that, while<br />
the emoluments of Members of Parliament should not be<br />
extravagant they should be of such a kind as not to deter able<br />
men from entering the Parliamentary service of the nation.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T.<br />
24th March, 1959. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
