<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4955</transcript-id>
    <title>INDO-CHINA CONFLICT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/02/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004955_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 18 FEBRUARY, 1979<br />
INDO-CHINA CONFLICT_<br />
Cabinet met today in special session to receive a<br />
report and briefing from the Defence Committee on events<br />
in Indo China. The Defence Committee met earlier today to<br />
consider the matter.<br />
The Australian Government views with real concern the<br />
incursion of Chinese armed forces into Vietnam. This<br />
situation has arisen out of the earlier Vietnamese<br />
invasion of KamLpuchea, and has developed to the stage where<br />
armed* conflict has now erupted between China and Vietnam.<br />
I recall that on the 13th February, my colleague the<br />
Foreign Minister, Mr. Peacock, drew attention to the fact<br />
that some time ago the Government had identified this<br />
deteriorating and potentially dangerous situation. As<br />
a result the Government ha õ been in close touch with<br />
other Governments which might be able to bring influence<br />
to bear on the situation.<br />
The most recent development in Indo China adds to our<br />
earlier concern and to that of the world community.<br />
The Australian Government calls on Vietnam to withdraw<br />
its forces from Kampuchea and on China to withdraw its<br />
forces from Vietnam.<br />
The Australian Government has already asked the USSR,<br />
both in Moscow and through its Ambassador in Canberra,<br />
to use its special relationship with Vietnam to bring<br />
about a cease fire and withdrawal of Vietnamese forces<br />
from Kampuchea.<br />
The Government cannot accept the use of force for the<br />
settlement of disputes, whatever their cause. The Government<br />
has noted the approaches in the past few days to the United<br />
Nations Security Council by both the Chinese and Vietnamese<br />
Governments the one for the withdrawal of Vietnamese forces<br />
from Kampuchea and the other for the withdrawal of Chinese<br />
forces from Vietnam. It has also noted that both sides have<br />
said they are ready to enter into negotiations for a peaceful<br />
settlement. It is our earnest hope that these opportunities<br />
to bring a halt to the fighting and to settle the matter<br />
peacefully will not be lost. </p>
<p>2<br />
Should the question come before the Security Council<br />
again, Australia, although not a member of the Council,<br />
would seek to participate actively in its deliberations.<br />
The maintenance of peace and stability in the region is of<br />
great and fundamental importance to Australia. Our concerns<br />
are widely shared and we are continuing to keep in close<br />
touch with other Governments. In particular, the Government<br />
is expressing its serious concern to the parties most<br />
directly involved, and is calling again upon them to seek<br />
an immediate halt to the conflict.<br />
The Government will continue to keep this matter<br />
under close review as the situation evolves in the<br />
coming days.<br />
I also propose to ask the Office of National Assessment to<br />
give a full briefing on the situation to the Leader of<br />
the Opposition, the Deputy Leader of the Opposition and<br />
the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
