<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7745</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, SHERATON HOTEL, PERTH, 19 SEPTEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/09/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007745.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4 IA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, SHERATON HOTEL, PERTH, 19<br />
SEPTEMBER 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, John Halfpenny's been very critical<br />
today of you bringing in the military to help sort out the<br />
civil aviation<br />
PM: Well I didn't have any doubts before this that I was<br />
right and if Mr Halfpenny's criticised me, that just<br />
reassures me that I'm right.<br />
JOURNALIST: He says though that your bad handling of the<br />
situation has deliberately worsened the dispute.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just let me make it clear that I have never<br />
taken any notice of John Halfpenny. I've never regarded John<br />
Halfpenny as someone who has any significance at all in these<br />
matters. Now you can quote John Halfpenny as long as you<br />
like if it satisfies you. It is a matter to me of supreme<br />
indifference if I should perhaps just amend that I repeat<br />
what I said at the beginning. If John Halfpenny is coming in<br />
against the Government and in any sense giving comfort to the<br />
pilots, that totally reconfirms our position in this matter,<br />
yes. JOURNALIST: What about the pilots advertisement this morning<br />
calling on you to back off. Will you back off?<br />
PM: Now what I'm saying a bout the advertisement that here is<br />
the Federation which in February of this year in its<br />
publications to its members said to them, ' prepare for the<br />
great battle in which we're going to shut down the industry'.<br />
These are the people who are now expressing their concern for<br />
the tourist industry, for the people on school holidays.<br />
They deliberately set about shutting down the airline<br />
industry in which they said they were going to take on their<br />
industry, the Government, the Arbitration Commission and<br />
everyone else. Now I have said from the beginning on behalf<br />
of the Government and the people of Australia, you are not<br />
going to take on the rest of Australia and win. If you are<br />
going do something which is different from all other workers<br />
and say that you'll have special treatment, then you're<br />
wrong. You're not going to do it. We are not going to<br />
destroy-a system in Australia which has created over one and </p>
<p>( PH cant) a half million Jobs, which has exercised wage<br />
restraint, which has seen a growth in profits, which has<br />
allowed investment, which has allowed jobs. All that's not<br />
going to be destroyed by the pilots and f or them to now be<br />
saying ' back of they've got their facts wrong. They ought<br />
to read their compass. I hope when they're in the the<br />
cockpit, they read their compasses better than they're<br />
reading the compass in this matter. They've just got it back<br />
to front.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you've also put your own credibility<br />
on the line. Have you painted yourself into a corner on<br />
this? Have you become obsessed with it?<br />
PM: Do I either look as though I'm painted into a corner and<br />
I feel obsessed? I'm simply doing what any Prime Minister<br />
must do and that is when the security of this country is<br />
threatened, to stand up and say those who will threaten the<br />
security of the country are not going to win. Now I've<br />
simply said in answer to a question when I was asked was my<br />
credibility on the line, I said yes. I said it is if as<br />
Prime Minister I'm not prepared to stand up f or the security<br />
and economic welfare of this country, I wouldn't deserve to<br />
be Prime Minister. Now that's quite straight forward. The<br />
fact is that this Federation will not be allowed to destroy<br />
the Australian economy.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, do you believe the Government's now<br />
on the way to winning this dispute?<br />
PM: Well there is no doubt that the Federation would never,<br />
never win it. I mean it's never going to be allowed to win<br />
it. So I've put it in that way. I don't talk in terms of<br />
victory for myself or for the Govenruent. I don't want to<br />
talk in terms of victory. The only rial entity whose<br />
interests are involved here is the Australian nation, the<br />
national interest, and that is going to win.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, there was a suggestion by a Melbourne<br />
industrial relations lawyer today, Anthony Mackin, that the<br />
coming ACTU Congress at the end of the month may herald a<br />
little more division in the union movement about this<br />
dispute. Are you concerned, particularly in the wake of what<br />
Mr Halfpenny said that you're going to hear more objections<br />
from the union movement about<br />
PM: but I've said what I've got to say about Mr<br />
Halfpenny. It comes down to a question of Bill Kelty and<br />
John Halfpenny. I'll tell you who to have your money on.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, there have been calls today for a<br />
national summit or a Premiers' Conference about this dispute.<br />
Will you consider any of those options? </p>
<p>PM: Of course I wouldn't. We have a system in this country<br />
through the Industrial Relations Commission and the<br />
guidelines which is there for everyone else. Everyone else<br />
abides by it and under their restraint that they've exercised<br />
under it, where they've processed their claims through that<br />
system, the rest of the country has prospered. We are not<br />
going to be setting up some special arrangments for who? For<br />
pilots? For pilots who've, as we've said, are averaging<br />
$ 80,000 a year for an average 8 hours flying, and they think<br />
that where everyone else will work according to these<br />
arrangements that we're going to rush around having national<br />
summits, Premiers' Conferences, special mediators, for these<br />
people-who are getting $ 80,000 a year for 8 hours flying? I<br />
mean you must be joking and they must be joking if they still<br />
think that that sort of thing's going to happen. The<br />
situation is that by their action they have resigned, they<br />
have resigned their employment. They are no longer as a<br />
result of their own action employed by Australian and<br />
Ansett. So what Ansett and Australian are doing is filling<br />
those vacancies in the ranks created by the pilots'<br />
resignation. That process is going ahead, it will go ahead<br />
and the national airline system will be restored.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you out to destroy the Pilots Federation?<br />
PM: Certainly not only not out to destroy any federation,<br />
they seem to be out to destroy themselves because there's a<br />
very strange sort of situation in an industrial position. If<br />
you instruct your members to resign, which they've done, and<br />
therefore you have no members employed by Ansett and<br />
Australian, and then flap around all over the place saying,<br />
' we want to negotiate', when you've got no members there<br />
employed, it's very strange. But the important thing is<br />
this; that the two airlines, in the situation created by the<br />
Federation, are now seeking to fill those ranks by recruiting<br />
people. Now it's my very strong view that when they have<br />
succeeded in doing that, that they should then have an<br />
organisation whether it's the Federation, whether they want<br />
to be in that or whether they want to form another union<br />
that that would be for the employees of Ansett and<br />
Australian. But it's very important, I think, that they<br />
should have an organisation, have a union. So it's the<br />
Federation which has destroyed itself by taking its members<br />
out. They've no longer any members employed there so the two<br />
airlines are filling the positions where there were<br />
previously Federation members. But certainly it's my<br />
position and that of the Government that when that is<br />
concluded there must be an organisation there.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you concerned about our safety record at<br />
all, Mr Hawke? The air traffic controllers have suggested<br />
that with a lot of foreign pilots, people new to the job,<br />
that Australia's safety record is </p>
<p>PM: We have a Civil Aviation Authority which has a statutory<br />
responsibility to look after the safety standards of this<br />
country. They will discharge their statutory responsibility.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, can I change the subject for<br />
seconds. The current account deficit's been tipped at above<br />
the $ 2B mark to come out on Thursday. What's your tip?<br />
PM: I have no tip.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would today's any comment re today's project<br />
on that figure?<br />
PH: Well I think the important thing about today's project<br />
the North West Shelf is as I said in my speech, that a<br />
significant part of the current account deficit figures that<br />
have been accumulating over the months is the bringing in to<br />
O Australia of equipment which is going to establish projects<br />
like the North West Shelf and we'll see that now coming onto<br />
stream and building up to bringing into Australia $ 2B or more<br />
in export income. Now as we look to the future therefore we<br />
can have great confidence that much of the deficit that we've<br />
been accumulating is as we've been saying, restructuring<br />
Australian industry, Australian manufacturing industry,<br />
building up more projects like the North West Shelf.<br />
Australia has got a very, very significant, prosperous<br />
future. We go through a period now where we can't be<br />
complacent about the level of imports and we must restrain<br />
demand to some extent. But in the long term what we're<br />
seeing happening and what we're participating in is a<br />
restructuring of the Australian industry, the development of<br />
our resources which is going to make our external position<br />
very strong in to the future.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you got a tip for the League grand final,<br />
Prime minister?<br />
PM: Well I've got to publish that later, I think. I think<br />
the newspaper which has my-tipping rights has got an<br />
exclusive on that. That's a bit later in the week.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, can I ask you about the capital<br />
creation for Qantas and Australian Airlines. There's been<br />
talk about non-preference shares, about partial<br />
privatisation. What's your own favoured option for raising<br />
capital for Qantas and<br />
PM: I haven't got a favoured option. This is something<br />
that's been looked at by a committee of the Party. We'll<br />
look at it in Government. I am not publicly discussing what<br />
my view about this is. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the specific wording of the pilots<br />
adtoday that you should butt out. Do you find that offensive<br />
at all?<br />
PM: No. I mean I've been in public life for 30 years and<br />
I've probably said a few offensive if I can remember I have<br />
to think hard, I may have in the course of 30 years said<br />
something slightly offensive. No, I don't get upset by those<br />
things. The only thing that really upsets me about the whole<br />
thing is the temerity of this Federation which set about,<br />
deliberately set about the destruction of the industry. I<br />
mean this is in their own writing, in their own publication,<br />
' we're going to close down the industry, we're going to have<br />
the great battle against everyone'. Now when they've done<br />
that to have the temerity to talk about their concern for<br />
others, I mean I find that hypocrisy galling. But the fact<br />
is that the Australian airline industry is going to be<br />
restored. There will be a full restoration of the industry.<br />
The only question is now is to whether these pilots, the<br />
members of the Federation, want to be part of that<br />
restoration or not. It's up to them, individually.<br />
ends<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
