<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18814</transcript-id>
    <title>Intervention - High-Level Political Launch of &#039;Education First&#039; Initiative</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>New York City, USA</p>
<p>It's a great honour to be champion of Secretary-General Ban's Education First Initiative.</p>
<p>This is a very significant tribute to Australia's work to improve education in developing countries through our aid program.</p>
<p>There's a reason universal education is second only to ending hunger in the Millennium Development Goals.</p>
<p>In my discussions with the Secretary-General, I've told him that for my country, improving education is a great national priority  -  one we want to share with our neighbours and partners in the world.</p>
<p>And for me personally, education is the great passion that brought me into public life, and I want to share the story with you today.</p>
<p>Recently my beloved father passed away.</p>
<p>He was a bright boy who grew up in a family of seven in a Welsh coalmining village.</p>
<p>His family knew great hardship and even though my father won a scholarship, he had to go to work at 14 to help put bread on the table.</p>
<p>He died at 83 but his lifelong dream of a higher education was never fulfilled.</p>
<p>My sense of injustice has never dimmed, and I am deeply saddened that John Gillard's story is a story lived out in homes and villages all across the world today  -  especially in the global south.</p>
<p>Bright kids who don't have a chance parents who send their children off to work knowing it's not the best thing for the future.</p>
<p>As members of the international community, we can help end that.</p>
<p>Education is vital to prosperity for nations and to opportunity for individuals it is the ultimate means of a civilised life for every person.</p>
<p>I am delighted to join my fellow Education Champions who are determined to put education first.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
