<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6692</transcript-id>
    <title>LAUNCHING BY PRIME MINISTER OF &#039;WHEN THE LUCK RUNS OUT&#039;, SYDNEY, 13 AUGUST 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/08/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006692.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
LAUNCHING BY PRIME MINISTER OF<br />
" WHEN THE LUCK RUNS OUTO<br />
SYDNEY 13 AUGUST 1985<br />
It is my pleasure today to launch Fred Hilmer's book<br />
" When the Luck Runs Out The Future for Australians at<br />
Work. It enables me not only to congratulate Fred on a<br />
stimulating book, but also to make some relevant points<br />
about the task of management in this country.<br />
The crucial role in the industrial, economic and social<br />
affairs of our nation played by labor relations is<br />
widely recognised and since March 1983 it has been a<br />
generally positive one. In the words of the recent OECD<br />
Report, the Government's Accord with the trade union<br />
movement in this country has been " remarkably<br />
successful", and " a major source of stability in<br />
industrial relations".<br />
You will be well aware that the Government has had<br />
considerable success in achieving strong growth with a<br />
third year of 5 per cent growth in prospect and creating<br />
more than 400,000 new jobs since it assumed office. Our<br />
continuing commitment to these objectives will be<br />
paramount in the approach that we as a Government take<br />
towards wages policy in the coming months. This is the<br />
very least that we owe to those currently or<br />
prospectively unemployed which includes many of our<br />
young people.<br />
At the same time the Government is very much aware, as I<br />
am sure are the business community and the general<br />
public, of the substantial contribution made by the<br />
Accord to improved industrial relations in this country.<br />
Fred Hilmer's book gives me an opportunity to make this<br />
point succinctly.<br />
It is quite correct, as he states, that the Pilbara<br />
region was for a long time a source of discontent and of<br />
problems for both State and Federal Governments, and<br />
adversely affected our standing as a minerals exporter.<br />
Fred's book says and I quote from it that: </p>
<p>" The Pilbara has a bad record of strikes and<br />
stoppages even by the worst standard of Australian<br />
industrial relations, and the effect of this record<br />
is disastrous."<br />
While that was undoubtedly true of the past, the book<br />
stops short of the Pilbara's recent experience which<br />
is quite different from the history recited in " When the<br />
Luck Runs Out".<br />
The Government responded to the Pilbara's problems with<br />
the establishment a year ago of the Western Australian<br />
Iron Ore Industry Consultative Council, which includes<br />
the Western Australian Government, the unions in the<br />
Pilbara, the companies, and the Federal Government. The<br />
Council has provided a forum for all sides to talk over<br />
their problems.<br />
There have been two significant results working days<br />
lost through industrial disputes have dropped and<br />
production has risen, both dramatically.<br />
The Pilbara's improved performance demonstrates that<br />
with co-operative rather than confrontational industrial<br />
relations, Australia can be a reliable supplier to the<br />
world, and that we can capitalise on our tremendous<br />
resources.<br />
What it further demonstrates is that the Government's<br />
policy of working co-operatively with the trade union<br />
movement an approach for which we are sometimes<br />
irrationally criticised can have benefits for all<br />
sections of our community and I have noted and applaud<br />
the recent observation by one of our political opponents<br />
that " union-bashing is no substitute for policy".<br />
Indeed, I would contend that the Government's good<br />
working relations with the trade union movement through<br />
the Accord are a major reason behind Australia's<br />
impressive list of economic achievements since March,<br />
1983. And I note in this regard Fred Hilmer's<br />
observation that unionism is no barrier to growth, as<br />
demonstrated by the fact that a number of small European<br />
countries with strong unions have consistently<br />
outperformed the Australian economy in recent years.<br />
There is no point, however, in denying that " When the<br />
Luck Runs Out" poses some tough challenges for us all<br />
governments, unions, business, and the Australian<br />
public. The book for example, suggests that:<br />
" Australians appear to be caught in a downward<br />
spiral. Individuals don't add the value they could<br />
at work. Their organisations in turn don't create<br />
wealth for the community, and the economy declines<br />
slowly and steadily relative to other economies<br />
overseas" </p>
<p>I would argue that this process is now being gradually<br />
reversed, but as a judgment on attitudes towards work in<br />
this country it is far from flattering.<br />
In his book Fred Hilmer identifies the contrasting<br />
factors in determining the industrial environments in<br />
Australia as " conscript mindset", and " volunteer<br />
mindset". The first he sees as a hangover from the days of penal<br />
settlements, of forced labor. The work attitude was<br />
negative. Workers and employers viewed each other as<br />
adversaries.<br />
The latter describes an opposite attitude, when<br />
individual's approaches to their work, as influenced by<br />
conditions, employee involvement and managerial<br />
attitudes, combine to stimulate an innovative, creative<br />
and more satisfied workforce.<br />
" When the Luck Runs Out" argues, not surprisingly, that<br />
the latter approach is the more productive and that it<br />
is not only in the best interests of individual<br />
companies, but more generally of our nation, through<br />
increased national wealth and job creation.<br />
So how can this result best be achieved? Fred Hilmer<br />
suggests that the key lies in management. It is up to<br />
management in his view to encourage these positive<br />
attitudes the " volunteer mindset" that makes the<br />
workplace more satisfying and productive for all<br />
employees. Six conditions necessary in the work environment to<br />
nurture a " volunteer mindset" are put forward:<br />
A trusting environment.<br />
Widespread experimenting in work, rather than<br />
being stifled by rules.<br />
A driving purpose with goals to which<br />
people can relate.<br />
A positive approach focussing on achievement<br />
rather than penalties.<br />
Real jobs where individuals have the<br />
opportunity to add value; and<br />
A network of teams rather than a rigid<br />
hierarchy or a loose collection of people.<br />
Many of the themes running through this book parallel<br />
those that the Federal Government has been mindful </p>
<p>4.<br />
of in its approach to reform of the Commonwealth Public<br />
Service. Management reforms, including opening up the<br />
executive ranks of the public service to candidates from<br />
the private sector, and focussing on results rather than<br />
simply processes, are aimed very much at this goal.<br />
As a Government we are concerned to achieve the greatest<br />
efficiency for the resources which we believe must be<br />
applied to particular public sector activities. We<br />
recognise legitimate community concerns about the size<br />
and cost of Government.<br />
But we also accept that as a Government we are not only<br />
obligated to provide a range of services to the<br />
community, but indeed that they are essential to<br />
achieving the equity objectives to which we attach such<br />
importance. And on this point we part company from our<br />
political opponents, who approach this issue with<br />
ideological fervour with their unequivocal commitment to<br />
privatisation. " When the Luck Runs Out" is a valuable contribution to<br />
knowledge about sensible management in our country. I<br />
commend Fred Hilmer for his work. I wish it well. I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
