<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21643</transcript-id>
    <title>Message from the Prime Minister The Hon John Howard MP Commonwealth Day</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/03/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Commonwealth Day is an opportunity to celebrate Australia's membership of the Commonwealth Family of Nations.  Today we reflect on the importance of our shared values, our commitment to peace and democracy, the protection of human rights, and our determination to work together with our fellow members around the world.</p>
<p>  This year in particular the Commonwealth embraces the crucial role of education in enhancing the potential for all people to contribute to the sustainable development of society and economy.  Australia, through the Commonwealth Fund for Technical Cooperation, helps member countries strengthen governance and improve the quality of life of their citizens.</p>
<p> Our thoughts this Commonwealth Day must turn also in sympathy and support to member states affected by the terrible devastation of the Indian Ocean tsunami. We are seeking to do all that we can to assist them in their reconstruction and rehabilitation efforts.</p>
<p>On a brighter note, a further activity that brings our nations close together every four years is the Commonwealth Games. I am pleased today to welcome the commencement of the Queen's Baton Relay at Buckingham Palace, which will pass across 71 Commonwealth destinations before arriving at the Opening Ceremony of the Melbourne Commonwealth Games in March next year. Australia looks forward to hosting this event.</p>
<p> This Commonwealth Day we are proud to renew Australia's commitment to the Commonwealth and celebrate our shared heritage and values.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
