<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2258</transcript-id>
    <title>NEWS INTERVIEW ON CHANNEL 7 NETWORK GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON - 17 JULY 1970 - INTERVIEWER: JOHN BOLAND</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/07/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002258.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO 30 p. m. Friday _ L7 Luly 1970<br />
NEWS INPrERVIEW CN CHANNEL Z7 NETWORK<br />
GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JC NKG1Oj RTON 17 JULY 1970<br />
Interviewer John Boland<br />
Q. Prime Minister, will police troops be used to clear the 1, 000 Tolai<br />
Mataungan Association squatters from the Kerevat area twenty-five miles from<br />
Rabaul?<br />
P M I hadn't heard that there were 1, 000 squatters there-, but I don't think the<br />
actual number matters very much. It fluctuated, I thought, between 100 and 400.<br />
And the actual use of police to clear the area would be a decision taken by the<br />
man on the spot, the Administrator. But I have little doubt at all that if this is<br />
the only way in which to clear people who are illegally occupying lands, then the<br />
police will be used to clear them from those lands. You must remember, this is<br />
land which was bought by the Administration for subdivision and allocation to<br />
Tolai through a Lands Board Tolai and Bainings, the local people and it is<br />
being illegally moved into by squatters. ShoLld this become necessary, this use<br />
of police, then we would certainly back up the Administrator in whatever was<br />
necessary to see that the land is allocated to the peo-ple for whom it was bought.<br />
Q. I underst", nd the reports this morning say that 700 additional Tolai moved<br />
in there there were 300 there. Now, that was a repot......<br />
PM: Well, however many it is they will have to get off.<br />
Q. Who ordered the 1, 000 police into Rabaul? Report.-are that Mr. Barnes<br />
said he received advice from the New Guinea Executive Council and reports are<br />
that the Executive Council of New Guinea says that they did not advise the sending<br />
in of extra police.<br />
PM: I think this is a misunderstanding that stems from your proper use of the<br />
word " reports". All the information I have is that Mr. Barnes said that he had had<br />
two meetings with the Administrator's Executive Council and at both those*<br />
meetings, the Administrator's Executive Council had strongly urged that law and<br />
order saould be supported. Well, that got transmuted and translated by certain<br />
journalists into the Administrator's Executive Council ask.-ed that police should be<br />
sent which was quite a different matter more definite matter than saying<br />
we want law and order supported. And that having been re73orted, then some<br />
Members of the Administrator's Executive Council said, " Wiell, we didn't<br />
specifically ask for police to be sent in" and that is quite right to the best of my<br />
knowledge. What they said was " We want law and order maintained". / 2 </p>
<p>Q. But there are about 1,000 police there?<br />
PM: Oh yes, but a lot went there before I arrived because I don't think the<br />
Mataungan leaders make any secret of their willingness to resort to force, and<br />
there were fears of clashes between the Mataungan Tolai and the anti-<br />
Mataungan Tolai.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, we are looking forward to having you and talking to you<br />
in depth about your tour of New Guinea, on Channel 7' s current affairs<br />
prog-amme, " This Week", on Sunday night.<br />
BACKGROUND: The interview with the Prime Minister about New Guinea will be<br />
telecast by HSV 7 Melbourne at 9. 50 p. m. on Sunday, and by C. T. C. 7 in<br />
Canberra at 10. 30 the same evening.<br />
Copies of the transcript, embargoed until 9. 50, will be issued in the<br />
Gallery on Sunday afternoon. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
