<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3336</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, AT THE OPENING OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA HOUSE, SYDNEY, FRIDAY 26 JULY 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/07/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003336.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM,<br />
AT THE-OPENING OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA HOUSE,<br />
SYDNEY,-FRIDAY 26 JULY 1974<br />
THIS IS AN IMPORTANT DAY IN THE HISTORY OF<br />
BOTH OUR COUNTRIES IMPORTANT IN SUBSTANCE, IMPORTANT<br />
IN SYMBOLISM. THE BUILDING ITSELF, ITS LOCATION<br />
IN AUSTRALIA'S OLDEST, GREATEST CITY, EXPRESSES THE<br />
CHANGING NATURE OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA'S RELATIONS WITH<br />
AUSTRALIA AND THE REGION IN WHICH WE ARE NEIGHBOURS<br />
AND PARTNERS. Now PAPUA NEW GUINEA WILL HAVE<br />
ITS OWN OFFICES IN AUSTRALIA'S INDUSTRIAL AND<br />
COMMERCIAL HEART AS WELL AS THE COMMISSION IN THE<br />
NATIONAL CAPITAL, PAPUA NEW GUINEA ALREADY IS<br />
REPRESENTED IN INDONESIA AND IS SHOR~ TLY TO ESTABLISH<br />
COMMISSIONS IN NEW ZEALAND AND FIJI. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
THESE MOVES ARE PART OF THE RAPID<br />
ASSUMPTION OF INDEPENDENT STATUS BY A VIRTUALLY<br />
INDEPENDENT NATION, BY THE BREAKING OF THIS SPEAR<br />
AND BY MY ACCEPTANICE OF HALF OF IT WE SYMBOLISE THE<br />
WAY IN WHICH THE RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN PAPUA NEW GUINEA<br />
AND AUSTRALIA IS CHANGING SWIFTLY YET DEVELOPING<br />
IN A SPIRIT OF MUTUAL TRUST AND CLOSE FRIENDSHIP.<br />
IN ACCEPTING HALF OF THIS SPEAR, I AGAIN REASSERT<br />
AND REAFFIRM AUSTRALIA'S ABSOLUTE WILLINGNESS TO<br />
CONTINUE TO CO-OPERATE CLOSELY WITH A UNITED<br />
PAPUA NEW GUINEA IN THE FULFILMENT OF ITS HOPES<br />
FOR A UNIT'D, PROUD AND FREE NATION,<br />
THE BREAKING SYMBOLISES A BREAK FROM THE<br />
OLD DEPENDENCE; MY ACCEPTANCE OF ONE OF ITS HALVES<br />
ON BEHALF OF AUSTRALIA FROM THE CHIEF MINISTER ON<br />
BEHALF OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA SYMBOLISES THE CONTINUITY<br />
OF OUR CO-OPERATION, OUR TRUST AND GOODWILL BETWEEN<br />
THE CHIEF MINISTER AND ME, BUT MORE IMPORTANT,<br />
MORE ENDURING, BETWEEN PAPUA NEW GUINEA AND AUSTRALIA. </p>
<p>TO THOSE OF US WHO HAVE CLOSELY WATCHED<br />
THE UNFOLDING OF EVENTS IN PAPUA NEW GUINEA IN THE<br />
WHAT HAS OCCURRED, WHAT HAS BEEN ACHIEVED,<br />
SEEMS LITTLE SHORT OF MIRACULOUS. IT IS BARELY<br />
THREE AND A HALF YEARS AGO SINCE I FORESHADOWED<br />
IN PORT MORESBY THE POLICY FOR INDEPENDENCE<br />
WHICH WOULD BE ADOPTED BY A LABOR GOVERNMENT IF<br />
WE WERE RETURNED AT THE 1972 ELECTIONS.<br />
WE ALL REMEMBER THE EXTRAORDINARY SHOCKWAVES<br />
WHICH THAT ANNOUNCEMENT GENERATED,-BOTH IN PAPUA<br />
NEW GUINEA AND AUSTRALIA, YET EVENTS HAVE MADE<br />
MY SUGGESTED TIMETABLE APPEAR IN RETROSPECT,<br />
MODEST AND MODERATE, INDEED, WE HAVE HAD A<br />
CLASSIC ILLUSTRATION OF THE POWER OF AN IDEA WHOSE<br />
TIME HAD COME. THE FORCES FOR INDEPENDENCE ALREADY<br />
EXISTED; THEY NEEDED ONLY EXPRESSION TO SPRING<br />
INTO VIGOROUS LIFE, </p>
<p>I~<br />
AT THAT TIME I WORKED FROM ONE BASIC<br />
ASSUMPTION, IT WAS THIS: THAT PAPUA NEq GUINEA<br />
WAS ALREADY PROVIDING, FROM HER OWN RESOURCES,<br />
MORE SKILLED MEN AND WOMEN THAN AUSTRALIA WOULD<br />
BE ABLE OR WILLING TO MAKE AVAILABLE FOR PAPUA<br />
NEW GUINEA PURPOSES FROM HER RESOURCES,<br />
SO IT HAS PROVED, IT IS THIS FACT WHICH PROVIDES<br />
THE BASIS FOR PAPUA NEW GUINEA'S INDEPENDENCE,<br />
WHAT COULD HARDLY HAVE BEEN FORESEEN IN 1970 WAS THE<br />
SPEED WITH WHICH EFFECTIVE POLITICAL PARTIES WOULD<br />
EMERGE IN THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY, THIS NEW FACT<br />
HAS PROVIDED THE FIRM BASIS FOR THE AMAZINGLY<br />
RAPID ASSUMPTION OF THE SUBSTANCE OF INDEPENDENCE,<br />
IF NOT ALL THE FORMS, IN THE LAST THREE YEARS.<br />
ABOVE ALL WE COULD NOT HAVE RECKONED ON<br />
BEING SO FORTUNATE IN THE CHOICE AND STATURE OF<br />
THE LEADERSHIP WHICH HAS EMERGED, AT A CRUCIAL TIME<br />
IN HER HISTORY, PAPUA NEW GUINEA HAS FOUND LEADERSHIP<br />
OF THE HIGHEST QUALITY AND INrEGRITY, A LEADERSHIP<br />
WHICH HAS ALREADY WON RESPECT THROUGHOUT THE REGION, </p>
<p>So SUCCESSFUL HAS THE TRANSITION BEEN THAT<br />
NEITHER THE GOVERNMENT OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA NOR OF<br />
AUSTRALIA NEED ANY LONGER FEEL UNDULY PREOCCUPIED<br />
WITH THE FORMALITIES OF INDEPENDENCE, IN ALL BUT<br />
FORMALITY, PAPUA NEW GUINEA IS INDEPENDENT,<br />
LET ME REPEAT THE WORDS OF THE GOVERNOR-GENERAL IN<br />
HIS SPEECH OPENING THE PARLIAMENT:<br />
" MY GOVERNMENT IS COMMITTED BY THE CLEAREST<br />
PLEDGES TO CONTINUE SUBSTANTIAL AID TO A<br />
UNITED PAPUA NEW GUINEA BEFORE AND AFTER<br />
INDEPENDENCE, SINCE PAPUA NEW GUINEA<br />
ACHIEVED SELF-GOVERNMENT IN DECEMBER 1973,<br />
THE RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENTS OF<br />
AUSTRALIA AND OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA HAS BEEN<br />
BASED ON THE PRINCIPLES OF EQUALITY, MUTUAL<br />
RESPECT AND MUTUAL CO-OPERATION, PENDING<br />
THE FINAL DECISION OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY<br />
TO DECLARE INDEPENDENCE FOR PAPUA NEW GUINEA,<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WILL CONDUCT ITS<br />
RELATIONS WITH THE GOVERNMENT OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA<br />
AS A GOVERNMENT OF AN INDEPENDENT NATION TO<br />
WHICH. AUSTRALIA HAS CERTAIN SPECIAL AND<br />
INESCAPABLE OBLIGATIONS," </p>
<p>-0-<br />
IN OTHER WORDS, THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY<br />
AND THE GOVERNMENT OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA WILL MAKE<br />
ITS OWN DECISION AS TO THE ACTUAL DATE OF INDEPENDENCE<br />
WHILE FOR ITS PARTI THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
WILL DEAL WITH THE GOVERNMENT OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA<br />
AS THE GOVERNMENT OF AN ALREADY INDEPENDENT COUNTRY,<br />
BEFORE INDEPENDENCE AND AFTER INDEPENDENCE,<br />
ALL AUSTRALIAN AID WILL BE DIRECTED THROUGH THE<br />
GOVERNMENT OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA, IT WILL BE DIRECTED<br />
TOWARDS THE GOALS AND PRIORITIES SET BY THE GOVERNMENT<br />
OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA, AUSTRALIAN AID WILL NOT<br />
INVOLVE INTERFERENCE IN THE PREPARATION OF PAPUA<br />
NEW GUINEA'S IMPROVEMENT PROGRAMS AND ANNUAL BUDGETS,<br />
THESE ARE AND WILL CONTINUE TO BE THE RESPONSIBILITY<br />
OF THE GOVERNMENT OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA,<br />
THE PROGRESS BEING MADE BY PAPUA NEW GUINEA,<br />
OF WHICH THIS BUILDING IS ONE OF THE EXTERNAL SIGNS,<br />
GIVES GROUND FOR THE HIGHEST OPTIMISM, YEI WE SHOULD<br />
NOT SEEK TO UNDERESTIMATE THE DIFFICULTIES IN THE<br />
PATH ON WHICH WE HAVE ALL EMBARKED, THE EFFORT TO<br />
BUILD A UNITED DEMOCRACY AT ANY TIME IS ONE OF THE<br />
GREATEST CHALLENGES STATESMANSHIP CAN EVER FACE; AND<br />
THESE ARE NOT ORDINARY TIMES: THEY ARE NOT EASY TIMES,<br />
DEMOCRACY EVERYWHERE IS UNDERGOING GREAT STRESSES<br />
AND GREAT CHALLENGES, </p>
<p>-7-<br />
EVEN THE VERY OLDEST AND GREATEST DEMOCRACIES<br />
ARE NOT EXEMPT FROM TURMOIL AND TRAVAIL. PAPUA<br />
NEW GUINEA IS DEVELOPING A CONSTITUTION FOR A<br />
NEW AND INDEPENDENT NATION. IT WILL DEVELOP THAT<br />
CONSTITUTION IN ITS OWN WAY, IN ITS OWN TIME.<br />
IT WILL COMBINE FOREIGN PRECEDENTS WITH ITS OWN<br />
TRADITIONS, THERE IS SOMETHING HOWEVER FAR MORE<br />
IMPORTANT TO DEMOCRACY THAN THE LETTER OF A CONSTITUTION,<br />
IT IS THE SPIRIT IN WHICH THAT CONSTITUTION IS<br />
APPLIED BY THE ELECTED MEN AND WOMEN WHO HAVE THE<br />
RESPONSIBILITY OF OPERATING IT. IT IS NOT ONLY<br />
WRITTEN RULES WHICH MAKE A DEMOCRACY STRONG; THE<br />
UNWRITTEN RULES ARE JUST AS IMPORTANT.<br />
IT IS ALL TOO EASY TO SUBVERT DEMOCRACY BY PERFECTLY<br />
LEGAL AND CONSTITUTIONAL MEANS IF THE WILL TO ABIDE<br />
BY THE UNWRITTEN RULES IS ABSENT. No NATION,*<br />
NOT EVEN AUSTRALIA ITSELF, IS EXEMPT FROM THE DANGERS<br />
WHICH FOLLOW A BREAK( DOWN IN THE ACCEPTANCE OF THlE<br />
UNWRITTEN RULES. THIS IS A MEASURE OF THE CHALLENGE<br />
FACING PAPUA NEW GUINEA. WE ALL RECOGNISE THE<br />
DIFFICULTIES, YET AGAIN IT MUST BE SAID THAT THE<br />
REMARKABLE PROGRESS OF THE LAST THREE YEARS GIVES<br />
THE BEST GROUNDS FOR CONFIDENCE THAT THEY WILL BE<br />
TRIUMPHANTLY OVERCOME.<br />
MAY THIS BUILDING BE A SYMBOL OF THE<br />
NEW MATURITY OF OUR PARTNERSHIP AS TWO FREE DEMOCRATIC<br />
INDEPENDENT PARTNERS. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
