<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10337</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP OFFICIAL OPENING OF SCALABRINI VILLAGE AUSTRALIA, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/05/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010337.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I11 May 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
OFFICIAL OPENING OF SCALABRINI VILLAGE<br />
AUSTRAL, SYDNEY<br />
E E O<br />
Thank you very much George, to the Deputy Premier of NSW, Andrew Refshuage, to<br />
my colleague, John Fahey, the Minister for Finance and also the Federal Member for<br />
this area, to Craig Knowles, to my other parliamentary colleagues, to the Fathers<br />
Provincial and most particularly my friend, His Excellency the Ambassador to the<br />
Republic of Italy in Australia, to Father Nevio who is synonymous with the Scalabrini<br />
Village, you can't talk about the Scalabrini Village without talking about Father Nevio<br />
and to all the other distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen.<br />
I remember very well when I came here in October of 1987. 1 came as Opposition<br />
Leader. I did say that if I ever became Prime Minister, and I've got to say in<br />
October 1987 1 thought it was a little distant, if I ever did become Prime Minister that I<br />
would return and I am very happy to be back here today. And I'm also very happy to<br />
recall some of the things that I said in October of 1987 and to say to all of you that<br />
what those words meant then meant just as much some, almost 10 years later. And the<br />
most important thing that I think I said in October of 1987 was that of the enormous<br />
gifts and benefits that the Italian people have brought to Australia, none was stronger,<br />
none was greater and none ought to be more cherished than the commitment of Italian<br />
people to the care and nurture of their family members, especially the elderly members<br />
of their families.<br />
It has been one of the great symbols of the contribution that Italian people have made<br />
to Australian life, particularly since the end of the Second World War. And their<br />
demonstration of that care and commitment is an object lesson to other sections of the<br />
Australian community and that was true 10 years ago and it remains true today and I'm<br />
sure that when one of my successors comes back here in 10 or 15 or 20 years time that<br />
he or she will be able to say exactly the same thing. He or she will be able to say that<br />
the demonstration of care and nurture within the family by Australians of Italian<br />
descent and Italian background is an object lesson to all of the rest of the Australian<br />
community. Ladies and gentlemen today is an occasion for me, on behalf of the Federal<br />
Government to honour the particular contribution of the Scalabrini Village, of the<br />
movement that is throughout the world committed itself to the care of the aged. It is </p>
<p>of course as people grow old that they are able to spend their years in retirement in<br />
touch with their cultural roots as well as in touch with the members of their family. I<br />
remember a conversation I had with Sir James Gobbo, now the Governor of Victoria<br />
and certainly one of the greatest of all Australians of Italian descent saying to me in a<br />
chat we were having about cultural issues, he said there is nothing more incongruous<br />
he said than the notion of an elderly lady of Italian descent who spent the first 40 years<br />
of her life in Italy being encouraged to sing the Road to Gundagai around the piano in<br />
a nursing home. And of course he put it well, there is nothing wrong with the Road to<br />
Gundagai, it's a terrific song and I know that a lot of Australians of Italian descent can<br />
sing it as well as other Australians, but the truth simply is that as you get older you<br />
reach out more and you need the support and the comfort and the familiarity of your<br />
cultural roots and your cultural background.<br />
That is why the Scalabrini Village is so important. It is why another organisation that I<br />
have association with within my own electorate, The Sir Moses Montefiori Jewish<br />
Home is so very important to Australians of Jewish belief It is important that people<br />
feel that comfort and ease in the culture which is their first culture and their first<br />
understanding and therefore it is a very, very strong commitment of my government to<br />
maintain as part of its approach to aged care policy, a respect for, and a promotion of<br />
villages and complexes which have a particular cultural identification.<br />
As Carl Melvey mentioned, and in saying that I was to particularly salute the<br />
impressive contribution that Carl Melvey has made to the Village. The great<br />
contribution that he has made to the community life of the Italian people in Sydney and<br />
also the very impressive contribution that Carl has made in his general professional and<br />
business life and I think you are indeed lucky to have a person of that business and<br />
commercial acumen to give you so much advice and to have had that counsel for so<br />
long and so persistently and in such a loyal fashion.<br />
We have ladies and gentlemen, as Carl mentioned, we have at a Federal level made<br />
some changes about the funding of nursing homes and I want to take the opportunity<br />
of saying to you today very directly that those new funding arrangements, once they<br />
are up and running, will tackle head on the problem that has been developing over a<br />
long period of time of how on a fair and equitable basis, whilst protecting the people<br />
who can't afford to make a contribution and our scheme will protect those people it<br />
will protect those people fully how you can get some more capital into the nursing<br />
home area. And as a result of those changes I can confidently predict that over the<br />
next few years a much larger amount of money, we calculate about $ 130 million over a<br />
four year period, will be injected in a much needed way into the nursing home structure<br />
of Australia because they have over the years those nursing homes they have become<br />
starved of capital. And no government, whether it is Labor or Liberal, State or Federal<br />
has unlimited resources to provide for exercises of that kind of what we have done<br />
whilst protecting people who can't afford to make a contribution we'll introduce a<br />
system that over the next four years you are going to see the injection of a much<br />
needed sum of about $ 130 million into the capital needs of nursing homes and I think<br />
when those reforms are up and running and when the finance and the equity and the<br />
protection they involve for the under-privileged is recognised and understood they will<br />
be seen as a very far-sighted, a very courageous and a very, very necessary structural<br />
reform. But most importantly we'll get more money into nursing homes in Australia </p>
<p>Ends 3<br />
and that is, with an aging population, an absolutely essential policy objective of any<br />
government. Can I finally say ladies and gentlemen that the retired people in Australian have been a<br />
very important goal, have been a very, very important element of the policies of my<br />
government over the last 13 months. I'm very proud that the commitments we made<br />
in relation to the taxation treatment of self-funded retirees were introduced in the last<br />
budget. I am very happy to say that many retired people will benefit from the tax<br />
incentives of private health insurance that will come into operation on the first of July.<br />
And I think in a number of ways the retired community of Australia will find Tuesday<br />
night's Budget a very, very welcome Budget. It will be a good Budget for retired<br />
people in Australia and most importantly of all over the last few years we have been<br />
able to achieve in Australia and I don't know that it started immediately on the second<br />
of March 1996 but certainly we have built on it and made it a little better and we have<br />
been able to achieve a very low level of inflation. And there is nothing that destroys<br />
the stability and the savings of elderly retired people in any community than high rates<br />
of inflation. And although some of the retired people may not welcome the slightly<br />
lower interest rates that have come with lower inflation certainly over a long period of<br />
time price stability is enormously important to the retired people.<br />
So ladies and gentlemen can I say to all of you in a very personal way I'm very, very<br />
happy to be back here. I love mixing with and coming to functions involving the<br />
Italian community in Australia. It's an opportunity for me on behalf of the rest of the<br />
Australian community to salute the enormous and unselfish generous contribution that<br />
Italian people have made to Australia. Italians comprise the largest group of<br />
immigrants to this country with a non-English speaking background. They have<br />
penetrated and reached and achieved in every area of Australian life, whether it's the<br />
professions, it's business, it's politics but most importantly of all they have in every<br />
area of Australian life made as individuals and as families and as part of the community<br />
they have made an enormous contribution and an ongoing contribution to the tolerant<br />
open, diverse and very cosmopolitan Australian society which we now have.<br />
I say on behalf of all the Australians of non-Australian descent, thank you. Thank you<br />
from all of us for the contribution that you have made. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
