<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9440</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP REPORT OF THE CIVICS EXPERT GROUP</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/12/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009440.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
REPORT OF THE CIVICS EXPERT GROUP<br />
It is my pleasure to announce that I have today received the report of the<br />
Civics Expert Group.<br />
The Report is appropriately entitled Whereas the people which is the<br />
opening phrase of our Constitution and declares the popular basis of our<br />
national government. Yet there is a sting in the tail of this title, as it reminds<br />
us how few people in the general community or even in this place would know<br />
the source and importance of these words.<br />
The Commonwealth established the Civics Expert Group in June 1994 to<br />
prepare a strategic plan for a non-partisan program of public education and<br />
information on the Australian system of government, the Australian<br />
Constitution, Australian citizenship and other civics issues.<br />
The Group is Chaired by Professor Stuart Macintyre, the Ernest Scott<br />
Professor of History in the University of Melbourne. The other members of<br />
the Group are Dr Ken Boston, the Director-General of the New South Wales<br />
Department of School Education, and Ms Susan Pascoe of the Catholic<br />
Education Office in Melbourne.<br />
The report reflects considerable credit on them all. They have completed<br />
their task with considerable style and thoroughness. It is obvious that a great<br />
deal of careful thought has gone into the report's recommendations, and that<br />
the Group has genuinely come to grips with the difficult subject of educating<br />
Australians about our system of government.<br />
The Report sets out a program to help Australians participate more fully and<br />
effectively in the civic life of our nation. It reflects the wide program of<br />
consultation undertaken by the Group, which met with State governors;<br />
representatives of State and Territory governments; leaders of federal<br />
political parties; Australia's government and non-government education </p>
<p>sectors; community groups and interested bodies in the field such as the<br />
Constitutional Centenary Foundation and the Parliamentary Education Office.<br />
I endorse the view of the Group that an active and informed citizenship<br />
should be " the mortar that holds together the bricks of our contemporary,<br />
multicultural Australia". For this, Australians need a better knowledge of how<br />
our government works, they need skills to become involved effectively, and<br />
they need an appreciation of the benefits of active citizenship.<br />
Education is the key. As part of its inquiries, the Group drew on a national<br />
survey of community understanding of civics issues. The findings of that<br />
survey, which are detailed in the Report, indicate widespread ignorance and<br />
misunderstanding about the structure and function of Australia's system of<br />
government, about its origins, and about the ways it can serve the needs of<br />
citizens. The ignorance is not just of matters of detail, it goes to a basic lack<br />
of understanding of the system and the principles on which it is founded.<br />
This reflects a fundamental failing in our education system which the<br />
Government is determined to address.<br />
The remedy is to build an active and informed community through our<br />
education system. The Group has put the view that education for citizenship<br />
is an essential component of a liberal education and should rank with English<br />
and mathematics as a priority for school education. I agree that it has been<br />
neglected for far too long. To feel confidence in our future, to be active<br />
participants in our national life, to feel pride in our democratic and inclusive<br />
society, people must understand our democratic institutions and have a<br />
sense of their history and the ideals on which they are based. To participate<br />
fully and effectively to be good citizens, in other words they must<br />
understand both the role of those institutions and the way they can become<br />
active participants in our civic life.<br />
This will require cooperative action by Australian governments. The<br />
Commonwealth government recognises that Commonwealth financial support<br />
would assist the State and Territory education authorities to implement<br />
proposals along the lines recommended. The nature and extent of the<br />
Commonwealth's support will be considered following consultations with the<br />
States and Territories.<br />
The Group has recommended that its report be made available for public<br />
comment and discussion for three months. I am happy to agree and would<br />
welcome comments on the report and its implementation by the end of<br />
February 1995.<br />
7 December 1994<br />
CANBERRA </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
