<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9557</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP - OPENING OF THE GLOBAL CULTURAL DIVERSITY CONFERENCE, SYDNEY CONVENTION AND EXHIBITION CENTRE, WEDNESDAY, 26 APRIL 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/04/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009557.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP OPENING<br />
OF THE GLOBAL CULTURAL DIVERSITY CONFERENCE, SYDNEY<br />
CONVENTION AND EXHIBITION CENTRE, WEDNESDAY, 26 APRIL 1995<br />
Your excellency, Dr Boutros Boutros-Ghali, distinguished speakers, ladies<br />
and gentlemen.<br />
It is my pleasure to welcome you to Australia, to Sydney and the 1995<br />
Global Cultural Diversity Conference.<br />
On behalf of Bob Carr, the Premier of New South Wales, and Sir James<br />
Gobbo, Chairman of the Australian Multicultural Foundation, who are cohosting<br />
this conference with the Australian Government we welcome your<br />
participation in discussions of great importance and we hope, in time, of<br />
great consequence.<br />
We are very privileged to have with us so many eminent speakers from all<br />
over the world. I thank you most sincerely for coming.<br />
Mr Secretary General, it is a particular pleasure and an honour to welcome<br />
you on your first visit to Australia, especially in this year in which we are<br />
commemorating the 50th anniversary of the founding of the United Nations.<br />
1995 has also been designated as the International Year for Tolerance and<br />
the first Decade for the World's Indigenous People.<br />
We are also pleased to welcome Dr Federico Mayor, Director-General of<br />
UNESCO, which celebrates its 50th anniversary in 1995 as well, and the<br />
Deputy President of South Africa, Mr Thabo Mbeki.<br />
The conference has brought together knowledgeable and concerned<br />
individuals to consider the ways by which we might make cultural diversity<br />
less of an impediment to human progress and more of a means to it. Less<br />
of a source of conflict, and more of a means by which the benefits of<br />
tolerance can be learned or re-learned. Less of a violent and destructive<br />
force, less of a vehicle for xenophobia and prejudice, and more of a means<br />
to creating a more peaceful, creative and secure post-Cold War World.<br />
In short we sen it as a contribution to the effort to make the 21st century a<br />
better one than this. </p>
<p>This conference was conceived as a means of marking all these milestones.<br />
And, I might say, Australia is an appropriate place to mark them.<br />
We are a country looking forward to the next century. We believe we have<br />
a constructive role to play in those issues which concern the United<br />
Nations. We have always believed that we were present and active at its<br />
inception in San Francisco but we have never believed it more than now.<br />
And we are nothing if not culturally diverse: more than 220 nationalities are<br />
represented in our population. Forty two per cent of our people were born<br />
overseas or have one parent born overseas.<br />
Australian society is rich in linguistic, racial, religious and cultural diversity.<br />
We have consciously devised policies to encourage and preserve this<br />
diversity and gain in return benefits to the nation and community.<br />
We count the creation of this rich, pluralistic and peaceful society we think<br />
one of the most successful multicultural societies in the world as one of<br />
our great national achievements.<br />
That is why I say that Sydney is an appropriate environment for this Global<br />
Cultural Diversity Conference.<br />
Not because we presume to think that Australia can be a model for the rest<br />
of the world the world is itself too diverse for that. But we have learned<br />
some useful things about living together, we have a deep interest in these<br />
questions and we think we can make a contribution in a world which<br />
desperately needs answers to them.<br />
Fifty years ago in San Francisco, a group of delegates, including Dr H V<br />
Evatt from Australia, met to design the United Nations. They hoped that the<br />
institution they were creating would ensure that the wars which had already<br />
ravaged the world twice in just thirty years would never be repeated.<br />
They wanted to construct a framework for a world in which international<br />
stability was based on common values of justice, development and peace.<br />
But in 1946 the lessons of the failed League of Nations were still fresh in<br />
everyone's minds and the consequences of that failure appallingly real. So<br />
there was a strong streak of realism as well as idealism in the blueprint the<br />
delegates drew up in San Francisco.<br />
They knew the United Nations needed to take into account the realities of<br />
global power. And they understood the importance of the nation-state. </p>
<p>The role of the nation-state was already cemented at the centre of<br />
international affairs, and its importance was to grow even larger as the great<br />
process of decofonisation got under way.<br />
Not surprisingly, therefore, the framework the architects of the United<br />
Nations developed had at its core the need to settle, or at least contain,<br />
conflicts between nation-states.<br />
In the event, as we know, the post-war reality fell short of the high hopes<br />
of San Francisco. The emergence of the Cold War and a bipolar<br />
international system imposed a very different dynamic on United Nations<br />
operations. Still, despite the complications and set-backs of the following half century,<br />
the United Nations managed to notch up substantial achievements. Not<br />
enough of them, no doubt, but many more than some of its critics allow.<br />
But fifty years on, the Cold War is over and there has never been a better<br />
time to ask ourselves if the United Nations we now bia-u is what we now<br />
need. And what we will need in the 21st century.<br />
Given the scale of change in the world since the organisation was formed, it<br />
would be astonishing if the answer was yes.<br />
Many distinguished figures, not least yourself, Secretary-General, have been<br />
engaged in juJst this task of renewal.<br />
Australia, through Gareth Evans especially, has been playing a role in this<br />
debate, as we did in Sani Francisco half a century ago.<br />
I do not want to explore these important structural questions this morning.<br />
There are many other forums at which that will be done.<br />
But I do want to draw the link between what we are talking about at this<br />
conference and these wider United Nations issues.<br />
Because cultural diversity, which we in Australia value as a source of<br />
strength and pride, has an external dimension, too.<br />
And the manifestations of cultural diversity we see on the television news<br />
more often seem to take the form of tragic and intractable conflicts.<br />
We have been reminded horribly of this by the suffering we have seen just<br />
this week in Rwanda.<br />
I want to pay tribute hero to the role of the Australian peacekeepers in<br />
UNAMIR, who were instrumental in providing medical assistance to the<br />
victims of the terrible massacre at Kibeho. </p>
<p>4<br />
They have shown the finest traditions of the Australian Defence Force, and<br />
richly deserve the Anzac Peace Prize they have been awarded,<br />
Ironically, the end of the Cold War which was otherwise so welcome<br />
made possible many of these new outbreaks of conflict around the world by<br />
releasing the political iron bonds which had contained them.<br />
So, in the former Yugoslavia, in the former Soviet Union, in Burundi, in<br />
Somalia, we see tragedies unfold large-scale horror and appalling<br />
inhumanity, stemming from ingrained, small-scale hatreds.<br />
Anid these conflicts are shaping the international system, and challenging<br />
the United Nations, just as profoundly as traditional disputes between states<br />
have done.<br />
They are the reflection of a world in which very often the ation and the<br />
state are rio longer the same thing.<br />
The nation-state, as it existed when the United Nations was founded, is<br />
going through a period of profound transition, and the international<br />
community has to respond.<br />
We see this most obviously in the economic area, where the global market<br />
place is already a reality.<br />
The engagement of the developing world in the international economy is one<br />
of the most far-reaching arid beneficial developments of our age but, as<br />
Auistralians know, it is part of a process which challenges our former ideas<br />
of economic sovereignty.<br />
Similarly, responses to the degradation of the environment cannot possibly<br />
come from one country alone, because both the causes and the effects are<br />
transnational.<br />
Arid the information revolution poses huge problems for laws of national<br />
copyright, and makes the national regulation of what our citizens see and<br />
hear almost impossible.<br />
In short, one of the mantras of modern international relations noninterference<br />
in the internal affairs of other-countries these days has a<br />
greatly modified and much reduced meaning.<br />
In this very different world, how should the international community<br />
respond to the ethnic and communal conflicts which so mar international<br />
peace, and properly disturb ouir consciences?<br />
I dto not mean by this how should we go about the important tasks of<br />
peacekeeping and peacemaking, or the immediate human responses of </p>
<p>providing food, shelter and medicine to those who are suffering? Those,<br />
again, are issues which require separate consideration.<br />
Instead, at a different level, I think that responses lie in some cases in<br />
redefining our idea of the state. In other cases, we need to rethink our view<br />
of the nation.<br />
Sometimes, the best response to intractable tensions may be the old<br />
fashioned remedy of redefining the borders of the state.<br />
That is what happened, peacefully, when the Czech Republic and Slovakia<br />
split, and it is the answer that many of the component parts of the former<br />
Soviet Union found.<br />
Part of the answer may lie in a radical redefinition of what constitutes a<br />
state. In Europe, the very homeland of the nation-state, and the source of much of<br />
the national conflict which has so scarred our century, the European Union<br />
is dramatically changing our ideas about what a state is, and how<br />
sovereignty is distributed.<br />
And after 1997, when Hong Kong reverts to China's control, China will<br />
comprise one state but with two distinct economic systems.<br />
A third response, and one I think that is important, is to build up the role of<br />
regional institutions and identities.<br />
Because the gap between individual states and multilateral organisations like<br />
the United Nations can sometimes be too great for quick and effective<br />
responses to humanitarian or security problems.<br />
And the cultural and historical background necessary to resolve problems<br />
will often lie more readily in the local region.<br />
In addition, an important factor in democracies like Australia is that our<br />
people will often more readily support commitments in our own region<br />
Cambodia, for example than outside it, because they can understand more<br />
easily how events there can affect them.<br />
When the government of Papua New Guinea was searching for a solution to<br />
the problems it faced on the island of Bougainville, for example, it found the<br />
idea of a regional peacekeeping force useful.<br />
Similarly, the United Nations operation in Haiti had a large regional element.<br />
And I think the problem of conflicting claims in the South China Sea a key<br />
security question in Asia is probably more amenable to a regional than an<br />
international settlement. </p>
<p>The greatest contribution of regional organisations, however, has so far<br />
been seen in economic frameworks like the European Union, NAFTA and in<br />
this part of the world APEC.<br />
APEC brings together eighteen very different economies and cultures united<br />
in the common purpose of sustaining prosperity and growth in the Asia<br />
Pacific. It is a practical example of what used to be called North-South<br />
cooperation.<br />
And I have no doubt that here, as in Europe, the act of working together on<br />
practical economic issues will have beneficial political and security<br />
consequences as well.<br />
So regionalism is central to the broader United Nations efforts to promote<br />
peace and prosperity not an alternative, but an addition.<br />
Finally, however, the answer to what we can do about troubling<br />
humanitarian and security problems may lie not so much in rethinking the<br />
state, as in redefining the nation.<br />
The challenge in many cases is how we can create societies rich in cultural,<br />
racial and religious diversity but do so in ways which encourage rather than<br />
compromise a sense of national identity.<br />
It is too glib to say that the answer lies simply in better understanding. The<br />
problems in the Balkans or in central Africa do not stem from a lack of<br />
familiarity with the culture of the antagonists.<br />
This means that the redefinition of the nation is a complex task. It involves<br />
economic and social development, justice, human rights, good governance,<br />
inclusive institution building, tolerance, respect for difference, the<br />
strengthening of civil society.<br />
So it is not an easy job or a quick one. And I do not pretend that the<br />
Australian experience is readily transferable to other parts of the world.<br />
But, as I said, I am certain that some of what we have done here can lead<br />
not only to the development of a culturally rich, diverse, and peaceful<br />
Australian society, but may suggest to others ways of improving harmony<br />
within and between states.<br />
This would be a fitting contribution to the current debate about the future of<br />
the United Nations and its operations, and to the International Year of<br />
Tolerance., It is true that we count what we have done here as a great success.<br />
Nowhere is that truer than in our changing relationship with Asia. </p>
<p>Just a generation ago, the White Australia Policy was still a reality in all but<br />
the technical detail.<br />
Australia came perilously close to marginalising itself in our region and in the<br />
world. Now, half of all our immigrants come from Asia.<br />
They are adding immeasurably to the richness of our society, to our arts, to<br />
our commerce, to the way we live our daily lives,<br />
And their values, like the values of all those who have come here before,<br />
will help shape our culture.<br />
This is a much more tolerant society than that which existed just a<br />
generation ago. Today, no Australian political party can hope to succeed<br />
with an immigration policy which excludes people on racial or ethnic<br />
grounds. Tolerance itself has become one of those words to which we<br />
attach a primary democratic value.<br />
Yet it is important, at this stage of our history, to put our multicultural<br />
successes in perspective.<br />
For instance, I think it would be a mistake for this generation of Australians<br />
to persuade themselves either that the transformation is complete and<br />
completely satisfactory, or, indeed, that all the achievements have occurred<br />
since we first took on the idea the word and the policies of<br />
multicultiralism. Under a different banner that of assimilation migrants from Europe and<br />
the Middle East were welcomed in the decades immediately after World War<br />
II and made a profound contribution to our national life and development.<br />
There are regions of Australia where in the 19th century people from<br />
Germany and Italy were more numerous and their cultures more pervasive<br />
than any from the British Isles.<br />
Today when we talk of the enrichment of our culture by people from all the<br />
countries of the world we sometimes forget that people have been coming<br />
from all over the world to this place for 200 years; that our landscape was<br />
interpreted by painters, scientists and explorers from Germany, Switzerland,<br />
Poland and France as well as Britain and that this artistic and intellectual<br />
tradition was consolidated in the 20th century.<br />
It seems to me we should remember that tolerance of cultural difference is<br />
ultimately a necessary condition for a successful new world country; and<br />
that those traditions of egalitarian democracy which emerged in the last half<br />
of the 19th century had the seeds of multiculturalism in them. If it is true<br />
that earlier generations of Australians traditionally took the view that where<br />
and to what rank people were born should be no measure of their character, </p>
<p>and that in Australia everyone should begin without these handicaps, then<br />
we can see ourselves as building on a tradition.<br />
And we can learn the lesson that the best traditions of a country, and the<br />
best instincts of a people, can be the basis of radical change. I think that is<br />
what we have learnt in Australia in the past couple of decades that<br />
societies can be changed, that an inward looking culture can be made<br />
outward looking, that what seems alien can be revealed as friendly, that<br />
where threats always seemed to lie there are now rewards and<br />
opportunities. And I think we must also always bear in mind that the dominant cultures of<br />
our history those of the British Isles and Ireland far from being hostile to<br />
the growth of a culturally diverse society, provided in democratic institutions<br />
and ideas its essential precondition.<br />
I make these points because it does not hurt to be reminded that our efforts<br />
are part of a much longer story: a story in which progress has been<br />
uneven. We do not know all the answers, and the story is far from over<br />
and we should not assume that the rapid strides we have made in the past<br />
two decades are a guarantee of success in the future.<br />
There is no more profound example of the distance we still have to travel in<br />
Australia than the position of Aboriginal people in our society and their<br />
relationship with non-Aboriginal Australians.<br />
Nor, of course, is there any better example of the fact that since 1788 this<br />
continent has played host to a multicultural society.<br />
This conference is not the place to offer a short history of the<br />
dispossession, brutality and neglect, which accompanied European<br />
settlement and which has continued in this century. Until we succeed in<br />
our ambition to affect a permanent reconciliation with indigenous<br />
Australians, our claims to have achieved a successful multicultural society<br />
will always be compromised.<br />
But we are at last determined on reconciliation a new partnership built on<br />
mutual respect, justice and equity and we have in the last two years put in<br />
place some long overdue foundations.<br />
We have given legislative expression to a decision of the High Court of<br />
Australia that the idea of terra nullius the farcical notion that no one<br />
owned Australia prior to British settlement was indeed a lie. The High<br />
Court established that there was a Native Title to land, rooted in traditional<br />
law and custom itself, within the common law of Australia,<br />
The legislation giving effect to this decision has survived criticism and a<br />
legal challenge. It was confirmed in the High Court just last month. And I<br />
might say what has also been confirmed is that Australians are prepared to </p>
<p>support such a dramatic change in the law that they want to see the<br />
relationship between indigenous and non-indigenous Australians put right.<br />
The establishment of a Native Title will not of itself redress the<br />
consequences of dispossession. In truth, of course, nothing will. But over<br />
the next ten years the Government will allocate some $ 1.5 billion to a<br />
permanent fund so that dispossessed indigenous communities will have the<br />
means to buy land and in so doing regain the potential for spiritual and<br />
cultural regeneration, as well as an economic base to improve their material<br />
well-being.<br />
The final step will be the implementation of social justice measures. We<br />
now have before us two major reports which draw on extensive<br />
consultations with Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people and in due<br />
course we will announce the measures calculated to be most likely to<br />
redress the wrongs and raise the living standards and life opportunities of<br />
indigenous Australians.<br />
There is no doubt that we will succeed best in this wherever we are able to<br />
give Aboriginal people the means of solving their own problems. It is<br />
equally true that we will make improvements in the quality of their lives,<br />
including their health, and raise morale and self esteem wherever we can<br />
deliver the means of their retaining contact with traditional culture and<br />
customs. That, after all, is the most fundamental principle of<br />
rulticulturalism. For us, the process of reconciliation is a basic test of our modern<br />
nationhood on it depends our relationship with both our past and our<br />
future. On it also depends a favourable measure of our achievements in the<br />
realm of cultural diversity.<br />
But to put Australia's progress towards a successful multicultural society in<br />
perspective, to make reference to ambitions not yet fulfilled, is certainly not<br />
to discount the scale of our achievements or the pride we take in them.<br />
The Australia I knew as a child and the Australia of today are radically<br />
different places. When we were growing up we did not and could not<br />
imagine the Sydney of 1995. And even if we had been able to visualise the<br />
city as it now is, we could not have conceived of the means by which it has<br />
been brought about. We could not have conceived of the necessary policy<br />
changes. Perhaps most importantly, we could not have conceived of the<br />
necessary changes in ourselves.<br />
That is at the heart of multiculturalism. It describes a response to the<br />
diversity that exists in Australian society. It is a policy for managing the<br />
consequences of that diversity in the interests of all.<br />
This means a policy which guarantees rights and imposes responsibilities. </p>
<p>The rights include those of cultural identity tho right to express and share<br />
individual cultural heritage, including language and religion. The right to<br />
social justice the right of every Australian to equality of treatment and<br />
opportuinity, regardless of race, ethnicity, religion, language, gender or place<br />
of birth.<br />
The responsibilities might be summarised as follows: that the first loyalty of<br />
all Australians must be to Australia, to its interests and its future; that all<br />
Australians must accept the basic principles of Australian society, including<br />
the Constitution and the rule of law, parliamentary democracy, freedom of<br />
speech and religion, English as the national language, equality of the sexes<br />
and the right of every Australian to express his or her views and values.<br />
That is the essential balance iin the multicultural equation: the promotion of<br />
individual and collective cultural rights and expression, on the one hand;<br />
and on the other, the promotion of common national interests and values.<br />
Arid Success depends on demonstrating that each side of the equation<br />
serves the othpr.<br />
In practical terms one side can be seen in Government programs to provide<br />
people who have just arrived in AuIstralia with assistance to locate and use<br />
the various welfare services, including health, housing and income support.<br />
Or in, for instance, the Translating and Interpreting Service which, by phone<br />
or in person, assists migrants to break down the language barrier they face<br />
until they become fluent in English.<br />
Or in the Special Broadcasting Service, whose daily television and radio<br />
broadcasts in 67 languages help to maintain the threads which link so many<br />
Australians to their n'ative culture,<br />
These are eminently practical measures calculated to minimise the trauma<br />
which migration has always entailed and make the transition to a new life in<br />
a new Culture that much easier. They do not demand or enforce an<br />
attachment to this country, they encourage it.<br />
We take the same view on citizenship. We do not oblige new settlers to<br />
take out citizenship but we actively encourage them to, and when they do<br />
we ask them to swear an oath which expressly acknowledges the principle<br />
of tolerance on which rMUlticulturalisni depends.<br />
The dividend of cultural diversity is largely paid in the form of a society<br />
which is both more rich and interesting and more harmonious and peaceful,<br />
In more recent times we have discovered a new dividend a productivity<br />
dividend. We have learned that cultural difference means different ways of looking at<br />
the world. In an economic environment which demands of enterprises that </p>
<p>I1<br />
they use every possible advantage to be innovative and flexible this is likely<br />
to be a tangible asset.<br />
We have learned that being among the very few countries whose people<br />
understand all but a few of the world's languages and cultures is a very<br />
considerable competitive advantage.<br />
In addition, we are discovering that our policies have provided us with the<br />
most valuable links to countries where we can do business: personal links<br />
and personal understanding between Australian enterprises and the markets<br />
they wish to enter.<br />
We are taking steps to capitalise on these connections and the great cultural<br />
diversity of the Australian workforce through a Productive Diversity Agenda.<br />
This is perhaps the most concrete example we could adduce to show that<br />
the encouragement of cultural diversity is much more than an act of<br />
benevolence it is an act of national self interest.<br />
I am sure it is the hope of everyone here that over the next three days<br />
persuasive arguments will be put to show that the global interest can be<br />
served by the affirmation of cultural diversity.<br />
We certainly do not say that what has occurred in Australia should be a<br />
blueprint for the world., Cultural diversity, let alone human diversity, makes<br />
the idea of a single template absurd. Nor do we expect this conference to<br />
be a celebration of our achievements.<br />
However, we do feel able to say that this very democratic, very open and<br />
very forward looking country has learned a good deal about the benefits and<br />
the management of cultural diversity. We are a country emerging, I think,<br />
into a great 21st century future. We will not be a nation state in the old<br />
sense of that term: we will be a more purposefully independent country<br />
than before, yet we will be more integrated with the world and with the<br />
Asia-Pacific region in particular than the Australians of 60 years ago, when<br />
the United Nations was created, could ever have imagined.<br />
We like to think that we might have in our modern nationhood at least some<br />
of the elements of a 21st century model diversity, tolerance, openness and<br />
worldliness within the boundaries of national purpose and cohesion. And<br />
perhaps as we pursue those goals we can help the world pursue them.<br />
I have very great pleasure in opening this conference and inviting the<br />
Secretary-General of the United Nations, Dr Boutros Boutros-Ghali, to deliver<br />
the keynote address.<br />
Sydney 26 April 1996 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
