<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17298</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Minister for Health Tasmanian Minister for Health Member for Braddon $4.78 million new cancer services boost for Burnie</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/05/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Burnie will receive $4.78 million to establish a new cancer care centre at the North West Regional Hospital.</p>
<p>The centre will include a patient support centre and a new chemotherapy treatment service, with 12 chemotherapy treatment chairs. A million dollars will also go towards a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) unit.</p>
<p>When fully operational this new facility at Burnie will provide an estimated extra 6,000 chemotherapy treatments per year.</p>
<p>The Rudd Government funding announced today is part of a $47.67 million state-wide partnership with the Tasmanian Government and private contributors to enable a balanced and coordinated project across Tasmania. The Tasmanian Government will provide almost $24 million towards this project, with $3.95 million in other contributions.</p>
<p>The Burnie regional cancer centre will be networked to enhanced cancer services across Hobart and Launceston and will enable all Tasmanians to have better access to essential cancer services closer to home.</p>
<p>The state-wide Tasmanian Cancer Care project will include:</p>
<p>     * improved radiation and medical oncology infrastructure and associated services</p>
<p>     * state-of-the-art multidisciplinary team facilities with video conferencing</p>
<p>     * patient support centres at all three sites</p>
<p>     * enhanced and expanded allied health and palliative care services</p>
<p>     * enhanced education and research facilities and linkages</p>
<p>     * a state-wide shared clinical patient record system.</p>
<p>Member for Braddon, Sid Sidebottom said Tasmanians have the second-highest incidence of cancer in Australia, and survival rates for people suffering from cancer are lower in rural and remote communities.</p>
<p>"This investment will mean people in the North West suffering cancer will have their loved ones and important support networks close to hand to help them cope with cancer treatment.</p>
<p>"This important partnership will make a real difference to the lives of Tasmanians," Mr Sidebottom said.</p>
<p>Since coming into office, the Government has committed more than $2.3 billion in cancer infrastructure, medicines, screening and research.</p>
<p>Under the National Health and Hospitals Network, the Government provides 60 per cent of the funding for capital upgrades for public hospitals.</p>
<p>The Australian Government's plan will see health services funded nationally and run locally through local hospital networks to deliver better outcomes for local communities.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
