<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41078</transcript-id>
    <title>Secretary of the Department of Defence</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/07/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce the appointment of Mr Greg Moriarty as Secretary of the Department of Defence.</p>
<p>Mr Moriarty brings a considerable range and depth of experience to the role and I congratulate him on his appointment.</p>
<p>He first worked in the Department of Defence from 1986-95, primarily in the Defence Intelligence Organisation. He also served in the Headquarters of the United States Central Command in the Persian Gulf during Operations Desert Shield and Desert Storm.</p>
<p>As an officer in the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Greg Moriarty served in a number of senior roles, including Senior Negotiator with the Peace Monitoring Group on Bougainville, Ambassador to Iran, Ambassador to Indonesia and as a Deputy Secretary of the Department.</p>
<p>Mr Moriarty became the first Commonwealth Counter-Terrorism Coordinator in June 2015, responsible for coordinating and implementing Australia’s counter-terrorism arrangements.</p>
<p>In August 2016, he joined my office as International and National Security Adviser and later became my Chief of Staff.</p>
<p>He holds a Bachelor of Arts Degree with Honours from the University of Western Australia and a Masters Degree in Strategic Defence Studies from the Australian National University.</p>
<p>I thank Mr Moriarty for his outstanding work in my office in which he demonstrated his leadership and strategic understanding as he has done throughout his career.</p>
<p>I also thank Brendan Sargeant for his dedicated service while acting in the role of Secretary of the Department of Defence.</p>
<p>Mr Moriarty’s appointment is for 5 years commencing on 4 September 2017.</p>
<p>At that time, Peter Woolcott AO will commence as my Chief of Staff.</p>
<p>Since February 2016, Mr Woolcott has served as Australian High Commissioner to New Zealand. His previous roles include Ambassador for the Environment (2014-16) Permanent Representative to the United Nations in Geneva and Ambassador for Disarmament (2010-2014), Ambassador for People Smuggling Issues (2009), Ambassador to Italy (2004 -2007).</p>
<p>From 2002-2004, Peter Woolcott worked as Chief of Staff to the then Foreign Affairs Minister.</p>
<p>Mr Woolcott’s extensive experience and expertise make him highly qualified for his new role, and I very much look forward to working with him.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
