<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6425</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 13 JULY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/07/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006425.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E. O. E. PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE 13 JULY 1984<br />
JOURNALIST: How do you think it went?<br />
PM: I think it was an excellent donference. I think that I<br />
can say on the evidence available to all of us that the<br />
Conference turned out in the way I asked it to in my speech<br />
on Tuesday that is that the great majority of delegates<br />
came to conclusions, made decisions, resolutions which were<br />
couched in an understanding of the responsibility, not just<br />
to the Party, but to the people of Australia as a whole. And<br />
certainly there has been both a ringing endorsement of the<br />
approach of the Government to this stage and the provision of<br />
a basis for it to continue in the future in the same direction.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, on industry policy this morning. Given<br />
Australia's comparative advantage in the fields of primary<br />
production and mining, don't you think it is rather foolish an~ d<br />
perhaps even dangerous to have an industry policy based, to quote<br />
the new platform, on the need for Australia to bring its trade<br />
pattern into line with other industrialised nations?<br />
PM: Well, you can look at that as you will, I suppose. What<br />
will be done in a way which is totally consistent with that<br />
statement of policy is to do these things for the various<br />
sectors of our economy. We will recognise the truth that the<br />
great primary industries remain fundamental to the eternal<br />
welfare of Australia and as generation of wealth here and also<br />
in terms of earning considerable export income for us and we<br />
will be doing those things which are necessary both here and<br />
in our relations with other countries to expand the possibilities<br />
for the primary sector. In regard to the mineral sector, we will<br />
clearly be pursuing policies which enable the expansion of that<br />
sector in a way which will utilise both foreign and domestically<br />
generated capital. And in regard to the manufacturing sector we<br />
will develop policies which can be looked at in two ways both<br />
industry specific in a way we have with the steel industry, with<br />
the automotive industry and we will be adopting policies, which<br />
as I put in my contribution today, which will take account of the<br />
industries that are here to try and make those that can be made<br />
more efficient, more efficient. We will try through the variety<br />
of policies, some indication of which we have already given to<br />
develop new ones. Now, that is precisely what we have been doing<br />
to this date and doing with very considerable successs and I<br />
believe that the policy and the general statements that have been<br />
adopted today give us a mandate to proceed in that fashion, Max.<br />
I have no problem in noting and appreciating the contribution<br />
that will be made to the formulation of that policy as a mandate </p>
<p>for proceeding with the general strategy which has been so<br />
successful to this point.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, where does the Left Wing of the<br />
Party go, given that they lost every major issue before the<br />
Conference. Have they got a future in the Labor Party or what<br />
do they do?<br />
PM: Well if you look at the history of the Labor Party, there<br />
is always a left, a right and a centre and I have no feeling<br />
that there is going to cease to be a left. I think I would say<br />
this, and I hope they won't regard it as gratuitous, indeed I<br />
know from some observations that there is. this feeling within<br />
the Left itself, that they need to have a-good look at themslves,<br />
that the positions adopted and the arguments embraced and the<br />
style pursued, seemed to many people, including many of their<br />
own, to be somewhat less than ideally suited to the conditions<br />
of the Party, the Government and the country as we go through<br />
1984 and into ' 85. 1 think there will be some re-thinking. I<br />
hope so.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, was there an attempted double cross<br />
on the conscience vote on abortion?<br />
PM: I don't think that is fair to put it as a double cross. I<br />
understood from what was said to me that it was being made<br />
clear that inrespect of that motion there was no intention to<br />
use that as the basis for repealing the conscience vote and I<br />
understood that if any attempt were made those that had been<br />
associated with that proposal yesterday would not support any<br />
attempt in this Conference-to repeal that. And that was<br />
essentially the position that those people did adopt. I think it<br />
was very interesting to see how the approach that was moved by<br />
Delegate Giles was repudiated by so many, not just the Right, and<br />
the Centre Left, but many Within the Left itself couldn't bring<br />
themselves to vote for that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you still hold the view that you expressed in<br />
the 1982 Conference opposed to the capital gains tax?<br />
PM: That's a good question. I support without reservation the<br />
policy that was adopted at the 1984 Conference. It was the one<br />
that I advocated. It was the one that I had been associated with<br />
in the lead-up to the Conference. Let me make it quite clear,<br />
as I have said on a number of occasions, -that what this Government<br />
has been attempting to do since we have been in-office is to<br />
develop a constructive debate within the community, not just only<br />
in EPAC, but of course that is a most relevant forum. We have<br />
been attempting to develop a constructive debate within the<br />
community about the whole tax structure. I have said I think in<br />
a large press conference before, we have got to try and get an<br />
understanding of the way in which the comumunity, individuals and<br />
organisations want to make part of their income available to<br />
government for the purpose of providing services through<br />
government back to the community and the sensible thing to do is<br />
to have that debate in a way which covers the whole range of tax<br />
on the one side and services provided on the other. And I am<br />
very encouraged by two things. Firstly, before we got to the<br />
/ 3<br />
' 1 </p>
<p>Conference there had been such a positive response from the<br />
business community and the trade union movement and other<br />
organisations to enter into this dissussion. -And secondly,<br />
by the way in which the Conference endorsed that approach.<br />
Now, as we go into next year, that debate will be encouraged<br />
and I am confident that as a result of that const ructive,<br />
consultative approach, Australia will be able to move towards<br />
a position where it has total tax base which satisfies, as I<br />
say, the two criteria of efficiency and equity and once we<br />
have done that this community is going to be very much better off.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, the Centre Left and the Right delivered<br />
quite respectable and moderate policies this time. Would you<br />
like to see the Conference system reformed in some way so that<br />
the government at a later date is-not embarrassed by say a major<br />
left wing policy..<br />
PM: If what?<br />
JOURNALIST: If at a later date the Left Wing embarrassed the<br />
Government on some major issue of policy?<br />
PM: Between conferences do you mean?<br />
JOURNALIST: Well, would you like to see the Conference systerm<br />
reformed in some way?<br />
PM: Well, could I pass onto an observation that was made by<br />
Alan Griffiths this morning. I met the business representatives<br />
at the Conference. There was a gathering at about 8.30. And in<br />
introducing me to the business representatives there he said<br />
he proposed what seems to me on reflection a rather radical<br />
reform. He thanked them for being there and wondered how we could<br />
continue the association and said I look forward to seeing you at<br />
the next bicentennial conference. I thought that was probably<br />
taking it a bit far.<br />
Now wait a minute, the question deserves more than that lighthearted<br />
observation. Look, Greg, when you are trying to work<br />
out what is the best way of enabling an input from the Party<br />
organisation of the formulation of policy, I guess you can always<br />
. say that there are better ways than what exists, but whatever<br />
you do, factionalism is going to continue within the. Party. But<br />
let me say this, that I don't believe that there will be any<br />
attempt by any of the factions now that the Conference is over<br />
to embarrass the Government. And the second point I would make<br />
is that I have total confidence in the capacity of this Government<br />
to continue to deliver the goods in regard to the aspirations of<br />
the Australian people in the important areas of the economy and<br />
the areas of social welfare. Now, to the extent that the<br />
Government continues to deliver the goods, as it will, then the<br />
Party will have no reason to want to embarrass the Government.<br />
And I am totally confident that by the time we get to the next:<br />
Conference in 1986 that the Government will again get the support<br />
and the clear support of the great majority of the Phrty. I'm<br />
totally confident about that and I don't see any reason to change.<br />
It's quite clear, I think, that in some branches of the Party<br />
there will be moves by some sectors to try and strengthen theiLr<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>position and that may produce some interesting changes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, you said this morning there are some<br />
areas of concern in the car industry plan. What are those<br />
and would you agree that the whole thrust of the Conference<br />
policy in relation to industry protection was much more<br />
protectionist and interventionist than the Government than<br />
the Government was pursuing up until now?<br />
PM: No, in regard to the second and in regard to the first,<br />
one sector of the major production union, the vehicle builders<br />
union, had expressed some concern, '. but overwhelmingly the<br />
view of the trade union movement as expressed through the ACTU,<br />
was totally supportive of the Goveprnment policy, as it should<br />
be because it is an excellent policy.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, to go back to taxation. Would you<br />
anticipate being able to be a bit more specific about the<br />
Government's plan during the election campaign or do you think<br />
that you will still be put in this position of a wide-ranging<br />
debate? PM: I think the debate, the consultative process, will be going<br />
on into 1985. I will obviously be talking with the Australian<br />
electorate in the post-Budget situation about where we are and I<br />
believe that the Australian public will be very satisfied about<br />
where we are after the Budget and then I will be explaining to<br />
them the ideas that we have about involving them in these<br />
processes of discussion and again I believe that that is what<br />
they will want of this government.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, will the Government be offering the<br />
rehabilitated David Combe a job and if so, have you got anything in<br />
particular in mind?<br />
PM: No, there wasn't any talk about offering a job. All<br />
t-hat has been said is what ought to have been said, made clear<br />
and that is that there is no blackball against David. He<br />
has talents and capacities which he may think are appropriate<br />
in respect of some jobs that may arise and he knows now and<br />
I'm glad that it has been done. He now knows that if he wishes<br />
to apply for anything that may arise then he is able to go<br />
into that application process free of any stigma or blackball. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, on the important question<br />
of light bulbs what exactly did go through your mind?<br />
I'll tell you. I'll give you one observation that<br />
was made by my Deputy Prime Minister who was sitting on my<br />
right who, as you know, he exhibits his beliefs and his<br />
commitments and his faith through the Conference and he<br />
made the observation he said Prime minister, do you realise<br />
that in extremis you invoked the Almighty? There' s just one<br />
thing I thought my God if that is a shot, they can'It miss<br />
from there. That was all.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, on uranium, now-that you have an<br />
unambiguous pro-uranium policy as part -of the platform,<br />
does that mean that any member-~ who advocates an anti-uranium<br />
policy outside the councils of the Party faces the risk of<br />
discipline? Well I, as you know, am not a strict disciplinarian.<br />
I rather try and operate on the basis of getting co-operation.<br />
I want to say this though, that I would think that if the<br />
decision had gone the other way and I had then been out<br />
advocating something else that there would have been a multitude<br />
of motions passed and actions suggested against me or anyone!<br />
who'd taken that position. So I would hope that those who<br />
have had the fairest of all possible opportunities to put their<br />
case and try and persuade the Party to an anti-uranium position<br />
will accept the logic of that. That does not of course meank<br />
that within the Party itself they don't have the freedom to<br />
try and move to change that. But I believe that any action<br />
outside the Party would not be proper and I don't think that:<br />
the authorities of the Party would view it with favour. Nowr<br />
I don't say that in a threatening way, but I hope that now<br />
those who have been so active will recognise that a clear<br />
decision has been taken. It's going to be implemented and<br />
I would hope that they would accept it and I think that's what<br />
will happen.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, on immigration yesterday you told<br />
the Conference that Mr Peacock basically broke an agreement<br />
he had reached with you. Today we hear, that Mr Peacock<br />
says you're lying. It doesn't augur well for the burying<br />
of an essentially very divisive issue.<br />
No, but what's very interesting, if you notice he said<br />
that I did that, I hoped he used the words. But then went<br />
on to concede that I wasn't. In other words that I had rung<br />
him, he concedes that. A conversation took place, but then<br />
when he realised that the figures came out that we'd changed<br />
our policy, then he couldn't get effect: to his agreement well<br />
I just leave you and the people of Australia to contemplate<br />
that answer, because he knows that the figures that emerged<br />
didn't show any change of policy. The figures that were<br />
available for anyone who wanted to study them showed nothing<br />
other than that this Government continued the policies of the<br />
previous Government. That is, that we allowed to Asian<br />
citizens that come here the same right as anyone else in<br />
respect of family union that they've been exercising that,<br />
I. s 1 ! IT. </p>
<p>P. M. cant... that there had been a voluntary decline relatively<br />
in people coming here from other sources, and if there hadn't<br />
been the same relative taking up of the family reunion by those<br />
here from non-Asian sources. That was not change of Goverrnent<br />
policy, that was a straight continuation of bipartisanship. He<br />
knows the facts. The people of Australia increasingly understand<br />
the facts. And Mr Peacock is going to have to face up, as I said,<br />
to the dilemma that his attempt to get into the gutter via<br />
Hodgman has created f or himself. And that is the position that<br />
he said that they are not in favour of reducing the number of<br />
Asian migrants. They want to restore the balance which<br />
arithmetically and logically means that they are going to have<br />
a quota concept which means more migrants, that they are saying<br />
to the Australian people no less Asians, but more non-Asians<br />
in other words a higher migrant intake. Now as I said at the<br />
Conference it's no wonder we're waiting like Halley's Comet for<br />
the emergence of the specific polic y, because he know's the<br />
dilemuma that his unprincipled responses have got him into.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could ASIO provide some transcripts to sort out<br />
this dispute that's been in this conversation?<br />
Have we got some serious questions?<br />
JOURNALIST: On a Victorian matter, Mr Hawke, do you have an<br />
agreement from the Centre Left to supportthe reaffiliation<br />
of the four unions in September?<br />
That's an internal matter which will work itself out<br />
quite satisfactorily I believe.<br />
JOURNALIST: As a result of the industry policy that was worked<br />
out today can you see the situation of the Government in terms<br />
of consultation with the unions will be setting down for various<br />
industries and manufacturing their investment pricing and employment<br />
strategy? No, not setting down, but I think the steel industry provides<br />
an example where in those particular circumstances out of a<br />
consultation process between the Government and the unions and<br />
the industry, you now have a greater degree of capacity f or others<br />
in the industry ' itself to be involved in consideration of investment<br />
decisions with their employment consequences. And that's not<br />
something which has been imposed upon the industry, it's something<br />
that they've welcomed. And as I said today if you go into that<br />
industry now and talk with management they quite directly express<br />
their strong satisfaction about the new atmosphere and environment<br />
that's come out of that approach. Now I believe that that sort of<br />
thing may be able to be done and is encouraged to be done under<br />
the policies that was adopted today. The essential thing is that<br />
you're not going to have any misrepresentation in this issue<br />
about this Government's policy and its relations with industry.<br />
There's not going to be the imposition of any control or the<br />
attempt to impose planning upon industry. What's going to be<br />
done is what we've successfully shown can happen in the steel<br />
industry and in the automotive industry something that<br />
increasingly industry itself is saying it wants to see and we'll<br />
gladly co-operate with them and with the trade unions to produce<br />
it. 11 </p>
<p>JcOeUrRtNaAiLnI SlTe: f t wDiunrgi ngd eltehge atdeesba-tmea deo n thTeu essdtaayt emone ntu ratnhiautm the ALP<br />
would lose electorally on the issue of uranium.. How do you<br />
feel about those remarks by those members.<br />
Well, like so much of their contribution in the debate,<br />
they were wrong. I quoted the factual research material of the<br />
Party which showed, and let me repeat, a clear majority of Labor<br />
voters in favour of the policy that I'd been espousing which has<br />
now been adopted as well as a clear majority of Democrat voters<br />
and the majority of the other voters, a clear majority of women,<br />
and very importantly in respect of one central part of the argument<br />
that's been used by the left that is you must keep uranium in<br />
the ground because this was relevant to the questions of world<br />
peace and disarmament the overwhelming majority, of the order<br />
of 80%, saying that that was nonsense, that. it was a quite<br />
separate issue. And I related to the polling that's been in<br />
the Bulletin on 29 May of this year and to all otherpolling that's<br />
been taken on it--the cl. ear majority of Australian people<br />
have a clear understanding both of the question itself and of<br />
the division between the issue of uranium mining and the issue<br />
of nuclear disarmament and peace. They-aremanifestly separate<br />
issues. And clearly the overwhelming majority of the Australian.<br />
electorate appreciate it. And I make the final point if they<br />
don't approve of the Labor Party's policy in terms of alternative<br />
Governments there's only the Liberal and National: Party who would<br />
mine everything.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you expect to see in September the National Executive<br />
taking the four unions back into the Party?<br />
I give the same answer as I did to the question from<br />
Michelle Grattan. That's a matter that will be decided within<br />
the processes of the Party and I'm quite confident about the<br />
way it will be resolved.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister do you feel that you're totally bound<br />
by the Platform adopted by the Conference or will you continue<br />
if necessary to interpret policy according to changing circumstances.<br />
Well you notice that the Party has re-affirmed the overall.<br />
resolution that there is the Platform and the rate of implementation<br />
is a matter for the Government. It's a very sensible decision that<br />
they have confirmed. It's been there before and this Government<br />
will operate within and according to the Platform. You may notice<br />
that the Conference on every issue of significance made decision~ s<br />
in accordance with what I indicated. I and the Government wanted.<br />
So clearly we have no problems.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke will you take advantage of Mr Shultz's visit<br />
in the next couple of days to discuss the Conference decision calling<br />
for restrictions on US warship visits.<br />
I have no doubt that that there will be some discussion in<br />
regard to that matter. / 8 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Do you believe that the creation of the Centre<br />
Left was an important factor in the success of the Conference,<br />
or do you think undue credit was given to them?<br />
PM: Well, you might have noticed, as distinct from yourself,<br />
ZTeg, and others who spent a lot of time obviously thinking<br />
and writing about this, but I have been very relaxed about it.<br />
I am simply saying I repeat here what I have said before<br />
that I think the organisation of the Centre Left was useful<br />
in imposing a discipline, if you like, upon those who grouped<br />
together in that way. I have no doubt that in the absence<br />
of that disciplined organisation we still. would have won. It's<br />
arguable, I think, that perhaps on some issues we may not have<br />
got the margin that we did. So : L'm therefore grateful for the<br />
discipline that was exercised, but I have no doubt that the<br />
results would have been the same, perhaps the dimension on some<br />
issues would not have been as great.<br />
JOURNALIST: Uranium, Sir. Can you suggest what would be your<br />
Government's decision if at some point in the future the French<br />
Energy Utility sought more Australian uranium at the same time<br />
as the French Government, Sir, continued with nuclear testing<br />
in the South Pacific.<br />
PM: Well, quite clearly, we wouldn't respond positively to such<br />
approach in the hypothetical situation you put.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was there any outcome or decision of the<br />
Conference which you would like to have seen emerge a little<br />
differently? PM: No. Look, when you have a week's conference which<br />
Fasses so many platform items and resolution, obviously if<br />
I were to write every one of them they wouldn't have been<br />
written exactly the same. It would be absurd to suggest that.<br />
In a process of taking account of a range of point of views,<br />
I am very satisfied that the basic thrust on all major issues<br />
that I have been developing over very many months, and in<br />
some things in respect of uranium that I have been developing<br />
for years, has been adopted and now, in -the process of having<br />
the main thrust of my position clearly endorsed, that gives<br />
me satisfaction. The fact that I might have worded some<br />
clauses and phrases differently is a mat-ter of no concern to<br />
me at all.<br />
1 1-1 I </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you agree with the personal<br />
view of Senator Walsh, that Australia may the Government<br />
may have to take delivery of the contracted shipments to<br />
France of yellowcake?<br />
PM: I think we may have to do that, yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: What is your interpretation of the resolution<br />
on visits by nuclear warships. Does it, do you think, place<br />
any practical restriction on the visits that US ships have<br />
been making to Western Australian ports,. and if so, will you<br />
implement that resolution?<br />
PM: Quite clearly the resolution is against home porting. It<br />
is saying, let's make sure that we talk with our ally the<br />
United States to ensure that visits don't constitute home<br />
porting. I am perfectly confident that that resolution enables<br />
the situation to emerge which is satisfactory to our ally, the<br />
United States and to us as a firm and committed ally of the<br />
United States.<br />
JOURNALIST: Isn't what you said about uranium and supplies to<br />
France in breach of the Party platform?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, when are you likely to visit<br />
New Zealand before or after the South Pacific Forum?<br />
PM: When am I likely to go to New Zealand before or after<br />
t-he South Pacific Forum? That's a touchy one, isn't it. I<br />
think it would be after the Forum. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
