<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11204</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   INTERVIEW WITH NEIL MITCHELL &amp;#150; RADIO 3AW                                                  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Economy, GST, budget, Kosovo refugees,</p>
<p> East Timor, heroin injection room, heroin trials, food prices, LPG</p>
<p> prices, industrial relations</p>
<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr John Howard, good morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Hello, Neil.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the economy  are we in for a boom?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's going very strongly, much better than anybody expected</p>
<p> a year ago. I think we may, in fact, have reached a stage where because</p>
<p> of a lot of reforms that have been undertaken our economy is fundamentally</p>
<p> that much stronger that we can look forward to maintaining high levels</p>
<p> of growth for longer periods of time. Now, I don't want to sound</p>
<p> complacent or triumphal, I'm neither, but I'm gratified</p>
<p> because what this means is that ordinary Australians have got more</p>
<p> money in their pockets. They've got lower interest rates. They've</p>
<p> got higher real wages. They've got a higher standard of living.</p>
<p> And they're showing it with their retail spending. You can't</p>
<p> underestimate the impact of that cut in housing rates. It's worth</p>
<p> about $320 a month.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay, well is inflation at risk now down the track? I see Alan Greenspan,</p>
<p> the US Federal Reserve Chairman, today is being a bit edgy about the</p>
<p> possibility of inflation.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>One of the difficulties, if I can put it like this, of a boom economy</p>
<p> like this is that people tend to micro-analyse the nuances in every</p>
<p> single remark that anybody makes. You can never relax. And you have</p>
<p> to keep your sights firmly fixed on things like inflation but at the</p>
<p> moment in Australia it's very low and there's no sign of</p>
<p> it breaking out at all in the near term. That's, I guess, all</p>
<p> I can say. The other point I'd make is that now is precisely</p>
<p> the time to press ahead with more reform. And some people will say,</p>
<p> we're doing so well, why both with any other reform.'</p>
<p> You've got to remember that we're doing well now because</p>
<p> of past reforms.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What sort of reform are you talking about, industrial relations?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm talking about taxation reform. I'm talking about industrial</p>
<p> relations reform - those two in particular. Now is the best occasion</p>
<p> in generations for this country to reform its taxation system because</p>
<p> inflation is low, the economy is strong, we can therefore absorb at</p>
<p> the adjustment process very easily and we'll get the benefits</p>
<p> of that reform very quickly.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>It's a fair argument  if things are booming along like</p>
<p> this, why fiddle with it...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But you've got to ask the next question  why are they booming?</p>
<p> They're booming because of past reforms, therefore if you want</p>
<p> to maintain the boom, if I can put it that way, you've got to</p>
<p> have further reform. If you don't maintain the boom, if you sit</p>
<p> back and say, oh well, she'll be right mate,' it'll</p>
<p> run out of puff. Now, it is because of us getting the budget in surplus,</p>
<p> it's because of past industrial relations reform and earlier</p>
<p> reforms than that. All of those things have come together and given</p>
<p> us this much stronger economic outlook. Now, that tells us that if</p>
<p> we want to keep the process going we can't let up on reform.</p>
<p> And those who say, no more reform is needed, let's put</p>
<p> the reform activity to one side and enjoy it,' they couldn't</p>
<p> be more short-sighted.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But such a dramatic change as the GST, I mean, there has to be an</p>
<p> element of risk in that, does there not?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think there's a risk if you don't. Because the present</p>
<p> system is so discredited and the present system is so out-of-date</p>
<p> and the present system is so much more uncompetitive than the system</p>
<p> that we are proposing that there is a risk, as the old saying has</p>
<p> it, in doing nothing.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>The Treasurer seems to be suggesting a risk of overheating which I</p>
<p> assume means that, well, interest rates aren't going down, if</p>
<p> anything they'd go up.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, he wasn't saying that.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, he's saying that he can't afford GST...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I didn't hear him say anything about interest rates.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>No, that's my interpretation. That's my interpretation.</p>
<p> Well, he doesn't now, I know, but that's my interpretation.</p>
<p> He's saying that the GST package can't be made any sweeter</p>
<p> because it could overheat the economy. Now, if the economy is that</p>
<p> fragile that it can be overheated we're not going to put interest</p>
<p> rates down, are we?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm not going to get drawn on a comment on interest rates</p>
<p> except, historically, to say they are lower now than they've</p>
<p> been for 30 years and every homebuyer's more than $300 a month</p>
<p> better off as a result. Beyond that I'm not going to speculate</p>
<p> about the future level. You try and produce policies that provide</p>
<p> a benign climate for interest rates but as to future movements, I'm</p>
<p> not going to speculate. What Peter was saying, what I'd say and</p>
<p> anybody in our positions would say, and that is that, yes, we do have</p>
<p> a surplus but you don't squander hard accumulated gains.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, how would you squander them, I mean, how are we in danger of</p>
<p> squandering them?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I'm not saying we are but Peter was making the point, as</p>
<p> I understand it, that you need, I mean, there are  the fact</p>
<p> that you've done well is, through prudence and care, is a reason</p>
<p> why you should continue to exercise prudence and care into the future.</p>
<p> That's what he's saying.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Was that a reason why there can't be any further compensation</p>
<p> in the GST package because it would overheat the economy?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm not going to comment about that.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, that's what Peter Costello's saying.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't think he's quite saying that. But, look, I'm</p>
<p> not going to comment about that. I mean, good try, Neil, but I'm</p>
<p> not.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, no, but can I just as you specifically...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You can ask me anything you like.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Do you agree there's a possibility that if there is further compensation</p>
<p> in the GST package it would overheat the economy?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I agree that any government has to exercise prudence and care with</p>
<p> a hard... accumulated budget surplus.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>With respect, Mr Howard, that doesn't answer the question.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I know it's not quite the answer you're perhaps seeking</p>
<p> but our position on the GST is we want to get it through. We're</p>
<p> not going to alter its essential thrust. We've always said that</p>
<p> we would agree to some fine-tuning of it and I've never sought</p>
<p> to define what that fine-tuning would be, nor has the Treasurer, and</p>
<p> I don't intend to do that now.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>All right. So there's still room for further sweeteners in the</p>
<p> GST?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Our position is that we're not going to alter its essential thrust</p>
<p> but we'll agree to fine-tuning if that is needed to get it through.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Is there still room for further compensation within the package?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm not using different language than what I've just</p>
<p> employed.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay, the budget next week - if you were to sum it up, you write the</p>
<p> headline for us, what sort of budget will it be?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think very much a budget about the education future of this country.</p>
<p> I think you'll find quite a bit in it about education.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Education. Now, I read in the Financial Review there's</p>
<p> a significant rift in Cabinet about education, about university scholarships,</p>
<p> disadvantaged students being cut back, is that right?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't talk about Cabinet discussions.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Will there be changes to...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not going to talk about individual things. You asked me to</p>
<p> try and give it some kind of theme. I think it will be a theme that</p>
<p> will be very good for education and what I might call the future intellectual</p>
<p> capital of this country.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>There are specific reports about small business getting new incentives</p>
<p> and a mentor system...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there are a whole lot of reports and pieces of speculation around</p>
<p> this time. I'm sorry to be difficult. I'd ask the same questions.</p>
<p> I'm just not going to answer them. You invited me to try and</p>
<p> write a headline. I've tried to do that but beyond that I can't</p>
<p> really say any more.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, let's the follow the headline point a bit - education budget</p>
<p> - conservative, a conservative budget financially or is it a bit (inaudible)</p>
<p> than you have been in the past?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we have always brought down fiscally responsible, conservative,</p>
<p> however you want to describe it, budgets, and we'll continue</p>
<p> to do that and Peter has made that very clear.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the refugees, you meet them today, the Kosovar refugees</p>
<p> in Sydney. What will you say to them?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, essentially what I'll be saying is welcome, we know you've</p>
<p> had a very hard time and we hope we can provide some hope, some relief,</p>
<p> some haven in what must be a horrific part of your lives. I don't</p>
<p> want to say a lot. They'll be very tired. And they'll want</p>
<p> to eat and be looked after and we want to do that.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Is there any indication that we will go to 4,000 or in fact beyond</p>
<p> 4,000?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we're certainly willing to go to 4,000 and as things stand</p>
<p> at the moment we will take 4,000.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay, more if necessary?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, at the moment we're committed to taking 4,000. We keep</p>
<p> assessing it. I don't know that we'd go beyond that but</p>
<p> I won't categorically rule it out. You don't categorically</p>
<p> rule out anything but I think 4,000 is a reasonable level given that</p>
<p> the Americans, for example, are taking 20,000 - a very reasonable</p>
<p> level.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Reports in The Age today from East Timor  people being</p>
<p> herded into sort of indoctrination, pro-Indonesian indoctrination</p>
<p> camps. Do you have any information as to the accuracy of those reports?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't have anything in front of me about those particular reports</p>
<p> but I know that the situation still remains very difficult. I'm</p>
<p> not pretending that everything has been resolved in East Timor. I</p>
<p> don't think anybody is. But I do know that it's a lot better</p>
<p> than it was a month ago and infinitely better than what it was six</p>
<p> months ago because we do have a very public commitment from the Indonesian</p>
<p> Government to have a ballot. And we do have a process that is more</p>
<p> likely than any other process to ensure that that ballot is free and</p>
<p> open. And Alexander Downer is right to warn, as I have, that we've</p>
<p> got very difficult months ahead of us but we've got to keep a</p>
<p> sense of perspective. If we are to continue successfully influence</p>
<p> the Indonesian Government we must work with them, putting our point</p>
<p> of view very strongly but not waving the finger excessively and pretending</p>
<p> that we can snap our fingers and bring about a change in policy without</p>
<p> exercising sensibly persuasion.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>We do have to accept though that we might have to take refugees from</p>
<p> East Timor. You look at these photographs today and you think, as</p>
<p> they're departing, the Kosovo refugees arrive, you say, well</p>
<p> inevitably we might have to offer to take refugees from this area.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Neil, we have a refugee program and once again I don't rule</p>
<p> that out. We'll behave in a humanitarian way as we have in relation</p>
<p> to the people from Kosovo. But the best shot that we can give the</p>
<p> East Timorese is to continue to use our influence, persuade the Indonesian</p>
<p> government to deliver a fair and open ballot. We've been quite</p>
<p> successful in that. Remember that it was submission to the Indonesian</p>
<p> government before Christmas that was the catalyst in bringing about</p>
<p> a change in its policy. The Indonesian brought about a huge change</p>
<p> in policy on East Timor.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>We'll take a quick call for Mr Howard then a break. There's</p>
<p> a couple of other things I want to ask about. Well one comes to mind</p>
<p> while we're talking about refugees, is the case of the heavily</p>
<p> pregnant Chinese woman allegedly sent back back to China where she</p>
<p> was aborted. I mean that's not a good sign of a refugee policy</p>
<p> if that happens is it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. I said yesterday that it certainly offended my instincts, I'm</p>
<p> sure the instincts of most Australians. The claim is being investigated.</p>
<p> I haven't got the results of that so therefore I can't say</p>
<p> anymore other than to assure you and your listeners, and Senator Harradine</p>
<p> who raised the matter, that I'm concerned if it did happen. Very</p>
<p> concerned. Mr Ruddock is as well. And we're finding out if it</p>
<p> did, and why.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Fair enough. But obviously it wouldn't be policy if the bureaucrats.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Certainly not policy, certainly not policy, no. Definitely not policy.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>We'll take a quick call and then move on to other matters. Hello</p>
<p> Robert, go ahead please.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Yes good morning. Mr Howard. Thanks for taking my call. Look Mr Howard,</p>
<p> just a quick one on the increase of food prices through the supermarkets</p>
<p> and so forth. Regarding this low inflation, if you spoke to every</p>
<p> household shopper they would swear to you that in the last six months</p>
<p> food has skyrocketed probably anywhere between 10% to 40% increase.</p>
<p> And just on that point, there's also another issue on the LPG</p>
<p> fluctuations. There's anything up to 40% from day to day. Why</p>
<p> is this?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Good question. LPG seems unanswerable.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I get a lot of anecdotal reports. Some people say to me that</p>
<p> supermarket prices are going up more than the official figures, some</p>
<p> don't. You've got to remember that our CPI includes a whole</p>
<p> lot of things, they are and not just food prices. The figures can't</p>
<p> be consistently wrong over such a long period of time. And I certainly</p>
<p> don't have the experience of people saying to me between 10%</p>
<p> and 40%. I really don't. I mean that is not my experience, and</p>
<p> can I say a lot of people talk to me about those sorts of things.</p>
<p> Don't think for a moment that I don't talk to people about</p>
<p> those sorts of things. I do on quite a regularly basis. But it's</p>
<p> not my experience to say figures in that magnitude. I think it's</p>
<p> fair to say that people remember price increases more than they remember</p>
<p> something remaining static in price, and they are more conscience</p>
<p> of any price variation in something they buy each day.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But you're happy with the way the basket works, with the CPI</p>
<p> being based on a basket of prices? I get this complaint a lot from</p>
<p> some people who say, well look, inflation's down but our cost</p>
<p> of living is up.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, a few comments about that. The basket is determined independently</p>
<p> by the statistician and he applies the principles that are applied</p>
<p> all around the world. It keeps getting revised. I have no reason to</p>
<p> question the accuracy of the methodology. And as to things constantly</p>
<p> going up in price, the volume of retail spending is so strong it indicates</p>
<p> that there's a lot of confidence on the part of consumers, and</p>
<p> they have quite a lot of disposable income with which to buy the goods.</p>
<p> And can I also tell you that a very regular thing that is said to</p>
<p> me, very very regularly by people in business, particularly small</p>
<p> business, and that is that the market is very price competitive, that</p>
<p> margins are thin. I was talking to a small printing operator yesterday</p>
<p> in Sydney who I've known for 20 years. I said how's business?</p>
<p> He said, volume terrific, margins wafer thin. And that is a constant</p>
<p> complaint of small business. Now that indicates to me that there's</p>
<p> an enormous amount of competition in the market and that is suppressing</p>
<p> margins. So that tends to support the accuracy of what the statistician</p>
<p> is saying.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Sand what about the LPG prices? We got a lot of reaction to this too.</p>
<p> They are all over the place and without any apparent logic to them?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think that is unavoidable when, you know, you have degree of</p>
<p> price competition and you have a degree of flexibility in the market.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>A quick call from Oscar. Go ahead please Oscar.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Good morning Mr Mitchell, and Mr Prime Minister. May I talk to you</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
