<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11061</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   INTERVIEW WITH MATT PEACOCK                   AM PROGRAMME, ABC RADIO</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> Prime Minister, thanks for joining us. Just how live an option</p>
<p>   is a double dissolution? We heard Senator Ron Boswell today saying</p>
<p>   it would be better to have no GST than half the GST and we should</p>
<p>   see the Government come out with its guns blazing to an election.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> Well, there are no degrees of being alive, Matt. There are a whole</p>
<p>   lot of options. The need for taxation reform has not changed. The</p>
<p>   implications of losing this opportunity for tax reform should be</p>
<p>   fully understood by the Australian people and we'll certainly</p>
<p>   be spending a bit of time over this week driving home to the Australian</p>
<p>   community just what is at stake not only for our economy long-run</p>
<p>   but for our exporters, for the costs of doing business, for the</p>
<p>   States. And one of the consequences of losing tax reform is that</p>
<p>   an historic opportunity to provide a secure funding base for the</p>
<p>   States so that they can provide increased support for hospitals</p>
<p>   and government schools and police, that is also something that is</p>
<p>   at risk. That is why the State Premiers, Labor and Liberal alike,</p>
<p>   were all very willing to sign the agreement when we had our Premiers'</p>
<p>   Conference. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> And they've already expressed concern, I note, in the last</p>
<p>   24 hours. You were obviously surprised by Senator Harradine's</p>
<p>   decision. Had you ever considered, until you got his phone call,</p>
<p>   that he might say no? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> Well, of course I had. I have always regarded it as an on-balance</p>
<p>   thing with Senator Harradine. I think you will remember, and I draw</p>
<p>   your attention to the fact, that whenever I was asked whether I</p>
<p>   was confident I always said that I was hopeful but never over-confident</p>
<p>   because I knew he had reservations about a tax reform package that</p>
<p>   included a goods and services tax. He said so before the election.</p>
<p>   But he also said before the election that the Government was right</p>
<p>   to put the matter to the people and I hoped that the thing that,</p>
<p>   in the final analysis, would tilt him in our direction was the fact</p>
<p>   that we had been so honest and upfront and transparent and had made</p>
<p>   such full disclosure before the election. I think this is a very</p>
<p>   crucial point, Matt, that it's one thing to say, when you're</p>
<p>   in the Senate, no to a government when it hasn't been completely</p>
<p>   honest and forthcoming before a poll. I mean, if I'd just gone</p>
<p>   to the last election and said in general terms I'm going to</p>
<p>   reform the tax system, I'm going to cut people's tax and</p>
<p>   rationalise the indirect tax system and nothing more and then when</p>
<p>   the fine detail came it was the package, then I could understand</p>
<p>   people saying, hang on, you didn't tell us the whole</p>
<p>   thing.' But I knew people might say that and that is why I</p>
<p>   went to the last election with such a detailed package because I</p>
<p>   knew we weren't going to win a majority in our own right in</p>
<p>   the Senate. I mean, that's impossible under the present voting</p>
<p>   system as a result of the enlarged Senate from 1984. I knew, therefore,</p>
<p>   my best hope lay in telling the full thing to the Australian people</p>
<p>   and then saying to the Senate, we made full disclosure, you really</p>
<p>   do have a moral obligation to pass our legislation. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> But there was more to disclose, wasn't there? In the end</p>
<p>   you gave Senator Harradine most of what he wanted and then were</p>
<p>   prepared to talk more. I mean, you offered something like $1.5 billion</p>
<p>   more than what we were told at the election and that was for pensioners</p>
<p>   and all those things that the Democrats and Labor have been saying</p>
<p>   were getting dudded. </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> It's not what they want because if it was what they want</p>
<p>   they would now say they'll pass the package. We went to the</p>
<p>   election with a completely fair and balanced package and that is</p>
<p>   what we presented to the Parliament. And we offered some more compensation</p>
<p>   because people had said they wanted more, not because we believed</p>
<p>   it was essential but, I mean, it stands to reason if you want, in</p>
<p>   the face of questions people ask, if you want to get something through</p>
<p>   it's silly not to offer a little bit, what I call fine-tuning,</p>
<p>   a little bit extra. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> $1.5 billion and plus? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> In the overall scheme of the plan, Matt, it was not a large amount,</p>
<p>   although it's significant. But you now have a situation where</p>
<p>   the Government made full disclosure to the Australian people. We</p>
<p>   didn't hold anything back and we now face a situation where</p>
<p>   having been honest, having been candid and upfront and forthright,</p>
<p>   we are now facing the prospect that the package will not be accepted</p>
<p>   by the Senate. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> Well, why not do what Peter Reith did with Cheryl Kernot and,</p>
<p>   to use your words, offer a little bit to the Democrats, how about</p>
<p>   a little bit of food? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> Well, Matt, the Democrats' demands go far beyond food. The</p>
<p>   Democrats want not only exemptions in relation to food and other</p>
<p>   things but they also want a radical change to the tax scales that</p>
<p>   we propose. They have what I regard as strange ideas about what</p>
<p>   represents a high family income. We don't think family incomes</p>
<p>   around $50,000 a year are high these days with so many two-income</p>
<p>   families. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> If they restricted it to food, would that give you room to talk?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> I'm not going to get into a hypothetical with you on this</p>
<p>   or that. I'm simply making the observation that although of</p>
<p>   course we'll have talks with the Democrats  Peter Costello</p>
<p>   has already had discussions with Senator Lees  and we'll</p>
<p>   have further discussions with the Democrats, we're perfectly</p>
<p>   happy to do that, but I think the public should understand that</p>
<p>   there's a huge gulf between what the Government would regard</p>
<p>   as a reasonable maintenance of its package and what the Democrats</p>
<p>   really want. And certainly their objections in relation to the fuel</p>
<p>   proposals are quite unacceptable to the Government. We made certain</p>
<p>   commitments to the bush and they were made by me in the name of</p>
<p>   the whole Government and we certainly do not intend to walk away</p>
<p>   from the commitments that we have made to the bush. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> But the Democrats are saying that their fuel proposal only applies</p>
<p>   to the city, why would the bush care if bus drivers in the city</p>
<p>   have to pay more? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> ...she wants to hack into also will damage the bush if they're</p>
<p>   hacked into. So, look, Matt, there is a long agenda that the Democrats</p>
<p>   have and, as I say, we'll naturally talk to them, of course.</p>
<p>   And Peter Costello has already had, as I understand it, a number</p>
<p>   of lengthy discussions with Senator Lees... </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> This weekend? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> ... of course we'll talk, but I think people should understand</p>
<p>   that there is quite a significant gulf and there does come a point</p>
<p>   where a fundamental reform loses its fundamental elements and loses</p>
<p>   the long-term value to the economy if it is significantly eroded</p>
<p>   by too many compromises. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> Have you left your run a little late here? I mean, have you given</p>
<p>   up on Senator Harradine now? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> Well, Senator Harradine made it perfectly clear to me that in</p>
<p>   the end his fundamental objection to a GST was greater than any</p>
<p>   other consideration. Now, I must accept his word. I had hoped on</p>
<p>   balance that he would respect the Government's mandate and</p>
<p>   that that respect would be greater than his concerns, particularly</p>
<p>   after we made an increase in the compensation  we offered</p>
<p>   an increase in the compensation. So I don't think on the basis</p>
<p>   of anything that Senator Harradine said to me on Friday  he</p>
<p>   made it very clear to me when I said to him, Brian, does this</p>
<p>   mean you will vote against the third reading?' He said, yes,</p>
<p>   it does.' And then he subsequently made comments over the weekend</p>
<p>   about his feelings about the impersonal nature of a GST. I might</p>
<p>   remind him that a wholesale sales tax has an indirect and impersonal</p>
<p>   nature too. And he seeks guarantees that things won't be removed,</p>
<p>   well, there's no guarantee if the present taxation system continues</p>
<p>   that a future Labor government won't do what it did in 1993</p>
<p>   and increase wholesale sales tax without any compensation. There</p>
<p>   are no guarantees of anything in these areas if there's a change</p>
<p>   of government. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> Prime Minister, your timetable's already been thrown out.</p>
<p>   The train carriages may already be backing up in the tunnel, particularly</p>
<p>   if you're going to talk to the Democrats. How will this affect</p>
<p>   business certainty? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> Well, I think business will be very disappointed but I don't</p>
<p>   think it's going to unsettle the business community. Business</p>
<p>   wants tax reform but business has got to live with the political</p>
<p>   process as we have. And I don't see any signs at the moment,</p>
<p>   other than that we have a booming business sector around this country,</p>
<p>   we have the best economic conditions for 30 or 40 years. I don't</p>
<p>   find any signs of trepidation within the business community. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> And yet your Treasurer says taxes will go up, yet John Anderson</p>
<p>   says you've got room to move to give the tax cuts now? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> Well, quite clearly, Matt, if we don't reform the indirect</p>
<p>   tax system for the States the way we want to do it State taxes over</p>
<p>   time could go up and there's nothing inconsistent in those</p>
<p>   two propositions, nothing at all. There's always some capacity</p>
<p>   to make taxation changes without fundamental reform and that's</p>
<p>   all that John was referring to yesterday but you won't get</p>
<p>   $13 billion of personal tax cuts. You won't get $4.5 billion</p>
<p>   taken off exports. You won't get a reformation... </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> But you're not ruling out personal income tax of some form</p>
<p>   without the GST? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> Matt, I'm not contemplating anything without our package.</p>
<p>   I want to make it very clear that my commitment to getting the package</p>
<p>   remains very strong. The Treasurer's commitment remains very</p>
<p>   strong. We had a lengthy discussion about the matter yesterday and</p>
<p>   we both remain very strongly committed to this package. Now, we</p>
<p>   are disappointed that Senator Harradine decided on balance not to</p>
<p>   accept the mandate we were given by the people last October and</p>
<p>   we'll now pursue alternatives. We'll talk to the Australian</p>
<p>   Democrats but I warn and caution immediately that I don't believe</p>
<p>   it's likely that we can find common ground because the demands</p>
<p>   that they are making are way beyond what we could contemplate without</p>
<p>   fundamentally altering the package. </p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> And in the end you're not frightened of a double dissolution</p>
<p>   on this issue. </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> Matt, I said on Friday that all things remain live options. We</p>
<p>   shouldn't have to go to another election. We fought an election</p>
<p>   on the GST last October. We are the only government since federation</p>
<p>   that has gone to the people with such a detailed alternative plan</p>
<p>   down to the last decimal point, describing all of the changes we</p>
<p>   want to make. We put it all on the table knowing full well that</p>
<p>   we wouldn't win control of both Houses but thinking in good</p>
<p>   faith that if we disclosed everything to the Australian people and</p>
<p>   won the election then we would at least be able to say to the Senators</p>
<p>   we've made full disclosure, we got our mandate, you have an</p>
<p>   obligation to pass it. Could I just say one other thing about the</p>
<p>   Senate. I heard this morning that Mr Beattie and other Premiers</p>
<p>   are calling for a Premiers' Conference. There's no point</p>
<p>   in having another Premiers' Conference. We had one in April.</p>
<p>   What I suggest the Premiers do is to have conferences of their Senators,</p>
<p>   the Senators from each of their States and to line them up, Labor</p>
<p>   and Liberal alike, and tell them the facts of life for their State</p>
<p>   revenues and their State finances. Mr Beattie should tell the Queensland</p>
<p>   Labor Party Senators that he signed on to a deal that will massively</p>
<p>   advantage Queensland for years into the future and that if his Labor</p>
<p>   Senators vote against that plan and his Democrat Senators vote against</p>
<p>   that plan they will be hurting Queensland and hurting the people</p>
<p>   of Queensland. And I would offer the same advice to Mr Carr in New</p>
<p>   South Wales, to Mr Court in Western Australia who has been an enthusiastic</p>
<p>   supporter of our program and I acknowledge that because there's</p>
<p>   a lot at stake in this for the States. The original idea of the</p>
<p>   Senate was that it was meant to represent the interest of the States.</p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> Do you need a referendum, do you think, another question on the</p>
<p>   Senate powers? </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> What we want is some acceptance of the responsibilities that Senators</p>
<p>   have both in relation to taking notice of the decision of the voters</p>
<p>   in elections and also in looking after the interests of their States.</p>
<p> PEACOCK: </p>
<p> Prime Minister, thanks very much for joining us. </p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p> You're welcome. </p>
<p> [ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
