<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18891</transcript-id>
    <title>Boosting The Skills Of The Laos Workforce</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Vientiane, Laos</p>
<p>Workers in Laos will be given training and skills to help their country to tackle key development challenges, including improving women's empowerment and helping people with disability.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister today announced in Vientiane the establishment of a new Laos-Australia Institute to provide comprehensive training to Government, civil society and the private sector.</p>
<p>The Institute  -  opening in 2013  -  will deliver $20 million in funding over four years to administer this training.</p>
<p>Education is one of the best investments the Government can make. Education transforms people's lives and helps to build a new generation of global leaders.</p>
<p>Australia is proud to support the Government of Laos in their efforts to achieve this major development priority.</p>
<p>This program will help selected organisations improve their human resource development planning - leading to more efficient delivery of basic services.</p>
<p>Australia, through AusAID, provides Laos with around 45 scholarships for study in Australia each year. To date, more than 1000 Lao people have been provided with the opportunity to study in Australia through Australian scholarships.</p>
<p>Many now occupy senior positions in government and private enterprise, and are playing leadership roles in Laos' development.</p>
<p>In addition to managing the Australia Awards in Laos, the Institute will provide at least 280 scholarships to students from disadvantaged backgrounds for study in the country's own institutions.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
