<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7948</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF JOINT NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PREMIER WAYNE GOSS, BARRON FALLS, CAIRNS, 10 MARCH 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007948.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF JOINT NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PREMIER WAYNE<br />
GOSS, BA1RON FALLSF CAIRNS, 10 MARCH 1990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister, two weeks today the Liberals<br />
are apparently gearing up for a fairly major offensive.<br />
O The coalition has a series of plans underway for a<br />
attack advertising. Are you worried that they're going<br />
to start zeroing in on capital gains tax?<br />
PM~: NO, I'm not worried. As always the conservatives<br />
campaign is based upon an insult to the intelligence of<br />
the Australian electorate. We've had a dry run of It in<br />
the last week with Mr Peacock conjuring up this $ 14<br />
billion hole from the forward estimates. It's been<br />
dismissed as ludicrous by every commentator because he<br />
said inflation and growth applies to one side of the<br />
national account but not to the other. I mean, it's been<br />
dismissed as a pathetic and dishonest attempt by a<br />
rattled leader of the conservatives to divert attention<br />
from his own incapacity to answer the real issues. And<br />
the major issue is where the money is coming from. Now I<br />
understand that they're going to run up a scare campaign<br />
on superannuation. The facts there are quite simple. He<br />
started of f by misrepresenting the position of the<br />
O Australian electorate as to the number of people covered<br />
by capital gains. The facts are very simple something<br />
like 64,000 people paying capital gains, significantly<br />
lose than one percent of Australian taxpayers and the<br />
-simple and indisputable truth that he's trying to hide<br />
from the Australian people with this scare campaign that<br />
is allegedly coming up, is this that billions of<br />
dollars that would otherwise go into the public revenue<br />
for spending on education, health, roads, defence and all<br />
the needs of the Australian people, those billions of<br />
dollars would be deliberately taken out of the public<br />
revenue by the conservatives and shovelled into the<br />
pockets of less than one percent of the wealthiest<br />
taxpayers in Australia. Now in their desperate attempt<br />
to disguise that fact they will go on this scare<br />
campaign. It will do them no good it's about time the<br />
conservatives understood that the Australian electorate<br />
is intelligent and they won't buy this deception.<br />
JOURNALIST: a number of people still haven't decided<br />
which way they're going to vote. </p>
<p>PM: Well, I don't either worry about that, nor am I<br />
surprised by it. I think that for people to wait and<br />
until election day and sum up all the considerations that<br />
will be put forward is, is quite an acceptable approach<br />
and I may say that I'm very content to allow those who<br />
are thinking about the electorate to wait up until<br />
election day and ask themselves some questions. Ask<br />
themselves the questions about interest rates, because<br />
now it's accepted that under the policies of my<br />
Government, interest rates are coming down. The banks<br />
have said so and it's equally clear that interest rates<br />
must rise under the conservatives because if you have a<br />
wages explosion and you bust the budget surplus, with a<br />
blowout of at least $ 6 billion, it's inevitable that<br />
interest rates must rise. So let them ask themselves<br />
that question. In this sort of environment where I'm so<br />
pleased to be with my friend and colleague, Wayne Goes,<br />
Sin this beautiful natural environment of Australia, let<br />
them ask themselves the question what is it that Wayne<br />
GOES and I are going to be doing today? Answer we are<br />
going to be signing an agreement between two Labor<br />
Governments, both committed to the preservation of the<br />
natural heritage of Australia. What was the alternative?<br />
The alternative was at the Federal level, the<br />
conservative parties who opposed my decision and the<br />
decision of Labor to save the wet tropics of Queensland,<br />
the rainforests of this area. They opposed it, they<br />
wanted the logging to go ahead. They were hand in glove<br />
with Wayne Gos', opponents here in Queensland and before<br />
Wayne came in I had to not only defeat the conservatives<br />
at the national level which we did, but then we had to<br />
fight with the conservatives here who wanted to challenge<br />
us in the High Court and when Wayne won on the 2nd of<br />
December he was in tune with the national feeling and the<br />
feeling of the people of Queensland they've withdrawn<br />
that challenge and today we are going to be signing this<br />
historic arrangements for the joint management of this<br />
and priceless heritage of Australia. So let the<br />
people ask themselves these questions.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister why is it that your letter to<br />
Mr Goss about this is dated today and Mr Goss' reply is<br />
dated yesterday?<br />
PM: Well that's a good question we'd better get a<br />
synchronisation of the dates I guess. The important<br />
thing is that the past of confrontation between the<br />
conservative government of Queensland and the<br />
environmentally conscious government of Australia is<br />
brought to an end and the interchange of letters<br />
constitutes an agreement between us, between two<br />
governments committed to what the overwhelming majority<br />
of Australians want and that is the protection of our<br />
priceless national heritage.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are these agreements aimed at helping people<br />
decide how to vote? </p>
<p>PM: No these agreements will perhaps have a bonus result<br />
of indicating to people where the commitment to<br />
protecting the heritage is but what we are doing is<br />
giving effect to what we said we would do, that is to<br />
replace the antagonism of the conservative government in<br />
Queensland in the past to protecting the environment to<br />
an agreement which sets out the management plan for the<br />
future in which we will co-operate jointly to ensure the<br />
management and protection of this area.<br />
GOSS: I just want to say something in response to this<br />
point over here and that's that the Prime Minister and I<br />
.0Just settle it, that we would get it out of the<br />
courts and that there would be a good compensation<br />
package for Queensland negotiating that. There was a<br />
breakdown in those negotiations. Now for the last two<br />
weeks we've been trying to put this agreement together<br />
O and I asked, I asked earlier this week, for a draft of<br />
the letter, the proposals forthcoming from the<br />
Commonwealth. That draft of the letter that we could<br />
expect to be forthcoming was faxed to my office at<br />
Parliament House yesterday afternoon. When I got that I<br />
drafted our response. Now my response was drafted<br />
yesterday on the basis of the, the draft fax I got from<br />
the Prime Minister's office about what I could expect<br />
today. Nothing in the dates at all. It's taken two<br />
weeks to knock that out.<br />
JOURNALIST: What caused the breakdown?<br />
GOSS: No breakdown at all. We'd agreed, the Prime<br />
Minister and I had agreed on the broad compensation<br />
arrangement in terms of capital works and ongoing<br />
funding arrangements. I think there might have been some<br />
tight bugger in the bowels down there in Canberra<br />
somewhere but, as a result of that, their $ 7 million<br />
became $ 10 million, our $ 12 million came down to<br />
million. We have dollar for dollar on the ongoing<br />
funding arrangements. Bob said before people should be<br />
asking themselves what the question is, the supplementary<br />
question is are the people of Queensland getting a good<br />
deal for the wet tropics? The supplementary answer is<br />
yes. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, Mr Peacock says your Government's<br />
attitude to the ethnic vote is sickening and<br />
sanctimonious. What's your view about that?<br />
PM: Well, what we're hearing now increasingly are the<br />
utterances of a very desperate leader of the Liberal<br />
Party. I notice him parading around there saying he's<br />
won the first three weeks of the campaign. Just as after<br />
the Great Debate he trotted out and said he'd won the<br />
debate. I mean, for someone to have to be getting up and<br />
saying these things he won the debate, held won the<br />
first three weeks and now to attack us on the question<br />
about the ethnic vote. I mean, it's a very sad </p>
<p>reflection on the state of a very, very rattled Leader of<br />
the Opposition. The facts are very, very simple. it is<br />
this Prime minister who from day one of his Prime<br />
Ministership, has recognised the multicultural nature of<br />
Australia, has recognised the enormous contribution that<br />
is being made from people who have come from 130<br />
different homelands to make Australia their own. I've<br />
said, and I emphasised it particularly in the<br />
Bicentennial year, that there was only one thing which<br />
determined whether you're an Australian and that is do<br />
you have a commitment to Australia? And I have, in all<br />
my public life before I went into the Parliament, I've<br />
had an identification with the people who've come to this<br />
Country because I know that this is the biggest decision<br />
that any person from another country can make. They<br />
can't make a bigger decision than to leave their own<br />
country of origin and come here and make this their own.<br />
And these people who've given so much to enlarging and<br />
O enriching Australia deserve, not the cynicism of a<br />
rattled Leader of the Opposition, they deserve what they<br />
have consistently received from me before I went into<br />
Public life and since i've been in the Parliament and<br />
since I've been Prime Minister that is encouragement<br />
and support, so that they can at one and the same time<br />
remember with pride the best of the traditions and<br />
cultures of the countries from which they come and to<br />
make a contribution to the growing and broadening and<br />
deepening and enriching of the Australia of which they<br />
are part.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think this is an echo of the debate<br />
involving Mr Howard over multiculturalism?<br />
PM: I don't want to go to that because you will notice<br />
that I have eschewed very deliberately since that time<br />
trying to do or say anything which would arouse those<br />
fires again. I believe that that was an aberration on<br />
the pert of the then Leader of the Opposition and I don't<br />
want to go to those elements of the Opposition who may<br />
still embrace that sort of position. I rather take the<br />
view that this country overwhelming understands its<br />
multicultural nature. The fact that some 40 percent of<br />
Australians this very day were either themselves born in<br />
another country or have a parent who was born in another<br />
country. Those are the realities and intelligent and<br />
responsible leadership demands that we recognise those<br />
facts and draw on the strengths of those facts.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister will you be raising with<br />
the Thai Government the proposals to turn the Burma death<br />
railway into a tourist ride? Apparently they are going<br />
to have actors playing Australian POWs the story is<br />
on the front page of the Courier Mail, you may not have<br />
seen it.<br />
PM: I haven't seen it, Peter. When I get myself<br />
acquainted with it, we'll see what the appropriate<br />
response should be.-</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, given your comments about<br />
the intelligence of the Australian electorate and the<br />
fact that parti~ cularly in western Australia and Victoria<br />
voters will distinguish between State and Federal issues,<br />
do you believe voters and Queensland should make the same<br />
distinction? PM; Well, in Queensland you've got this position that<br />
there were many reasons why I'm standing next to Wayne<br />
Goss, the* Labor Premier now of Queensland, many reasons.<br />
The most important ones are the intrinsic and<br />
qualities of Wayne Goss and of Labor, but also part of<br />
the reason why he's Premier is that you had corruption,<br />
corruption in Queensland. No suggestion that you had<br />
corruption when you talk about the other States, no<br />
su. ggestion of venality or corruption in Victoria no<br />
suggestion, there has been no suggestion on the part of<br />
S politicians of venality or corruption. None. None at<br />
all. Incompetence perhaps, yes, bad decisions but no<br />
suggestion of corruption. Here in this State and one of<br />
the reasons why Goss is Premier is not only his own<br />
intrinsic merits, but because the people were nick of the<br />
corruption of conservatism and the National Party which<br />
is seeking the support of people here in Queensland is<br />
the same National Party which inflicted corruption as<br />
well as incompetence on this State for some 30 years.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the metal workers, do you..<br />
managed to intervene in that yet at all or<br />
PM: No, no, I may over the weekend make a phone call, I<br />
00yet.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Beg your pardon?<br />
S JOURNALIST: What do you think of Mr Campbell's actions?<br />
PM: I've got no commnent to make upon them. I've made<br />
the general point about the fact that the Accord has<br />
delivered to this country, despite the predictions of its<br />
imminent demise which have been going on for seven years,<br />
the Accord has delivered 1.6 million new jobs, five times<br />
faster than the conservatives could ever or did deliver,<br />
twice as fast as the rest of the world, a 60 percent<br />
reduction in industrial disputes, a record level<br />
( train whistle sounds, toot toot)<br />
PM ( cont): That's a supporting hoot a record level of<br />
profits which has gone into a record level of investment.,<br />
That is the achievement of the Accord and it is a, a<br />
silliness in the extreme to say, look there might be a<br />
stoppage for a day in one industry. What does that mean<br />
about the respective industrial relations policies of the </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
