<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10403</transcript-id>
    <title>Address at  Dinner hosted by the Foreign Policy Association, New York</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/06/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010403.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>June 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER V<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
DINNER HOSTED BY THE FOREIGN POLICY ASSOCIATION<br />
NEW YORK<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
Thank you very much Mr John Merow for those very kind and warm words of introduction. If you want a<br />
job as my PR adviser in Australia after those very kind words, the offer is open.<br />
Can I say to acknowledge the presence of the Australian Ambassador to the United States, Andrew<br />
Peacock, another old political friend of mine, Michael Baume, the Consul-General in New York, very well<br />
Michael, and the other distinguished guests, and<br />
may I particularly acknowledge the presence of Mr Paul Volcker, the former Chairman of the Federal<br />
Reserve system of the United States may I say a mean whose steady and courageous leadership of the Fed<br />
at a time of very high inflation, both here and around the world, laid the sure foundations for the greater and<br />
more consistent economic prosperity that the United States and the western world is now enjoying.<br />
My friends, I am very greatly honoured and personally delighted to have the opportunity of addressing this<br />
joint gathering of the Australian American Association and the very prestigious Foreign Policy Association<br />
here in New York.<br />
I do so as the Prime Minister of a nation.... ( interjection).. but ladies and gentlemen, the relationship<br />
between Australia and the United States is a relationship which I am very proud as the Prime Minister of<br />
Australia to recognise and to endorse as amongst the most important of all of the bilateral relationships that<br />
Australia has around the world.<br />
The relationship that Australia has with the United States is enduring. Its foundations are built hard and fast<br />
on the bedrock of the values and aspirations that our two societies share.<br />
We both celebrate the role of the individual and the spirit of private enterprise. We both share an<br />
unequivocal commitment to democracy, to free speech, the freedom of the press and the independence and<br />
the authority of the rule of law. We both believe in the right of every citizen, regardless of colour, race or<br />
creed, to equality of opportunity to dignity and to individual self respect.<br />
We share common views about the kind of society and sort of world we wish to bequeath to our children.<br />
And all of this has been given very eloquent expression in the history of our two nations. It continues to be<br />
given expression in the current efforts of our two nations to shape a future for our societies in which all have<br />
the scope to achieve his or her ambitions and to shape the world in which there is space for every nation to<br />
fujlfil its potential in peace and stability.<br />
Our common endeavours are reflected in the shared sacrifices made by our men and women in war. I was<br />
given a poignant reminder of this history when I visited the Arlington Cemetery last Saturday. There I<br />
visited the joint grave of an Australian pilot, Francis Milne, and an American pilot, Joseph Paul. They died<br />
in a fighter plane which crashed during the war in Papua New Guinea in 1942. They were found in 1987<br />
and, as their remains could not be separated, they were buried together in Arlington. </p>
<p>Our common endeavours to create a peaceful and prosperous world continued in the decades that followed<br />
World War 11. We cooperated in establishing new global political and trade institutions, the United Nations<br />
and the GAIT the predecessor to the World Trade Organisation so putting in place codes of acceptable<br />
international conduct. We will work together in strengthening APEC the Asia Pacific Economic<br />
Cooperation Forum so that it fulfils its potential in sustaining the Asia Pacific's growth and stability.<br />
Our great alliance, the AiNZUS alliance, founded in the Cold War and now approaching its fifth decade in<br />
operation, will help preserve the stability of the Asia-Pacific region. Last year we held in Australia the<br />
largest joint military exercise for many years, involving 25,000 men.<br />
The business community so well represented here tonight has played an immense role in the building of the<br />
relationship between Australia and the United States. You are the largest single foreign investor in the<br />
Australia economy and therefore a vital underpinning to the current prosperity of the Australian people.<br />
As John was kind enough to say in my still relatively new government has introduced a number of major<br />
economic relforms. But let me just take a moment to say some very basic things about the character of the<br />
Australian economy and in the process let me give you some key facts which are important to any<br />
understanding of contemporary economic conditions in my country. According to the latest OECD outlook<br />
in 1997 and 1998 Australia's real economic real economic growth and employment growth will be higher<br />
than in any of the G-7 nations and higher than the OECD average.<br />
Our business investment growth will be higher than in any of the G-7 nations and higher than the OECD<br />
average Our inflation level will be lower than the G-7 and OECD averages.<br />
Our government outlays as a percentage of GDP will be the third lowest in the OECD after the United<br />
States and Korea.<br />
Our public debt to GDP ratio will be the third lowest in the OECD area.<br />
Might I say by way of emphasis that whereas Australia would meet the criteria for membership of Europe's<br />
economic and monetary union, only one European country currently meets those criteria namely<br />
Luxembourg. But I hasten to add that we have absolutely no intention of lodging an application to join the<br />
union. The United States remains the largest source of our imports. Your largest bilateral trade surplus is with<br />
Australia. It is in relative terms larger than your deficit with Japan. I should remind you, of course, that<br />
we have one or two ideas for opening up the US agricultural market which would improve our trade<br />
balance. Australia has 40 per cent as much invested in the United States as the United States does in Australia<br />
which for our relative size is a major commitment. The output of Australian-owned companies in your<br />
country is now larger than our exports to the United States.<br />
Our societies and our economies face similar challenges in dealing with technological revolution and<br />
globalisatiori. We share the aim of equipping our citizens, especially our young, to take advantage of the<br />
new horizons that are being opened up. We learn from each other's experiences. My conversations with<br />
President Clinton and </p>
<p>Dr Greenspan again reinforced for me how important the great flexibility of your huge economy has been to<br />
your extraordinary success in the area of job creation.<br />
These shared values and interests, and the friendship which is based on them, are too valuable ever to take<br />
for granted. And I say on behalf of the Australian Government, and I know it is reciprocated in the United<br />
States, that we will never take the association for granted.<br />
Last year for the first time ever the Defence Secretary of the United States, the Secretary of State and the<br />
Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staffs were altogether in Australia for our annual alliance talks. President<br />
Clinton came to Australia last year. He and his wife received a spontaneous welcome from the Australian<br />
people that demonstrated their high regard that the United States retains in our nation, and how warm is our<br />
friendship towards all of you.<br />
I take the opportunity on the occasion of my first visit to your country as Prime Minister to reaffirm my<br />
government's strong commitment to the alliance and to our enduring friendship with the United States and<br />
its people.<br />
Our alliance and our friendship remain as relevant as ever. Australia and the United States have a shared<br />
destiny in the Asia-Pacific region. The effectiveness of our cooperation will have an influential bearing on<br />
the future course of that region.<br />
Australia's approach to Asia has a strong bipartisan element. If there is any difference on the part of my<br />
government with our predecessors in government, it lies in my objection to the impression that was<br />
sometimes given in the past that Australia had to pursue an Asia-only policy and downgrade the weight it<br />
gave to associations with Europe and the United States. My own view has always been that Australia does<br />
not need to choose between her history and her geography.<br />
Our links with the United States are a vital element of Australia's wider association with the Asia-Pacific<br />
region. Australia's geography, the extent of her economic integration with the countries of Asia and the<br />
human ties created by the presence in Australia of many Asian migrant communities, underline the huge<br />
scale of Australia's national interests in the Asian area.<br />
Sixty per cent of our exports go to East Asian countries. Seven of our top 10 export markets are in East<br />
Asia. We have long played an important role in the region. Japan's first trade agreement after the Second World<br />
War was signed with Australia in 1957.<br />
Australia is the world's largest minerals trader, and has played a major role in the industrialisation of Japan<br />
and Korea. We are now playing a similar role in fuelling China's growth. We are an important source of<br />
the region's food. We are a major destination for Japanese investment and officially at least the largest<br />
destination for Chinese foreign investment after Hong Kong.<br />
We have close and active defence relationships with a wider range of countries in Asia than perhaps any<br />
other country. In particular, we have a security agreement with South-East Asia's largest country,<br />
Indonesia, and participate in the Five Power Defence Arrangements with Singapore and Malaysia. </p>
<p>We now have substantial communities from Asian countries in our country. They have made a tremendous<br />
contribution to Australia. They have enriched and diversified Australia's culture. Their entrepreneurial<br />
drive has strengthened our economy and they have earnt a highly respected place in our society.<br />
Australians, especially young Australians, are learning more about the enormous diversity of our<br />
neighbourhood. There are more people studying Japanese in Australia than any other country outside China<br />
and Korea, and there are many tens of thousands of Asian students in Australian institutions at any one time.<br />
These growing people-to-people links especially among the younger generations will have an enormous<br />
and positive influence on all areas of Australia's relations with its regions into the next century.<br />
The role of the United States has been crucial to the unprecedented stability and growth that the Asia Pacific<br />
region has achieved. I believe it would be an error of historic proportions for the United States to diminish<br />
the level of its engagement in the Asia Pacific region. It would profoundly affect events in the region for the<br />
worse. And I am also convinced that it is in the interest of the United States to remain deeply engaged in the Asia<br />
Pacific region.<br />
The United States military presence has provided the security which allows the countries of the region to<br />
focus on economic development. United States capital, technology and management skills will continue to<br />
be vital in sustaining the region's growth. The United States for example is still the largest or second largest<br />
market for all East Asian countries except Brunei.<br />
The traffic is two-way. Nearly 40 per cent of US trade is now with East Asia, twice that with Europe. The<br />
countries of ASEAN as a group are now the United States' third largest export market.<br />
We welcome the fact that on crucial issues the United States is exercising the leadership that is necessary in<br />
the region.<br />
It continues to play a vital role in providing nuclear deterrence. It has taken the lead in persuading North<br />
Korea to abandon its nuclear programme.<br />
And successive administrations have kept the key US alliance relationships in the region with Japan, Korea<br />
and Australia. in good repair. US decisions after successive defence reviews to retain a fo rward-deployed<br />
military capability in the region have underpinned stability.<br />
President Clinton is working hard and successfully with the Japanese Prime Minister,<br />
Mr Hashimoto, to keep the US-Japan relationship strong.<br />
The administration's commitment to deeper engagement with China and its disavowal of notions of<br />
containment and confrontation are central to the region's future stability. As President Clinton said during<br />
his visit to Australia, the direction China takes in years to come, the way it defines its greatness in the future,<br />
will help to decide whether the next century is one of conflict or cooperation. A stable, open and<br />
prosperous China is in the interests of all of us.<br />
The United States convened in 1993 the first APEC leaders' meeting, thus consolidating APE * C as the<br />
region's most important body and the only forum where the leaders of the region's major powers can meet. </p>
<p>The United States has played an important part in maintaining the momentum for ongoing trade<br />
liberalisation in the region and it must continue to do so.<br />
In every single one of these areas, Australia has been a good and faithful partner. In each case we have<br />
given practical, financial or strong public backing to the United States. When it matters we have been a<br />
friend and allie prepared to stand up and be counted.<br />
One of the strengths I believe Australia brings to the partnership with the United States is the different<br />
perspective fr-om which she views the region. We are located on the other side of the Pacific. Al1though it is<br />
not too far away. It is only about five full length feature movies away from the west coast of the United<br />
States. We are geographically closer to the Asian countries than is the United States. But we would not<br />
claim any monopoly of wisdom but we are particularly aware of their diversity, and perhaps of those nations<br />
and perhaps where they are coming from and what their aspirations are.<br />
Australia and the United States have fundamental interests and objectives in common. We will both always<br />
stand up for the values and principles on which our own societies are based.<br />
In responding, for example, to human rights shortcomings in a number of countries in the region, our view is<br />
that we must take full account of the remarkable progress and change that are taking place in the Asia<br />
Pacific region. We need also to take account of the cultural diversity in Asia and the self-confidence and<br />
justifiable pride that the nations of Asia have in their achievements in particular the dramatic shift in the<br />
number of families which have moved from poverty to a more secure middle class.<br />
The pace and scale of change in Asia in the past two decades have been unparalleled. From a region<br />
preoccupied by internal and external threats and poverty, East Asia has become the engine of world<br />
economic growth.<br />
During the past decade, more than half the world's economic growth has come from East Asia. The region<br />
now accounts for just under a third of global output. The region's importance to the global economy will<br />
grow: the World Bank, for example, estimates growth at over seven per cent a year in the period to 2004.<br />
Apart from one or two anachronistic regimes such as those in Burma and North Korea, the economic<br />
transformation of the countries of East Asia has produced enormous improvements in the living standards of<br />
ordinary people, stability that is unprecedented in their modern history, and in most cases more open<br />
societies. Many factors have contributed to these developments. A principal one of course is the natural talent and<br />
enterprise of the people of the region. A second is the stability in the region, to which as I have mentioned,<br />
the United States has made such an important contribution. A third factor that we should acknowledge is<br />
the leadership that many of these countries have had.<br />
Under President Soeharto's leadership for example, Indonesia the fourth most populous country in the<br />
world has achieved progress in building a nation that is nothing short of remarkable when you consider the<br />
thousands of islands and hundreds of ethnicities that comprise Indonesia. Stability in South East Asia is in<br />
no small measure due to Indonesia's success and to the economic and strategic directions it has chosen.<br />
Under first Lee Kuan Yew, and now Goh Chok Tong, Singaporeans have come to enjoy one of the world's<br />
highest living standards. </p>
<p>6<br />
At a time when Japan's economy needs to be deregulated, Japan is fortunate to have a forward-looking and<br />
decisive leader in Mr Hashimoto. In China, President Jiang Zemin has reiterated his commitment to the<br />
liberal economic policies first introduced by Deng Ziaoping.<br />
The modernis; ation and liberalisation of East Asian economies are moving fast. While significant barriers to<br />
our exports remain, tariffs are dropping throughout the region.<br />
These are important trends. They create internal dynamics and forces which are more likely to produce the<br />
results we seek than any outside pressure. They are giving the people of the region greater scope to fulfil<br />
their aspirations.<br />
Our approach must be to encourage these trends, to reinforce the growing integration of the countries of the<br />
region into the world economy, and to encourage the broadening and deepening of their relationships with<br />
countries outside the region. This is overwhelmingly in our strategic Interests, in our economic interests,<br />
and in the interests of the peoples of the region itself<br />
Against this background, may I say, that the most effective way of promoting respect for human rights and<br />
freedoms in the region will be in the context of broad and active bilateral relationships and through dialogue.<br />
We are not naive or starry-eyed, but we believe that a cooperative bilateral approach dealing with specific<br />
human rights issues will produce more results than generalised public hectoring or lecturing and<br />
confrontation. As our close neighbour, Indonesia is of particular importance to Australia. Indonesia is going through a<br />
period of generational change and economic and political transition. Indonesia does have human rights<br />
problems. A~ t the same time, in the last two decades, the number of its population living in poverty has<br />
declined from 60 per cent to 15 per cent. It is in our interests that Indonesia see through this period while<br />
maintaining its stability and the overall trend towards a more open economy and a more open society. That<br />
means giving it both support and space to work through its challenges.<br />
We do remain particularly concerned about the human rights situation in East Timor. A confrontational<br />
approach, however, and refusal to accept its place as an integral part of Indonesia, will not bring the right<br />
results for those we wish to assist.<br />
Earlier today Hong Kong became part of the People's Republic of China. It would be unrealistic to imagine<br />
that this historically significant event will not bring changes in the former British colony.<br />
However, there is no doubt. China's best interests lie in keeping to the one country-two systems<br />
commitment it made in relation to Hong Kong. China has good reason to fulfil its promises to retain Hong<br />
Kong's substantial autonomy and its existing freedoms. Australia, like other countries in the region, has<br />
important interests in Hong Kong which give us a stake in Hong Kong's success. We have made our<br />
position clear to the Chinese government. China's management of Hong Kong will have a strong bearing on<br />
how it is viewed by the rest of the world.<br />
China's growth is giving it greater influence. Naturally, it would like to define, to the extent it can, its own<br />
terms for its increasing engagement in the region's and the world's institutions.<br />
Yet the reality is that China's growth depends more than ever on its access to the markets, capital and<br />
technology available in the rest of the world. It has an increasing interest in joining and strengthening global<br />
institutions such as the World Trade Organisation. </p>
<p>China must be allowed a fair say in the development of these institutions. Its involvement must also be on<br />
terms that strengthen them and do not damage the interests of others.<br />
All of the countries in the Asia-Pacific region have an interest in cooperating to maintain the stability and<br />
prosperity of the region and a responsibility to do so.<br />
The unparalleled position of power and influence that the United States has occupied since the end of the<br />
Cold War, however, gives it a particular degree of responsibility.<br />
The United States has the capacity to exercise that responsibility. The predictions of decline made of the<br />
United States in the 1980s and early 1990s have proved totally groundless. To the immense satisfaction and<br />
admiration of friends such as Australia, the dynamism and inventiveness of the US economy and the United<br />
States people and the strengths of its society have won through.<br />
Australia for its part will seek to ensure that its partnership with the United States continues to make the<br />
most effective contribution to the region's stability and prosperity into the next century.<br />
And ladies and gentlemen, may I conclude in saying on a personal note that this is the twelfth occasion that I<br />
have visited your country since I first came here as a relative new graduate into the profession of law in<br />
Australia in 1964. On every occasion I have found welcome. On every occasion I have been impressed<br />
with the openness and the vitality and the friendship of the people of the United States. It is a matter of<br />
particular pride and personal satisfaction to me that I have the opportunity of addressing this gathering as<br />
the Prime Minister of Australia, as the leader of a country whose close association with the United States<br />
has underpinned not only our security but also our stability. But most importantly it has given us an<br />
opportunity to share values across the Pacific, to share those fundamental beliefs of personal liberty, of<br />
individual effort, of ajust society and a belief that it is appropriate always to aspire to the ideal of a better<br />
world. The United States and Australia have been through much travail in the past. We have shared many bitter<br />
experiences, we have stood shoulder to shoulder in many parts of the world in the defence of freedom and in<br />
the promotion of liberty.<br />
I like to believe that on all occasions we have done it with a generous attitude to other parts of the world<br />
and in a common belief that the values that we share and the values we have sought to defend are worth<br />
sharing and worth defending. And if we can continue that partnership into the future I believe that we in our<br />
different parts of the world and together in the Asia Pacific region can play a very important role in building<br />
a better and a more prosperous and a more stable world in the remarkable proficious circumstances that the<br />
end of the Cold War and what might be the dawn of a new era of economic growth and economic stability<br />
has given to both our societies and to all of the societies of the world. I thank you most warmly for your<br />
gracious invitation tonight. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
