<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9019</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS, RADIO 2UE, SYDNEY, 3 NOVEMBER 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009019.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS, RADIO 2UE, SYDNEY, 3 NOVEMBER 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
JL: My guest is the Prime Minister of Australia Paul Keating, good morning and<br />
welcome.<br />
PM: Good morning, John.<br />
JL: How are you?<br />
PM: Good, thank you, it's good to be here.<br />
JL: Caught in the traffic?<br />
PM: Just for a few minutes.<br />
JL: What is your reaction to the polls showing Bronwyn Bishop at 2-1 winner over<br />
John Hewson as the Liberal leader?<br />
PM: I think it is a matter of what John Hewson's reaction is, that's the more important<br />
one.<br />
JL: No, I think yours would be much more interesting than his.<br />
PM: This is a matter for the Liberal Party to worry about. There seems to be a lot of<br />
angst within the Liberal Party about Mrs Bishop. Their complaint seems to be that<br />
someone without any proven policy ability, without any ideas has come so far and<br />
is annoying so many of them.<br />
JL: How do you think she has come so far?<br />
PM: I think basically there is a vacuum in conservative politics and when there is a hole<br />
in this game, someone generally will try and fill it. </p>
<p>IL: How would you fancy lining up against her in the House. It would be tough<br />
wouldn't it, you couldn't call her ' scumbag' or ' vermin' or any of your favoured<br />
terms could you?<br />
PM: No but I don't use those I've used ' scumbag' once in my life.<br />
IL: Only once?<br />
PM: Only once, and never heard the end of it.<br />
IL: ' Vermin'? Well you never will.<br />
PM: The thing about it is, Bronwyn's speed is to attack public servants under privilege.<br />
It is a bit different in the House of Representatives. In the House of<br />
Representatives we actually strike back it is a little different.<br />
IL: And you think it might be different for her?<br />
PM: Look, the House of Representatives is like a big blotting paper. Senators mostly<br />
disappear whenever they arrive there.<br />
IL: I see.<br />
PM: You've seen that with Fred Chaney and a few others big noises in the Senate,<br />
hardly a whimper out of them in the House of Representatives. I mean, State<br />
Premiers have disappeared in there, there are all sorts of people who have<br />
disappeared in there. So, I wouldn't be too concerned about that. I think this is a<br />
matter basically for the conservative side of politics and the issue is, I think, John<br />
Hewson lost the 1993 election and that means that all the policy issues he ran on..<br />
that is, his abandoning of them have left him in a rather incredible position.<br />
IL: Why do you think they found themselves in trouble? Do you think that the<br />
conservatives moved too far to the ight and, as they moved to the ight, you lot<br />
moved to the ight and took the centre ground, and now I don't think there is any<br />
alternative but for them to head severely back to the left.<br />
PM: The thing is John Hewson won't lead. On the republic he says you tell us why we<br />
have got to change, you explain to us why we have to change and if you explain<br />
well enough, we may follow. In other words, the onus is on you the Labor<br />
government, you lead. The same on Mabo. We won't have a policy, we'll see<br />
what the government comes up with. So, it is a case of you lead, we don't provide<br />
any leadership and we'll obstruct wherever we get an opportunity. Now, I think<br />
that is engendering its own destruction within side the Coalition. I don't think they<br />
have mapped out ( inaudible) they have for themselves and John Hewson has<br />
not mapped out a place for the conservative parties in Australia. They have no </p>
<p>ideological or policy bearings, whether it be in social policy, in economic policy or<br />
the greater issues it just seems to me that they have lost their way.<br />
JL: Yes, it seemed to me the only one who was prepared to talk out about Mabo on<br />
the conservative side was Sir John Gorton, how did you react to Sir John's<br />
statements?<br />
PM: This is very much sort of old blue blood orthodoxy, you know that blacks are<br />
inferior. Now, this is an old them isn't it? Well, too old a theme for anyone with<br />
any sense of understanding of these issues or work better than that, just human<br />
understanding. He is not mainstream. The mainstream Liberal party has ' Peter<br />
Reith around talking about Aboriginal home lands ie trying to make the link with<br />
the South Afican home lands. Today, we have got Richard Court saying that he<br />
will line up the Coalition to support his West Australian legislation on Mabo.<br />
Now, does that mean he has spoken to John Hewson? Does it mean that he has<br />
his support in cutting across the High Court decision?<br />
IL: Tell me, are you happy with the outcome of Mabo, you could hardly be totally<br />
happy because it really is a compromise isn't it?<br />
PM: No, the good thing about the Mabo outcome to date John, is when you peel<br />
through it there are no ugly compromises sitting in it. Mostly a big national issue<br />
like this, as you leaf through it somewhere there is a horrible comprise sitting<br />
looking at you.<br />
IL: But, there are a number of compromises in it.<br />
PM: There are interests' which are accommodated, but I don't think they are<br />
compromised. I think there is a difference between accommodation and<br />
compromise and the thing has got nice lines of logic in it from the point of view of<br />
the Aboriginal community and miners, industry, the states et cetera. There is no<br />
reason why the Coalition can't support it. The only reason is, that John Hewson is<br />
basically boxed in, he is boxed in every way he goes. He is boxed in principally in<br />
many respects, by John Howard John Howard is in many respects the villain in<br />
the piece for him. He won't let Hewson move anywhere. If he wants to move<br />
anywhere on the republic, he says you change to the republic I'll be against you.<br />
You shift your ground on Mabo, you'll deal with me.<br />
IL: Surely, John Hewson is the leader, why doesn't John Hewson say to John Howard<br />
you better hang on a minute I'm the leader and this is what I intend to do?<br />
PM: Well, that takes a little bit of guts, doesn't it?<br />
IL: And you don't believe that John Hewson has got a little bit of guts?<br />
PM: That takes a little bit of hitting power and that is what he lacks. In the end, he has<br />
been corralled by all these characters so he has got Howard corralling him on the </p>
<p>right, he is afraid to move on any of these issues; his instincts on the republic are<br />
good, I think, but he won't say anything decent about it, he won't support any of<br />
the changes; I think no rational person could believe other than the High Court<br />
decision on Mabo is right, he is boxed in there; and then because he is boxed in and<br />
because he won't make a break for himself, then of course, the others are around<br />
the Bishops of this world and the Costellos.<br />
IL: What is the situation with Western Australia, I mean Richard Court unveils his<br />
legislation tomorrow, how will that affect your legislation?<br />
PM: Commonwealth legislation will take precedence over that State legislation. What<br />
he wants to do is abolish native title, he wants to turn free hold land into some<br />
other kind of statutory title denying Aboriginal people the right to be able to apply<br />
for native title.<br />
IL: Can you understand him wanting to do that?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JL: Don't you feel that his is the State that will be most affected?<br />
PM: It will be most affected because it is so big it is almost half the continent and<br />
there is still lots of unalienated crown land which can be subject to a native title<br />
claim. But again, it is not in the areas of, the built up areas which is where native<br />
title has already been extinguished by freehold title in the south eastern part of the<br />
state. Look, it is the old conservative line in some respects Court says I don't<br />
mind giving Aboriginal people some land under a title I confer on them. In other<br />
words, if it is conferred it is OK, but if they have it as an inherent right it is not<br />
OK. In other words, if it is theirs by right, by the common law, but they have only<br />
got to establish who has the title, it is no good. If you can confer it on them, from<br />
a parliament, then it is OK.<br />
IL: Well, if the High Court makes a decision, surely then Richard Court can't turn his<br />
back on it can he?<br />
PM: This is the point about all these characters John. How often have we heard from<br />
the Liberal party about the rule of law? Over the years the Labor party has been<br />
lawless, it doesn't believe in the proper norms we have heard all this stuff for<br />
years. The moment anything comes along which they don't like Reith says the<br />
High Court needs to be reformed, it is a social experimentation place, it needs to<br />
be kicked back into line. Court says there ought to be a referendum to knock over<br />
the High Court decision, so too does Bronwyn Bishop these are the people who<br />
believe in the rule of law. I mean, these people believe in only their own interests<br />
and the interests of their constituency.<br />
JL: What is the story with this wretched teak table? </p>
<p>PM: There is no story at all about it.<br />
JL: Well, it is becoming a story. I heard Mrs Fraser expressing points of view on the<br />
subject this morning, crying the praises of Margaret Betteridge. Did she simply<br />
say don't buy it? What is the real story?<br />
PM: Look, the real story is that for years the Lodge has lacked a decent dining table<br />
and Hazel Hawke wrote to the Australiana Fund and to the Prime Minister's<br />
Department saying in the final refurbishment of the house, at least we ought to<br />
have a table which can accommodate an official party of people. On that basis<br />
they all trotted off last year to try and find one.<br />
JL: Who found one?<br />
PM: Well, it was found by, I think in the first instance, the person you mentioned, Ms<br />
Betteridge.<br />
JL: She found the table to begin with?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JL: And did she then suggest that that would be the table for the Lodge?<br />
PM: Well, to find it and then to propose an offer to me and my wife, show photographs<br />
of it and invite us to go and look at it, would lead you to assume, would it not, that<br />
it was one that she approved of<br />
JL: Why did she then disapprove of it?<br />
PM: Look, I think this is the revenge of the ' hyphenated names'.<br />
JL: The what?<br />
PM: They hyphenated names. It is all the people with their hyphens showing didn't<br />
you see, there is more double names in this stunt than you have ever seen in your<br />
life it is all the basically it is either the blue rinse set or the hyphenated names<br />
striking back. Whenever you read it there is Dawson-Damer there is all these<br />
sort of, hyphenated names. Basically, it is the old Tory antique club who have got<br />
on the back of this and Tamnie is holding the side the up with a plum in her mouth,<br />
doing her best for them too.<br />
IL: Why did Margaret Betteridge change her mind?<br />
PM: I think that a bit of peer group pressure probably got to her. That is, some of the<br />
other hyphens on the committee suggested that it wasn't ideologically pure enough.<br />
IL: Did you get rid of her? </p>
<p>PM: No, I read about it the same as you John. I read about it in a newspaper.<br />
IL: You didn't call her and abuse her?<br />
PM: She was offered another job as I understand it, along with a group of other people,<br />
or 90 other people in a review of departmental functions and she chose not to<br />
take it, but to take the alternative which was a package.<br />
JL: Was she offered the other job on your recommendation? What I'm asking is, did<br />
you want to get rid of her?<br />
PM: No, this is handled bureaucratically, it is not handled by me. Can I say though, just<br />
as because this is an aside, this would be the only country in the world..<br />
JL: That would have an issue about a dining table.<br />
PM: Exactly.<br />
JL: But it has become an issue and you the Prime Minister.<br />
PM: It has only become an issue because of these bone-heads around the place who<br />
want to talk about something that takes their fancy.<br />
IL: Yes, so you didn't deliberately get rid of her?<br />
PM: Look, the fact is, there has been a restoration going on since about the middle<br />
1 980s of these official houses. It is just about complete and this was a full time<br />
job, but where the work was basically over. Now, I think, the department has said<br />
look, the job is basically coming to an end and it is redundant, would you like<br />
another position? Answer no, I prefer to take a package.<br />
IL: OK, I have been lead to believe from people that have talked to me about it, that it<br />
was a pretty good table at a pretty good price and would have served the purpose<br />
pretty well, even though it might not have been ideologically pure. Was it a good<br />
table at a good price?<br />
PM: Yes, I think so, I think that is true but, I mean about the last thing I need is to<br />
spend any time worrying about dining room tables. So, I couldn't care less, it was<br />
only basically sent on approval and if it didn't suit, it didn't suit.<br />
IL: OK, so long as you get a feed, you don't mind where you get It?<br />
PM: The current one will do me.<br />
IL: OK, you finally got the Budget through after more than a little, again the word<br />
required is compromise because you did have to compromise didn't you? </p>
<p>PM: At the edges we did, but by and large the bulk was through and we will see the<br />
Budget deficit track down now to around I per cent of GDP by the middle<br />
the thing is John, we do have now substantial recovery on our hands, you can<br />
start to see that strengthening week by week, you can see it in the stock market,<br />
you can see it in our trade figures. What we need to accommodate the investment<br />
that must carry the jobs with it is a smaller budget deficit by the middle 1 990s.<br />
That is largely what the Budget does, what it sought to do from the outset. Now,<br />
we did introduce some changes to secure its passage, but in terms of money they<br />
did not materially alter the Budget balance in the next three years.<br />
IL: Does it mean that we can now look forward to this sort of messing around with<br />
every Budget while ever there is a hostile Senate?<br />
PM: We have never had a majority in the Senate from 1983. What was different this<br />
time, is that John Hewson decided to vote against the government's money<br />
legislation he took an unprincipled decision. Look John, it takes 38 votes to stop<br />
a Budget measure, the Greens have got two votes and the other 36 belong to John<br />
Hewson. So, everyone put the weight on the Greens whereas the villain in the<br />
piece was Hewson sitting back, smugly, giggling up his sleeve in his office while<br />
everyone ran around to recruit the Democrats and the Greens. You might<br />
remember saying, I think I said to you on your program, that were we to have lost<br />
the last election, a Labor opposition would have voted for the Coalition<br />
Government's money bills in the Senate.<br />
JL: Yes.<br />
PM:... including the GST. Because I have always believed, perhaps old fashionedly,<br />
that is, that the government's money legislation shouldn't be held to ransom by an<br />
unrepresentative chamber like the Senate which was put there to protect states'<br />
interests, it was not there to muck around with the Government's financial<br />
legislation. Now, John Hewson ripped that convention up and threw it out the<br />
window. Why did he do that? Because basically, he has got no experience in the<br />
game, he has blown in out of the financial market and the first serious thing he<br />
really does is stand up the Government's Budget. So the, everyone says, how will<br />
it be carried? So, the focus is on then the ones who are likely to carry it the<br />
Democrats and the Greens who in the end did carry it, along with the Labor<br />
Party. The Coalition voted against all these measures ight throughout.<br />
IL: Yes, but they only carried it with a number of compromises. Do you still look<br />
upon the Senate as unrepresentative swill?<br />
PM: The Senate is an unrepresentative chamber. You get a dozen Senators elected for<br />
NSW with a population of 4-5 million and you get a dozen Senators elected for<br />
Tasmania with a population of around 400,000 obviously, it takes many more<br />
votes to elect a Senator from NSW than it does from Western Australia or say<br />
Tasmania. </p>
<p>IL: OK, the two from Western Australia, where they a nuisance?<br />
PM: The fact is the Budget succeeded and it passed and the Hewson tactic failed. In<br />
fact he had to admit that it failed. What sort of an Opposition are they? They<br />
won't lead on any matter and all they want to do now is vote everything down in<br />
the Senate, to use their numbers. You see John, what happened the Senate is<br />
elected you know this, that at each election half the Senate comes out for<br />
election. In the current Senate half of it was elected not in 1993, but in 1990.<br />
Now in 1990, we didn't do particularly well in certain states, so it means when you<br />
put the 1990 result and the 1993 result together for the current Senate, the Liberal<br />
party has 36 Senators, the Labor party has 30 Senators and the balance is made up<br />
by Democrats and Greens. So you can make a decision, the public of Australia<br />
made a decision on 13 March 1993 to elect this Government, but what is sitting in<br />
the Senate is half the Senate which was elected three years earlier, which has not<br />
been elected on these contemporary issues, there was no contemporary decision<br />
made in March 1993 and yet these characters hold the government in the House of<br />
Representatives to ransom. That is my point about it being neither representative<br />
nor contemporary. Now, all right it has always been thus, but it hasn't always<br />
taken on to itself the job of knocking down Budgets. That is the point. Yes, it is a<br />
states' house; yes, it is unrepresentative and yes, it is not contemporaneously<br />
elected that has always been true, but it has always kept its place as a house of<br />
review. It is not doing that now.<br />
JL: No. Do you believe that those two Senators from WA were doing what they were<br />
elected to do?<br />
PM: They are both new Senators. One has been there a year, and one has just arrived.<br />
These are very large issues to have laid upon them, and a lot of public weight,<br />
which in the normal course of events, if the 36 Coalition Senators were voting for<br />
the Government's financial legislation, say look we lost the election. The whole<br />
thing here is, John, that John Hewson won't accept that he lost the last election.<br />
He is carrying on in Canberra as though he won the election and he is entitled to<br />
behave in the Senate on the basis that in some way the Government has acted<br />
dishonourably. Let me just make this point, we have had this debate running<br />
around about how they were too honest. I mean, they were too honest when John<br />
Hewson was telling everybody in January and February this year there was a<br />
double-dip recession coming along. We were going to drop back into a<br />
depression, and here we are with the economy growing quite strongly now, and<br />
the stock market back to its 1987 levels. I mean, he knew that was untrue when<br />
he said, he frightened the hell out of everybody right through the campaign. Then<br />
they had the ads with the gun shots, the people in the gun shot sightes, and people<br />
falling through trap doors. I mean, he was too honest, my god, if that is honesty.<br />
Now, by contrast, the Government is going to pay the tax cuts in the middle of<br />
November, it's introduced the legislation.<br />
JL: Can we really afford those tax cuts, though, really? </p>
<p>PM: Yes, sure. And to not afford them means that the real incidence of tax rises. It<br />
means that even modest inflation on the tax system just takes the tax take up on<br />
ordinary people.<br />
Now, as well as that we have put in the home child care allowance, which is a<br />
payment mainly to supporting parents at home, which is mainly women, which will<br />
be about $ 30.00 per child, per fortnight, no, sorry $ 60.00 a fortnight, and the<br />
generalised child care rebate, and a whole lot of other things. All the things the<br />
Government said it would do in the election campaign, it has in fact done.<br />
IL: What are you going to do about making it easier for Australians to employ other<br />
Australians?<br />
PM: To give you a quick answer, that is, the changes in industrial relations, which<br />
Laurie Brereton is now piloting through the Parliament which will allow<br />
tremendous flexibility for smaller businesses in the economy. Now, we have two<br />
streams of changes in our industrial legislation, one is enterprise agreements which<br />
largely the large companies are involved with, that is your BfLPs and your Fords<br />
etc, where they make an enterprise arrangement for the whole company with a<br />
group of constituent unions and their employees', and then you have got the<br />
smaller areas, you know, the smaller manufacturing businesses, your stationery<br />
shops, your cake shops, or whatever it might be, and what we just succeeded in<br />
negotiating is a change to the industrial relations legislation which will allow the<br />
employer and employees of a small business to come to an enterprise agreement..<br />
JL: But only with the approval of the union.<br />
PM: No, no. The union doesn't have to approve it, only if there are unionised<br />
employees in employment, in other words let's say we are talking about..<br />
JL: Well it would be very hard to find any business that wouldn't have some unionised<br />
PM: Well that's not true. I think you would find that most small businesses..<br />
IL: Well you just mentioned a cake shop, surely the person baking the cake is going to<br />
belong to some bakers union, more than likely, which would mean that the shop<br />
assistant who wanted to work on Saturday for no penalty rates would have to get<br />
the approval of the union before that could be done.<br />
PM: Well the first thing I would say is most of these places aren't unionised, I mean,<br />
mainly because it is simply too arduous to get round and unionise very small<br />
places. You find that a great bulk of unions are in the bigger businesses. And in<br />
the event that the owner of the cake shop wants actually to create a new<br />
agreement, they can do it without any reference to the union. Now if a union<br />
person is employed there and a union gets a chance to be involved, the business </p>
<p>and the employees, there has got to be consent which is 50 per cent plus one. So,<br />
if there is 50 per cent plus one of the people..<br />
JL: But it is not 50 per cent plus one. Some unions say it is 75 per cent plus one. We<br />
have had discussions on that subject, that it is not 50 per cent plus one.<br />
PM: Well I can assure you that the legislation will make it a simple majority, and that<br />
will mean that if the employees of a place organise themselves to make a better<br />
arrangement you will find that unions won't be stopping the ( inaudible) provided<br />
that there is not a diminution in benefits. In other words if the package of<br />
employment benefits is reconfigured to suit the employer and the employee in a<br />
way which improves the productivity of the business and the wages and salaries of<br />
the employees, I don't think anybody is going to stop it.<br />
JL You don't think, but you don't know? I mean, the militant unions are a bit of a<br />
handful.<br />
PM: But there is not that many militant ones left. You have got an inflation rate, John,<br />
at 2 per cent. There is not that much militancy out there now.<br />
IL: No. But there are militant unions. I mean, we had discussions the other day to<br />
somebody I can't quite remember.<br />
PM: You will always find one. But if you look at Australian trade unions at the<br />
moment, if they were too militant you wouldn't have an inflation rate bobbing<br />
around at 2 per cent.<br />
IL: Yeah, well some of the nice ladies who listen to us at Lithgow worked in the Berlie<br />
factory there, 70 per cent of them wanted an alteration made to the structure, and<br />
they couldn't get it through because that wasn't a majority. Now the union in that<br />
case said that 70 per cent wasn't a majority. Now, how in the world can anybody<br />
get anything done if 70 per cent isn't a majority?<br />
PM: Well, what they could do there is actually go through what is called a section 134<br />
agreement. That is a full enterprise bargain, a fll enterprise workplace bargain, as<br />
the larger companies do. I mean this new stream we are putting in is for the small<br />
businesses. But look, how it will work, in the main, in the main, if someone wants<br />
to vary the coverage of a federal award they will be able to do it without reference<br />
to anybody.<br />
IL: Ok, well why couldn't the people at the Berlie factory at Lithgow do it? 70 per<br />
cent wanted it, but that wasn't the majority. They wanted 75 per cent plus one.<br />
PM: Well, the answer is I don't understand that. If the majority of employees wanted<br />
change I can't see why any union would want to sort of spike it.<br />
JL Well they have, and they did in that instance. </p>
<p>PM: Providing it is not about a reduced set of benefits, that is, taking their actual<br />
overall package down.<br />
JL: Well, if 70 per cent say that that is fine, that's nobody's business.<br />
PM: You will find that 70 per cent, I'm sure, never said that. I mean they are not about<br />
going there to take less.<br />
JL: No, but it was a new arrangement and 70 per cent wanted it, and the union said,<br />
no, it has got to be 75 per cent plus one to be a majority. I mean, the union can't<br />
even add up.<br />
PM: Look, what we have done, we have got away from the centralised industrial<br />
structure where the arbitration commission decided every wage and salary in the<br />
economy, largely. And we basically left it to enterprise agreements for large<br />
companies and then enterprise award flexibility arrangements for the smaller ones.<br />
The good managers will actually exploit all these things and so will the good<br />
union. You will always find there will be managers who don't take the options up,<br />
and there will be some unions that can't see the benefits. But by and large we<br />
think these much more flexible arrangements are a huge leap forward on anything<br />
Australians had over the last ninety years.<br />
IL: So, can we have our daily guaranteed that a majority is 50 per cent plus one.<br />
PM: Well, you certainly will in the legislation.<br />
JL: 50 per cent plus one, not 75 per cent plus one.<br />
PM: Yes. A simple majority.<br />
IL: A simple majority which would be 50 per cent plus one. Ok, well we will get back<br />
onto the union involved with the Berlie activity in Lithgow.<br />
There are very loud rumbles coming from Canberra that you are considering a<br />
Cabinet reshuffle, true or false?<br />
PM: False.<br />
IL: False.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JL: Everything is going to stay.<br />
PM: Well, the Government was elected in March, it is October now, it is not that long<br />
ago. </p>
<p>JL: Fairly loud rumbles that Laurie Brereton wants out of industrial relations, right or<br />
wrong? I mean you wouldn't blame him.<br />
PM: I have never seen a fellow enjoy himself so much getting this legislation through, I<br />
mean, he is absolutely thrilled to bits.<br />
JL: The union movement isn't all that happy with him, are they?<br />
PM: Well, look, he is a tough customer, Laurie, and he stood the unions up and said<br />
these are the core things that the Government needs, and in the end he negotiated<br />
himself a package which delivered the goods.<br />
JL: You have been taking a bit of a belting in the press of late. Have you got the press<br />
gallery offside? What has happened there?<br />
PM: Well, I have been there for a long time as you know, John.<br />
IL: Yes, but you had a good relationship with them.<br />
PM: 24 years and 11I years as a Minister, and it waxes and wanes a bit, but they are not<br />
too bad at the minute.<br />
JL: Kerry-Ann Walsh gave you a good work out in the Bulletin last week, and I think<br />
Laurie Oakes is at you again this week.<br />
PM: Well he runs hot and cold, old Laurie.<br />
JL: What about Kerry-Ann?<br />
PM: Well she has only just returned to the scene after a few years away. So, we have<br />
got to see her put in a bit more form yet.<br />
JL: I see. Do you keep an eye on all of them?<br />
PM: Yes. I keep a good close check on what they all say and do.<br />
IL: Do you believe that they are accurate in their criticism of late? The criticism has<br />
been fairly strong.<br />
PM: The problem the press gallery has at the moment is it is a proprietorial problem.<br />
There is basically very little investment in, well someone put it to them yesterday,<br />
human capital. People are not there long enough, they are mostly very young, they<br />
are arriving in there early twenties and they are leaving in their later twenties. And<br />
we are not seeing the development of the political personalities, I think, we need<br />
to, and this does give, I think, it means that instead of having experience in yard<br />
sticks to measure events by, the gallery is more prone these days to ebb and flow </p>
<p>on particular issues or personalities without the experience of having been around<br />
a while.<br />
JL: I must say, as much as I would like to, we couldn't by any stretch of the<br />
imagination say that Laurie Oakes was in his late twenties.<br />
PM: No, no. Laurie if one of the stayers.<br />
IL: And Michelle Grattan.<br />
PM: And Michelle.<br />
IL: Julie Flynn.<br />
PM: There is a couple of hundred up there though. I mean Alan Ramsey, you could put<br />
people like that in it. But by and large it has changed enormously, and I don't think<br />
that the newspapers in particular, or even the television stations are doing the right<br />
thing by the nation in not developing people and leaving them there long enough<br />
to develop a mature, and to see, and to get some experience of election campaigns,<br />
of changes in the economic cycles. Not to leave them there for three for four<br />
years. Three or four years is no where in a place like Canberra.<br />
IL: A few weeks back we were talking about the Olympic Games, when I first came<br />
back from overseas. And there were suggestions made to me that I thought were<br />
good suggestions concerning the Olympics and the merchandising of souvenirs at<br />
Olympic Games time. Now, the Olympic Games are going to be a hell of a thing<br />
for Australia, I believe people are going to arrive here in Sydney and say it has<br />
been the best kept secret in the world, I think it is going to wonders for our<br />
tourism.<br />
PM: I think that is right too.<br />
IL: A lawyer in Forbes in NSW who listens to us through 2PK in Parkes, he feels that<br />
legislation should be passed to make it law that every souvenir and piece of<br />
merchandise sold in relation to the Olympics be made in Australia. Apparently<br />
Korea had similar laws in place and it was a great success and they made a fortune<br />
according to him. In contrast Spain lost millions because their Barcelona t-shirts<br />
were made in China, this man says. Now would you introduce legislation to say<br />
that all the souvenir goods for the Olympics would have to be made in Australia?<br />
PM: Well that's something I would need to speak to our Olympic Committee, but one<br />
thing we will be doing is probably introducing legislation to protect the Olympic<br />
logo, which will become part and parcel of the Sydney Olympics. That is, Sydney<br />
having succeeded, and the Australian Olympic Committee being the relevant<br />
authority in the management of the Games and the advertising and merchandising<br />
associated with it. They would be the ones who need to protect the logo and<br />
would be the ones who would have a view about whether things are made here. I </p>
<p>think it is very hard to say that things should be made here, because often things<br />
are not made here, or they are made competitively somewhere else. But the logo<br />
requires core protection and it gets it generally by national legislation.<br />
JL: I don't quite understand why it would be very hard to pass legislation that things<br />
had to be made here? I mean, you just pass legislation.<br />
PM: If that was true we could just say that, if you take that argument you could apply<br />
for the whole economy and say, well everything needs to be made here, but you<br />
are not going to get your video recorders made here, or your compact disc players<br />
made here.<br />
JL: But we are not talking about that. We are talking about souvenirs and things that<br />
we are capable of<br />
PM: I think, well, this again gets back to Australian entreprenuership, John, I think a lot<br />
of people will see, as you say, the opportunity and take the view that Sydney has<br />
been a very well kept secret and they will exploit it and sensibly, and they will<br />
make things which are attractive. I mean, we are getting our act together, if you<br />
look at now just the catering of the tourism industries in major cities and provincial<br />
areas of Australia compared to three or four years ago it has changed enormously,<br />
as Australian merchandises are now picking up the opportunities that tourism<br />
offers.<br />
IL: But would you make it easy? Would you offer some kind of concession to people<br />
to make souvenirs available that are made in Australia, or would you make it tough<br />
for the?<br />
PM: I think before I answer any of that I wouldn't mind a talk to the Olympic<br />
Committee about it.<br />
JL: I am sure they would agree.<br />
PM: They have obviously got a perspective on this after having been through so many<br />
Olympic Games themselves, and also the challenges, or the competitions for<br />
Sydney and for Brisbane and Melbourne and Sydney. So, I don't know that I<br />
would say more then at least referring the matter to them.<br />
IL: While I am on the subject of tourism this coming Friday, I think, the Crown<br />
Monarch, of Cunard line arrives to become a resident here in Sydney. It will be<br />
doing tours from Sydney to Cairns looking at the Barrier Reef and then back again.<br />
It will be the first big tourist liner to make its base here. One slight problem it has<br />
because of maritime laws, they have to take a jaunt out into the middle of the<br />
Pacific Ocean because they have to go offshore. So, I think a day and a half, or<br />
two days are wasted going out into the middle of the ocean turning round and<br />
coming back again, because they might upset those people who have vessels going<br />
up and down the Coast. Now, nobody has vessels going ' up and down the Coast, </p>
<p>so we are making it very hard for the Cunard people, and probably any other<br />
people that want to bring tourist vessels here to Australia. Don't you think it is<br />
time we had a look at antiquated Maritime laws that restrict tourism?<br />
PM: I do. And I think, I am relying on my memory now, but I think we have a thing<br />
called continuous voyage permits which can be taken where there is a new trade or<br />
business been established, a foreign ship can be brought onto the Coast and<br />
operate in the way in which you described.<br />
JL Well obviously there are difficulties, because the same difficulty, I think, existed in<br />
the Caribbean and they had the sense to alter the laws there, there was one tourist<br />
vessel there, now I think there are 22 flzlltime in the Caribbean. Now, that's the<br />
sort of thing, this leaves the Mediterranean for dead, the Whitsunday's.<br />
PM: Absolutely. This is something we should be in. I will check this up for you John.<br />
JL: Because I think it is pretty important, it would be great for Australia.<br />
PM: Well it is one of our great growth industries, tourism. It has happened largely in<br />
the 1980s and we are seeing a greater sophistication of tourism services in the last<br />
few years, particularly as the going got a bit tougher, we got a bit better at it. And<br />
those services will proliferate and it doesn't surprise me at all that you will see<br />
major shipping lines operating.<br />
IL: Well, you see, you take this Cunard vessel, I think, it accommodates something<br />
like 600 people. Probably 60 per cent would come from the United States, so we<br />
would be getting American money in. But we shouldn't just have one tourist<br />
vessel, I mean, we should have 22 full time going up and down the Coast.<br />
PM: Absolutely.<br />
IL: So, will you have a look at that?<br />
PM: I will indeed. I will get back to you about it.<br />
IL: Because in the area of tourism we are way in front of the rest of the world in what<br />
we have got to offer, it just that sometimes funny old fashioned laws that have<br />
been in place for a long time are a bit restrictive.<br />
PM: Basically all the coastal shipping all about, largely it is not even about passengers,<br />
it is basically about freight. It is not about tourism.<br />
JL Ok, well thank you for your time. I hope the press sees the charming side of you<br />
soon.<br />
PM: Well we are getting the big things into place. Governments are either there to do<br />
the big and right things or they are there to mark time. Now, basically I was hired </p>
<p>16<br />
to re-start the economy. That's why I was, I think, chosen as leader of the Labor<br />
Party, it's probably why we were re-elected. The economy is now growing again<br />
and growing quite markedly. Big social issues are coming along like<br />
unemployment, we have got this white paper on unemployment coming down at<br />
the end of the year, which will probably be, I think, we are ahead of the world<br />
again in trying to deal with a long-term problem there. In big social issues like<br />
Mabo we are moving a very large solution into place which would confound most<br />
countries similar to us. And as well as that we are also making a place for<br />
Australia in Asia with the development of APEC, and I will be going to Seattle in<br />
November for that. And all the big things the Government is doing, not just what<br />
it said it would do, but giving Australia the leadership and the capacity the country<br />
needs from a Government prepared to take risks and do things. Now that's why I<br />
am there, that's why the Government is there. And we have all got to put up with<br />
a bit of criticism from the press from time to time, or problems with Budgets.<br />
Providing the big core things are going into place, it is all worth it.<br />
JL: Thanks for your time, let's hope we can talk to each other soon.<br />
PM: Good John.<br />
JL: Prime Minister of Australia, Paul Keating.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
