<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>556</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 51/1962 - ROYAL TOUR - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000556.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M No_-/ 16 2<br />
FOR PRESS RBOYAL TOUR<br />
Statemen b _ t _ he P Miiei . njsterhtRt. oG. Menzies<br />
The Australian Secretary to The Queen for the<br />
Royal Visit, Sir Roy Dowling, D. S. 0o, will meet<br />
in Canberra on Monday, 16th July, with State representatives<br />
to consider proposals for the Royal Visit next year.<br />
State representatives will be asked to put forward<br />
ideas for the programme within each State. These will include<br />
events of special significance which might form the basis of<br />
visit plans, Admiral Dowling will leave for London on Wednesday,<br />
18th July, where he will discuss with Her Majesty and Prince<br />
Philip, proposals put forward by the Commonwealth and States.<br />
It is expected that Admiral Dowling will be in London for about<br />
three weeks. State repr( sentatives who will attend are<br />
New South Wales Mr. G. M. Gray, Victoria Mr.<br />
J. C. Macgibbon, Queensland: Mro RoB. McAllister;<br />
South Australia: Mr. L. King, Western Australia<br />
Mr. R. Doig, C. V. U0Tasmania: Mr. F J. Carter, C. B. E.<br />
The Secretary, Prime Minister's Department, Mr.<br />
E. J. Bunting, will open the meetingo Also attending<br />
will be the Administrator of the Northern Territory, the<br />
Honourable Roger Bo Nott, the Secretary of the Department of<br />
the Interior, Mr. WNA. NcLaren, C, B. E. and Mr. J. H. Scholtens,<br />
Chief Ceremonial Officer of the Prime Minister's Department<br />
who will be in charge of arrangements for the Royal Visit to<br />
the Australian Capital Territory.<br />
CANBERRA, 12th July, 1? 62. </p>
<p>BACKG! OUND NOTE<br />
The meeting will commence at 10 aom. in<br />
the office of the Secretary, Prime Minister's Department<br />
and is expected to last all day. It will not be possible<br />
to issue any statement about the work of the meeting at<br />
its conclusion because any proposals or broad outline<br />
agreed at this meeting are tontative until discussed with<br />
Her Majesty the Queen in London by Admiral Dowling.<br />
It is expected that a statement will be issued<br />
some time after Admiral Dowling's return about the precise<br />
timing of the ao-al Visit in each State. Any announcements<br />
then about arrangements in each State will be made by the<br />
appropriate State authorities,<br />
CANBERRA,<br />
12th July, 1962, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
