<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4612</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS - 25 JANUARY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/01/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004612.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
lj&gt; A U STRAL1L<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 25 JANUARY 1978<br />
ATTACHED IS THE TEXT OF A LETTER SENT TODAY BY THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER, IN RESPONSE TO REGENT CORRESPONDENCE FROM<br />
THE PREMIER OF SOUTH AUSTRALIA.<br />
THE STATEMENT REFERRED TO IN THE FIFTH PARAGRAPH OF THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S LETTER MAY BE FOUND IN HOUSE OF<br />
REPRESENTATIVES HANSARD FOR 20th OCTOBER, 1977,<br />
PAGES 2333-2340. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CANBERRA<br />
2 5 JAN 1978<br />
My dear Premier, I have received your letters of 17 and 18<br />
January 1978. At the outset let me say that I welcome your<br />
assurance that your Government will continue to co-operate<br />
with the Commonwealth Government on matters of genuine<br />
security. As you are aware, the functions and activities<br />
of the Australian Security Intelligence Organization<br />
have been the subject of an exhaustive inquiry<br />
by the Royal Commission on Intelligence and Security<br />
constituted by Mr Justice Hope. The Royal Commission<br />
made a large number of recommendations directed to improving<br />
the effectiveness of A. S. I. O. and removing deficiencies in<br />
past practices. The Royal Commission found that:<br />
" My basic finding is that Australia needs<br />
and should have a security intelligence<br />
service to investigate and provide intelligence<br />
about threats to the internal security of the<br />
nation."<br />
He also found that there is a need for continued co-operation<br />
between the work at Federal level and the State Police<br />
Forces. The Commonwealth Government endorses this fully.<br />
My Government carefully considered the findings<br />
and recommendations of the Royal Commission and, as I<br />
informed Parliament on 25 October last year ( copy attached),<br />
we have accepted the Royal Commission's basic judgements<br />
and recommendations for a sweeping range of reforms. As I<br />
foreshadowed in that statement, the Attorney-General will<br />
introduce amendments to the A. S. I. O. Act reflecting the<br />
legislative changes the Royal Commission recommended. In<br />
consequence the functions of A. S. I. O. will be clearly and<br />
precisely stated. The legislation will also establish<br />
appeal procedures under which, broadly speaking, persons<br />
who are affected in Commonwealth employment, in immigration,<br />
or in citizenship matters by unfavourable assessments by<br />
A. S. I. O. will be able to appeal to a Tribunal. The Chairman<br />
of the Tribunal will be a Judge. / 2 </p>
<p>The collection and maintenance by A. S. I. O. of<br />
appropriate records, the preparation of security assessments<br />
and the utilization of those assessments by Government<br />
authorities have been, as you know, the subject of special<br />
and extensive study by the Royal Commissioner. The Government<br />
has, as I have stated, accepted the Royal Commissioner's<br />
judgements on these matters. I believe that these reforms<br />
will effectively balance the requirements of national security<br />
and the civil rights of individuals. I should add that the<br />
Director-General of Security, Mr Justice A. E. Woodward, has<br />
assured me that he has taken action to give effect to those<br />
recommendations of the Royal Commissioner that concern<br />
improvements in A. S. I. O.' s internal administration and management<br />
and generally to all other recommendations which do not call<br />
for policy decisions by the Government.<br />
The Commonwealth recognises that State Police Force<br />
Special Branches have a variety of functions and are the<br />
responsibility of the States. The Royal Commissioner concluded<br />
that, given appropriate inter-governmental arrangements, it is<br />
both important and quite proper for A. S. I. O. to co-operate with<br />
the Police Forces of the States in respect of matters within its<br />
charter. My Government agrees with this approach and will be<br />
seeking the views of the States about co-operative arrangements<br />
when the legislation has been prepared. You will also reca] ll<br />
that on various occasions I have written to you on aspects of<br />
Commonwealth/ States co-operation dealin for example, with<br />
international terrorism. Commonwealth! tate co-operation on<br />
such matters must of course be bi-partisan in approach.<br />
My Government's objective in this matter, and I am<br />
sure this is also the objective of all State Premiers, is the<br />
preservation of the security of the nation with the minimum<br />
intrusion on the rights and freedoms of individuals. When<br />
the legislation implementing the reforms I have mentioned<br />
above is drafted I shall be communicating with all State Premiers<br />
specifically on this aspect.<br />
I refer to your request concerning the destruction<br />
of some of A. S. I. Q.' s records. The Royal Commission gave<br />
consideration to the principles that should govern the<br />
destruction of records of A. S. I. O. and concluded that only<br />
records that are not, or are not now, of actual or potential<br />
security relevance should be destroyed. The Director-General<br />
is proceeding with the destruction of records according to<br />
those principles. Because this is a matter of interest to all States<br />
I am sending a copy of this letter to the other Premiers.<br />
Yours sincerely,<br />
( Malcolm Fraser)<br />
The Hon. D. A. Dunstan, M. H. A.,<br />
Premier of South Australia,<br />
ADELAIDE S. A. 5000 </p>
<p>October 1977 REPRESENTATIVES 2333<br />
ROYAL COMMISSION ON<br />
INTELLIGENCE AND SECURITY<br />
Ministerial Statement<br />
Mr MALCOLM FRASER ( Wannon-Prime<br />
M inistcr)-hy leave-On 21 August 1974 the previous<br />
Government established a Royal Commission<br />
on Intelligence and Security and<br />
appointed the Honourable Mr Justice Hope as<br />
the Royal Commissioner to inquire into and<br />
make recommendations on the intelligence and<br />
security services the nation should have available<br />
to it. The Government has now completed its<br />
consideration of the eight reports presented to it<br />
by the Royal Commissioner.<br />
The Royal Commission's Eight Reports<br />
The first report outlines the procedures followed<br />
by the Royal Commission and requires no<br />
further comment. The second report makes<br />
findings and recommendations on security<br />
checking and a security appeals tribunal. The<br />
third report dealing with the machinery for ministerial<br />
and official control, direction and coordination<br />
of Australia's intelligence and security<br />
services was the subject of the statement I<br />
made in the. House on 5 May this year. At that<br />
time, I announced the appointment of a Ministerial<br />
Committee, supported by a Permanent<br />
Heads Committee, to provide a better system for<br />
co-ordinating the intelligence and security<br />
services. I also announced our decision to establish the<br />
Office of National Assessments and legislation to<br />
establish that Office has subsequently been<br />
passed by Parliament. The fourth report<br />
specifically relates to the Australian Security<br />
Intelligence Organisation. The fifth and sixth<br />
reports relate to particular specialist intelligence<br />
collection agencies. The seventh report, wvritten<br />
by a consultant to the Commission, is an historical<br />
study of Australian intelligence and security<br />
services. The eighth concerns administrative arrangements<br />
for the storage and custody of the<br />
Royal Commission's records. I will not be commenting<br />
further on these last two reports in this<br />
statement. In accordance with undertakings previously<br />
given to the House, I am tabling those parts of<br />
the Royal Commission's reports which the Royal<br />
Commissioner considered can be made public<br />
without prejudice to national security and announcing<br />
the Government's decisions on them.<br />
The third report was in an abridged form prepared<br />
by the Royal Commissioner and was<br />
tabled on 5 May. I now table the first report-thesecond<br />
report other than Appendices 2-A, 2-C </p>
<p>2334 REPRESENTATIVES 25 October 1977 RylCmiso nScrt<br />
and 2-F, and volumes I and 2 of the fourth<br />
report. For the first time the Parliament and the<br />
people of Australia are being authoritively<br />
informed of fundamental considerations relating<br />
to Australia's national security. For the first time<br />
Parliament and people can read the careful<br />
assessments of an independent judicial authority<br />
who has had full access to all the information<br />
and the time and resources to thoroughly analyse<br />
them. The Royal Commission's Basic Judgments<br />
Mr Speaker, the Government has accepted the<br />
basic judgments of the Royal Commission on<br />
Intellirence and Security and has implemented a<br />
sweeping range of reforms to achieve them. In<br />
essence Mr Justice Hope's basic findings are<br />
these: AUSTRALIA'S NEEDS FOR<br />
INTELLIGENCE AND SECURITY<br />
SERVICES<br />
Australia needs a highly professional system<br />
of intelligence and security services, and this<br />
need is more apparent than ever before.<br />
Australia needs intelligence of quality, timeliness<br />
and relevance.<br />
( 1I) THREATS TO INTERNAL SECURITY<br />
Such a professional system should include a<br />
security intelligence service to investigate and<br />
provide intelligence about threats to the internal<br />
security of the nation. Australia faces, and has<br />
faced or may face, threats to its internal security<br />
from various types of action to which I shall later<br />
refer. ( 111) CIVIL LIBERTY AND NATIONAL<br />
SECURITY<br />
A balance must be struck between the need to<br />
respond decisively to this threat and the imperative<br />
of preserving Australia's open processes of<br />
debate, discussion and commerce. Mr Justice<br />
Hope has recognised that a balance between the<br />
rights of individual persons and the preservation<br />
of the security of Australia as a nation is no<br />
simple or easy thing to achieve'. ( Fourth Report,<br />
paragraph 10). He concludes, quoting from the<br />
1975 Rockefeller Report on the Central<br />
Intelligence Agency: in the final<br />
analysis, public safety and individual liberty sustain<br />
each other'. ( Fourth Report, paragraph 10).<br />
( IV) PROTECTION OF CONFIDENTIAL<br />
INFORMATION AND SECURITY<br />
CHECKING<br />
Australia has classified information which the<br />
Australian Government has a duty to protect in the interests of the nation. These secrets are not<br />
limited to matters of national defence or foreign<br />
policy; they extend to matters relating to national<br />
resources and the national economy; their disclosure<br />
would prejudice Australia's national security.<br />
Thus the security checking of public servants<br />
should continue to be undertaken subject<br />
to a series of basic reforms.<br />
THE NECESSITY FOR SECRECY<br />
The actual activities, programs and priorities<br />
of the intelligence and security services should<br />
not be revealed, as to do so would be to jeopardise<br />
national security.<br />
( VI) COMPLIANCE WITH THE LAW<br />
The intelligence and security services should<br />
always comply with Commonwealth and State<br />
laws. ( VII) PARLIAMENTARY<br />
RESPONSIBILITY<br />
The intelligence and security agencies should<br />
continue individually to be subject to ministerial<br />
responsibility, and in addition should be<br />
collectively subject to central oversight and coordination<br />
by scnior committees of Ministers and<br />
permanent heads. Considerations of the nation's<br />
interest should prevail over the full range of the<br />
agencies activities, and to this end the Government<br />
and the Opposition should develop a bipartisan<br />
approach to intelligence and security<br />
matters. Australian Security and Intelligence<br />
Organisation<br />
In his fourth report concerning ASIO Mr<br />
Justice Hope's basic finding is that Australia<br />
needs and should have a security intelligence service<br />
to investigate and provide intelligence about<br />
threats to the internal security of the nation.'<br />
( Fourth Report paragraph 657). He stated:<br />
On the basis or what has been submitted or provided<br />
to me, I find that Australia races, and. has faced or m<br />
face, thre~ ats to its internal security . and that AS I0<br />
should invcstigate...<br />
Espionage, which is the covert collection or ( generally<br />
secret) intelligence.<br />
' Active measures' a general expression to cover a variety<br />
or activities by which a power can weaken another power or<br />
strengthen itself vis-a-vis that other power, including<br />
the establishment or'agents ofrinfluence'<br />
the dissemination ol'disinformation'<br />
other rorms ofrclandestine or deceptive action<br />
subversion, which is activity whose purpose is directly or<br />
ultimately, to overthrow constitutional government, and in<br />
the meantime to weaken or to undermine it. Sabotage, which<br />
is the destruction, da. paging or impairment or derence<br />
installations, etc., which would be userul to an enemy or a<br />
foreign power. Royal Commission on Security </p>
<p>Roya COocmtiosiboneorn e19c7u7i ty2R5E PRESENTATIVES 2335<br />
Mr Justice Hope continued:<br />
Two further kinds of activity should be investigated by<br />
ASIO, although they may not always involve a direct attack<br />
on Australia.<br />
Terrorism, which is politically motivated violence, or the<br />
threat of that violence.<br />
The organisation in Australia of, or of assistance for, violent<br />
political activity in foreign countries. ( Fourth Report<br />
paragraph 661).<br />
I will now briefly summarise the royal commissioner's<br />
comments on two of the major areas<br />
of threat-espionage and subversion.<br />
Espionage<br />
Mr Justice Hope rejected the views that some<br />
people had expressed to him that espionage was<br />
not a significant problem in Australia. The royal<br />
commissioner especially warned that I'Australia<br />
must not be so naive as to think that it has some<br />
exemption from clandestine operations or that it<br />
need not take steps to protect itself against them'.<br />
( Fourth Report, paragraph 41 The royal commissioner<br />
stated that this conclusion was substantiated<br />
' by a large amount of intelligence held<br />
by ASlO which cannot be made public'. ( Fourth<br />
Report, paragraph 41 However, in the royal<br />
commissioner's words, there are ' some matters<br />
which can be stated publicly and which l'-that<br />
is the royal commissioner-' regard as supporting<br />
the conclusions I have come to.' ( Fourth Report,<br />
paragraph 40).<br />
The royal commissioner notes the considerable<br />
evidence of espionage against Australia<br />
during the Second World War and the Petrov<br />
Commission's findings that from 1943 until<br />
Petrov's defection, Union of Soviet Socialist<br />
Republics intelligence agents had been operating<br />
in Australia. He further says that independently<br />
of the Petrov Commission's findings he<br />
was-these are his word s-' completely satisfied<br />
that the USSR intelligence services were operating<br />
in Australia up to the time of Petrov's defection<br />
and that a number of Australians, some consciously<br />
and some unconsciously did reveal<br />
information about classified material to USSR<br />
intelligence officers or their agents'. ( Fourth<br />
Report, para. 40) He refers to the case of Mr 1. F.<br />
Skripov. Mr Skripov re-opened the Soviet Embassy<br />
in 1959 and was expelled in February<br />
1963 because of his clandestine intelligence<br />
activities. The royal commissioner states that the<br />
numbers of intelligence officers now operating<br />
clandestinely in Australia ' are much larger than<br />
in the 1940' s and 1950' s and are growing'<br />
Again these are his words: ' For exal, th<br />
proportion of USSR intelligence officers represented in that country's diplomatic mission<br />
in Australia is consistent with overseas estimates<br />
of USSR representation in the USA and NATO<br />
countries'. ( Fourth report, paragraph 40) In this<br />
connection, the royal commission quotes an estimate<br />
of Professor Leonard Shapiro, Chairman of<br />
the Institute for the Study of Conflict that<br />
around half of those ( Soviets)<br />
accredited as diplomats to NATO countries are<br />
usually engated in intelligence operations of one<br />
kind or another ( Fourth Report, paragraph<br />
40, footnote 4-18).<br />
Subversion<br />
The royal commissioner states:<br />
The amount of domestic subversive activity in Australia<br />
has varied from time to time. The material before me does<br />
not establish ( hat there is a very large amount at present.<br />
( Fourth Report, paragraph 76).<br />
As against this, the two main communist parties, the Communist<br />
Party of Australia and the Socialist Party of<br />
Australia, have strong influence in some unions.<br />
They exercise a power greatly in excess of that which their<br />
numbers would justify, among other reasons because they<br />
often strongly support the interests of trade unionists and put<br />
their full force behind industrial issues.<br />
At other times, they make use of industrial disputes for<br />
their own political purposes.<br />
The Trotskyists and other left radical groups are active in<br />
academic and political areas and are succeeding in establishing<br />
themselves in many places of influence.<br />
Right radical groups are still active and the basis for extreme<br />
right wing action is certainly not dormant. ( Fourth<br />
Report, paragraph 77).<br />
ASIO -Functions and Performance<br />
In considering threats such as these Mr Justice<br />
Hope also examined various ways of establishing<br />
a security intelligence service. He concludes that<br />
' The essential conception of ASIO as an<br />
intelligence, and not an executive agency, is right<br />
for our national circumnstances.' ( Fourth Report,<br />
paragraph 660) He notes that ASIO ' maintains<br />
liaison both here and abroad with the internal security<br />
services of several friendly nations' and he<br />
concludes: ' These relationships contribute significantly<br />
to ASIO's overall efficiency'. ( Fourth<br />
Report, paragraph 707) Again those are the<br />
royal commissioner's words.<br />
The royal commissioner was criticial of some<br />
aspects of the past performance of ASlO. The<br />
Government is determined that ASIO's performance<br />
should be beyond reproach. We have<br />
therefore accepied -all of Mr Justice Hope's<br />
major recommendations and we propose to<br />
amend the Australian Security Intelligence<br />
Organisation Act accordingly. The major effect<br />
of those amendments will be to ensure that<br />
ASIO's activities will be expanded to enable it to<br />
Royal Commission on Security </p>
<p>2336 REPRESENTATIVES 25 October 1977 RylCmiso nScrl<br />
investigate and to report on activities which*<br />
threaten Australia's internal security. ASTO will<br />
have a statutory responsibility to advise the<br />
Government about the following:<br />
Espionage<br />
Sabotage Subversion Terrorism Domestic activity related to violence abroad<br />
and what the Royal Commissioner refers to as<br />
, active measures.<br />
Mr Justice Hope has updated ASlO's functions<br />
to enable it to respond to the reality of the<br />
1970' s. The relationship between the Director-<br />
General of Security and the Government will be<br />
defined in accordance with the royal commissioner's<br />
recommendation based on his<br />
finding that, under the existing ASIO Act, there<br />
are legal doubts as to the extent to which the<br />
Minister can give lawful directions to the<br />
Director-General of Security. The Director-<br />
General of Security will be accountable to the<br />
Attorney-General and the Prime Minister.'<br />
The royal commissioner considers that the<br />
legal powers exercisable by ASlO regarding its<br />
collection of intelligence should be clarified and<br />
the responsibility for their supervision and control<br />
identified. Subject to the conditions specified<br />
by the royal commission ASIO may obtain warrants<br />
from the Attorney-General for purposes<br />
relevant to security to facilitate the acquisition of<br />
information about intelligence activities threatening<br />
Australia's security. This is consistent with<br />
the pattern established in other countries with a<br />
Westminster system of government. Mr Justice<br />
Hope said:<br />
The circumstances in which these powers might be exercised<br />
are not frequent. ( Fourth report. para. 139).<br />
For example, in regard to ASIO's use of telephone<br />
taps thejudge comments:<br />
' The number or warrants issued since the enactment or<br />
legislation ( authonising them) has been quite modest. The<br />
intelligence yield has often been extremely valuable'.<br />
( Fourth report, para. 14 1)<br />
In the performance of its statutory responsibilities<br />
ASIO will carefully observe the principles<br />
delineated by the royal commission:<br />
That it operates within the terms of its statute and is<br />
concerned only with matters relevant to security.<br />
That it always complies with the law.<br />
And that it observes standasrds of propriety by not<br />
intruding on the rights and freedom of persons except<br />
to etxhtee ta tt requirements of t he nation's security<br />
justify, and the law allows. ( Fourth report,<br />
para. 786). Honourable members will notice that the royal<br />
commission has made a number of recommendations<br />
regarding the policies and practices to be<br />
followed by the Government and ASIO. The<br />
Government has accepted these: Significant<br />
features of them include: The Leader of the<br />
Opposition shall be kept informed about security<br />
matters and shall have access to the Director-<br />
General and his annual classified report. The<br />
Government will continue the practice of ' no<br />
comment' on allegations about ASIO's activities.<br />
ASIO shall not provide security intelligence in<br />
any form, either directly or indirectly on an attributable<br />
basis or not, to the Press or other<br />
media. As the Commonwealth agency responsible<br />
for the defence and maintenance of<br />
Australia's internal security ASTO is entitled to<br />
the confidence and respect of the nation.<br />
I also refer to five recommendations taken<br />
from Volume III of the fourth report relating to<br />
ASIO's future effectiveness. The Director-<br />
General of Security has advised that these five<br />
paragraphs can be made public without prejudice<br />
to national security. They are:<br />
That the Director-General receive strong support and encouragement<br />
from the Government in his task of improving<br />
thee ecvenessof ASIO.<br />
That ASIO management be active in opening and maintaining<br />
communication with staf~.<br />
That the Government recognise that, in the future, quite<br />
large sums will be needed to improve AS 10' s capacity that<br />
those giving consideration to ASIO's budgetary bids take<br />
into account that past levels of expenditure should not be<br />
taken as a realistic benchmark.<br />
That ASIO ensure that the Government is made aware of<br />
its needs for resources.<br />
That ASIO should receive strong and sympathetic support<br />
from the Public Service Board in improving its personnel<br />
policies. ( Fourth report, Volume IIIl, para. 818-822).<br />
1 have been advised by the Director-General of<br />
Security, Mr Justice Woodward, that he has<br />
taken action to give effect to those recommendations<br />
of the royal commission that concern<br />
improvements in ASIO's internal administration<br />
and management and generally to all other<br />
recommendations which do not call for policy<br />
decisions by the Government.<br />
Mr Speaker, I have outlined in broad terms<br />
the nature of our reforms. Further details of the<br />
action being undertaken by the Governmentwhich<br />
are in any event set out as recommendations<br />
in the fourth rep9. rt which I have tabledwill<br />
be given by the Attorney-General ( Senator<br />
Durack), when he introduces amendments to the<br />
ASIO Act. Royal Commission on Security </p>
<p>Roya OCocmtoisbioenorn 1e9c7u7i ty2R5E PRESENTATIVES 2337<br />
Security Checking and Security Appeals<br />
The Australian Security Intelligence Organisation<br />
carries out security checks for Commonwealth<br />
departments primarily in relation to<br />
Commonwealth employees but also in a limited<br />
way for a range of special cases which the royal<br />
commission refers to as ' immigration cases'. In<br />
the second report, the royal commissioner examines<br />
the need for and basis of this security checking<br />
process. Mr Justice Hope finds that Australia<br />
needs a system of security checks for two main<br />
reasons: The serious nature of the security threat<br />
to Australia-Honourable members may wish to<br />
refer to the second report, paras 12-13 and the<br />
fourth report, paras 34-36-and the fact that, as<br />
the royal commissioner said:<br />
Australia has secrets which the Australian Government<br />
has a duty to protect in the interests of the nation. ( Second<br />
Report, para. 196).<br />
The royal commissioner reported that the security<br />
checking system has not been formally<br />
reviewed since the early 1950s, and found that it<br />
contains a number of faults, including: The existing<br />
security checking categories are too wide.<br />
That is, they strain ASIO's resources unnecessarily<br />
and are objectionable from a civil liberties<br />
viewpoint. There is some confusion about the<br />
nature of the security assessment ASIO provides.<br />
There has been some blurring of the demarcation<br />
between the responsibilities of ASIO and<br />
those of departments and instrumentalities.<br />
There have been deficiencies in the preparation<br />
and content of ASIO's security assessments and<br />
the use of them by departments. In this regard,<br />
Mr Justice Hope observes that security checking<br />
is a complex and difficult task. He said:<br />
ASIO's information, even if accurate, will rarely, if ever,<br />
be cornpete. It can be led into error by the erroneous and<br />
incomplet e' nature of the material on which it makes its<br />
assessments. ( Second report, para. 11) 5).<br />
All investigations and judgments about persons and thei r<br />
actions can involve mistakes. ASIO and its ofuicers are no<br />
exception. ( Second report, para. I 15).<br />
The Government has decided to implement a<br />
number of reforms designed to overcome the<br />
deficiencies in existing arrangements. Principal<br />
amongst these reforms are the following: A Security<br />
Appeals Tribunal will be established.*<br />
Steps will be taken to reduce to the minimum<br />
possible number the people to he security<br />
checked. ASIO's security checking procedures<br />
will be revised and improved. From now on, persons<br />
who are the subject of adverse or qualified<br />
assessments, will be notified of that fact and of<br />
the general nature of the supporting information<br />
except to the extent that in the interests of<br />
national security they cannot be notified in certain<br />
special circumstances contemplated by the royal commission. In such special cases the<br />
Attorney-General as Minister responsible for the<br />
ASIO Act-not the Prime Minister as Mr Justice<br />
Hope proposes-will have to issue a certificate<br />
vetoing notification. Persons having been<br />
notified of an adverse or qualified assessment<br />
will be able to have the assessment impartiailly<br />
examined by the Security Appeals Tribunal.<br />
Mr Speaker, these reforms are designed to<br />
make security checking for Commonwealth employees<br />
more efficient and most importantly, to<br />
reduce as far as possible the intrusion into the<br />
private lives of Commonwcalth employees. I<br />
shall now outline further details of some of these<br />
reforms, and also indicate those instances in<br />
which the Government has, after careful consideration,<br />
modified the royal commissioner's<br />
recommendations. The Security Appeals Tribuinal<br />
The royal commissioner has found:<br />
Without adequate machinery for review of security. assessments<br />
of persons grave and permanent injustices<br />
can occur. ( Second report, para. 200).<br />
He concluded:<br />
ASIO's scrty assments should be subject to an<br />
appeals systemt. ( Second report, para. 115).<br />
The Government agrees with this view. The Security<br />
Appeals Tribunal recommended by the<br />
royal commission will be established to review<br />
adverse or qualified security assessments and any<br />
supporting information provided by ASIO relating<br />
to such assessments.<br />
The royal commission recommended that the<br />
Tribunal's review function should be made<br />
retrospective to the inception of ASIO in 1949.<br />
The Government has given careful consideration<br />
to this proposal but has decided that the matters<br />
Sutbject to the Tribunal's jurisdiction should be<br />
those occurring on or after the date on which the<br />
Tribunal is established. We have been advised<br />
that there would be legal and substantial administrative<br />
problems associated with the royal<br />
commissioner's recommendation. There is no<br />
Commonwealth statutory precedent for a<br />
retrospective grant of a right of appeal against an<br />
administrative decision. The comparable<br />
appeals system established under the Administrative<br />
Appeals Tribunal Act 1975, is expressly<br />
stated to apply to decisions given on or after the<br />
commencement of that Act. However, the<br />
Government has devised certain procedures to<br />
give effect to the 13pirit of the royal commissioner's<br />
recommendation.<br />
First, ASIO has been instructed to undertake a<br />
review in the manner recommended by the royal<br />
commission, of any existing adverse or qualified<br />
Royal Commission on Security </p>
<p>2338 REPRESENTATIVES 25 October 1977 RylCmiso nScrt<br />
assessment of persons currently in the employ of<br />
the Commonwealth. If in the light of that review,<br />
the adverse or qualified assessment is maintained,<br />
the person concerned will be notified,<br />
and will be entitled to appeal to the Tribunal<br />
against the new assessment. Second, the legislation<br />
establishing the Tribunal will allow the<br />
Government to refer to the Tribunal particular<br />
cases of people no longer in the employ of the<br />
Commonwealth. The Government intends to exercise<br />
this discretion in any case in which it<br />
appears a wrong assessment may have been<br />
made in the past. The Security Appeals Tribunal<br />
will be mainly concerned with Commonwealth<br />
employees, except for the ' immigration cases'<br />
about which I shall comment shortly. Thus all<br />
Commonwealth employees, as that term is<br />
broadly defined in paragraph 20 of the second<br />
report, will have appeal rights against adverse or<br />
qualified assessments.<br />
Legislation will be introduced to establish the<br />
Tribunal and, although the Tribunal's findings<br />
will generally be advisory, they will be binding in<br />
those cases the royal commissioner recommends.<br />
The Government has concluded thatithe Tribunal<br />
should have the composition and powers<br />
detailed in Part H of the second report except for<br />
the modifications I have outlined. The procedures<br />
of the Tribunal envisaged by the Royal<br />
Commission will be given further consideration.<br />
In addition, the panel from which the Tribunal<br />
will be constituted will be enlarged to include<br />
more than one former public servant and more<br />
than one former member of the defence force.<br />
Security Checking<br />
The security checking process will be substantially<br />
altered to make it more finely tuned to<br />
national security requirements. In contrast with<br />
existing practice not all public servants or applicants<br />
to the Public Service will be security<br />
checked. From now on, security checking of public<br />
servants will take place only when it can be<br />
reasonably expected that they will require access<br />
to classified security matters or areas. In accordance<br />
with Mr Justice Hope's recommendations,<br />
ASIO's security assessments will vary in accordance<br />
with the level of access required. Far more<br />
extensive investigation will take place, for<br />
example, for persons requiring access to the<br />
highest classification than for those requiring<br />
access to the lowest. All aspects of ASIO ' s security<br />
assessments will be prepared in accordance'<br />
with the royal commissioner's recommendations.<br />
The royal commission recommended that positions<br />
in the Public Service for which security<br />
checking will be required should be publicly designated as such. However, the reports do not<br />
recommend how this could be implemented. The<br />
Government has the matter under consideration.<br />
Immigration Cases<br />
ASlO has provided security checks for the<br />
Commonwealth Government in certain<br />
immigration cases. The term ' immigration cases'<br />
refers to government activity relating to such<br />
matters as visas, entry permits, deportation, citi<br />
zenship and passports. Mr Justice I-ope has recommended<br />
that the reforms regarding security<br />
checking and security a ppeals for Commonwealth<br />
employees be applied to these immigration<br />
cases with some minor modifications of<br />
detail as necessary. ASIO's investigative work in<br />
this area will be directed to protecting th ' e security<br />
of the nation and its assessments will be<br />
closely linked to judgments about any potential<br />
security threat involved. As in all other matters,<br />
ASIO's role will be advisory. Australian citizens<br />
and persons whose continued presence in<br />
Australia is not subject to any limitation imposed<br />
by law will have full appeal rights to the Security<br />
Appeals Tribunal in respect of these immigration<br />
cases. The Government has accepted Mr Justice<br />
Hope's recommendations regarding immigration<br />
cases and the Minister for Immigration and<br />
Ethnic Affairs ( Mr MacKellar) will provide<br />
further details regarding their implementation at<br />
a later stage. Compensation<br />
The Royal Commissioner makes a number of<br />
observations about the possible payment of compensation<br />
in relation to wrong security<br />
assessment. He notes that a wrong security assessment may<br />
sometimes cause detriment to the subject of the<br />
assessment, although the detriment flows from<br />
the consquent action of the employer authority.<br />
The Royal Commissioner recommends that<br />
the Security Appeals Tribunal should have<br />
power to report about compensation matters.<br />
However, the Government, having adopted<br />
the recommendation of the Royal Commissioner<br />
that the Tribunal will be solely concerned with<br />
ASIO's assessments, not executive decisions of<br />
government, has decided that compensation<br />
matters will be for the Government to determine,<br />
not the Tribunal.<br />
Australian Secret Intelligence Service<br />
The fifth report is about. the Australian Secret<br />
Intelligence Service, ASIS, an agency of the Australian<br />
Government the existence of which has<br />
not hitherto officially been acknowledged. The<br />
Royal Commission on Security </p>
<p>Roya OCocmtoisbioenro n 1e9c7u7 ity2R5E PRESENTATIVES 2339<br />
Government agrees with Mr Justice Hope's<br />
recommendation that ASIS should be publicly<br />
acknowledged and on his recommendation the<br />
fifth report will not be published as to do so<br />
would Jeopardise national security. The report<br />
has been made available to the Leader of the<br />
Opposition as the royal commissioner recommended.<br />
The royal commissioner recommended<br />
' that the Government accept the<br />
continuing need for an Australian Secret<br />
Intelligence Service and that ASIS be retained to<br />
fulfil that role'. He reported that ASIS is a ' singularly<br />
and well run and well managed<br />
a ' gency right in concept for Australian<br />
circumstances'. The main function of ASIS is to<br />
obtain, by such means and subject to such conditions<br />
as are prescribed by the Government,<br />
foreign intelligence for the purpose of the protection<br />
or promotion of Australia or its interests.<br />
The Government has accepted his recommendation<br />
that the Service continue and be responsible<br />
to and under the control of the Minister for<br />
Foreign Affairs. The funding of ASIS has in the<br />
past been secret but, will in future be the subject<br />
of a one-line appropriation like ASIO. ASIS's capacity<br />
to serve Australia's national interest will<br />
continue to depend on its activities being fully<br />
protected by secrecy. The Government wil<br />
therefore adhere strictly to the practice of refusing<br />
to provide details of ASIS's activities nor will<br />
it be prepared to enter into any discussion on the<br />
Service. The Defence Signals Division<br />
The sixth report is about the Defence Signals<br />
Division. On the recommendation of the royal<br />
commission this report will not be made public.<br />
The Defence Signals Division is an organisation<br />
concerned with radio, radar and other electronic<br />
emissions from the standpoint both of the information<br />
and the intelligence that they can provide<br />
and of the security of our own Government communications<br />
and electronic emissions. It is an<br />
agency which serves wide national requirements<br />
in response to national priorities. The royal commissioner<br />
found that there were overriding<br />
advantages to Australia in co-operation with certain<br />
other countries in these matters.<br />
In close conjunction with the defence force<br />
DSD provides a capability which is just as much<br />
an integral and essential part of a modern defence<br />
posture as a capability in air or ground defence<br />
or maritime surveillance. That capability is<br />
a sophisticated one for which long periods of<br />
training and development are required. The<br />
royal commission said that ' the pr~ eservation of<br />
secrecy as to the agency's operations is vital'. This finding is accepted by the present Government.<br />
The royal commission recommended the<br />
retention of DSD, paid tribute to its work and<br />
pointed to ways in which the agency could be<br />
further developed and improved. It stated:<br />
DSD is a very capably managed agency and believed to<br />
be so by most of its staffand others who deal with it.<br />
The Government will pay close attention to the<br />
recommendations of the royal commission. In<br />
recognition of the enhanced status that the royal<br />
commission recommends should be accorded to<br />
the agency it will be restyled as the Defence Signals<br />
Directorate. In discussions of intelligence<br />
matters, this Government will not provide<br />
further information about DSD, nor confirm or<br />
deny speculation or assertion about it.<br />
Conclusion<br />
There are a number of matters particularly<br />
those covered by the fifth and sixth reports and<br />
parts of the fourth report which cannot be made<br />
public. As I mentioned earlier the Royal Commissioner<br />
has made particular recommendations<br />
on publication. All of Mr Justice Hope's reports<br />
have been made available to the Leader of the<br />
Opposition. In respect of ASlO, ASIS and DSD<br />
the Government will maintain its long-standing<br />
practice, endorsed by the royal commission of<br />
not providing information by way of comment,<br />
confirmation or denial, on matters affecting security<br />
or intelligence.<br />
Mr Speaker these reforms, together with the<br />
establishment of the Office of National Assessments<br />
and the system of co-ordination and oversight<br />
of intelligence and security policy announced<br />
in my 5 May statement, are of fundamental<br />
significance to Australia. They are also of<br />
significance in a wider sphere. As Mr Justice<br />
Hope states in his third report:<br />
Australia is, on balance, fortunate to have been able to<br />
develop close intelligence links with some of the major<br />
intelligence agencies in the western world...<br />
Mr Justice Hope's reports underline the significance<br />
of Australia's intelligence and security<br />
relationship with non-communist countries, and<br />
the importance to these countries of high quality<br />
Australian intelligence and security services.<br />
These reforms ensure that Australia's contribution<br />
in this wider sphere will be even more<br />
effective. I believe that honourable members will be<br />
assured by Mr Justice Hope's reports about the<br />
essential and fundamental need for further<br />
action by the Australian Government. He has<br />
brought to his task a perceptive realism with<br />
which he balances the requirements of national<br />
security on the one hand with the requirements<br />
Royal Commission on Security </p>
<p>4 2340 REPRESENTATIVES 25 October 1977<br />
of personal liberty on the other. He has maintained<br />
a standard of excellence in the performance<br />
of his royal commission and in the quality<br />
of the advice he has tendered the Government.<br />
His reports show a clarity of expression and<br />
probity of thought which I am sure all honourable<br />
members will applaud. I commend my predecessor<br />
for the action he has taken in launching<br />
the royal commision and my Government<br />
extends its appreciation to the New South Wales<br />
Government for releasing Mr Justice Hope for<br />
this major, arduous and important task.<br />
I present the following paper:<br />
Royal Commission in Intelligence and Security-Ministerial<br />
Statement, 25 October 1977.<br />
Motion ( by Mr Sinclair) proposed:<br />
That the House take note of the Paper.<br />
Debate ( on motion by Mr E. G. Whillam)<br />
adjourned. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
