<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18171</transcript-id>
    <title>The Inaugural Indonesia-Australia Dialogue</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/10/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The Australian Government today welcomed the beginning of the inaugural Indonesia-Australia Dialogue, to be convened from 5-6 October in Indonesia.</p>
<p>Announced during the visit to Australia by President Yudhoyono in March 2010, the dialogue brings together leading Australians and Indonesians from a wide range of backgrounds to promote people-to-people links and foster a closer understanding of each other.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister said the inaugural Indonesia-Australia Dialogue was a significant development in our growing strategic partnership with Indonesia, our close neighbour and an important regional leader.</p>
<p>It complements annual leaders' summits, our governments' agreement to launch Comprehensive Economic Partnership Agreement negotiations and annual foreign and defence ministerial discussions  -  a format Australia has with close partners.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Rudd said Indonesia was in the top tier of Australia's core relationships, and this forum would take the partnership to a new level. </p>
<p>The dialogue will promote a better understanding between Australia and Indonesia at the people-to-people level, one area of the relationship President Yudhoyono identified as lagging during his visit to Australia.</p>
<p>Twenty Australian participants have been drawn from a wide cross-section of Australian society including politics, business, academia and media.  Participants were chosen because they are prominent in their fields and can help impart understanding of a modern, dynamic Australia to the Indonesian participants in the Dialogue.</p>
<p>The Australian participants will be led by co-convenor John McCarthy, AO.  Mr McCarthy is a former diplomat with a distinguished career, including ambassadorial postings to India, the United States, Japan, Indonesia, Thailand, Mexico and Vietnam. </p>
<p>Mr McCarthy's Indonesian counterpart, Dr Rizal Sukma, is the Executive Director of the prominent Centre for Strategic and International Studies think tank in Jakarta. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
