<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5309</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENTS TO THE ADVISORY COUNCIL FOR INTER-GOVERNMENT RELATIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/03/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005309.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA WEDNESDAY, MARCH 26 1980<br />
APPOINTMENTS TO THE ADVISORY COUNCIL<br />
INTER-GOVERNMENT RELATIONS<br />
The Prime Minister today announced eight re-ap d<br />
one appointment to the Advisory Council of Inter ye nt<br />
Relations. The Advisory Council which was established in 1976 with the<br />
object of improving inter-government relations and co-operation<br />
is an essential feature of the Commonwealth Government's<br />
Federalism Policy. The 22 member Council has members representing<br />
Commonwealth, State, local government and the community.<br />
The Hon. I. G. Medcalf, Attorney-General, Minister for Federal<br />
Affairs and Leader of the Government in the Western Australian<br />
Legislative Council and the Hon. Kathleen Venn are re-appointed<br />
on the nomination of the Premiers of Western Australia and<br />
Tasmania respectively.<br />
The Australian Council of Local Government Associations has<br />
re-nominated Warden F. L. Britton of Tasmania, Councillor F. A. Roger<br />
of Queensland and Councillor William Thwaites of Victoria.<br />
The three citizen members re-nominated after ' consultation<br />
with the State Premiers include Mrs Patricia Bernard ( New South<br />
Wales), the Hon. Peter Howson ( Victoria), and Mr H. E. Peterson<br />
( Queensland)<br />
The Hon. Justice Kemeri Murray was appointed as a citizen<br />
member following consultation with the Government of<br />
South Australia.<br />
The contribution of those members appointed for a second term<br />
has been appreciated by the Commonwealth, State and local<br />
governments and their further contribution to the activitiesof<br />
the Council is welcomed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
