<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7488</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, KARACHI AIRPORT - 9 FEBRUARY 1989 E &amp; OE - PROOF ONLY</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/02/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007488.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, KARACHI AIRPORT 9 FEBRUARY 1989<br />
E 0 E' PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: There are reports today in the Pakistani press<br />
that R3Jiv Gandhi is very concerned over the recent<br />
successful missile testing and highly unlikely to be drawn to:<br />
signing any non-proliferation treaty.<br />
PM4: I suppose you can understand that. if one side is<br />
Wprepared to make a parti. cular advance the other is going to<br />
be concerned but I tnink the lesson of history is that the<br />
interests of neither side in 311y potential conflict are<br />
advanced if they just keep building up the capacity for<br />
destruction of the other. That certainly I think been<br />
understood at the level of the superpowers. I hope it wl<br />
be understood regionally.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you be putting that argument to Mr Gandhi?<br />
PM: As I have said before, I don't in advance indicate what<br />
I will be saying to people with whom an going to speak.<br />
But I think it's fairly obvious that there is a compelling<br />
logic in that which has recommended itself to the<br />
superpowers. * As I have said, Australia without seeking to<br />
intrude itself into the affairs of this region is entitled on<br />
its record to say that it has a real interest and a<br />
commitment and a capacity to contribute to the causes of<br />
O disarmament. So we will be talking frankly with the Prime<br />
Minister of India as I indeed did with the Prime Minister of<br />
Pak istan.<br />
JOURNALIST: How potentially dangerous is this sort oft<br />
stand-off between India and Pakistan?<br />
PM: I think the greatest disaster, actual as well as<br />
potential, is that it is a diversion of resources. I think<br />
that good sense will prevail between these nations and with<br />
the friends of these nations to stop any actual conflict.<br />
But the real on-going not a potential the real on-going<br />
-disaster is that in two countries which have such demand u-pon<br />
governments to provide services for their people who are in<br />
need, so much is diverted into the defence area and the<br />
capacity for destruction. That's not a potential, as I say,<br />
but an actual disaster.<br />
JOURNALIST: Given that last argument about the diversion of<br />
resources, would the Australian governmenttever consider<br />
making aid conditional on some sort of nuclear monitoring as<br />
the US Congress has done to Pakistan? </p>
<p>PM: think we are in a different position to the United<br />
States in that respect but I don't think at this stage we're<br />
looking at conditionality.<br />
ends<br />
0<br />
I I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
