<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9847</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP PRESS CONFERENCE, HANKYU HOTEL, OSAKA, JAPAN 17 NOVEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009847.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I,<br />
PRIME MINISTERI<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, HANKYU HOTEL, OSAKA, JAPAN<br />
17 NOVEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Prime Minister, In the Japanese press today there are suggestions not<br />
only in the Asian press that without the presence of Bill Clinton, it<br />
seemed a very bad signal to just how Important APEC is, and If 1 could<br />
add to that question, in Bogor, yourself, President Clinton and President<br />
Soeharto played a key role In the Leaders Meeting, without, you know, Mr<br />
Clinton on the weekend, Is there a chance that you won't be able to stIffen<br />
the resolve ( InaudIble).. free trade?<br />
PM: Well, obviously, it would be better had President Clinton been able to<br />
come, and I am very disappointed that he can't come. But he has a huge<br />
fiscal crisis a Budget Crisis on In the United States, and the Federal<br />
Government In the United States, In some parts of it, have now ceased to<br />
work for a number of days, so it is obviously a matter of great gravity for<br />
him. It Is true that the President has worked with others myself Included<br />
at now the 2 previous meetings-of APEC. The bIg meeting was the<br />
declaration meeting of Bogor the declaration for free trade by 2010 for<br />
the developed countries, and 2020 for developing countries, and now the<br />
Action Agenda Is under discussion here.-in Osaka. There has been a lot<br />
of commitment by all countries to this Including the United States and<br />
we are moving positively towards what I think will be a very substantial<br />
outcome here In Osaka. So, yes it would help If he was here, but again,<br />
the only thing that I am sure that would keep him away from here is this<br />
kind of crisis.<br />
J: How damaging is it to Australia that while you are here trying to promote<br />
Australian trade, you have got the waterfront effectively being shut down<br />
back home? </p>
<p>PM: Well, what I'm here is trying to promote a future for Australia for the next<br />
half century not the next 5 days. And this is what this is about it's<br />
about Australia's integration with the economic community of the Asia-<br />
Pacific, and It Is very much both a medium and a long-run thing, The<br />
dispute on the waterfront is one that's now had 2-3 years in the making.<br />
And that is, around -this principle that one particular company has had a<br />
religious view that Individual wage contracts are a good thing, and<br />
working under an award Is not, and that they will pay more for a contract<br />
than they will pay under an award. The ACTU and the union movement<br />
want this question of no discrimination you can at least offer working<br />
people a choice. But there is no choice there is no choice at all when<br />
there is much greater emoluments and salaries available under contracts<br />
for the same work. Now, that's the Issue on principle the CRA has been<br />
promoting it now for 2-3 years, and we are seeing the culmination of this<br />
dispute when they put civil actions on the employees. Now, I'm confident<br />
that we can get a resolution on It. The parties are now meeting around<br />
the four principles I alluded to yesterday, and I had an Indication from<br />
both parties yesterday morning the previous evening, in fact that during<br />
yesterday, we would have the matter resolved. Nevertheless, they are<br />
still speaking around the same subjects, and I think that's a very good<br />
sign.<br />
J: So you are saying that the company Is completely to blame for the<br />
present situation?<br />
PM: It wants to bust unionisation of Its sites. That Is, they will pay more in the<br />
first Instance to be rid of the union, and when the unions are gone, each<br />
Individual then has no-one to deal with but the company. Now, this has<br />
always been if you look at the United States a recipe for lower wages.<br />
Unions understand this this is what the antecedents of the dispute are.<br />
What brought it on, was putting the civil actions on. In other words, not<br />
content to have some wins at the sites industrially, they have gone after<br />
the Individuals. That's when the ACTU, of course, were forced to<br />
intervene. But that said, I am pretty sure particularly after my<br />
conversations with Mr Davis from CRA that he wants the dispute settled,<br />
and that the points that were broadly agreed on the evening before I left<br />
for Japan are the ones which will give a resolution of the dispute. Now,<br />
some of those points have been widened, I think, over the course of<br />
yesterday. They are now seeking to get them back to those essential<br />
points.<br />
J: Are you adamant that you won't change the Government's legislation?<br />
PM: It doesn't need to be changed the Government's legislation Is not an<br />
Issue here. It's all about the question whether or not there Is </p>
<p>3<br />
discrimination in offering a proposition to a worker under an Award,<br />
versus [ a worker] under a contract. That's the issue. You see, the people<br />
on the conservative side of the IR agenda in Australia the Liberal Party<br />
in particular say we will give you a choice. Well, there is no choice, if in<br />
fact you get more under the contract and you get less under an award.<br />
People say well, at least they are getting more. Well, in the short term<br />
they will, but in the long term will they? They probably won't.<br />
J: The ACTU says that the legislation allows this to happen, and that it<br />
should be changed.<br />
PM: Yes, but the ACTU is not pressing that point with me. They were not<br />
pressing that point they haven't pressed that point with me.<br />
J: Prime Minister, John Maitland announced a short while ago that the CRA<br />
mines in Queensland would be closing today, and that they are bringing<br />
forward a national stoppage to Sunday. They don't seem to share your<br />
optimism about the resolution of the dispute.<br />
PM: Well, there are two matters here. There is the waterfront stoppage, which<br />
was an action by the whole union movement, which then, of course, then<br />
effects a whole myriad of companies and Individuals across the board In<br />
the country, and then there is the question of CRA Itself. CRA has made<br />
this a site-by-site matter, and they do have mining Interests. And so, what<br />
you are probably seeing Is the CFMEU starting to narrow the dispute to<br />
CRA. But hopefully we'll get beyond all that.<br />
J: Mr Keating, have you spoken to any of the main parties today?<br />
PM: Yes, I have.<br />
J: And that's what gives you hope?<br />
PM: Well, I think that people do want us to get this settled, but it's a matter of<br />
whether... l1 think Ideology Is going to try and fear over common sense, and<br />
I think common sense will always win.<br />
J: What sort of signal do you t hink this sends to the public In the debate<br />
between the Coalition and the Government way<br />
PM: The signal to the public is this would be on In every business across the<br />
country for the rest of time certainly the next half dozen ' years if the<br />
Coalition were to win an election. What you are seeing with CRA Is a<br />
taste of what you will get under a Coalition government.<br />
I </p>
<p>J: Mr Keating, on APEC The agreement that you will be signing on Sunday<br />
allows for flexibility. What is your definition of flexibility, and do you think<br />
it differs from that of some of the Asian countries?<br />
PM: Well, we haven't published a declaration at this point, and we are not In a<br />
position to publish now the large bulk of the communique. But one thing<br />
is clear, I think, and that is that the essence of Bogor is going to be<br />
reflected here. There has been a mighty amount of work put Into this by<br />
at least the Australian Government, by the Government of Japan of<br />
course they have got pr incipal carriage of It by the United States, by all<br />
of the other players in the region. And I think they realise what the<br />
importance of the stakes are here. And that Is, to see that East Asia is<br />
going to be adequately resourced Into the future. That is, to keep growth<br />
going In East Asia, where we will need to have a free flow of goods and<br />
services, and to not have the Income disparities say, between coastal<br />
provinces of China, and the Inland provinces of Chinas* disparity of<br />
opportunities of the kind you see in Africa and these other continents. All<br />
of this leads to a more harmonious political and strategic environment.<br />
These are the issues at stake, and I think that's why people will see the<br />
broader picture.<br />
J: Would you be hoping that the language In the final communique will<br />
sound somewhat less ambiguous than what we have been led to believe It<br />
Is at the moment?<br />
PM: There's only one line that you need to really watch and that Is whether It<br />
says 2010 for the developed countries, and 2020 for developing<br />
countries. That's the key bit.<br />
J: Not the farm sector considerations?<br />
PM: There's not going to be I would be -surprised now after the work we have<br />
done and others that there are going to be exclusions for particular<br />
sectors.<br />
J: And you are confident those dates will specifically be In that<br />
communique? Not just a reiteration<br />
PM: That's what I'm here for to bang those nails Into the wall. Or to do my<br />
best to do it.<br />
J: Hasn't it already been agreed that those dates will be In it?<br />
PM: What Is agreed is what walks out of the final meeting that's what's<br />
agreed. I </p>
<p>J: Yesterday before you left you were predicting that the strike would be<br />
wrapped up and all over by midday of course, it wasn't. I was just<br />
wondering if during the nature of your discussions earlier this morning<br />
there were principles involved In this dispute are you prepared today to<br />
put any timetable on when you think it will be resolved?<br />
PM: No. But I had an indication then from the ACTU and the company that It<br />
would be near to resolution by the middle of yesterday a written<br />
indication. So, the fact that we-are still making progress, and around the<br />
same points, augers pretty well for it.<br />
J: You have had a written indication from both sides?<br />
PM: Indeed.<br />
J: How hard will it be to bang those nails into the wall just how hard?<br />
PM: Again, the situation politics of meetings is what we have all spent our lives<br />
being involved In, and so has everybody else there. And so it Is a matter<br />
of keeping. the key elements of the Bogor -Declaration, and the prospects<br />
it holds for everybody under close and serious attention. And I think if<br />
that happens if that happens we will get the result we want.<br />
J: Mr Keating, there seems to be an encouraging sign out of the US today in<br />
terms of potential cutbacks In their farm subsidy programs. What<br />
Implication will that have for us?<br />
PM: That will have very positive Implications for us, I think. I think we are<br />
starting to see an understanding that in the end, If the US wants to<br />
subsidise sectors from its central budget, In the end the whole of the USeconomy<br />
will be weaker, and it won't have the increments to growth and<br />
to product and to employment that it would otherwise have. It is,<br />
essentially, taking the trade liberalisation story further by taking some of<br />
these subsidies down.<br />
J: Given that you said earlier that you had some written Indication yesterday<br />
an undertaking from the parties that you believed it would be settled<br />
yesterday, I was just wondering if in the light that it wasn't, could you tell<br />
us whom you believed reneged on that deal that you ? 7<br />
PM: It's not a matter of reneging, It's a matter of clearing of details, but details<br />
have become more amplified. I think that is what's happened. </p>
<p>J: So, basically, did you have to spend the morning trying to get them back<br />
to those four principles is that what you are saying?<br />
PM: Well, the four principles are the key issues.<br />
J: Is that what you had the agreement on?<br />
PM: yes.<br />
J: An agreement from the ACTU, the CRA, that that would be what they are<br />
negotiating around?<br />
PM: We had an agreement between the parties, which was then put In writing,<br />
and which was then communicated between the two of them with an<br />
Indication from both of them that certainly from the company that It had<br />
to go and sort some of the details out. But hopefully then they could clear<br />
their way midday yesterday, or thereabouts.<br />
J: So what went wrong?<br />
PM: I think what happened was when you throw a matter like this inside a big<br />
industrial company which has been fighting an Issue like this for 2 or 3<br />
years, you know, all their fine-print people come out of the woodwork.<br />
J: So it was on the company's side that the problem was struck?<br />
PMV: In terms of progressing it to that point yesterday, I think yes, yet it may<br />
have been In the afternoon the ACTU then In other matters as well -I<br />
don't know.<br />
J: So the best way to describe it is that we have an agreement In principle<br />
for an end to this dispute?<br />
PM: There is an agreement In principle around these four points they need to<br />
be confirmed as to what some of the text to the points mean.<br />
J: Does the legislative remedy. ( inaudible)...?<br />
PM: No. Itfs not relevant to that.<br />
J: Have you found it at all frustrating being preoccupied with International<br />
events in the last 3 weeks, and you haven't been involved in the domestic<br />
scene? </p>
<p>PM: No. I mean, I haven't been away for that long I have been in and out of<br />
the country. Let me tell you this bringing back to Australia a set of trade<br />
arrangements for the next half century are the antithesis of frustration<br />
the absolute antithesis of frustration.<br />
J: Do you think there just needs to be some goodwill on both sides of this<br />
dispute to solve this?<br />
PM; Look, it's been fought out site by site for over 3 years. This has been a<br />
particularly drawn out and intractable matter, and you know, like all<br />
matters of weight and substance like this, where issues are hotly debated<br />
and disputed, it will take some goodwill to get to the point of settlement.<br />
J: Prime Minister, I heard what you said before, but there seems to be a<br />
sense that If this was a G7 Summit, that Bill Clinton would be here come<br />
hell or high water.<br />
PM: No. I think that the Presidenits commitment to East Asia is quite a<br />
profound one, and the concept of an Asian Pacific grouping is a profound<br />
one, and I think he would have major reservations and misgivings about<br />
not being here. And I say " major", underlined, because he was Involved<br />
with this from Seattle from the first meeting in Seattle through Bogor,<br />
and remember, he came to Indonesia two days after the Congressional<br />
drubbing the Democratic Party took in the United States. And I think he<br />
would have come here had it not been for a paramount fiscal crisis.<br />
J: With things obviously so difficult ( inaudible) could his absence make<br />
the difference between getting ( inaudible) ? 7<br />
PM: Well, I hope not. I think Vice-President Gore Is coming in his place, so<br />
the US will be represented.<br />
J: Are you running a bit of a lone race in trying to hammer home the things<br />
that you want?<br />
PM: We have made our presence felt I hope in these negotiations. I certainly<br />
had many opportunities of discussing now with Prime Minister Murayama<br />
with my visit here where I spent a lot of time on this subject, on the details<br />
of this subject with Ministers Hashimoto and Kono, and twice when they<br />
had the return visit to Australia about two months ago. And subsequently,<br />
of course;, we have had discussions with the Diet Members' League<br />
Agriculture Committee, and we have had, of course, visits here by Bob<br />
McMullan, Minister for Trade, and the Foreign Minister, Gareth Evans,<br />
and they have been involved In negotiations. And last week I also sent<br />
back with my own annotations, changes in the Declaration which the </p>
<p>Japanese Foreign Ministry communicated to us yesterday that the bulk of<br />
which were included in the Draft. So, you know, we have been in there<br />
trying.<br />
J: Prime Minister, do you have any comment on the Senate's consideration<br />
of holding up appropriations at all?<br />
PM: No I'm just not up with that, I'm not sure where that matter Is.<br />
PM: Prime Minister, Senator Evans Indicated yesterday that a deal had<br />
virtually been stitched up how much more is left for the Leaders to do on<br />
Sunday?<br />
PM: Well, again, this we believed was the case exactly at the beginning of the<br />
Bogor meeting, and then we found that a couple of countries were not<br />
completely happy with some of the text. I mean, I think we are going to go<br />
In here in a fairly good position, but It will be a matter of keeping It there.<br />
J: How would you characterise the mood last time there was a sense of<br />
euphoria that reached this landmark decision, the mood this time, Is It a<br />
case of. ( inaudible)...?<br />
PM: Well, last time it was.. let's just retrace where we have been. APEC; was<br />
a mini-OECD body, which met at Ministerial level from Its Inception you<br />
show me your economic statistics, and I'll show you mine. We have<br />
turned APEC now into a Head of Government body a complete change<br />
to get the authority of Leaders to be brought to bear to decisions and<br />
then met as a group, decided to meet a second time, and at the second<br />
time take on the ambitious project of open trade In the Pacific in goods<br />
and services by these certain time-frames. That was the big leap. Here<br />
Is [ about] putting flesh on the boneas of that structure that is, putting an<br />
Action Agenda down. And then, at the following meeting In The<br />
Philippines, will be about national country offers, and * the longer this<br />
process goes, the more likely it will be bureaucratised, and the less likely<br />
it will be the major input of the Leaders. But it will still need their authority<br />
to guide it. We're in that second stage with this one.<br />
J: Mr Keating, President Kim said that he would like to see APEC remain a<br />
consultative body rather than a negotiating body is that a sort of sign<br />
that they are backtracking on this?<br />
PM: People have all sorts of different expressions for these things and again,<br />
part of the translation Is part of the problem in all this. I think President<br />
Kim has been a very strong supporter of APEC, and he knows that to<br />
keep. I mean, on of the great challenges for Australia, for the United </p>
<p>States, Korea, Japan, is how we accommodate the burgeoning Chinese<br />
economy in the Asia Pacific. How we will let it come into the Asia Pacific<br />
economies, and how we resource it properly. And I think President Kim<br />
knows as well that it can only happen with this sort of forethought, this<br />
sort of structure. I think we might make this the last, okay?<br />
J; You said a couple of countries weren't particularly happy can you tell us<br />
which countries?<br />
PM: Oh well, in a communique of this depth, there would be at some point<br />
none of them would be happy. It's a matter of what is distilled from their<br />
real motivations in this, what they're prepared to trade away. I mean, the<br />
essence of a negotiation is trading that which is not paramount to you to<br />
keep that which is. I mean, I think this is what is of its essence a<br />
negotiation around those principles. Thank you.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
