<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3399</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR EG WHITLAM QC MP, AT THE ALP REGIONAL COUNCIL - TOWNSVILLE, SATURDAY 21 SEPTEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/09/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003399.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO : 4.00 PN<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
AT THE A. L. P. REGIONAL COUNCIL TOWNSVILLE<br />
SATURDAY 21ST SEPTEMBER, 1974<br />
I take this opportunity here in his home city and<br />
among the people he represents of congratulating Percy Tucker<br />
as Leader of the Labor Party in Queensland. I have orked with<br />
him for many years as a colleague and known him even longer as<br />
a friend. The Labor Party in Queensland has a fine leader, a<br />
respected leader, a leader who will carry it to victory in this<br />
State and work with the Australian Labor Government for the<br />
achievement of our common goals.<br />
Four days ago my colleague the Treasurer brought down<br />
the second Labor Budget in a quarter of a century. This is<br />
my first opportunity to speak to a gathering of the party since<br />
the Budget was presented. I welcome the chance to be with you<br />
because the Budget gave all of us something to celebrate. We<br />
have heard the expected outcry from the Opposition, the predictable<br />
condemnation from the wealthy, the privileged, the richest<br />
private schools, the stockbrokers, the speculators, the vested<br />
interests. What are the facts? The Budget on Tuesday was the<br />
most democratic and most radical in our history, the most<br />
comprehensive expression of the Government's ambitions and the<br />
party's philosophy that we have yet seen. It was a fair Budget,<br />
a humane Budget, a confident Budget. It was a great Labor Budgeta<br />
landmark in the party's struggle for humanity and justice.<br />
You'll remember that for weeks and months beforehand<br />
we had a welter of advice and speculation about what the Budget<br />
should contain. Economists, academics, union leaders, politicians,<br />
leader-writers the whole community was engaged in a quite<br />
unprecedented debate on the future of the economy. And I welcomed<br />
that debate.. For there was a very clear lesson to beldrawn from<br />
the abundance of conjecture and advice. It proved there was no<br />
obvious or conventional solution to our economic difficulties.<br />
Imagine what would have happened if there had been a Liberal-<br />
Country Party Budget on Tuesday night. There would have been no<br />
room for doubt or speculation then. We all know what their Budget<br />
would have done. How easy, how simple how savage that Budget<br />
would have been! Back to Dranconian measures and conventional<br />
remedies massive unemployment, bankrupt businesses, idle factories,<br />
indiscriminate monetary restrictions. And-an end to our plans<br />
for a fairer society and a brighter future for Australians.<br />
Well,. that wasn't our method. Of course we could have<br />
chosen the Liberal remedies, and I dare say if we had the Tory<br />
pundits and commentators would now be applauding our responsibility.<br />
But we weren't going to take it out on the weak, on the poor, on<br />
the disadvantaged, on the children, on the Aborigines, on the<br />
migrants, on the workers of this country. I have long held the view<br />
that the Budget is not just an economic document but a declaration<br />
of the Government's view of the kind of society we want and the<br />
kind of people we are. That is what our Budget was about. Nothing<br />
we have done has so clearly demonstrated, so clearly symbolised,<br />
this Government's philosophy and concerns, its priorities and<br />
aspirations. The choice was between Liberal remedies, discredited<br />
Liberal remedies, with the abandonment of our program, or a<br />
continuation of that program with a balanced and selective attack<br />
on inflation in which the burdens will fall on those best able to </p>
<p>-2-<br />
bear them. We have framed a Budget which will raise the living<br />
standards of the great majority of our people. We have framed<br />
a Budget that will let us carry on the fight against inflation<br />
-through flexible, discriminating measures and on a . s sound<br />
co-operation between government and unions, employeis ind<br />
employees, and all sections of the community.<br />
This wasn't one man's Budget or a victory for-one<br />
set of ideas over everything else. The Budget was the product of<br />
weeks of intensive discussion within Cabinet, with the Government's<br />
economic advisers, with the representatives of employees and<br />
industry. It represented the collective view of the Government,<br />
the whole Labor team, and in a true sense the ideals and<br />
aspirations of the whole party. Every Australian citizen is<br />
assured of a fair deal, a fair share, a fair go from our Budget.<br />
We have reduced taxation for employees on all but the highest<br />
incomes. We have cut back on lurks and tax dodges. We have<br />
made certain that those who live on rents and dividends and<br />
capital gains contribute their fair share of taxation to the<br />
revenue. We have made provision for those most in need the war<br />
veterans, the families with handicapped children, the old, the<br />
sick and the Aboriginals. And with all that, we have advanced<br />
and augmented our great programs for hospitals, schools, roads<br />
and new cities. It is the quality of these services that will<br />
determine the true standa~ d of living of our people just as much<br />
as the thickness of their pay packets.<br />
In everything we have done we have kept faith with the<br />
people, the people who twice elected. us to govern. We have laid<br />
the foundation for true national co-operation in the fight against<br />
inflation. That fight can now go forwat'with confidence. It<br />
won't be a fight in which only the fittest survive. The fittest<br />
will carry * the heaviest burden. So every employee, every trade<br />
unionist, every producer knows that from now on the f-ight will<br />
be waged by the whole community fairly and squarely. And I put<br />
it to you that it is in the interests of employees and their<br />
organisations to join that fight and safeguard the gains they<br />
have won for themselves and their families. I am not going to<br />
kid the workers of this country that the fight will be easy. I do<br />
say that the fight will be fair. Our Budget has ensured that the<br />
lowest paid worker will be especially protected from the consequences<br />
of an anti-inflationary strategy. We have established the<br />
essential conditions on which that strategy of restraint and<br />
co-operation can work. I appeal to the whole Labor movement to give<br />
it a chance to work. The rewards will be great. Employees and<br />
workers have most to gain from eventual success.<br />
One of the great aims of the Budget is to raise the<br />
standard of essential community services not just the services<br />
my Government provides, but those of the States. There has never<br />
been a Government more generous to the States. Yet I don't suppose<br />
there has been a Government more maligned and traduced by the<br />
Premiers. Our increased grants to the States did not begin with<br />
this Budget. They began with our first Budget last year and they<br />
have been augmented in numerous offers of special assistance. Our<br />
Budget on Tuesday provided massive increases-' in grants to the<br />
States of all kinds. The States will receive the largest increase<br />
in direct and special purpose grants ever made. They will receive<br />
36 percent of the total outlays in this Budget. The Budget provide~ i<br />
for a 32.4 percent increase in total expenditure and 39.5 percent<br />
of that increase will be payments to the States. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
That is the answer to the phony, neurotic accusations<br />
of centralism we hear from the Premiers. Is it centralist for<br />
our Budget to allow a greater increase in the outlay for the States<br />
than for our outlays? Is it centralist to provide the States<br />
. with record grants for roads, schools, hospitals, ii,,.-ities,<br />
sewerage and the improvement of the cities? Is it cuerlralist<br />
to approve grants of $ 56 million to the States for locdl government<br />
bodies on the recommendation of the Grants Coinmissica? Of course<br />
not. All we say is that when the taxpayers of the nation provide<br />
money for the States on such a scale they should at least have<br />
some say through their national government in how that money<br />
is used. The whole centralist catchcry is threadbare and dishonest.<br />
I suggest that for the people of Townsville the real centralism,<br />
the really pernicious and arrogant centralism, is exercised<br />
from Brisbane. Here you have a region rich in resources, a region<br />
rich in potential, rich in confidence and pride. You are part<br />
of a State equally rich and proud. My colleagues in the Australian<br />
Government share your confidence; we share your aspirations.<br />
We want this State and this region to develop and prosper. We<br />
are determined you will do so. The tragedy is that the development<br />
of Queensland and your region is being held back not by us,<br />
but by the very State Government that professes most loudly its<br />
faith in the future of your State and in need for development.<br />
on issue after issue important plans for Queensland's<br />
development have been blocked by Mr Bjelke-Petersen. Take our<br />
plans for this city, for Townsville itself. One of the first<br />
things I promised on behalf of a Labor Government promised in<br />
my policy speech in 1972 was to make Townsville a regional<br />
growth centre. Despite our representation8, despite our<br />
* correspondence, despite our personal pleas these plans have been<br />
stalled. By now the whole scheme for a greater, more prosperous<br />
Townsville could be well advanced just as it is in Albury-Wodonga.<br />
Instead it is a victim of Mr Bjelke-Petersen's prejudice and<br />
suspicion. I don't ask him to like me or to like the Labor Party.<br />
What he thinks of the Australian Government is his business.<br />
What he does for Townsville is your business and Queensland's<br />
business. The blunt truth is that Mr Bjelke-Petersen would rather<br />
deny Townsville its limitless prospect for growth than swallow his<br />
pride and work with a Labor Government. Yet here is a Premier, a<br />
Country Party Premier, who professes his belief in rural development<br />
and decentralisation. Where would Albury-Wodonga be today if the New South Wales<br />
and Victorian GOVernnlents took the same short-sighted view? They<br />
are not Labor Governments. There is little love lost between me<br />
and Sir Robert Askin or Mr Hamer for that matte They are big<br />
enough men to put the interests of their States before their<br />
personal animosities. The result has been a genuine creative<br />
partnership between the three Governments for the development of<br />
Albury-Wodonga. Our Budget on Tuesday allocated $ 40 million for the<br />
new city. A further $ 37.4 million has been provided for the<br />
establishment of other growth centres at Monarto in South Australia,<br />
Geelong in Victoria and Bathurst-orange in New South Wales. If it's<br />
good enough for Sir Robert Askin and Mr Hamer,-why isn't it good<br />
enough for Mr Bjelke-Petersen? 4 </p>
<p>Townsville cannot afford to see its progress hampered<br />
by political rivalry. The north cannot afford it, Queensland cannot<br />
afford it. Your city is firmly established as one of the great<br />
regional capitals in Queensland and its future pr : e-ss is<br />
unlimited. It has a major university, it is the centre of our<br />
northern defence programs, the chosen site of a marine science<br />
institute of international renown. With so much at stake, the<br />
future of Townsville and its region, and indeed all northern<br />
development, will depend on a healthy and productive<br />
relationship between the State and national Governments. Townsville<br />
has more to lose than any other city in Australia if politics is<br />
allowed to cloud and disrupt the one aim we all want to achieve<br />
the development of the north, with more industry, more job<br />
opportunities, and improved facilities for present and future<br />
generations of Australians.<br />
If North Queenslanders have reason to complain about<br />
government from the south they should direct their complaints to<br />
Brisbane rather than Canberra. All our objectives for the State<br />
and particularly for the north our plans to halt spiralling<br />
land prices, to improve the quality of life, to make urban<br />
development more equitable and efficient have been held up in<br />
Brisbane. ' Our 1973/ 74 Budget allocated $ 2 million for land<br />
acquisition and development works in Townsville, $ 1.2 million<br />
for similar work in the Moreton region and $ 1.2 million for<br />
Gladstone. It is incredible that none of these funds have been<br />
spent simply because we cannot reach agreement with the<br />
Queensland Premier.<br />
So there is a real danger that Queensland's development<br />
will fall behind. I instance our plans f6r Land Commissions.<br />
* The Budget this year provides $ 24 million to South Australia for the<br />
purchase of land. That land will be resold to home buyers at<br />
fair and reasonable prices. The land price spiral in* South Australia<br />
has been effectively brought under control. We are providing<br />
$ 16 million to Victoria for a similar purpose. Even Sir Robert<br />
Askin has agreed in principle to our Land Commission. Queensland<br />
says NO. Or take our sewerage program. In 1973/ 74 Townsville<br />
was eligible for assistance under the national sewerage scheme.<br />
Mr Bjelke-Petersen wouldn't take the money. In 1574/ 75 we are<br />
allocating $ 13 million to Queensland for sewerage works. Townsville's<br />
share will be well over a quarter of a million.<br />
The other States are getting on with the job. Why should<br />
the people of Queensland put up with unsewered houses because of<br />
Mr Bjelke-Petersen' s dislike of Canberra? This is an issue on which<br />
the Premier must carry the can. And why should Queensland be<br />
denied, an international airport at Townsville? Again I ask:<br />
if it's good enough for the Liberal Premiers of New South Wales<br />
and Victoria why isn't it good enough for the Country Party<br />
Premier of Queensland?<br />
The Premier clings to his obstinate ban on shipping<br />
between Queensland ports. He prefers to hold back development and<br />
decentralisation in the State rather than let an Australian<br />
Government ship do the work. This is ideologidal prejudice of<br />
the silliest, most self-defeating kind. Within 14 days of taking<br />
office in December 1972 I offered the use of Australian National<br />
Line ships for intra-State trade on the Queensland coast.<br />
Mr Bjelke-Petersen said the matter would receive consideration.<br />
I spoke to him about it in March last year. I wrote to him again<br />
in April and June this year. My last letter brought no reply. </p>
<p>Ineed hardly stress the importance of a regular<br />
intra-State shipping service. It would provide an alternative means<br />
of transport when the highways or railways are cut by floods.<br />
It would provide a more rational and diversified transport system.<br />
It would maximise the efficiency of the Townsville Harbour Board's<br />
facilities for handling freight. There are some types of freight<br />
that can only be carried by sea. We have seen the farcical<br />
situation of foreign-owned ships engaged to carry bauxite from<br />
Weipa to Gladstone because the Queensland Government refused to<br />
let an Australian Government ship do the work. There are ships<br />
plying between Queensland and the other States with space in their<br />
holds for 1000 tons of intra-State cargo on every voyage. I am<br />
afraid the Premier's intransigence finds little support from the<br />
people of North Queensland. The North Queensland Chambers of<br />
Commerce don'It agree with him. The Queensland Harbour Board<br />
Association doesn't agree with him. The Townsville District<br />
Development Bureau and the Townsville City Council don't agree<br />
with him. Why should the people of Townsville agree with him?<br />
We have put forward other measures to help Queensl and's<br />
industrial development. For years I have been concerned at the<br />
high cost of electricity in Queensland compared with other<br />
eastern States. There are complex reasons for these higher costs<br />
but the Australian Government wants to help reduce them. I wrote<br />
to Mr Bjelke-Petersen on 5 June. I proposed that the Australian<br />
Government, in conjunction with Queensland, undertake a study of<br />
ways and means of increasing efficiency and reducing costs within<br />
the Queensland power system. The Premier has not replied; his<br />
department told us it was examining our offer.<br />
I wrote to the Premier within weeks of the Government<br />
assuming office and offered to assume responsibility for the<br />
uneconomic ' State railway system. Railways impose a crippling<br />
burden on State finances and distort their whole budget. We<br />
waited a long time but eventually we got our answer. The<br />
Queensland Government was not even prepared to discuss our proposal.<br />
The fact is that no Government has treated Queensland<br />
more generously, more openly, than mine. I read a remark by<br />
Sir Gordon Chalk the other day that the Queensland Budget this<br />
year would be " the best State Budget in Australia". I congratulate<br />
the Treasurer of Queensland. I trust the people of Queensland<br />
will remember that this * situation has been largely made possible<br />
by the Australian Government' s grants. Let's hear no more about<br />
us starving or strangling the States. It's claptrap! Total<br />
revenue assistance to Queensland in 1970/ 71 to go back four<br />
years was $ 223 million. The estimated total in the present<br />
Budget is nearly double $ 434 million. Payments for general<br />
purpose capital funds have increased in the same period from<br />
$ 93 million to $ 145 million. Our assistance has increased over<br />
a whole range of special purpose grants universities from<br />
$ 7 million to $ 41 million; colleges of advanced education from<br />
million to $ 24.5 million; Aboriginal advancement from<br />
$ 216,000 to $ 2,085,000; community health from nothing to $ 2.9 million<br />
/ 6 </p>
<p>How revealing to contrast the priorities of the<br />
Queensland and Australian Labor Governments! What are! the issues<br />
that occupy us, the matters that dominate our rftin(. I We could<br />
be pardoned for thinking that nothing is more important to the<br />
Queensland Premier than appointing a Queen of Queensland. Is that<br />
really an issue in 1974? Do we want a Queen of New South Wales<br />
and a Queen of Victoria as well? A Queen of Western Australia<br />
and a Queen of Tasmania? Does Canada need a Queen of Ontario and<br />
a Queen of Price Edward Island? Perhaps I am wrong. Perhaps<br />
the most important issue in Mr Bjelke-Petersen's mind is the<br />
Privy Council. He wants decisions made by judges appointed by<br />
his own Government to be subject to veto by judges appointed by<br />
the British Government. Is that a burning issue in 1974? We<br />
know how much the Premier of Queensland relies on the courts. He<br />
is still using the courts to fight our legislation, to challenge<br />
the decisions of the joint sitting of the Australian Parliament,<br />
to overturn the wishes of the Australian people who twice gave<br />
their endorsement to the program of reform initiated by the<br />
Australian Labor Party.<br />
I have no personal animosity towards Mr Bjelke-Petersen. I just<br />
wish he'd make up his mind what he wants for his State. We know<br />
what he wants for the Country Party a mandate to govern with<br />
percent of the vote, or preferably less. The fact is the<br />
Queensland's electoral boundaries are flagrantly rigged in the<br />
Country Party's favour. Its not just a little extra weighting<br />
for the benefit of remote rural seats. It's a masterpiece of<br />
malapportionment. In the 1972 State elections it took 12,849<br />
votes to elect one Labor member. It to * ok 9,163 votes to elect<br />
one Liberal member and 6,977 votes to elect one Country Party<br />
member. Provincial cities like Townsville suffer as much as<br />
Brisbane. ' The boundaries are blatantly designed to reduce<br />
their representation. The average enrolment in a provincial<br />
city electorate is 14,476. In the Western and Far Northern Zone<br />
it is 8,153. In the Country Zone it is 10,779. Under any fair<br />
system of boundaries the Townsville area would merit at least<br />
one additional seat in the Queensland Parliament.<br />
So apart from a gerrymander, what does Mr Bjelke-Petersen<br />
want for Queensland? Does he want it to be part of Australia<br />
or a private realm of his own? Does he want it to share in<br />
the nation's progress or become a backwater? I wish he'd. shake<br />
off his hangups and pettifogging obsessions about State rights<br />
and centralism and the monarchy and the Privy Council and get<br />
down to the business of government. I wish he'd forget his<br />
persecution complex and realise that the Australian Government<br />
is ready and willing to work with him for the good of Queensland.<br />
I wish he'd spare us his tantrums and posturing and let us get<br />
on with the job together. It is frankly not a pretty sight<br />
to see a proud and important State held back by its own Government.<br />
What we need is not a full-time Queen of Queensland but a fulltime<br />
Premier of Queensland. Less vaudeville, less invective,<br />
less vote-rigging more action, more enterprise, more co-operation.<br />
/ 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
In the 21 months since we came to office the<br />
Australian Government has offered the States a new deal. We<br />
have offered Queensland a new deal. The Budget we brought<br />
down this week confirmed that offer. It opened the way to<br />
a limitless future for this State and for all Australians<br />
a future based on equity and justice. To achieve those goals<br />
we ask nothing more, we need nothing more, than a reasonable<br />
spirit of co-operation and goodwill. Let us get on with the<br />
job of building a stronger and more prosperous Queensland<br />
in a stronger and more prosperous nation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
