<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2542</transcript-id>
    <title>SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON, CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/02/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002542.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: Until 10.00 am 23/ 2/ 1972 CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM 23 February 1972<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr William McMahon, M. P.<br />
On behalf of the Australian Government I welcome you to<br />
Canberra for the Second Session of the South Pacific: Most<br />
of you have been he-re before, but this is the first ti; we meet<br />
together in Australia as neighbours and friends to discuss matters of<br />
bommon interest. During my period of office as Foreign Minister, I wholeheartedly<br />
supported the concept so I have a direct personal interest<br />
in the Forum. Obviously there was a need for a forum for political<br />
discussions as well as discussions about other matters of common<br />
interest. In short we need -a forum such as this. And I recommended<br />
to my colleagues we should identify ourselves with the Forum when it<br />
was set up. I assure you we will co-operate in every way we can. We<br />
share a common purpose for peace, . security and progress in the South<br />
Pacific Region and our destinies are permanently linked in many ways.<br />
Historically, the first links were forged when Captain Cook<br />
explored the Pacific two hundred years ago. He then established links<br />
between Australia, New Zealand and the Islands which have increasingly<br />
brought us closer together in friendship and trade. And, we share the<br />
conviction that independence, freedom and security are the rights of<br />
our peoples. We are all involved in the hectic movement of political<br />
and economic change that marks our time. This helps to strengthen our<br />
relationships and gives us a regional identity in the wider world beyond<br />
the South Pacific. And like you, we are busy with the adventure of<br />
nation building, economic development and social progress. We possess<br />
in common the tradition of parliamentary democracy and a community of<br />
interest in the ties and institutional patterns of the British<br />
Commonwealth. But we recognise, too, a wider Pacific community with<br />
which each of us is already linked in the South Pacific Commission.<br />
This Forum has, in a sense, other and wider political interests<br />
to pursue. Equally it is able to build on our experience of co-operation<br />
and adaptation to change which has marked the twenty-five years of the<br />
Commission. We live in an era of aroused expectations, stimulated by<br />
the ease of travel and the soread of communications If a world where<br />
every Government has to chart a course and navigate according to its<br />
assessment of its own best interests. But none of us can be wholly<br />
self-sufficient, or live in isolation. Neither can we afford to neglect<br />
opportunities to widen our duderstanding of the environment in which we<br />
live, or to make known our interests to those who share that environment<br />
with us. We must continually develop our capacity in self-reliance<br />
against the background that the formal protection by other powers which<br />
was previously part of our colonial experience, is no longer wholly<br />
valid. For these reasons I welcome you to this meeting. </p>
<p>S 2.<br />
There are many practical issucs and questions of immediate<br />
concern on the agenda, and we look forwafdto the opportunity to learn<br />
about your problems and the solutions which you favour. In fact and<br />
substance this is a meeting where we are all equal and where the<br />
importance of regional co-operation is uppermost in our minds.<br />
our first meeting in Wellington was a natural success.<br />
It showed that despite our diverse histories, we had 1problems in<br />
common and the will to solve them. I am confident that this meeting<br />
will be as successful and my Government will spare no effort to make<br />
it so. It is my hope that from this meeting will develop a stronger<br />
friendship to reinforce our sense of regional identity and common<br />
pu. rpose, harnessed to the welfare arnd prosperity of all the peoples<br />
of the South Pacific.<br />
We are glad so many of you have found it possible, in spite<br />
of your many and urgent responsibilities, to spare the time to see at<br />
first hand a little of our country and our Australian community which<br />
shares to the full in the welcome I give you today.<br />
I declare the Forum open.<br />
CAN) ERRA<br />
23 February 1972 </p>
<p>N </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
