<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7022</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER`S REMARKS AT THE PRESENTATION OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEACE AWARDS THE LODGE, 22 OCTOBER 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007022.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
PRIMIE MINISTER'S REM4ARKS AT THE<br />
1VnESENTATION OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEACE AWARDS<br />
THE LODGE, 22 OCTOBER 1986<br />
I am sure that none of us6 here least of all those whose<br />
efforts andc achievements have earned recognition as<br />
recipient3 of Australian Peace Awards regard such awards<br />
as an end n themselves.<br />
The individual3 and organisations selected for these Awards<br />
represent only a very small proportion of the many<br />
Australians who are working for peace and who have given<br />
effect to the ideals of the International Year of Peace with<br />
dedication and commitment.<br />
Just as the Government believes that the issues of peace and<br />
disarmairent are too important to be left to the super-powers<br />
and the other nuclear powers, so by your efforts you have<br />
demonstratod that ordinary Australians believe these issues.,<br />
cannot be left to Government. And you are right.<br />
The Australian Peace Atwards seek to recognise the<br />
contributions which Australians have made across a wide<br />
range of octivities designed to promote arms control, peace<br />
and international security. In particular, the Awards<br />
honour efforts made to strengthen the United Nations as the<br />
principal international organisation devoted to the<br />
maintenance of peace; to promote international co-operation<br />
and the resolution of conflict on the basis of the UN<br />
Charter; and to focus attention on the important building<br />
blocks for creating lasting stability and peace in the<br />
world, including effective and verifiable arms control, the<br />
protection of human rights, the interrelationship between<br />
peace, economic development and social progress, the<br />
elimination of racial discrimination, and other related<br />
issues.<br />
The recipients of these Awards whom we honour today have<br />
contributed towards these objectives in a significant and<br />
inspiring way.<br />
Your contributions cover a wide range of activities<br />
including promotion of the ideals of the IYP among trade<br />
unions, women's groups, rural communities, municipal<br />
organisations, academia, aboriginal people, and others. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Despite its diversity, your work has a common theme: a<br />
desire to leave a world at peace as the inheritance of the<br />
next generation.<br />
On behalf of the Government, I warmly congratulate you on<br />
your achievements and on the valuable work you are<br />
undertaking. You have not succumbed to the paralysis of despair. It<br />
would be a tragedy if our young people, in particular, were<br />
to be so weighed down at the remote prospect of nuclear war<br />
as not to care adequately about their own self development<br />
or to contribute to our society in a positive and energetic<br />
way. You have sought to decode the often confusing language of<br />
arms control, its acronyms and its technical jargon. You<br />
have not allowed the so-called experts to monopolise the<br />
debate.<br />
Above all, you have let the political leadership of this<br />
country, and of the international community, know of your<br />
desire for tangible progress towards a saner, safer world.<br />
For our part, the Government will continue to exert pressure<br />
on the super-powers to reach arms control agreements for<br />
deep cuts in their nuclear arsenals leading to their<br />
ultimate elimination. It would be a disaster if the<br />
progress made at Reykjavik were to go for nothing and the<br />
arms race to continue its bizarre and dangerous course<br />
unchecked. We need not only your support but your continued<br />
representations and pressure towards this end, which is of<br />
critical importance for Australians and for all mankind.<br />
I congratulate the many Australians who have contributed to<br />
the success of the IYP in Australia.<br />
Today we congratulate, in particular, those Australians who<br />
have made an outstanding contribution.<br />
Through the presentation of these Awards, we honour you for<br />
your idealism, your practical work and the inspiration you<br />
have given to others. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
