<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9092</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP NATIVE TITLE BILL- IMPLEMENTATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/12/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009092.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
NATIVE TITLE BILL IMPLEMENTATION<br />
The passage of the Native Title Bill is an important step towards justice for<br />
Australias indigenous people.<br />
Australia now has a coherent framework for dealing with native title, as<br />
established by the High Court in June 1992.<br />
The Government is moving now to implement the scheme.<br />
The legislation will come into force from 1 January 1994. There will be no<br />
hiatus between the cut-aff date for validation of past grants and Acts, 31<br />
December 1993) and the commencement of operation of the new land<br />
management regime. This will provide the certainty sought by the<br />
Government and interested parties.<br />
The full Institutional structure for determining native title claims and managing<br />
dealings affecting native title land, and permanent appointments to those<br />
Institutions, will be put in place as rapidly as possible in the new year. In the<br />
meantime, from 1 January, the President of the Administrative Appeals<br />
Tribunal has agreed to act as President of the Native Title Tribunal and the<br />
Registrar of the MAT will act as Registrar of the Tribunal. I am grateful to<br />
Justice O'Connor and her colleagues for their active help and co-operation in<br />
this important national enterprise.<br />
A Task Force in my Department, headed by a Deputy Secretary, supported by<br />
other key agencies such as the Attorney-General's Department and the<br />
Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commission, is already well advanced<br />
on arrangements to implement the legislation. In particular, the necessary<br />
regulations are being prepared; designated Aboriginal organisations to<br />
represent claimants are being identified; discussions are under way with<br />
States and Territories willing to co-operate with the Commonwealth scheme<br />
on recognition of State and Territory institutions and processes according to<br />
the criteria in the Bill; and a range of other matters is being addressed. 155/ 93 </p>
<p>2<br />
The Government is determined to devote the resources and the effort<br />
necessary to establish the Native Title framework and to make it work.<br />
We wish to do so in co-operation with States and Terrtories. A national<br />
approach remains our clear objective.<br />
The Commonwealth Government is also committed to sharing with co-<br />
Operating States and Territories the costs of compensation for any necessary<br />
validation of past grants and Acts and for administrative and legal expenses.<br />
Our intention is to finalise these details early in the new year.<br />
The legislation Is constitutionally sound. Any challenge to it would prove<br />
fruitless and be counter to the common objective of certainty in land<br />
management. The Bill provides every opportunity for States and Territories<br />
to retain control of land management as It affects native title, and they should<br />
support the Bill.<br />
We now move on to address the wider opportunities presented by Mabo for a<br />
just reconciliation between indigenous and non-indigenous Australians. In<br />
particular, we will be giving priority to establishing, in consultation with<br />
Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people, the land acquisition initiative<br />
provided for in the legislation. The target date for the establishment of the<br />
land acquisition arrangements is 1 July 1994.<br />
With the passage of the legislation Australia has an unparalleled opportunity<br />
to establish a new era of legal, social and economic justice for the oldest<br />
Australians the original occupants of our country.<br />
CANBERRA 23 DECEMBER 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
