<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9531</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP SIR JOHN MONASH MEMORIAL LECTURE, REGENT HOTEL, MELBOURNE 29 MARCH 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009531.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
/ b<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED 6.3OPM 29 MARCH 1995<br />
* AS DELI VERED*<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
SIR JOHN MONASH MEMORIAL LECTURE, REGENT HOTEL, MELBOURNE<br />
29 MARCH 1995<br />
Thank you very much, Race, for inviting me to give this lecture.<br />
Sir John Monash stands among the highest order of Australians and I count it as<br />
an honour of the highest order to deliver the lecture which bears his name.<br />
Let me also add my voice to Kim Beazley's when he gave the inaugural address<br />
last year, and say how pleased I am to see the Monash Graduate School of<br />
Government up and flourishing.<br />
It is mandatory these days to judge the worth of things by the degree to which<br />
they increase a nation's " competitiveness". I will not take issue with this. You<br />
will hear me use that word more than once tonight. We do have to be<br />
competitive world competitive and we cannot be that without an efficient<br />
government sector.<br />
But let me also say that an efficient government sector a knowledgeable,<br />
professional, imaginative government sector is equally essential to the creation<br />
of a good society; and, because it is an investment in our human resources and<br />
is bound to make us stronger and more cohesive, it will in itself make us more<br />
competitive.<br />
And let me just say this I hope the direction of your thinking is pragmatic. I<br />
hope it is about imagining what might be done and how to do it. I hope it is<br />
about what can be done, not what can't. </p>
<p>The world and especially bureaucracies. public and private is full of people<br />
who learn first to cover themselves off against all misadventure, and only<br />
afterwards address the task. And, of course, the worst misadventure is to have a<br />
mistake pinned on them.<br />
This is a very conservative and debilitating phenomenon.<br />
It is a short step from avoiding risk, to avoiding responsibility, and a very short<br />
one then to avoiding doing anything at all.<br />
The disease of carefully disguised inactivity or professional nay-saying can<br />
afflict any organisation, including political parties. It is no better or less irritating<br />
than professional idealism that is the habit of talking loftily without the faintest<br />
intention of acting practically. That is why I say I hope that the Monash<br />
Graduate School of Government will inject into the culture of government an<br />
ethic of doing. Not finding the obstacles to achievement, but the paths to it.<br />
Dare I say that I have a strong feeling that John Monash would have approved of<br />
nothing less.<br />
Monash was nothing if not a doer. He was a man of true greatness. He made a<br />
mighty contribution to our military history, of course, and in doing that he was<br />
one of those who forged the great tradition of the first AIF<br />
He remains Australia's most famous soldier.<br />
When we ask why did he succeed in so much? we can find all kinds of<br />
reasons. Clearly he had a powerful, logical mind and superb gifts as an<br />
administrator. Lloyd George called him " the most resourceful General in the<br />
whole of the British Army", the " greatest strategist" and said that he would have<br />
and should have become Commander-In-Chief.<br />
Yet for all his success as a soldier, few gave the country more than Monash<br />
gave us as a civilian.<br />
In fact, it is difficult to think of another Australian who left behind such a unique<br />
combination of memorials to his work. I doubt if anyone ever left so many in<br />
such a small area.<br />
There is the Anderson Street Bridge which he built across the Yarra and, within<br />
a mile of it, a statue commemorating his service as a military commander. Then,<br />
within the same small precinct, there is the Shrine which he helped to build. All<br />
of this just down the hill from the Richmond school he attended. And all of it<br />
connected to the power supply he founded in the 1920s at Yallourn. </p>
<p>Now, of course. I wouldn't venture a guess at what he would make of the plans to<br />
privatise his creation, but I have a feeling that he would not let sentiment or<br />
ideology stand in the way of the most practical means of delivering electricity to<br />
Victorians. He seems to me to have been an eminently practical man, and I imagine quite<br />
immune to ideological fashion. I can no more imagine him in the New Right than<br />
in the Old Left. I suspect he was of the camp which says so long as It is a<br />
useful idea which will help us meet our goals, it does not matter what we call it.<br />
Of all the things John Monash bequeathed us, I'm inclined to think that at this<br />
stage of our history none is more important than his pragmatic philosophy.<br />
In fact, we can safety infer from his remarkable achievements the qualities which<br />
must have most distinguished him: self discipline, the courage of his convictions,<br />
an enormous capacity for work, vision, decisiveness.<br />
Seen from our vantage point what strikes us most about the man is something<br />
like an absence of doubt.<br />
I dlaresay there have been many Australians whose intellectual powers matched<br />
Monash's and whose ambitions were the equal of his.<br />
But very few achieved what he achieved.<br />
I hope you get my drift. In Government one is always trying to narrow the gap<br />
between vision and realisation, between policies and implementation, between<br />
ideas and their concrete manifestation in effective and useful reform.<br />
So when we look at a career like that of John Monash, we ask what lessons can<br />
be drawn for government, for public policy in the modern era.<br />
Now I might say, inter a/ ia, that I was struck by something he said in a letter he<br />
wrote as a young man to his first love. He said that many people had tried to trip<br />
him up, tried to stop him in his youthful ambitions, and that he had been forced<br />
to leave those so-called ' friends' behind and had become unpopular. There will<br />
be others in the room who have had this experience.<br />
Of course the problems of governments is that they can't afford to be unpopular<br />
at least not for too long. But nor can good governments afford to merely pursue<br />
that which is popular.<br />
Good policy is not always popular not at first, at least.<br />
Yet I suspect more general and more productive conclusions can be drawn than<br />
this one. </p>
<p>Ever since the war in which Monash played so illustrious a part, the same<br />
question has been asked: how different would the world be if all that youthful<br />
ambition, energy and intellect had not been wasted on those battlefields? How<br />
many scientists and engineers; how many artists and philosophers; how many<br />
leaders were lost?<br />
How many Monashs?<br />
Of course, it is not so much a question as a melancholy reflection. It is really a<br />
statement of despair.<br />
A more useful question for our times might be what gave Monash that certainty<br />
what gave him the confidence which enabled him to achieve so much? What<br />
gave him the ability to inspire the same confidence in others?<br />
All sorts of largely imponderable psychological possibilities aside, we might<br />
reasonably conclude that this characteristic flowed from a clear set of values to<br />
live by: from an unshakable respect for the democratic institutions of this country<br />
and for the cultural traditions Australian, British, Prussian and Jewish he<br />
inherited; from a profound sense of civic duty; and an equally profound belief in<br />
his country's future.<br />
Marry these beliefs to talent and ambition, and you have at least the beginnings<br />
of a great nation-builder.<br />
The question begs to be asked can we, in the altogether different country we<br />
now live in, marry them to the talents and ambitions of contemporary<br />
Australians? Can we put the same certainty, the same absence of doubt, into the lives of<br />
young Australians?<br />
I don't know the answer to that, but I believe we must try.<br />
For example, if you ask me what is my best reason for replacing our present<br />
Head of State with an Australian, it is that the affections of young Australians for<br />
the British Monarchy are not what they were in Monash's day or my father's<br />
day. And they will diminish further we can be sure that within the space of half<br />
a generation the affection will not be as great as it is today, our day.<br />
But Australians will continue to need a Head of State who inspires their respect<br />
and affection. They will need someone who embodies the nation's ideals and<br />
aspirations. </p>
<p>Someone who is to their generation what Monash became to his. He would, of<br />
course, have made a splendid Governor-General. His equivalent today would<br />
make a splendid President and you will forgive me for making the observation<br />
that it is hard to imagine him contesting a general election for the office.<br />
The move to an Australian Head of State will of course help to define us to<br />
ourselves and to the world.<br />
And it is important to define ourselves just now.<br />
Some of the reasons for this seem to me self-evident. We are living in an era of<br />
extraordinary change both within Australia and in the world and in our<br />
relationship with the world. Knowing who we are and letting others know will<br />
surely be a useful aid to our success.<br />
We are not talking in terms of the ideology of 19th century nation states or<br />
century nation states for that matter.<br />
We are talking about drawing a line around the loose, pluralistic, federal<br />
democracy which is contemporary Australia and having that line define our<br />
loyalty, our values, our identity.<br />
We are talking about a definition of ourselves which embraces not just the<br />
multicultural facts of our contemporary existence, but our increasing integration<br />
with the cultures of the region and the world, and with their economies.<br />
We are talking about definitions of a people who are in many ways more worldly<br />
than their predecessors, whose tastes and values are less vigorously defined,<br />
and whose greatest need in the 21st century may well be the capacity to cope<br />
with change.<br />
Most of you will know that last year we commissioned an expert group to provide<br />
us with a report on civics education in Australia on the community's<br />
understanding of our democratic values, institutions and history and on the best<br />
means of increasing it.<br />
We received an outstanding report which left us in no doubt that we should<br />
proceed to adopting civics education on a nationwide scale.<br />
It is reasonable to think that by this means we can invest Australians not only<br />
with more knowledge of their country but with more faith in it who knows, with<br />
some of the certainty that Monash and his generation seem to have felt. </p>
<p>But again we would stress that the values will be different to those of earlier<br />
generations. We can and should teach our best traditions the democratic,<br />
egalitarian traditions. We should make sure that our great institutions are<br />
understood, respected and appreciated.<br />
We should teach our history and give all Australians the means by which they<br />
may understand themselves as part of the Australian story.<br />
But some elements of the old tradition will be left behind, or at least the<br />
emphases must change. Some of our old traditions, for instance, cast women in<br />
a roles which are entirely unacceptable and inappropriate today. Some do not<br />
speak of the tolerance which underpins modern multicultural Australia.<br />
The creation of this extraordinarily diverse contemporary Australian culture is<br />
perhaps our greatest post-war achievement, and I believe we should enshrine<br />
the values which sustain it for the generations of today and tomorrow.<br />
Monash and his generation felt an attachment to the British Empire and British<br />
civilisation which we can neither share nor emulate.<br />
Yet I'm inclined to think that, properly understood, our contact with the world at<br />
large and our increasing ability to understand and communicate with different<br />
cultures offers a future which is just as fulfilling.<br />
We will never feel about our region what earlier generations felt about the<br />
Empire; but there is a growing sense of excitement about Australia's Asia-Pacific<br />
future which matches the promise it holds. If it is true that earlier generations of<br />
Australians felt it was a blessing to have inherited the Empire and its institutions,<br />
the next generation might yet see their own region as conferring something<br />
similar on them.<br />
I think I hardly need to say again that this is why we have pursued the goals of<br />
APEC with such determination.<br />
I said after the Bogor Declaration last year that this was something which future<br />
generations might thank us for. It was not something which had to happen: it<br />
was something we decided to make happen.<br />
It will mean greater prosperity and more jobs in the future. It is a big step<br />
towards setting Australia up in the 21st century. It is a big step towards setting<br />
the countries of the region up. Yet it should be recognised that the benefits are<br />
by no means all in the future. </p>
<p>They have already begun to flow. most importantly in the fillip that the process of<br />
developing APEC has given to a regional consciousness. In Australia I think this<br />
has been a quite profound development. Just three years ago to talk about our<br />
future in Asia still produced scepticism and even hostility. It doesn't any more.<br />
Two years ago to talk about getting all the heads of government together, from<br />
Washington to Tokyo to Beijing to Jakarta, was commonly met with cynicism. To<br />
suggest, even just 12 months ago, that at Bogor those heads of government<br />
would agree to free trade between the developed countries by 2010 and<br />
between all by 2020 was to invite derision.<br />
But these things happened and Australia played a leading role in making them<br />
happen. That in itself should give us confidence. But nothing comes close to<br />
the confidence we can draw from the burgeoning business we are already doing<br />
in the region and, especially as APEC develops, the limitless potential for doing<br />
more. If John Monash set one example it was that each generation has a responsibility<br />
to the next.<br />
Yet that heroic generation of Monash's did not see Aboriginal Australians as part<br />
of the country's future. We do. And it seems to me that the next generation<br />
could reasonably ask of ours that we do all we can to finally set things right with<br />
the original inhabitants of this continent. So we are doing it with Mabo; with the<br />
Land Fund, with the process of reconciliation; and, by every practical means at<br />
our disposal, with solutions to the problems of Aboriginal health.<br />
On the other hand, Monash's generation did not have a moment's doubt about<br />
projects which were deemed to be plainly in the national interest. Irrigation<br />
projects, land clearances for farms, forest industries all proceeded without<br />
hesitation or impediment. It is not so now and we should be thankful that it's<br />
not: even if it means we must accommodate the rather unsettling thought that<br />
our generation might have thwarted Monash's efforts to develop the brown coal<br />
resources in the La Trobe Valley it certainly would not have happened without<br />
an Environmental Impact Study.<br />
But the truth is we can no longer pretend that the pursuit of ecologically<br />
sustainable development is an option for Australia rather it is an imperative, a<br />
challenge we have to meet, an obligation we have to the Australians of the 21st<br />
century. Now there are a lot of commentators out there some incessant, some periodic<br />
who say that all these government concerns are only marginally legitimate. </p>
<p>In waves they descend upon the political debate saying we must only address<br />
the economy. Everything else, they say, is a diversion or an indication that the<br />
Government has jumbled its priorities.<br />
It is humbug of course. We cannot successfully attend to the needs of our<br />
economy without attending to the social fabric, to cultural and human needs, to<br />
national cohesion.<br />
We delivered an arts statement last year because in the next century nations will<br />
increasingly succeed or fail according to the capacity of their people to think<br />
creatively and creatively adapt new technology.<br />
We delivered it for any number of other reasons, but none were so important as<br />
this and probably none so plainly illustrates that governments cannot separate<br />
the economic from the cultural or social.<br />
These efforts are of the same character as building bridges or power stations or<br />
even shrines of remembrance they are all parts of contemporary nation<br />
building. And all successful nations make these efforts.<br />
But the commentators are right in so far as it is true that we can do none of these<br />
things unless we create a competitive, adaptable, successful Australian<br />
economy and therefore it is no less true that this is our greatest responsibility<br />
to future generations.<br />
If we are talking about putting certainty and faith and belief into the lives of<br />
Australians, we are talking about an economy which in an uncertain world<br />
delivers opportunity and security to Australian families.<br />
Above all we are talking about jobs.<br />
Nothing erodes belief in a society as efficiently as unemployment: nothing<br />
sustains it as efficiently as jobs.<br />
This is something which has not changed. Employment remains by far the most<br />
effective way to distribute the nation's wealth and the most concrete proof that<br />
we continue to take our egalitarian ideals and traditions seriously.<br />
Today it is being put around that the economic recovery is over. It is, we're told,<br />
just a fleeting moment and now the sky is falling in. For those who have fallen<br />
prey to this notion, and have begun to walk around with heads bowed and<br />
thinking tomorrow will never come, let me provide the antidote. I mean the facts.<br />
Let me start with the growth in employment and the decline in unemployment. </p>
<p>The recovery has created 560,000 jobs since March 1993 on average 720 new<br />
jobs every day.<br />
Over 1994, unemployment has decreased by 1.7 per cent, the greatest one year<br />
reduction since the Bureau of Statistics began the Labour Force Survey 30 years<br />
ago, and the second highest reduction last year in the OECD.<br />
Last month the figures were as strong as they have been at any time in the last<br />
two years, with 90,000 new jobs created. So long as we are vigilant with the<br />
macroeconomic settings, the indications are that this is sustainable. And vigilant<br />
and active we are being.<br />
This extraordinary job growth is occurring against a backdrop of restrained<br />
wages growth. Wage inflation is very much under control the last quarter's<br />
data show an overall annual increase of about 4.1 per cent. This is entirely in<br />
keeping with the Accord commitments of the Government and the unions.<br />
It has happened in part because the new industrial relations system gives a high<br />
priority to enterprise-based bargaining an essential response to internationally<br />
changed circumstances which require the Australian labour market to be taken<br />
into the modern competitive environment. Enterprise-based bargaining is one of<br />
the reasons for employment growth.<br />
There are now 1.44 million people covered by certified agreements 56 per cent<br />
of those covered by Federal awards.<br />
These agreements recognise the mutual interests of companies and workers.<br />
They have delivered responsible and mature wage outcomes on average,<br />
increases of 4.2 per cent in agreements signed in 1994.<br />
And those increases have usually been offset by considerable increases in<br />
productivity. These recent changes need to be put in the context of the sustained progress<br />
which has been made in real unit labour costs over recent years.<br />
The story is this: the costs of production in Australia have fallen from what was<br />
close to a record high in 1982 to less than the average of 1966-73.<br />
Real unit labour costs today are 13 per cent lower than they were in 1982. So<br />
long as we maintain the momentum towards enterprise based bargaining and<br />
other structural economic reform, the sustained low level of labour costs since<br />
1986 will continue into the future. </p>
<p>In other words, we have seen long term gains. And we are not about to let them<br />
slip. While some people are talking about a change in the weather, what we are<br />
experiencing is in fact a change in the climate.<br />
The move to enterprise bargaining is occurring in a climate of industrial peace.<br />
In the period between 1975 and 1983 the average annual number of working<br />
days lost per 1000 employees due to strike activity was 590. Since 1983 the<br />
figure is 208 a reduction of 65 per cent.<br />
From 1988-94 the era when formal enterprise bargaining began the average<br />
was 185 days.<br />
These figures are well under the OECD average and the rate of reduction is very<br />
much faster.<br />
In short, we used to be seen as a notoriously strike-bound country. That is<br />
emphatically no longer the case.<br />
As I said, the whole climate has changed. We have seen and we will continue to<br />
see structural change which will deliver to the next century an Australia with a<br />
modern, flexible, competitive industrial relations system an essential<br />
underpinning of a modern, flexible, competitive economy.<br />
I won't recite in detail the other major structural reforms to the Australian<br />
economy of the past decade which are fundamental to our present<br />
competitiveness and which set us up to be competitive well into the future.<br />
It is enough to say that the deregulation of our financial markets, the lowering of<br />
tariff barriers, the relaxation of exchange controls, and the floating of the dollar,<br />
were essential steps. The effects on our competitiveness have been both<br />
profound and irreversible. So long as we follow through what has been both<br />
profound and microeconomic reform, we will have sustainable growth into the<br />
future. No microeconomic reform we have undertaken has been more important than<br />
our investment in vocational education and training.<br />
You will hear it said these days, usually by the same people who insist that the<br />
sky is falling in, who are generally the same people who insisted that we were<br />
about to have a double dip recession or a depression, that the Government has<br />
lost its enthusiasm for microeconomic reform.<br />
Of course to say that we haven't even to point to proof of our endeavours is to<br />
invite the charge of complacency. It is a serious charge. But it cannot be<br />
sustained. </p>
<p>Not if you look at the introduction and operation of the Industrial Relations<br />
Reform Act. And not if you look at our investment in vocational education and<br />
training. I won't go into training in detail. But the future is the focus of this address, and<br />
the future depends on education and training our economic success vitally<br />
depends on it.<br />
The information highway is already here. A revolution in work is occurring before<br />
our eyes. By early in the next century as many as a third of all jobs will be in the<br />
so-called knowledge-based industries.<br />
Today, without question, knowledge is the most valuable resource a nation can<br />
have. And the knowledge keeps changing: in the German metals industry it<br />
turns over every five years; in their information technology industry it is every<br />
two years.<br />
For all these reasons, the $ 1.5 billion the Commonwealth will spend on<br />
vocational education and training between 1993-97 is an essential investment.<br />
We have to move as quickly as our competitors and develop a world class<br />
training system in which employer associations, training institutions and industry<br />
are directly linked.<br />
That is what we are doing. We are working as fast as we can to build the bridge<br />
by which Australians can get from the old to the new into new opportunities,<br />
new jobs, new technology. From school to work, unskilled to skilled, from the<br />
social margins to the mainstream, from manufacturing to knowledge-based, from<br />
unemployment to employment.<br />
We established the Australian National Training Authority in 1992. In Working<br />
Nation last year we established the National Employment and Training<br />
Taskforce; introduced a Youth Training Initiative to enable fifteen to seventeen<br />
years to get into training or jobs through individual case management, and<br />
created the revolutionary Job Compact.<br />
The initiatives are working. There is a major cultural change under way a<br />
change in the climate. By 2001, 95 per cent of 19 year olds will have completed<br />
Year 12 or an initial post-school qualification or be participating in some form of<br />
education or training.<br />
And the shift is towards vocational training. Unmet demand for TAFE places is<br />
now 36 per cent greater than it is for higher education. The proportion of<br />
students choosing TAFE over university has increased from 15 to 25 per cent. </p>
<p>This is an investment a massive investment In our human resources. in what<br />
Peter Drucker calls "' the only meaningful resource today" knowledge.<br />
Training is a wealth transfer. It is a profoundly democratic and just investment<br />
and in the times which are coming it is essential to the maintenance of the social<br />
fabric. It is probably the most important initiative we can take to redress lifetime<br />
income inequalities.<br />
It is also essential to a healthy economy. A better trained workforce is a more<br />
productive and more innovative workforce. Skill formation begets technical<br />
change, and technical change begets productivity and on productivity depends<br />
the competitiveness of companies and nations.<br />
Microeconomic reform continues with the recovery. And let's consider the shape<br />
and size of that recovery.<br />
Last year the Australian economy grew faster than that of any other developed<br />
country. And it grew with low inflation. Job growth, as I have said, was<br />
exceptional beyond the most optimistic forecasts. And only Canada recorded a<br />
fall in unemployment at a rate faster than Australia's.<br />
When I was in Europe recently I was able to point out that, under the<br />
convergence criteria set down under Maastricht, we would meet the targets for<br />
economic and monetary union where every other European country, with the<br />
exception of Germany and Luxembourg, would fail.<br />
The criteria concern inflation rates, interest rates, deficit ratios and government<br />
debt. At present Australia meets every one of those. And it is worth looking at the<br />
comparisons of government debt. Only one European government has debt<br />
lower than 50 per cent of GDP that is France with 49.5 per cent.<br />
Australia's government debt is 34 per cent of GDP. It is very low.<br />
There is a lot of scaremongering around at present. This is utterly predictable<br />
and totally familiar behaviour, but it does create anxieties in the community<br />
which are very often baseless. And it does deny to Australians the confidence<br />
they are entitled to enjoy after the work they have put in. And I believe it also<br />
makes it significantly harder to efficiently deal with the real problems which<br />
remain.<br />
And there can be no doubt that the real problem remaining for Australia is the<br />
current account deficit. </p>
<p>Yet the fundamentals of the economy are strong, and that the medium term<br />
settings and underpinnings for a sustained recovery are well in place.<br />
The uncertainty, the apprehension about the basics, the notion that the good<br />
news may not last for long derives almost entirely from the recent increases in<br />
the current account deficit.<br />
I want to devote most of the time that remains to addressing this subject.<br />
As a percentage of GDP the current account deficit is now at a high level, but not<br />
the highest historically. In fact Australia has always run a current account deficit<br />
for the simple reason that the investment opportunities here have generally<br />
outweighed our savings capacity.<br />
Our increasing integration with international financial markets in the 1980s has<br />
increasingly encouraged us to call on foreign savings rather than our own, and<br />
as a result we have seen the current account become not just a fact of our<br />
economic life but frequently a problem in it.<br />
The actual size of the current account deficit should not be the sole focus of<br />
debate about our external position. What matters are the much more<br />
complicated issues of the composition of the current account, the circumstances<br />
that have led to its change, the confidence of overseas investors in Australia's<br />
economic fundamentals, and the outlook over the medium term for both exports<br />
and imports.<br />
We cannot deal with the problem without an understanding of these issues.<br />
As far as the recent large increase in the current account deficit is concerned, it<br />
has to be understood that now, as at such times in the past, the growth is<br />
stemming in large part from a surge in imports of capital equipment. It is, of<br />
course, part of the general surge in productive investment.<br />
The data are instructive. In the first 7 months of this financial year the current<br />
account deficit grew by $ 6.1 billion compared to the same period a year earlier,<br />
with capital equipment imports increasing by 23 per cent. By comparison<br />
intermediate goods imports grew by about 10 per cent, and consumption imports<br />
by around 12 per cent.<br />
Increased capital equipment imports reflects a general view that the prospects<br />
for growth are excellent and that the fundamentals for future prosperity are in<br />
place. So the increase in part reflects our economic success and the confidence<br />
it has created. At the same time, to some extent it contributes to further<br />
economic success. </p>
<p>The productive investment we are experiencing is crucial to the continuation of<br />
Australian structural reform, to the modern isation and expansion of our<br />
underlying private economic base.<br />
It also should be noted that when strong investment surges have dissipated in<br />
the past, so too has the level of the current account deficit decreased.<br />
Nor can we ignore the fact that foreign business has been willing to finance the<br />
relatively high deficits, and they are doing this because they believe it to be<br />
good business. At this juncture, with our strong credit ratings intact, the<br />
financing of the deficit can be understood to have a sound financial basis in<br />
which overseas lenders fully expect to receive healthy returns.<br />
In other words, financing the deficit reflects continuing financial market<br />
confidence in Australia.<br />
But it is not confidence the Government takes for granted. It is not something we<br />
are complacent about, It is a continuous, hands-on process. Maintaining<br />
confidence in our external financial situation depends on having policies which<br />
deliver sustained and balanced economic performance.<br />
At the same time it needs to be recognised that there are structural reasons for<br />
the increase in the current account deficit. Some of these the Government can't<br />
influence, but there are important ones we can.<br />
To begin with, over the last several decades Australia's terms of trade have<br />
been falling with world commodity prices. This means that without structural<br />
progress on the export side it becomes increasingly hard to balance our trade.<br />
And there have been significant developments on the export side. The<br />
proportion of GDP coming from exports has increased from 13 per cent in 1982<br />
to 22 per cent today.<br />
Again, it is important to understand the composition of economic data, since in<br />
large part this increase is due to a highly desirable change in the make up of<br />
exports. Our traditional export base, of rural and resource commodities, has declined as<br />
a percentage of all exports from 62 per cent in 1983 to 46 per cent last year. By<br />
contrast, our exports of Elaborately Transformed Manufactures have increased<br />
from 10 to 17 per cent in the same period. This last area is one which will<br />
become of even greater significance as world economic development proceeds.<br />
As an exporting nation we are now much more solidly placed than we were in the<br />
past. This has come about in part from an extraordinary improvement in our<br />
international competitiveness. </p>
<p>The index of international competitiveness has risen by 40 per cent since 1983.<br />
You will forgive me for making the point that in the eight years before 1983 there<br />
was no change in the index in other words, we were no more competitive in<br />
1983 than we had been in 1975.<br />
You see what I mean when I say that these are not fleeting changes. they are<br />
long-term structural gains sea-changes.<br />
As with the fundamental developments in the labour market, the reorientation of<br />
our export base enhances our capacity to grow and deal more confidently with<br />
adverse international economic circumstances.<br />
As I suggested earlier, another factor contributing to current account pressures<br />
has been significant international moves towards financial deregulation. World<br />
capital flows are much greater these days, and it stands to reason that more<br />
financing in Australia will be drawn from overseas funds.<br />
We should not forget that this is a two-way flow. We opened up the Australian<br />
financial system to the world in 1983/ 84, and now about $ 76 billion of Australian<br />
private capital is invested abroad. This phenomenon is rarely mentioned, but it<br />
is a significant consideration in any useful interpretation of our overall<br />
international financial situation. Seventy-six billion is not an insignificant amount<br />
when the net debt is around $ 160 billion.<br />
Another fundamental but complicated issue when it comes to understanding the<br />
current account challenge is the distinction between the short and medium term<br />
prospects for both exports and imports.<br />
As a percentage of GOP our current account deficit is high and it is not likely to<br />
decrease for some time. But decrease it will and for several reasons.<br />
One is that recovery from the drought is bound to increase our export revenues.<br />
It will also decrease some of our recent imports caused by grain shortages.<br />
Another is that some of the countries which are significant importers of<br />
Australian goods are recovering from recession and we can expect our exports<br />
particularly non-rural exports to grow as they do.<br />
Finally, partly in response to current account pressures, the Government moved<br />
to dampen domestic demand at the end of 1994. When these effects flow<br />
through we can expect significant decreases in the growth of import demand. </p>
<p>Yet nothing in the circumstances I have outlined diminishes the Government's<br />
responsibility to manage our external position. The current account deficit has to<br />
be addressed.<br />
Perhaps the major issue is that the larger our foreign borrowings the greater our<br />
exposure to fluctuations in economic sentiment in financial markets abroad.<br />
The advantages that come from overseas borrowings need always to be<br />
weighed against the adverse possibilities arising from changes in market<br />
perceptions and activities.<br />
The obvious way to diminish these risks is to increase national savings. We<br />
have been concentrating on this for some time. You will recall the introduction of<br />
the Superannuation Guarantee Levy in 1992.<br />
Our policy commits us to increasing the overall level of Australian<br />
superannuation contributions to 9 per cent from employers and 3 per cent from<br />
employees by the year 2002/ 3.<br />
Obviously these savings increases will promote the potential for financial capital<br />
needs to be met from domestic sources, and the risks associated with borrowing<br />
from overseas will be proportionately decreased.<br />
National savings increases through superannuation also mean that it will<br />
become easier to meet the financial needs of Australian retirees, whose<br />
numbers will swell in coming years.<br />
We take the issue of the current account deficit extremely seriously. We are<br />
consistently assessing policy and in the forthcoming Budget we will be<br />
addressing elements of structural change which have the potential to reduce<br />
both internally and externally derived pressures.<br />
There should be no mistake about our intention to use the Budget to resolve the<br />
outstanding issues in economic management. It is an excellent opportunity to<br />
fine-tune the recovery and put in place longer term reforms which are consistent<br />
with our needs for sustainable and balanced economic and social development.<br />
As I said earlier in this address, we are living in a period of unprecedented<br />
change. It is much more likely to accelerate than go away. Change breeds<br />
change, but it also breeds success in turn it develops the capacity to cope with<br />
and even lead the changes.<br />
But that does not alter the fact that in times of change there is uncertainty. And<br />
let me say that every effort of the Government is directed towards removing that<br />
uncertainty creating in every way we can the elements of a national life in<br />
which all Australians can find a place. </p>
<p>17<br />
A job, training, health and education services, security, a sense of belonging and<br />
a sense of loyalty to the country, dare I say it a sense of excitement about<br />
Australia these are the goals.<br />
Inevitably the whole picture of our intent fades from time to time. But I can tell<br />
you it does not vary.<br />
And I can also tell you that we know we won't get there if we allow our the<br />
political culture to be clogged with timidity and prevarication.<br />
As a Government we know that we won't do anything for the cause of certainty<br />
by allowing opinion polls or media opinion to drive policy. Governments which<br />
do not listen are not good governments. Governments which only listen are not<br />
good governments either.<br />
I think the same sort of spirit Should pervade the public sector. The task of<br />
government is to make good policy and deliver it. It is to anticipate necessity,<br />
not wait for it to dictate the terms of our existence.<br />
I have a very distinct feeling that John Monash would have offered similar<br />
advice. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
