<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4155</transcript-id>
    <title>PUBLIC SERVICE AND STATUTORY AUTHORITY STAFF CEILINGS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004155.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
. RJMA US TRA L I S<br />
PRIME MINISGTER<br />
FOR PRESS 14 JUNE 1976<br />
PUBLIC SERVICE AND STATUTORY AUTHORITY STAFF CEILINGS<br />
A review has been made of staff ceilings for the<br />
Public Service and statutory authorities for 1976/ 77. In line<br />
with the Government's announced economic policies, the review<br />
took account of decisions taken by the Government to bring about<br />
economies in programs and activities, and our continuing<br />
determination to ensure that departments and authorities operate<br />
as efficiently as possible.<br />
Following the review, I have approved staff ceilings<br />
for 30 June 1977 which, overall, will have the effect of<br />
reducing the ceilings in Commonwealth departments, and in those<br />
authorities for which staff ceilings are set, from 326,400 to<br />
322,357, an overall reduction of 1.2% o Staff ceilings under the<br />
Public Service Act -I be reduced by 1 o6% and ceilings for other<br />
statutory authori-i's by 0.9%.<br />
I am reminding all Ministers of the importance of<br />
achieving the revised ceilings as part of the Government's<br />
intention to' conftain overall Commonwealth expenditure.<br />
I have also directed that staff ceilings be kept under<br />
continuing review during 1976/ 77, a0nd that I be kept informed oi<br />
progress towards achieving the ceilings set, any difficulties<br />
which might be encountered by individual departments or authorities<br />
in reaching their ceilings, and potential areas where further<br />
reductions might be made.<br />
The ceilings now approved for 30 June 1977 will be subject<br />
to further review and possible adjustment in the light of the<br />
Government's Budget decisions, and decisions yet to be taken on the<br />
reports of the Administrative Review Committee and other relevant<br />
enquiries. -7~ </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
