<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3090</transcript-id>
    <title>TEXT OF TELEGRAM SENT TO ALL PREMIERS - BY THE PRIME MINISTER 3/12/73</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/12/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003090.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEXT OF TELEGRAM SENT TO ALL PREMIERS<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER 3/ 12/ 73<br />
My dear Premier, You will remember that on 30th May last I tabled the'<br />
report by the Interim Committee for the Australian Schools Commission<br />
and that on 12th June I cabled you that my Government had decided<br />
to accept the educational programs and financial recommendations of<br />
the Committee for 1974 and 1975. Although the consequential legislation<br />
was passed by the House of Representatives there is some doubt whether<br />
it will be passed by the Senate this year.<br />
Your planning for the amount of funds available during<br />
the first quarter of 1974 should at this stage make contingency<br />
provision for this situation. The Australian Government understands<br />
that your education authorities will have entered into commitments<br />
on the basis of our earlier assurances and it is our intention to give<br />
you the maximum flexibility to honour those commitments during the<br />
first quarter of next year. There might however be no statutory<br />
authority for the amounts promised for recurrent grants to state<br />
schools, for disadvantaged schools, for special education, for primary<br />
school libraries and for our joint programs of librarian training,<br />
of special education teacher training, of teacher development and of<br />
special projects. There might be no extra amounts available for<br />
your general capital program or for secondary school libraries unless<br />
you can find flexibility within the existing legislation providing<br />
grants for science laboratories, secondary libraries and capital<br />
expenditure. The secondary libraries and science laboratories programs<br />
are limited by statute to their specific purposes and the capital grants<br />
are required by statute to apply 70% of the aggregate of payments to<br />
facilities in addition to and not in replacement of existing facilities<br />
at Government schools. These statutes provide for maximum expenditure<br />
during the 1973/ 74 financial year for general capital works and science<br />
laboratories and during calendar year 1974 for libraries. In order to<br />
give your planning the maximum flexibility, we would be willing to<br />
accelerate in the first q'uarter the total amount of payments which<br />
would otherwise be made under these statutes during 1974. Furthermore<br />
we would be willing to release your Government from its obligation,<br />
which is not specifically provided for in the statutes to use these<br />
funds in addition to state funds, i. e. you could use the maximum<br />
available in this quarter under the three specific statutes currently<br />
in force and divert your own expenditures on such projects to other<br />
expenditure. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
On a strict calculation, the maximum accelerated amount<br />
we could grant for Government schools in the first quarter of<br />
1974 under existing statutes would be New South Wales $ 14.3m,<br />
Victoria $ 13.7m, Queensland $ 4.5m, South Australia $ 0.8m, Western<br />
Australia $ 3.5m, Tasmania $ 1.2m, Total $ 38.0m. This would<br />
compare on the basis of a calculation of one eighth, i. e. the<br />
first quarter of our proposed two year program, with the following<br />
amounts New South Wales $ 22m, Victoria $ 18m, Queensland $ 8.2m,<br />
South Australia $ 6.5m, Western Australia $ 4.5m, Tasmania $ 1.8a.<br />
Total: $ 61.0m. I realise that the alternative we are considering<br />
represents a crisis for your education system. Under the circumstances<br />
I feel it is necessary to advise you of our present thinking so<br />
that you can at least begin planning for the contingency I have<br />
mentioned. SGN. E. G. WHITLAM<br />
3 DECEMBER 1973<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
