<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18129</transcript-id>
    <title>Address to the National Commemoration Ceremony to mark the 10th Anniversary of the September 11, 2001 attacks</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/09/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Distinguished guests.</p>
<p>Friends of Australia, from many countries.</p>
<p>Ladies and Gentlemen.</p>
<p>This weekend many Australians read the story of a young New York firefighter  -  James Dowdell.</p>
<p>He wears his father's uniform.</p>
<p>Ten years ago today, Kevin Dowdell was one of the hundreds of firefighters  -  New York's bravest  -  who were killed when the towers came down. </p>
<p>Kevin led his men in there. </p>
<p>And his life of service lives on in his sons.</p>
<p>Today James Dowdell is a firefighter like his father before him. </p>
<p>Patrick Dowdell has worn his country's uniform in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>The Dowdells' story is one among hundreds, among thousands, which we remember today.</p>
<p>Lives lived out in years of service and of peace, lives lost on days of terror and of courage.</p>
<p>Not only on that dreadful day in New York and Washington and Pennsylvania  -  but in the long decade since, from Bali and Jakarta to London and Mumbai and beyond.</p>
<p>But Australia has a special link to the Dowdells' story  -  and it holds special meaning for our American friends as well.</p>
<p>So I am glad Rob Frey is among us today.</p>
<p>Rob, your part in this story is important.</p>
<p>Everyone should know it  -  so I want to share it again.</p>
<p>Many Australians and Americans worked together in the late 1990s to be ready to protect the 2000 Sydney Olympics from possible terrorist attack.</p>
<p>One group of Australians spent two months in New York training and working, including a long time with New York's Fire Department Rescue 1.</p>
<p>They worked hard together and became more than colleagues ... they became mates.</p>
<p>So when it was time to go home the Australian commander gave Rescue 1's chief his Australian Army “slouch hat”  and the chief presented the Australians with a battle scarred fire helmet.</p>
<p>Dated December 1998 and signed by members of the Rescue 1 crew, including Kevin Dowdell.</p>
<p>After September 11, Kevin Dowdell's remains could not be found.</p>
<p>But that helmet was found in Australia.</p>
<p>And Rob Frey found Kevin's sons.</p>
<p>Rob went to America to return the helmet their father signed. </p>
<p>Rob and James stood proudly together in the Congress of the United States as a symbol of the friendship between our countries.</p>
<p>And so today, I think of two good men.</p>
<p>Rob and James.</p>
<p>Far apart for now, friends forever.</p>
<p>Just as we think of two great nations.</p>
<p>Australia and the United States.</p>
<p>Whose people believe that “all men are created equal”, that “Jack's as good as his master”.</p>
<p>And as we mark two anniversaries.</p>
<p>The 60th anniversary of the Alliance between Australia and the United States.</p>
<p>When the ANZUS treaty was signed in San Francisco.</p>
<p>And the 10th anniversary of the attacks on America.</p>
<p>When the ANZUS treaty was invoked for the first time.</p>
<p>September 11 was truly a dreadful day, a day which saddened and changed our world.</p>
<p>None of us who lived through it will ever forget.</p>
<p>And our peoples mark it today in many ways.</p>
<p>From here, in Reconciliation Place, where we light a candle.</p>
<p>To Sydney's Botanical Gardens, where a tree is dedicated.</p>
<p>To many Australian cities where interfaith services take place.</p>
<p>To New York, where many bereaved families gather.</p>
<p>We remember all the victims. </p>
<p>Thousands of Americans  -  ten Australians  -  so many other innocent people  -  from so many peaceful nations.</p>
<p>In all these places, meeting in a mood of reflection  -  marking as we do shared sacrifice and loss.</p>
<p>But in all that reflection, finding resolution as well.</p>
<p>Australia and the United States have worked together for peace in the world for many years.</p>
<p>September 11 changed many things but it could not change that.</p>
<p>We will make decisions in coming years to ensure our work in the world  -  and the co-operation between our forces  -  only grows in the future.</p>
<p>And while our fight against terrorism did not end in May, a great blow was struck against terrorism when Osama bin Laden was killed.</p>
<p>Our work together around the world goes on.</p>
<p>But today, around the world, we pause from that work, to remember.</p>
<p>To remember the courage and the suffering our two countries have shared.</p>
<p>To remember that in our darkest days we have been glad to see each other's face and hear each other's voice.</p>
<p>In our days together under attack in the Pacific.</p>
<p>In our decades together from Korea to the Gulf.</p>
<p>On September 11. in Washington and Pennsylvania and New York. </p>
<p>And so on this day, on behalf of millions of Australians, I say this:</p>
<p>We do not forget. We never forget. </p>
<p>United always in remembrance.</p>
<p>United always in our resolve. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
