<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9256</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P.J. KEATING, MP NEW EDUCATIONAL REALITIES CONFERENCE MELBOURNE, 15 JUNE 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/06/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009256.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PLEASE CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
NEW EDUCATIONAL REALITIES CONFERENCE<br />
MELBOURNE, 15 JUNE 1994<br />
I am grateful for the opportunity to speak to you today very pleased to address so many<br />
people whose concern is Australian education.<br />
With an economy now performing as well or better than any in the world, with so much<br />
now in our favour, we have a marvellous chance to lay the basis of an Australian society<br />
which is fair and cohesive, rich in opportunity and reward.<br />
A great responsibility falls on our generation to seize the opportunity. It falls particularly<br />
on people like yourselves because education is where one of the great efforts must be<br />
made. It will be fuindamental to our success.<br />
I am particularly pleased because you come from all parts of the education sector, from<br />
industry and from the wider community. Success depends on your involvement. Our<br />
modern education system needs your participation your efforts, all your ideas.<br />
If we are to be a sophisticated and cohesive society, a society through which run both the<br />
threads of ambition and those of tolerance and care; if we are to be a modern, competitive,<br />
successful society in which opportunity and the common good are both enlarged; if we<br />
want to succeed in the world and in our own region where so many chances are our<br />
education system will have to meet the challenges.<br />
If we want our children and succeeding generations to have the chances we have had and<br />
more, if we want them to trust in and maintain our democracy and our best traditions our<br />
education system will have to pass on the knowledge and instil the faith. </p>
<p>If we want to put half a million Australians back in touch with the workforce; if we really<br />
want to make the good society a reality for all Australians it is going to depend on our<br />
education system and the people who run<br />
We will need what is fashionably called a " vision" though I am not sure that " vision" is<br />
precisely the right word. I have a suspicion that sometimes visions have a little in common<br />
with hot air. I am not sure that the founders of compulsory primary education or our first<br />
universities talked about " vision" very much at all. I don't think the real visionaries ever<br />
do. I think the best of them have been like the best of parents they have simply taken every<br />
care and responsibility for the future of succeeding generations. They have had not just<br />
imagination but courage and persistence, and I daresay an absolute determination to see<br />
that policies and programs work.<br />
So what I offer you today I'm less inclined to call a vision than a schedule of necessity<br />
the series of things we need to do, must do and can do.<br />
The worst judgement that can be passed on a government or on a generation is not that<br />
they lacked something as vague as vision but something as concrete as responsibility, the<br />
responsibility to do what was necessary to secure the future.<br />
In this there is no substitute for effort a great national effort. I have said this many times,<br />
I know. I said it in One Nation more than two years ago and I repeated it in the White<br />
Paper just a few weeks ago.<br />
It is not just rhetoric it is the only way to succeed.<br />
We are all aware of the criticisms which are made of us: bureaucracies for not following<br />
through and delivering; business for standing back and not getting involved; government<br />
for not having the imagination or courage.<br />
Well, the Government, I believe has shown the imagination and courage in education.<br />
And I believe business will get involved it is so obviously in their interests. And the<br />
bureaucracy wijll deliver because government and business and every parent and every<br />
child in the country depends on it and we are watching.<br />
In the past decade the Government has massively expanded Australian higher education.<br />
Seventeen universities have been created in the last eight years, many of them in areas<br />
away from thi-main urban centres.<br />
We now enrol thirty per cent of all seventeen to twenty-two year olds. Today we can say<br />
that our higher education system is truly open and accessible. </p>
<p>Perhaps even greater than this achievement has been the dramatic increase in secondary<br />
school retention rates. In the space of a decade we more than doubled the number of<br />
youiing Australians completing Year 12.<br />
But comparing the present with the past is much less useful than comparing it with where<br />
we have to be in the future. In international terms the present figure is acceptable but the<br />
base it came off was deplorable. Fourteen per cent of our young people still drop out of<br />
school early and don't go on to further education or training.<br />
The Youth Training Initiative announced in Working Nation will maintain the momentum<br />
of reform. It is designed to reach these young people at this turning point in their lives,<br />
and stop the cycle of disadvantage and alienation.<br />
Through the Initiative, unemployed fifteen to seventeen year olds will be case managed<br />
and assisted into worthwhile education, training or work opportunities.<br />
Young people who are still unemployed after six months will be offered a variety of labour<br />
market and vocational training programs which may lead to permanent employment.<br />
The Youth Training Initiative goes some way toward completing the expansion of postcompulsory<br />
schooling we began a decade ago.<br />
Our record in vocational education and training is not similarly impressive. Only one in<br />
five Australians aged-sixteen and seventeen are in vocational preparation. The OECD<br />
average is one in two. We have to reach a comparable level and do so quickly.<br />
This is the great education challenge for Australia in the nineties to bring vocational<br />
education and training up to the level our economic and social ambitions demand. A level,<br />
for example, which compares with Germany, which has four times the number of<br />
apprentices relative to the size of the workforce and twice as many people with education<br />
or training qualifications other than university degrees.<br />
Our objective and all Australian governments have agreed to it is that by the year 2001<br />
ninety-five per cent of nineteen year olds will have completed Year 12 or an initial postschool<br />
qualification, or be participating in formally recognised education and training.<br />
In a successful Australian economy of the future, the key competitive advantage will be<br />
our general skills.<br />
To quote one very instructive example. Comparative studies of the hotel industry in<br />
Germany and Great Britain in the 1980s found that the productivity of German workers<br />
was fifty to sixty per cent higher than their British counterparts. The productivity of<br />
German hotel managers is also higher because they did not have to regularly monitor their<br />
staff. The difference was that the German workers had had specific vocational training<br />
and the British workers had not. </p>
<p>The same lesson can be drawn from the example of Australian car manufacturers who<br />
have embraced training to lift quality and productivity.<br />
In cooperation with TAFE they developed a Vehicle Production Certificate. They now<br />
build world class cars. They export. The industry has a future. The car production<br />
workers have a future.<br />
The moral of the story could be applied to the nation as whole. Our long term prosperity<br />
depends on nothing so much as the quality of our workforce both their vocational skills<br />
and their general education.<br />
Over the last five years we have taken measures to massively increase the quantum of<br />
vocational education and training.<br />
In cooperation with the States and Territories, we established the Australian National<br />
Training Authority ANTA to drive the expansion.<br />
It was a watershed in Commonwealth-State cooperation of the kind we need to succeed<br />
with in our education system, and we laid the foundation for expansion with 1. 1 billion in<br />
growth funding over the period 1993-1996.<br />
In Working Nation we announced an ambitious plan for the expansion of entry level<br />
training by 50,000 places over the next two years. This program will be supported by a<br />
revised system of payments to employers who provide young people with training places.<br />
The introduction of a training wage will also provide employers in new and emerging<br />
industries with a single scheme of payments. Traineeships will be expanded across the<br />
whole workforce and the supply of training places increased.<br />
It is not enough to just expand the system. The system has to meet the goals we set it.<br />
We need to find the means by which the different education sectors can be effectively<br />
linked with each other and with the worlds of work and culture. We need to make the<br />
system more responsive to economic and cultural change.<br />
Post-compulsory education has been fundamentally changed by the increase in retention<br />
rates. Yet the curriculum still reflects the days when most of those completing senior high<br />
school were hoping to go on to university.<br />
Now that a large proportion do not have this intention, schools need to provide studies<br />
which are integrated with relevant vocational education. In future there should be no<br />
segregation of general and vocational education. </p>
<p>That is why Working Nation announced the creation of a new Australian Student<br />
Traineeship Foundation a scheme delivered through regional partnerships between<br />
schools and industry which will enable Year-I 1 and 12 students to combine school studies<br />
with work experience in local industry and off the job training.<br />
The traineeships will allow young people to complete their training and apprenticeships in<br />
a shorter time. More generally, they should serve as a model for the next century when<br />
schools must link as easily with vocational education and training as they now link with<br />
universities. Similarly we must link industry and tertiary education indeed, we need to escape from<br />
the tradition of keeping work and education in different spheres.<br />
The task is to create an environment in which educational institutions and government<br />
authorities involve industry in mainstream planning and decision-making and one where<br />
industry feels bound to be involved.<br />
The delivery of tertiary education must be more flexible to meet the wider range of<br />
industry needs.*<br />
The introduction of the second stage of the Government's Open Learning Initiative, which<br />
includes the development of an electronic support network, will mean that employees will<br />
no longer have to spend time away from the workplace in order to galn qualification.<br />
Employers and education providers should be able to develop programs which meet the<br />
needs of individuals at their own pace, at their own place.<br />
Employers also need to be involved in developing a more streamlined and responsible<br />
vocational sector. At present, they understandably complaln about the maze of<br />
authorities, boards and processes they need to negotiate before they can get appropriate<br />
training programs.<br />
The National Framework for the Recognition of Training, which was meant to solve this<br />
problem, has so far failed to deliver either national recognition or portability. In<br />
cooperation with State and Territory Governments, the Commonwealth is seeking the<br />
means of overcoming the problem.<br />
One possibility is to increase the powers of ANTA, in order to give employers and training<br />
providers a " one stop shop" where training can be nationally accredited in a single<br />
streamldined process. Working Nation contained measures which Will assist cooperation<br />
between business and training authorities. Administrative arrangements will be<br />
streamldined. Industry will be put in the driving seat to make training administration simple<br />
and relevant to industry needs. </p>
<p>The National Employment and Training Taskforce will enable traineeships to be fasttracked.<br />
The new Enterprise Stream for traineeships will allow enterprises to develop<br />
their own training standards, develop their own nationally accredited programs and issue<br />
their own national vocational qualifications.<br />
Working Nation suspended the Training Guarantee for two years, and it will be abolished<br />
altogether if business seriously comumits itself to creating new entry level training places.<br />
That really is the bottom line. None of these reforms will be effective unless business<br />
increases its own effort and cooperates with providers in setting directions for the future.<br />
The presence of so many business people at this conference suggests that Australian<br />
industry is in fact keen to establish a genuine partnership with government and the<br />
education industry.<br />
Industry wants more than specific vocational skills. They want employees with general<br />
skills, general knowledge, judgement, self-discipline, literacy and numeracy.<br />
That is one very practical reason why the emphasis we are now placing on vocational<br />
education and training must not be seen as antithetical to traditional educational values. In<br />
fact, we should be strengthening those values as we go.<br />
Education is a foundation of the nation's culture and strength. It is where knowledge and<br />
appreciation of our heritage and institutions is passed on; where our sensibilities are<br />
broadened; where moral, ethical and aesthetic faculties are shaped.<br />
I don't think that I am alone in suspecting that some of these things are not the priorities<br />
they once were.<br />
Yet our success as a nation and as a society, as much as the responsibility we have to our<br />
children, demands that we do not let these values slip from our education system.<br />
Perhaps most of all, our children should know what the privileges and responsibilities of<br />
Australian democracy are. What their great inheritance is. What change is desirable and<br />
possible. The creation of an Exert Group to provide the Government with a plan for a program of<br />
public education and information on Australian government, citizenship and the<br />
constitution may be seen in this context that is, as a means of strengthening our<br />
democracy by enlivening our appreciation of it.<br />
The composition and terms of reference of this group will be announced soon.<br />
It is scarcely less important that we improve our understanding of the nations with whom<br />
increasingly we deal. </p>
<p>It will profoundly assist our relationship with the countries of our region if we understand<br />
the languages they speak. Z.-<br />
Today less than four per cent of Year 12 students study an Asian language. Only twelve<br />
per cent are studying a second language of any kind. Yet the study of a second language<br />
has a substantial practical significance both for the student and for our national<br />
development. In the Budget the Government announced funding for a joint Commonwealth/ State<br />
National Asian Languages Strategy which will see all Australian school children in Years<br />
3 to 10 learning a-seco6nd language by the year 2006.<br />
Sixty per cent of them will study one of four priority Asian languages Japanese,<br />
Indonesian, Modern Standard Chinese and Korean and forty per cent will study any<br />
other second language of their choice.<br />
Twenty-five per cent of all Year 12 students will be studying a second language and one<br />
per cent of students will go on to do a " Year 13" in Asia under the Young Australians in<br />
Asia Program..<br />
The program will greatly enrich our education system and with it the life of the nation. In<br />
one sense, it is one more practical step in the process of opening Australia up to the region<br />
and the world. In another sense, it is symbolic: symbolic of our willingness to meet other<br />
countries half-way in our relationships with them, and symbolic also of our will and<br />
capacity to devise for our education system new building blocks for necessary social and<br />
cultural growth.<br />
If we are to enter the twenty-first century with an education and training system large<br />
enough and good enough to meet the aspirations of individuals and the needs of Australia,<br />
we will need a national effort.<br />
We will need State and Territory Governments to cooperate with business, and business to<br />
engage as it has never done before. The States must streamlJine their training<br />
bureaucracies: business must increase its own training efforts and share the responsibility<br />
for shaping and implementing the training agenda.<br />
As in so much else, the Australian education system will have to become more flexible.<br />
The borders between schools and vocational training, and between education and work,<br />
will need to come down.<br />
Education must be a prime mover of necessary change, a vehicle by which the nation can<br />
grasp the unprecedented opportunities which are now presented and all Australians can<br />
share in the rewards and the responsibilities. </p>
<p>8<br />
I said in Paris a few days ago that to be an Australian in this decade is to be present at a<br />
defining moment in our history. Your presence at this conference I take as encouraging<br />
evidence that you not only share this belief: but are willing to share the responsibility that<br />
flows from it.<br />
Thank you </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
