<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11334</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          ADDRESS AT THE THIESS ULTIMATE POWER DINNER          CABRAMURRA, NSW</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/10/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..................</p>
<p>  [Tape Starts]</p>
<p>  As a ten year old pupil of the Earlwood Primary School in Sydney in 1949,</p>
<p>   by courtesy of the ABC booming school broadcasts into our classroom, I remember</p>
<p>   the occasion of the inauguration of the Snowy Scheme, and that distinctive</p>
<p>   voice of one my predecessors, Ben Chifley, announcing in October 1949 along</p>
<p>   with the then Governor General Sir William McKell, and Sir William Hudson,</p>
<p>   the inauguration of this great Snowy Mountains Scheme. I don't think it's</p>
<p>   any exaggeration to say that of all the great national development projects</p>
<p>   that our nation has experienced, none has gone anywhere near capturing the</p>
<p>   imagination as has the Snowy. Not only did it capture the imagination of</p>
<p>   a post war Australian community anxious to throw off the drudgery of war</p>
<p>   time controls and restrictions, keen to embrace new citizens from different</p>
<p>   parts of the world, but beyond that it enabled us to demonstrate to ourselves</p>
<p>   and to demonstrate to the world our superb engineering skills, our technical</p>
<p>   capacities, and as Mr Charlton said in his speech, the great capacity, the</p>
<p>   can-do character, of the Australian nation.</p>
<p>  It remains 50 years on an astonishing engineering achievement rightly recognised</p>
<p>   around the world as such. It was as we have been reminded, a dangerous undertaking.</p>
<p>   And the deaths of 121 people are recorded during the years of the construction</p>
<p>   of the various elements of the Snowy Scheme.</p>
<p>  It is of course very much part of the history and the fabric of post war</p>
<p>   Australia that the Snowy River Scheme enabled us to see for the first time</p>
<p>   perhaps as an entire nation, the advantage of people of different backgrounds,</p>
<p>   of different ethnicities, of different cultures, of different nationalities</p>
<p>   working together. So many of them have recently been devastated and uprooted</p>
<p>   by war in Europe. Many former enemies, enemies only a few years earlier</p>
<p>   forgot old animosities and worked together within the embrace and within</p>
<p>   the environment of a new nation. And in the process they made an enormous</p>
<p>   contribution to shaping and defining the modern Australia which is a beacon</p>
<p>   of tolerance and understanding to the rest of the world.</p>
<p>  100,000 people worked on the scheme from 30 different nations. It was finished</p>
<p>   on or just below budget, it was finished on time, and it was an incredible</p>
<p>   demonstration of what this country can do and what this country can achieve.</p>
<p>   And tonight is an occasion to acknowledge the contribution first and foremost</p>
<p>   of the men and women who toiled and made this possible, of the great engineering</p>
<p>   skills of some of the people that have already been mentioned, the dedication</p>
<p>   and leadership of Sir William Hudson. And can I also as the Prime Minister</p>
<p>   of Australia on this 50th anniversary celebration, can I acknowledge</p>
<p>   the contribution and the dedication of two of my predecessors as Prime Minister,</p>
<p>   in particular Ben Chifley, the Prime Minister of Australia when the scheme</p>
<p>   was launched. And of course who was part of the Government that oversaw</p>
<p>   the establishment of the Snowy Mountains Authority in the 1940s. And then</p>
<p>   through the 1950s and '60s, the leadership of Sir Robert Menzies and the</p>
<p>   late Senator Sir William Spooner who for many years as Minister for National</p>
<p>   Development, in partnership with Sir William Hudson, played a major role</p>
<p>   in giving political guidance to the development of the scheme.</p>
<p>  We honour the men and women of the Snowy. Not only for their great engineering</p>
<p>   achievement, not only for the fact that it underpins now in 1999 the power</p>
<p>   generation of our nation, but also the provision of much needed water to</p>
<p>   so many of our citizens and many of our farmers who are well represented</p>
<p>   here tonight, and a constant reminder that in a vast dry continent such</p>
<p>   as Australia, the nurturing and the preservation of our precious resource</p>
<p>   water continues as one of our great national priorities. But we also honour</p>
<p>   most importantly what the Snowy Scheme represents to us 50 years on, of</p>
<p>   the aspirational character of the Australian people. It was inaugurated</p>
<p>   at a time when we had just come out of a war. It was inaugurated at a time</p>
<p>   when we were about to begin one of the great periods of economic growth</p>
<p>   and expansion that our nation has experienced. It was also inaugurated at</p>
<p>   the beginning of our first real comprehensive contact with building a nation</p>
<p>   of many backgrounds, and of many cultures and of many peoples, and many</p>
<p>   countries and many nationalities.</p>
<p>  And the important thing for us to recognise today is that in each of those</p>
<p>   respects the Snowy has been a resounding success. It told us that we had</p>
<p>   engineers the equal of any in the world. It told us that we had people of</p>
<p>   vision and commitment to national development the equal of any in the world.</p>
<p>   It told us that we could bring people of different nationalities in an environment</p>
<p>   of cooperation and tolerance, in putting aside older animosities which have</p>
<p>   become a model to the rest of the world, and it is a reminder to us in 1999</p>
<p>   that there is nothing that the Australian people can't do. There's nothing</p>
<p>   that the Australian people can't aspire to achieve if they make the commitment,</p>
<p>   they display the vision, and they have the determination. And that is the</p>
<p>   great legacy of the Snowy, and it is the thing that binds all of us together</p>
<p>   in saluting those who played a part in bringing it to fruition, and we honour</p>
<p>   their contribution on this very delightful occasion, in this most remarkable</p>
<p>   setting. Thank you.</p>
<p>  [Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
