<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9641</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP WORLD CONFERENCE OF THE INTERNATIONAL COUNCIL FOR SMALL BUSINESS, SYDNEY WEDNESDAY 21 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009641.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
WORLD CONFERENCE OF THE INTERNATIONAL COUNCIL FOR<br />
SMALL BUSINESS, SYDNEY WEDNESDAY 21 JUNE 1995<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
I am grateful for the invitation to speak to you at the closing of this 40th World<br />
Conference of the International Council for Small Business.<br />
I want to use this speech to say some things about Australia's trade policy and what<br />
we are doing to help our business people make the most of the enormous<br />
opportunities which exist in this Asia-Pacific region, the fastest growing in the world.<br />
The Minister for Trade, Senator McMullan, is today issuing a statement called<br />
" Winning Markets: Australia's future in the global economy" and I want to use this<br />
opportunity to formally launch this document.<br />
This international conference about small business is an appropriate place to do this<br />
because one of the things which has been very much on the Government's mind in<br />
drawing the strategy up is the increasingly important role of small and medium<br />
businesses in Australia's trade.<br />
I also want to use the opportunity to speak to those of you who are here from<br />
overseas about the opportunities for business in Australia. Because this country<br />
offers overseas investors a very competitive environment, and is an ideal base for<br />
companies including small companies wishing to tap Asian markets.<br />
It is now a very familiar notion that the globalisation of production is dramatically<br />
reshaping the way national economies work and businesses operate. More than<br />
one third of world trade is now conducted by firms trading within their own structures<br />
across national boundaries.<br />
I am sure this has been a theme of many of the formal and informal discussions you<br />
have had at this conference. </p>
<p>The driving fact behind globalisation, of course, is the rapid movement of people<br />
and information. Indeed, the movement of people and information rather than goods<br />
is the fastest growing segment of world trade.<br />
The information revolution has generated whole new areas of business many of<br />
them created by small enterprises and it is transforming the way other business is<br />
done. More and more firms, for example, are marketing their products and services,<br />
locating their production, conducting their research and sourcing their materials<br />
wherever in the world it makes the best economic sense to do so.<br />
Your choice of Sydney as the venue for this conference reflects these changes.<br />
The Council's World Conference has convened outside North America only three<br />
times since it first met 40 years ago. And all three of those meetings have been in<br />
the past five years.<br />
The globalisation of production is confronting businesses with unprecedented<br />
challenges. And small and medium-sized enterprises are no more immune from<br />
these changes than are large ones.<br />
Markets in most economies are becoming increasingly contestable. For small and<br />
medium-sized businesses increasingly that means opportunities abroad and<br />
overseas competition at home.<br />
The result is that few businesses, including smaller ones, can afford to look to<br />
domestic markets alone. This is especially so in Australia with our relatively small<br />
population and an economy tightly integrated into world markets.<br />
But despite these challenges, small and medium-sized enterprises may, in fact, be<br />
the best placed to exploit the opportunities of globalisation.<br />
They tend to be less bureaucratic than large firms and more innovative and<br />
responsive. They have probably gained most from those improvements in<br />
communications and transport which have reduced the cost and complexity of<br />
international business.<br />
Globalisation has also been driven and encouraged by the great growth over recent<br />
years in direct foreign investment. In the second half of the 1 980s foreign direct<br />
investment grew at an annual average rate of 30 per cent, more than twice the rate<br />
of world exports.<br />
The trend has been obvious for Australian investment. In 1980 this country's stock<br />
of equity investment overseas was around $ 7 billion. By 1994 it was around<br />
billion.<br />
Australian companies have understood that, in a world of integrated production,<br />
often the best way to secure entry into a market is by establishing operations there. </p>
<p>And as we have seen here, such investment will often lead not only to increased<br />
sales in the new market, but also to more exports from Australia.<br />
This country's small and medium-sized enterprises have been vital to the success of<br />
our shift towards an international ised economy. Around 4,500 such Australian<br />
businesses are now regularly and actively involved in international trade. They<br />
generate $ 6.5 billion in international turnover. And we expect this to double over<br />
the next five years.<br />
But a great many other small and medium businesses farmers, tourist operators,<br />
hotel and transport providers are also responding to the challenges of international<br />
trade. Their level of involvement is certain to increase.<br />
Success in global markets is vital for Australia's continuing prosperity.<br />
During the past decade this Government has reversed the long-term decline in<br />
Australia's performance as a trading nation. In 1980 the proportion of our GDP<br />
provided by exports of goods and services had fallen below the OECD average. In<br />
1993 it was again above it.<br />
Our exports of manufactures have been doubling every five years.<br />
They now account for almost one-third of our total goods exports.<br />
We have also diversified the composition of our merchandise trade. The most<br />
dramatic shift has been in the value-added area precisely where it was most<br />
required. Five years ago, elaborately transformed manufactures accounted for 16 per cent of<br />
our merchandise exports. Last year it was 22 per cent.<br />
Another major shift has been in the strong growth of our exports of services. These<br />
now form a quarter of total exports. In fact, the services trade deficit is now less<br />
than a third of what it was a decade ago. On current trends, we will soon have a<br />
surplus. Tourism and education make an enormous contribution to services trade, but we are<br />
also seeing rapid growth in telecommunications, financial services and legal<br />
services. Australia now has a trade surplus in computer software, for example.<br />
Earnings from exports of computer software have grown by 60 per cent over the<br />
past five years to nearly $ 400 million.<br />
The Winning Markets trade strategy which Senator McMullan is releasing today is<br />
designed to improve on this performance. It reflects extensive consultation with<br />
business, and is focussed particularly on getting smaller Australian firms exportready<br />
and operating off-shore. </p>
<p>Australia's natural resource-based exports minerals and agriculture are, of<br />
course, the core of our export trade and they will remain so. Increasingly we are<br />
adding value to these exports and tailoring them to particular markets.<br />
Winning Markets gives greater priority than in the past to value-added exports, and<br />
especially in manufacturing and services. This is in part because these are the<br />
areas where the Government can add its own particular value for our exporters at<br />
present. The Winning Markets study starts by acknowledging that the factors that will<br />
determine Australia's success as a trading nation are our fundamental economic<br />
policy settings, our access to overseas markets, and the extent to which we can<br />
develop a trade and investment culture, especially among our small and mediumsized<br />
companies.<br />
It recognises that our trade performance depends, often crucially, on domestic<br />
factors. In Australia's case, our macro-economic policy settings have provided a solid basis<br />
for our exporters. We have kept inflation low, and growth high.<br />
We have introduced greater competition through lower tariffs and, more recently,<br />
the adoption of the Hilmer reforms on competition policy, thereby reducing the costs<br />
of doing business.<br />
We have a national commitment to invest in innovation and research and<br />
development. Later this year, the Government will bring down a statement on<br />
support for innovation and best practice in Australian business<br />
Over the long-term, one of the things which will matter most for our future is the<br />
investment the Government has put into upgrading education and training for our<br />
workforce. Over the past decade the proportion of students completing year 12, and the<br />
proportion of young Australians going on to university, have more than doubled.<br />
We have opened up tens of thousands of opportunities in vocational training.<br />
The skills base and the technical excellence we have nurtured, our world class<br />
scientific and research base, our telecommunications capacity these are highly<br />
prized assets in a fast growing region where individual countries are in fierce<br />
competition for resources and wealth.<br />
These are all quality reforms with lasting benefits.<br />
But, of course, just as you need to continually meet new challenges to stay ahead in<br />
your businesses, Government must be able to respond to current developments in<br />
its policy settings.<br />
And that is what my Government has been able to do time and again. </p>
<p>I am pleased to say that you will see further evidence of this tomorrow when we<br />
meet with the major union groups to conclude a further agreement under the Accord.<br />
This will ensure a continuation of low inflation and job creation. It will provide the<br />
means for us to radically lift our national savings performance.<br />
I am also pleased to be able to let you know that it will address a particular concern<br />
of many businesses domestically, namely the treatment of unfair dismissals.<br />
It is crucially important that all employees can feel confident that they will be treated<br />
fairly in their place of employment. After all, Labor Governments have been<br />
traditionally concerned with the rights and protections of workers.<br />
One of the most important areas where employers have considerable responsibility<br />
is to ensure that in the event of dismissal of employees the action is not harsh or<br />
unjust or unfair, and that the right weight is given to following correct procedures.<br />
In the area of unfair dismissals, the Government is committed to shielding<br />
employees from the small minority of unscrupulous or unjust employers who may not<br />
at times be acting ethically in this area. The Government will maintain this principle<br />
in its approach to questions of dismissal.<br />
With this as background it may still be the case that some of the application of the<br />
current unfair dismissal laws have not always been what all business, and small<br />
business in particular, have thought is right. Indeed, there have been expressions<br />
of public concern that the Government is interested in addressing.<br />
The essential challenge in the area of unfair dismissals is to get the balance right<br />
between the right protection for employees and making sure that the process is not<br />
so legalistic as to mean that the system is not working properly.<br />
Laurie Brereton and I have talked through this issue with both the ACTU and a<br />
number of employers and employer groups.<br />
As a result of these discussions it has been decided to take some action in the area<br />
of unfair dismissals, and the Minister will be announcing further details this<br />
afternoon. Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
The Government's policies have delivered tangible success.<br />
Australia's international competitiveness has increased around 40 per cent since the<br />
early 1980s.<br />
This competitiveness is reflected in the number of companies establishing regional<br />
headquarters in Australia.<br />
I </p>
<p>Since 1993, when the Government intensified its efforts to attract regional<br />
headquarters here, another 54 companies have located operations and brought jobs<br />
to Australia. These include firms like IBM, Oracle and Data-General.<br />
The reasons are straightforward:<br />
our management pool is 7 to 8 times bigger than Singapore's and 3 to 4 times<br />
bigger than Hong Kong's<br />
office accommodation in Australian capitals is some 6 to 8 per cent less<br />
expensive than comparable space in Singapore and Hong Kong<br />
we offer high quality, low-cost expatriate accommodation, health and<br />
education<br />
our international telephone calls are about the cheapest in the world<br />
we have well qualified and highly competitive support services, such as<br />
lawyers, accountants, management consultants and computer specialists<br />
Australian salaries for qualified and professional executives are 60 per cent<br />
more competitive than Singapore and 50 per cent more than Hong Kong<br />
our rapidly expanding commercial and cultural ties with the Asia-Pacific<br />
region help support business operations across the region<br />
Our diverse multicultural population is another important asset for this country.<br />
Many Australian SMEs are operated by people from non-English speaking<br />
backgrounds. They often have skills, personal links and knowledge of business<br />
networks in their home countries that can help companies win new markets.<br />
One of the real advantages for Australia of our location in the fastest growing region<br />
of the world is that, much earlier than in Europe, we understood the nature of<br />
competition from the dynamic new Asian economies. We realised that we needed to<br />
compare ourselves and compete not just with our own past performances, or with<br />
other mature industrialised economies, but also with the ' Tigers" around us.<br />
The second part of Winning Markets describes how Australia goes about improving<br />
our access to overseas markets and exploiting these more effectively.<br />
Australia has important traditional markets in Europe and the United States and<br />
smaller emerging markets in the Indian Ocean region and Latin America.<br />
But Asia remains our main target for export growth. The reason is that, by the year<br />
2000, the East Asian economies will constitute the largest market in the world,<br />
surpassing Western Europe and North America. </p>
<p>Last year alone showed how things are changing. Australia's merchandise exports<br />
to South-East Asia grew by 12 per cent. South-East Asia now accounts for about<br />
per cent of those exports compared with 9 per cent a decade ago. Korea overtook<br />
the United States to become our second-largest export market after Japan. And if<br />
you add together the markets of China, Hong Kong and Taiwan, the China region is<br />
now our third largest trading partner.<br />
Because Australia's trade is diverse we need our trade policy to operate on a wide<br />
range of fronts. For example, we need to address the obstacles that face our<br />
exporters of agricultural and mineral commodities, of manufactures, our overseas<br />
investors and our exporters of skills and ideas. They all have different problems<br />
and need different responses<br />
The best way of doing this is undoubtedly through the multilateral trade system of<br />
the World Trade Organisation.<br />
Australia alone cannot prise open markets. Even if we had the disposition to do so,<br />
we don't have the clout that would enable us to operate unilaterally.<br />
An effective and comprehensive multilateral trade system is our best protection<br />
against the worst excesses of the unilateralists, or of inward-looking bilateral or<br />
regional arrangements.<br />
One of the goals set out in Winning Markets is that of rekindling global enthusiasm<br />
for multilateral trade liberalisation. We saw at the recent G7 summit that support for<br />
such liberalisation is pretty thin in Europe and the United States.<br />
We hope that by the time of the first meeting of the World Trade Organisation in<br />
Singapore next year, Australia can build support for an ambitious agenda that will<br />
include the further liberalisation of trade in agriculture ( with the help of the<br />
Australian chaired Cairns Group), the development of fairer global investment rules<br />
and real movement on the liberalisation of trade in services.<br />
This is a sector of great interest to many small and medium businesses. Australia<br />
has already successfully shaped the course of global negotiations on<br />
telecommunications. And we will be just as active in the negotiations on<br />
professional services, where Australian firms, large and small, are increasingly<br />
turning to export markets, only to find a bewildering array of barriers.<br />
I am sure that the successful APEC leaders' meeting, which President Clinton<br />
chaired in Seattle, did a great deal to bring about the conclusion of the Uruguay<br />
Round. I think APEC can also assist in further global trade liberalisation.<br />
Australia has invested a lot in APEC and we will continue to do so. The Asia-Pacific<br />
region has the fastest growth in the world three times that of established<br />
industrialised countries.<br />
APEC encompasses a dynamic region that already accounts for more than 40 per<br />
cent of the world's population, half of the world's GOP and 46 per cent of its exports. </p>
<p>The enormous achievement of APEC so far has been to reinforce a region-wide<br />
trend towards liberalising trade and investment in the Asia-Pacific.<br />
It provides the framework in which regional governments can take the hard<br />
decisions on economic deregulation and structural change. Recent deregulation in<br />
Indonesia and China, and tariff reductions in Malaysia, indicate the direction Asia is<br />
heading. These developments strengthen the region's dynamism and ensure<br />
continued high growth rates.<br />
And this process will be strengthened as a result of the historic commitment of<br />
APEC leaders at Bogor last year to free trade and investment in the region by 2010<br />
for developed countries and 2020 for developing countries.<br />
APEC may be the most productive manifestation we have yet seen of what used to<br />
be called the North/ South dialogue.<br />
The commitment to free trade and investment in APEC goes well beyond the<br />
liberalisation of tariffs. It will address a host of market access issues that<br />
increasingly matter to Australia's traders and investors in the globalised trade<br />
environment services, investment, transfer of technology and intellectual property.<br />
Different standards alone add an estimated 5 to 10 per cent to the costs faced by<br />
exporters entering a market for the first time. So APEC's work in areas such as<br />
standards, the mutual recognition of testing procedures and the streamlining of<br />
customs procedures can offer real gains to business.<br />
It is vital that small business is in a position to take full advantage of the<br />
opportunities provided by free trade and investment in APEC. This will be the major<br />
theme of the meeting of APEC ministers responsible for small business policy to be<br />
held in Adelaide later this year.<br />
With many US business people here, it may be worth noting a fact that seems to<br />
receive little attention in the United States: that US exports to East Asia are growing<br />
at twice the rate of East Asian exports to the US.<br />
US projections have put Asia, even excluding Japan, as the United States' largest<br />
export market by 2010.<br />
So APEC is important to the United States as well as to Australia.<br />
The access Australia achieves to markets through multilateral activities like APEC,<br />
the World Trade Organisation and other forums such as the development of links<br />
between the ASEAN Free Trade Agreement and the Australia-New Zealand Closer<br />
Economic Relations Agreement is supported by our bilateral activities with<br />
individual governments.<br />
A model of what we can do in this area is found in the many layers of government<br />
and commercial cooperation Australia has built up with Indonesia. </p>
<p>It is perfectly true, of course, that only businesses can do business. But sound and<br />
creative govern ment-to-govern ment relationships provide a foundation of confidence<br />
which is often reassuring to business people.<br />
Another theme of this Government's work bilaterally and a direction we want to<br />
continue to move in is encouraging the development of alliances and partnerships<br />
between Australian and overseas companies. Linkages with other firms, particularly<br />
large ones, is a key strategy for SMEs wanting to exploit the opportunities of<br />
globalisation. Examples of what we already have done in this area is the establishment of a fund<br />
to examine ways in which Australian and Korean companies with complementary<br />
capabilities could capture opportunities in the " information superhighway" which<br />
neither can do alone.<br />
Similarly, we have set up a fund to help establish consortia of Australian and<br />
Singaporean companies to bid for large projects to encourage involvement in the<br />
expanding Asian infrastructure market.<br />
The third key element of Winning Markets involves fostering a trade and investment<br />
culture among local business.<br />
Recent studies in Australia have found that a major factor distinguishing those firms<br />
that export from those that do not is the presence, or lack of it, of an export culture<br />
within the companies.<br />
Such a culture has begun to take root in Australia but it still needs nurturing.<br />
Recent studies of Australian manufacturers and service exporters have identified<br />
huge untapped export potential in both areas. A relatively small number of firms in<br />
these sectors is exporting at present.<br />
The research also showed that the major constraints on the ability of SMEs to<br />
operate internationally include difficulties in getting timely information on market<br />
opportunities and managing uncertainty and risk.<br />
The Government is already assisting exporters through our export assistance<br />
agency, Austrade, and another body Ausindustry.<br />
Ausindustry works to help businesses commercialise research and development<br />
technology, and assist their activities such as product design and quality systems,<br />
marketing and networking.<br />
Austrade works to help exporters secure positions in overseas markets.<br />
Following extensive client research by Austrade, Senator McMullan is announcing<br />
today a new client service strategy which will mean more and better services for<br />
Australian exporters. </p>
<p>Austrade will now provide extensive information and advice free of charge to new<br />
and potential exporters. This is a major commitment to the needs of potential<br />
exporters among Australian small and medium-sized businesses.<br />
A second group of companies seeking practical assistance to enter and build export<br />
markets will receive subsidised services.<br />
A third group, including experienced exporters building on established overseas<br />
business, can receive tailored, intensive assistance from Austrade on a cost<br />
recovery basis.<br />
As a result of the work done on the Winning Markets strategy and the discussions<br />
which have been held with business, Senator McMullan is also announcing a<br />
number of other decisions which will help Australian exporters and strengthen the<br />
trade policy debate in Australia.<br />
Among these initiatives are a parliamentary enquiry into export-related airfreight<br />
issues. Over half Australia's non-primary merchandise exports are transported by<br />
air. The enquiry will examine Australia's airfreight infrastructure and recommend<br />
how services to exporters, particularly of perishable products, can be improved.<br />
To enable the Government to record and follow-up more effectively Australian<br />
business concerns about export barriers, an export barriers reporting scheme will<br />
come into effect from 1 July 1995 as part of a new unit within the Department of<br />
Foreign Affairs and Trade.<br />
To build a stronger export culture in Australia and to link trade research and<br />
education more closely with business interests, a Chair and Centre in the Practice of<br />
International Trade will be established, with business support, at the Melbourne<br />
Business School at the University of Melbourne.<br />
In response to the difficulties experienced by smaller Australian companies in selling<br />
their products to some of the more difficult, unfamiliar markets such as Japan,<br />
Austrade is examining the feasibility of setting up an Australian enterprise to<br />
manage effective distribution for Australian processed and manufactured products in<br />
selected markets. The project would draw heavily on private sector involvement and<br />
would operate on a fully commercial basis.<br />
Finally, consultations with industry have shown that the cost of market information is<br />
an important barrier to the expansion of exports from small and medium-sized<br />
enterprises. So a new integrated, electronic exporter and marketing service on the<br />
Internet called the " Australia TradeBlazer' program will be established by<br />
Austrade. In its first stage, it will provide on-line access to relevant export<br />
information.<br />
The Winning Markets strategy, and the associated announcements which are being<br />
made are a further commitment by the Government to ensuring that Australian<br />
companies and our small and medium-sized enterprises especially will continue<br />
to be able to compete with the best in the world's markets. </p>
<p>Governments commonly talk about their " commitments", I know. They talk about<br />
them at least as often as small businesses talk about the failure of government to<br />
actually deliver.<br />
I suspect our relationship needs a different language: one which reflects the fact<br />
that we are engaged in the same project, which is the creation of a dynamic export<br />
economy. Perhaps we need to see the relationship as a joint venture and talk more<br />
in terms of shared goals and common efforts to which both must deliver.<br />
From the Government's point of view, small and medium sized businesses are an<br />
arm of national policy and, notwithstanding the fact that we cannot act for you or<br />
give you the ideas and courage you will need to succeed, we will do all we can to<br />
make you stronger.<br />
Thank you for having me with you today.<br />
Ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
