<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22907</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview, Paralympic Village</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/10/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Doorstop</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Parlympic Games</p>
<p>E&amp;OE……………………………………………………………………………………</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, the Olympics were such a huge success, can the Paralympics really match that do you think?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It’s not a question of matching it. It will be a success in it’s own right and I believe that the public support for the Paralympics will be terrific. I’m certainly getting behind it and I know that people all over the country are inspired by it and there’s a real spirit here. Everything’s different. You don’t try and compare. You just make sure it’s a huge success in it’s own right and I know that it will be.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>And what about the Australian team?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, they’ll do damn well as they always do. They’ll be very competitive and they will be very effective. I think it’s going to be a great success. It’s a great spirit tonight and there’s enormous enthusiasm amongst the Australian team. We’ve got over 4,000 athletes from 124 different countries. When you think back to the more humble beginnings of the Paralympics in Rome in 1960, it’s got bigger and better every four years.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Can I just ask you, we’re featuring the basketball and of course Australia and the UK contested the final in 1996 – Australia got the gold.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>As was appropriate.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If it happens again?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I’ll be pretty happy. Very happy.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, thank you very much.</p>
<p>(Ends)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
