<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6630</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, LUMEAH DAY CARE CENTRE, MELBOURNE, 26 MAY 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/05/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006630.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNT IL 2. 30 Pm.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING ADDRESS BY THE PRIME 1MINISTER<br />
LUMEAH DAY CARE CENTRE MELBOURNE 26 MAY 1985<br />
Mr Moderator, Ladies and Gentlemen.<br />
I welcome the opportunity of joining you today at<br />
Lumeah. This day is the culmination of ten years dedication and<br />
commitment on the part of many people. Outstanding<br />
among them has been Virginia Davey previously the<br />
welfare officer at Lumeah; a woman of tireless energy,<br />
she is being especially honoured today.<br />
Back in 1975 a number of senior citizens from the<br />
Preston area were invited to share in activities at<br />
Lumeah. The number of non-resident participants grew<br />
until, by 1983, 56 people were using the Day Care<br />
Centre, in addition to those resident at Lumeah.<br />
That success zorely strained the old facilities and made<br />
necessary the new complex we see today. It is a credit<br />
to all involved.<br />
I am pleased the Government has been able to provide<br />
financial assistance of some $ 331,000; we know that this<br />
money will be put to good use.<br />
The challenge of meeting the growing and changing needs<br />
of the aged is one of the most important with which the<br />
Government has to reckon.<br />
By next Century the aged will represent a larger, and a<br />
growing, proportion of Australia's total population.<br />
We as a Government aim to ensure that their needs the<br />
needs of the aged are met in-a way which is affordable<br />
by the aged themselves and by the rest of the community.<br />
We are dedicated to providing a range of services for<br />
the aged which is equitable, comprehensive, balanced and<br />
cost effective.<br />
We also wish to ensure that every aged person is able to<br />
select, with his or her relatives, the combination of<br />
services most appropriate to his or her medical, social<br />
and emotional needs. </p>
<p>One step the Government has taken to this end has been<br />
to place all programs for the aged in one Department.<br />
The creation of the new Department of Community Services<br />
highlights the importance the Commonwealth places on the<br />
services area and its recognition of the need to plan<br />
and co-ordinate effective action for the aged.<br />
The setting up of the Office of Aged Care within the<br />
Department of Community Services will give particular<br />
focus to the development and implementation of the-<br />
Government's policies on aged care.<br />
Overall expenditure for the new Department in 1984/ 85 is<br />
likely to be over $ 1600 million. of that total, over<br />
$ 1200 million will be expended on services for the aged.<br />
Lumeah and its various facilities will receive<br />
assistance of over $ 900,000 out of this 1984/ 85<br />
alloca,. tion.<br />
Even with that" Ohigh level of Government expenditure, the<br />
Federal Labor Government considers~ there is plenty of<br />
room to improve services fo'r the aged.<br />
The aged are not a uniform group; they have a wide range<br />
of needs and requirements.<br />
To date the Commonwealth's involvement in care of the<br />
aged has been virtually limited to the provision of<br />
nursing home accommodation. Besides being very costly,<br />
such accommodation is not necessarily the most important<br />
requirement for care of the aged.<br />
An Australian Bureau of Statistics Survey in 1980 showed<br />
that of the people aged 65 years and over who were<br />
moderately or severely handicapped, nearly threequarters<br />
live in the community compared with only onequarter<br />
in institutions. Other available data,<br />
including the views of older people themselves, also<br />
indicates that old'er people need and want more support<br />
services in the community at large.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen, this is why the introduction of<br />
the Federal Government's Home and Community Care Program<br />
is such an important initiative.<br />
Through this Program, and in co-operation with the </p>
<p>States and voluntary, Church, and community agencies, we<br />
are working towards a situation where there will be a<br />
comprehensive range of integrated home care and<br />
community based services. Although the final parameters<br />
of the Program have not yet been agreed with the States,<br />
I have already announced that the Commonwealth will be<br />
contributing $ 300 million over the next three years for<br />
this integrated program.<br />
This is not to say that we want to stop supporting<br />
nursing home care; it fulfils a vital service for the<br />
frail aged. The facilities here at Lumeah are an<br />
excellent example of what is best in this regard. Nor<br />
do we want. to penalize those who are residents of<br />
nursing homes. But, as a Government, we are anxious to<br />
establish a more rational and less costly way of<br />
assisting nursing home patients.<br />
It may come as a surprise to many of you to learn that<br />
although the_-Commonwealth is paying $ 48.50 per day in<br />
nursing home benefits for each bed in a participating<br />
nursing home ih Victoria, it is paying only $ 27.80 per<br />
day in Tasmania. The other State's are in between these<br />
extremes. I think most people would regard it as ' a duty of their<br />
Government to do something to rationalize these nursing<br />
home benefits.<br />
Nursing home benefits are directly related to the cost<br />
of operation. The variation in these costs is due to a<br />
variety of factors, including the different staffing<br />
requirements. which are determined by State Governments.<br />
However, the Commonwealth Government and the tax payer<br />
foot the bill.<br />
Because the community can no longer afford a widening of<br />
this discrepancy between participating nursing home<br />
costs, the Treasurer announced on 15 May that there<br />
would be a freezing of nursing home benefits in Victoria<br />
and South Australia.<br />
This decision is an important part of the Federal<br />
Government's efforts to restrain public expenditure in<br />
pursuit of its objectives of maintaining strong growth<br />
and increased employment. It is also an important step<br />
in redirecting priorities towards developing better care<br />
services for the overwhelming number of the aged who </p>
<p>can, and who want to, live in their own homes.<br />
The residents at Lumeah, a deficit funded nursing home,<br />
will not be directly affected by this recent decision to<br />
. J freeze the level of nursing home benefits in Victoria.<br />
You will only be marginally affected by the decision to<br />
restore the required nursing home patient contribution<br />
to the 87.5 per cent it was until last October.<br />
in conclusion I should like to acknowledge the untiring<br />
efforts of all those organisations throughout Australia<br />
without whose selfless work no Government's aged welfare<br />
program would be able to operate.<br />
In particular, today, I want to congratulate the Uniting<br />
Church on its efforts in this regard<br />
1' Your nursing home, hostel, and day care centre are<br />
a very important part of the total caring network.<br />
I now have great pleasure in declaring the Virginia<br />
Davey Day Care and Para-Medical Wing open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
