<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11069</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   RADIO INTERVIEW WITH KENDALL HODGMAN                   NEWS RADIO, ABC</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>John Howard joins us live from Melbourne where he has just announced</p>
<p> $20 million funding for community agencies as part of the Federal</p>
<p> Government's Tough on Drugs strategy. Prime Minister, thanks</p>
<p> for joining News Radio.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's a pleasure.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Let's start out with your vision of tackling the burgeoning drug</p>
<p> problem in Australia, what is the solution?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the way to go about it is to attack it on three levels. You</p>
<p> must have effective law enforcement, you must have effective education</p>
<p> of children in particular against the dangers of commencing drug taking</p>
<p> and you must have adequate treatment facilities for addicts who want</p>
<p> to kick their habit. And our Tough on Drugs strategy of $290 million</p>
<p> is about providing more resources in those three areas. One is no</p>
<p> more important than the other two. They are all important. You have</p>
<p> got to give the police and the customs extra resources. You have got</p>
<p> to station Australian Federal Police in countries like Thailand so</p>
<p> they can pick up intelligence about drugs that are being sent to Australia.</p>
<p> You also need to warn young people, particularly through the schools,</p>
<p> about the dangers of drugs and you also need adequate treatment facilities.</p>
<p> And what I announced today was in that third area. We are providing</p>
<p> to something like 50 organisations all over Australia an additional</p>
<p> $20 million which will really give those organisations more resources</p>
<p> to help people who have got a problem and who up until now haven't</p>
<p> been able to get enough assistance. And one of the more distressing</p>
<p> elements of the drug problem that I have encountered is talking on</p>
<p> talkback radio to the parents of young people who have got a problem,</p>
<p> want to do something about it but can't find a place in a treatment</p>
<p> facility. Now, whatever views you might have on other aspects of how</p>
<p> to fight the drug problem, I think everybody agrees that there should</p>
<p> be adequate facilities for people who have got an addiction and want</p>
<p> to do something about it. Now, hitherto this has been mainly something</p>
<p> that has been dealt with at a State level. We think there is a federal</p>
<p> responsibility as well and that's why we have made a lot more</p>
<p> money available and I am very pleased with the range of facilities</p>
<p> that we are helping today in all parts of Australia, in every State</p>
<p> and we have had hundreds of applications and we have made grants to</p>
<p> 50-odd organisations. And from the response that I got at the launch</p>
<p> today it is obvious that the resources are very welcome.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Apart from the drugs problem I would like to cover three big R's and,</p>
<p> I think, there are probably three R's I'd like to cover </p>
<p> reconciliation, republic and revenue. And by that I mean tax and Telstra</p>
<p> privatisation. What do you see your role as in shaping this course</p>
<p> of change for Australia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we need a new taxation system. We have needed a new taxation</p>
<p> system for 20 years. And we had an election where we put our political</p>
<p> bodies on the line, we laid out the detail and the people voted for</p>
<p> us and we are asking the Senate to respect the decision of the Australian</p>
<p> people last October and I hope that it will. It is yet to take a vote</p>
<p> and I think we should wait and see how the Senate responds. I hope</p>
<p> it will respond in accordance with the wishes of the Australian public.</p>
<p> The Australian public did return us. There will be enormous benefits</p>
<p> for our exporters if we can get a new tax system. They will be a lot</p>
<p> cheaper because under a GST exports are cheaper. We will be cutting</p>
<p> the costs of our domestic industries, we'll be particularly cutting</p>
<p> the cost of our fuel for our farmers and miners and that's very</p>
<p> important, and we'll be providing significant personal income</p>
<p> tax cuts, $13 billion worth in addition to family package, particularly</p>
<p> targeted to families with children of $2 billion on top of that $13</p>
<p> billion. So there's a huge reform at stake and our argument very</p>
<p> simply is that we told the public all about this before the election</p>
<p> and the public voted for us and we told them all the detail of it.</p>
<p> We probably exceeded the detail provided in an election campaign,</p>
<p> provided by any former government, and we are just saying a very simple</p>
<p> thing to the Australian people and also to the Senators who will finally</p>
<p> make a decision on this before the 30th of June, please</p>
<p> remember that the Australian people voted for us and if you believe</p>
<p> in representative democracy then you'll take note of that decision.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Because I have not spoken to you before I am interested in getting</p>
<p> an insight into John Howard the person. What would you say are the</p>
<p> qualities you bring to Australia?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Candour, tenacity, an understanding of what the mainstream is concerned</p>
<p> about. A belief in the infinite decency of the Australian people,</p>
<p> a confident view of our past, not a blinkered view, not a view that</p>
<p> says we never made mistakes, we didn't treat some people less</p>
<p> well than we should have. Of course we have blemishes but I have an</p>
<p> essentially optimistic view both of Australia's past and of Australia's</p>
<p> future and that's what the Australian people need. But it has</p>
<p> to be a realistic optimism, it has to be an optimism tempered by a</p>
<p> recognition that we are forever part of a globalised world economy</p>
<p> and anybody who thinks that we can turn back the clock and put up</p>
<p> the walls of protection and return to a fortressed Australia are kidding</p>
<p> themselves.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Okay. So recent events in East Timor, for instance, have given Australia</p>
<p> cause to reflect on its role in the region over the past quarter century.</p>
<p> What have you as our current Prime Minister learnt from the lessons</p>
<p> of the past?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think I am rather more interested in what I have done and</p>
<p> I have probably done more than any prime minister, particularly in</p>
<p> recent times, to alter Australian policy on East Timor. I have no</p>
<p> doubt that the views I put to Dr Habibie, the Indonesian President,</p>
<p> before Christmas when I wrote to him urging a significant change in</p>
<p> the policy of the Indonesian Government, I have no doubt that that</p>
<p> had a major impact on Indonesian thinking. Now, it's very easy</p>
<p> from the vantage point of 1999 to say that something that was done</p>
<p> in 1975 or 1979 was wrong. I don't do that. I can understand</p>
<p> why attitudes were taken then. The important thing is to get it right</p>
<p> now and we say that ultimately the views of the East Timorese people</p>
<p> must be obeyed and if they ultimately opt for independence, well independence</p>
<p> they will have. We would prefer in their interests and in the interests</p>
<p> of the stability of the region to have a period of autonomy before</p>
<p> that full independence occurs. The resources of that territory are</p>
<p> very meagre, they will be even less if there is an abrupt withdrawal</p>
<p> of Indonesian support. In any event, Australia has special responsibilities</p>
<p> because we are close to East Timor and we will discharge our responsibilities.</p>
<p> The Australian Government will not be reluctant to see that we discharge</p>
<p> our responsibilities. And it's because we are willing to do that</p>
<p> and because we have been a good friend of Indonesia's and of</p>
<p> the people of East Timor that we can express our views so very strongly.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Staying with reconstruction and reconciliation to the task of healing</p>
<p> the wounds between black and white Australia. We have heard your reasons</p>
<p> for not saying sorry, for not.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, no. People keep saying, not saying sorry. I mean, a person can</p>
<p> be personally sorry and I have said any number of times that I am</p>
<p> personally sorry for any injustices committed against any Australian</p>
<p> in the past. As an individual human being of course I am sorry and</p>
<p> if you actually analyse what I said at the Reconciliation Congress</p>
<p> in 1997 you'll find that I had quite a bit to say about that</p>
<p> from a personal point of view. I have just expressed a view about</p>
<p> a national apology in relation to the events of earlier generations</p>
<p> where I don't believe that is appropriate and that remains my</p>
<p> view.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>This morning the Australian newspaper has reported that Cabinet</p>
<p> has approved the Constitutional preamble which fails to recognise</p>
<p> the aboriginal custodianship of Australia's past, is that the</p>
<p> case?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think people should wait and see the preamble before they jump to</p>
<p> conclusions.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Okay. Given that this has been a major sticking point as far as the</p>
<p> Constitution debate is concerned, are you expecting further tension</p>
<p> on the road to reconciliation?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't think that last statement is correct. I think the</p>
<p> two are somewhat different issues. As far as reconciliation is concerned</p>
<p> I said on election night that I would like to see it realised and</p>
<p> we'll try very hard and there's goodwill on the part of</p>
<p> the Government and there's a lot of hard work being put in to</p>
<p> see if some agreement can't be reached in relation to a document.</p>
<p> But it's not going to be easy and I don't want to raise</p>
<p> expectations unduly but there's goodwill on our part and there's</p>
<p> immense goodwill on the part of most Australians. But equally most</p>
<p> Australians are far more interested in the future than the past and</p>
<p> the more there is a dwelling on the past in so many things the less</p>
<p> attention is commanded of the Australian people.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>You recall your election victory speech, you set a very tight timeframe</p>
<p> for reconciliation. It is a sensitive process. Do you think it is</p>
<p> possible to achieve in two years?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the reconciliation timetable was not set by me it was set by</p>
<p> the Act of the Australian Parliament that established a council for</p>
<p> reconciliation and that puts a timeframe of a couple of years on it.</p>
<p> So it was with that in mind that I made those comments.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Is it possible?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am going to try, I can't make...do more than that.</p>
<p> It's difficult but there's goodwill and in order to achieve</p>
<p> an outcome there has to be goodwill on all sides. And I know that</p>
<p> there are many people within the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander</p>
<p> community who have immense goodwill towards whoever is in government,</p>
<p> whether it's a Coalition government or a Labor government. And</p>
<p> they are interested in a positive future between indigenous and other</p>
<p> Australians.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Okay. From reconciliation onto another one of the R's </p>
<p> the republic. From your position of Prime Minister of Australia how</p>
<p> do you rate the importance of the debate?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I have never rated it as highly as some other people have but</p>
<p> I have always said that I would not in any way prevent the Australian</p>
<p> people making a decision on this issue. And that is why we promised</p>
<p> to have a Constitutional Convention and I said that if out of that</p>
<p> Convention there was strong support for a particular model I would</p>
<p> put that model. And that is exactly what I have done, I have remained</p>
<p> true and straight to the commitments I made to the Australian public.</p>
<p> I don't find that people are very excited about the issue either</p>
<p> way. It is rarely raised with me in my ordinary work as Prime Minister.</p>
<p> I don't find Australians generally particularly interested either</p>
<p> way. Now, that may change as we get closer to the referendum and it's</p>
<p> too early to make a judgement either about the outcome or indeed about</p>
<p> the level of interest. But speaking as of now I have to say to you,</p>
<p> Kendall, that it is not something that people raise with me. The only</p>
<p> people who raise the issue with me are journalists.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>So if you had your way how would you have preferred to have spent</p>
<p> the amount of money that is going to be spent on the referendum?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I've never really thought about that because I have always</p>
<p> taken the view that you have to spend some money on democracy. I mean,</p>
<p> it's very easy for people to say well it's a waste of money</p>
<p> to have this or that. If you carry that to its logical conclusion</p>
<p> you don't have any elections. Now, heavens above you can't</p>
<p> have a democracy without consulting the people. I have accepted all</p>
<p> along that there would probably be a referendum so therefore I have</p>
<p> not really devoted any attention to that. Look, I made a promise to</p>
<p> the public and I intend to keep that promise.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>So let's get onto other aspects of revenue now, you have a very</p>
<p> big year ahead as far as getting the tax package up and ready for</p>
<p> implementation by next year. You have said it is the most important</p>
<p> piece of legislation you will ever present to the Parliament. What</p>
<p> difficulties do you foresee given what has happened in the Senate</p>
<p> with Telstra?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't know that I can add much to what I said a few moments</p>
<p> ago that in order to make this law it needs to pass through the Senate</p>
<p> and the Australian people voted for the package. We are going through</p>
<p> a process of Senate inquiries at the present time, we'll get</p>
<p> reports from Senate committees. I suspect that many of those reports</p>
<p> will reflect already known views about the issue from the different</p>
<p> vantage points of politics and in the end the Senate will have to</p>
<p> make a decision. And I can only say again to the Labor Party, to the</p>
<p> Australian Democrats and to the Independents in the Senate that we</p>
<p> did have an election last October, we did lay out all of the detail</p>
<p> of our plan before the election, we didn't hold anything back,</p>
<p> no government in the history of Australia has gone into more detail</p>
<p> on an important issue than did we before the last election. We were</p>
<p> told by many people it was politically foolish to do so and we were</p>
<p> told that it was crazy and all those sorts of things. But in the end</p>
<p> we did it, we were honest with the Australian people, we were up-front</p>
<p> with them, we laid out our plan, we won the election and what we are</p>
<p> saying to those who hold the numbers in the Senate, please remember</p>
<p> that.</p>
<p>Now, if in the face of all of that they don't take heed of the</p>
<p> Australian people well, we argue that that would be a very, very disappointing</p>
<p> thing for them to do to say the least. But I don't want to at</p>
<p> this stage pre-empt what the Senate is going to do. The Senate has</p>
<p> made it clear, or the Labor Party and others in the Senate have....they</p>
<p> said they want to have an inquiry process, well we accept that they</p>
<p> had the numbers to bring that on and that's happening now. I</p>
<p> understand that the Labor Party is committed to having a definitive</p>
<p> vote before the 30th of June. Clearly our prospects of</p>
<p> getting it through before the 30th of June are greater</p>
<p> than after the 30th of June. So we just have to wait and</p>
<p> see but it is an important test of whether the authority and the will</p>
<p> of the Australian people is heeded.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Before you go Prime Minister, just a couple of quick fire questions</p>
<p> on the day's current affairs. How damaging do you think that</p>
<p> the IOC bribery scandal has been to Sydney hosting the Olympic Games</p>
<p> next year?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, in the end when we get to the games people will have put it</p>
<p> behind them but I can't say that the publicity of the past few</p>
<p> months has been in any way helpful. But it's one of those very</p>
<p> difficult situations. Everybody wants the games to be a success. As</p>
<p> an Australian and as the Australian Prime Minister the time the games</p>
<p> are being held, I am immensely proud of the fact that they have come</p>
<p> to Australia and it is an Australian event, it's not just a Sydney</p>
<p> event although they are being held in Australia. And I am quite certain</p>
<p> that as we get to the countdown when that torch relay commences in</p>
<p> Australia there will be a tremendous surge of excitement but the excitement</p>
<p> and the pride will be directed towards the performance of the athletes.</p>
<p> I don't think it will be directed elsewhere and that is how it</p>
<p> should be.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Do you have any advice for Phil Coles?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, look, if I had any advice in relation to that I wouldn't</p>
<p> be giving it publicly but I can only say that the events....a whole</p>
<p> range of events in relation to this have been, to say the least, extremely</p>
<p> disappointing.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>And what's your response to the Australian Conservation Foundation's</p>
<p> comment that the Beverley Uranium Mine will make for the creation</p>
<p> of a nuclear waste dump in the outback more likely?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am very surprised at that. I hadn't had it reported to</p>
<p> me previously, you are the first person who has drawn it to my attention.</p>
<p> Now, I am not criticising you for raising it but I don't believe</p>
<p> that that is the case at all and I am surprised at the comment.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Politics aside, Prime Minister, when you're making decisions</p>
<p> particularly economic decisions which impact on everyone, what do</p>
<p> you see as the quintessential ordinary Australian on whose behalf</p>
<p> you are making decisions?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there's, I don't think of one particular model of an</p>
<p> ordinary Australian and I don't usually use the expression ordinary'</p>
<p> very often myself. I try and avoid using it, it sounds rather a patronising</p>
<p> expression. I often use the mainstream'. But I try and</p>
<p> make decisions based upon the maximum benefit for the maximum number</p>
<p> of Australians. And there is no doubt that the economic decisions</p>
<p> that we have taken have benefited to a very significant degree the</p>
<p> maximum number of Australians. We have delivered historically low</p>
<p> interest rates, historically low inflation, very strong economic growth,</p>
<p> 400,000 more jobs in three years, the strongest growing economy in</p>
<p> the western world, an economy which is, despite the Asian downturn,</p>
<p> been able to shift exports away from the Asia-Pacific region into</p>
<p> more profitable destinations.</p>
<p>So all of those things have greatly benefited millions of Australians.</p>
<p> Now, there are some Australians who haven't got the benefit of</p>
<p> that but if we'd have taken different decisions fewer Australians</p>
<p> would have been helped and more Australians would have been harmed</p>
<p> because high interest rates affects the mainstream of the Australian</p>
<p> community, high inflation does. More unemployment, all of those things</p>
<p> adversely affect more people. So what one tries to do is to take decisions</p>
<p> that are fair and take decisions that maximise benefits for the largest</p>
<p> number of Australians possible.</p>
<p>HODGMAN:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, thank you for your time today.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's been a pleasure.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
