<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17974</transcript-id>
    <title>New biodiversity fund protects species from climate impacts</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/07/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard, Minister for Climate Change and Energy Efficiency Greg Combet and Minister for Sustainability, Environment, Water, Population and Communities Tony Burke today announced a new Biodiversity Fund to protect Australia's unique species from climate change impacts. </p>
<p>We need to take action to protect Australia's diverse environment from the threats posed by climate change. </p>
<p>The ongoing fund will initially provide $946 million over six years for a range of projects to foster and preserve biodiversity around Australia. </p>
<p>The fund will support farmers, community groups and natural resource management bodies to take action on-ground that will protect biodiversity in the landscape. </p>
<p>It will support restoration and management of areas of the landscape which can store carbon while also achieving biodiversity outcomes including: </p>
<p>? reforestation and revegetation in areas of high conservation value </p>
<p>? management and protection of biodiverse ecosystems, including publicly owned native forests and land under conservation covenants or subject to land clearing restrictions </p>
<p>? action to prevent the spread of invasive species across landscapes. </p>
<p>These measures will ensure the protection of Australia's ecosystems and improve the resilience of Australia's unique species to the impacts of climate change. </p>
<p>Biodiversity plays a crucial role in maintaining the productive capacity of our landscape and protecting our natural ecosystems. </p>
<p>Further information in relation to the Government's clean energy future and carbon price announcement is available at <a href="http://www.cleanenergyfuture.gov.au">www.cleanenergyfuture.gov.au</a>  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
