<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7893</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER FEDERATED IRONWORKERS&#039; ASSOCIAITON NATIONAL COUNCIL MEETING NEWCASTLE - 12 FEBRUARY 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/02/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007893.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( rWi(' 1 AtnATWR' 1 nVT. TUVr-V Wrhmraunnr TIW'TT. flWT. TUV<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
FEDERATED IRONWORKERS' ASSOCIATION<br />
NATIONAL COUNCIL MEETING<br />
NEWCASTLE 12 FEBRUARY 1990<br />
Steve Harrison, National Secretary<br />
Members of the National Council<br />
Delegates It gives me great pleasure to be in Newcastle again for a<br />
much happier reason than my recent visits and to see what<br />
great progress you have made in restoring your city to its<br />
. normal life.<br />
We know that it will take time for the physical and<br />
emotional scars to mend. I can assure you that we will not<br />
forget the people of Newcastle and their needs as they face<br />
this very difficult time.<br />
The cost has been heavy, and for some, tragic, and yet it<br />
could so easily have been much greater.<br />
Through luck, and the exemplary efforts of the emergency<br />
service personnel, loss of life was kept lower than may have<br />
been expected. We all owe these men and women a deep debt<br />
of gratitude for their untiring and selfless work in the<br />
days following the earthquake. It was in the best of<br />
Australian tradition that so many responded to others in<br />
hardship and need.<br />
I know, too, that the FIA played its part, with many members<br />
willingly giving of their time and money to help victims of<br />
the disaster, and with the union making a substantial<br />
donation to the Lord Mayor's Earthquake Relief Fund. </p>
<p>When I came to Newcastle six weeks ago, it was immediately<br />
clear that special relief arrangements would be necessary.<br />
Arrangements have been put in place, with the Commonwealth<br />
and State Governments sharing costs equally, to ensure that<br />
what must be done will be done, quickly and efficiently.<br />
All the money in the world is of no use of course, unless<br />
the will to overcome adversity is there. This will is<br />
something that the people of Newcastle have in abundance.<br />
It is amazing to see how well you are coping, as a<br />
community, with this natural disaster.<br />
Despite the loss of life, damage and destruction across the<br />
city, which unfortunately has been exacerbated by the recent<br />
flooding in the Hunter region, there is enormous confidence<br />
in the future and rightly so.<br />
I was heartened to read recent results from a Survey of<br />
Manufacturing Conditions and Future Prospects of NSW. It<br />
shows one of the highest levels of business confidence in<br />
Newcastle in the five year history of the survey.<br />
The major cause of this confidence is the number of<br />
investment projects underway and proposed.<br />
For instance, tourism investment in the Hunter region has<br />
stimulated the region's construction industry.<br />
And the region's coal mining industry is looking to the<br />
future with optimism, founded on the strong likelihood of<br />
firmer coal prices and further productivity improvements.<br />
The Hunter Valley accounts for 30 per cent of our coal<br />
production and provides 25 per cent of our coal exports.<br />
With continued improvements -in areas such as working<br />
arrangements, the Hunter Valley will be well placed to<br />
enhance its position as a competitive world coal supplier.<br />
Hunter Valley wine producers have also been working hard in<br />
export markets. The National Agricultural and Resource<br />
Outlook Conference, recently held in Canberra, suggests that<br />
total wine exports could earn Australia over $ 200 million by<br />
the middle of this decade.<br />
Similarly the fishing industry in the Newcastle area landed<br />
nearly $ 10 million worth of seafood in 1988-89. About $ 1<br />
million of this was destined for our export markets.<br />
All this, and I have not yet touched on the backbone of the<br />
Newcastle economy your resurgent steel industry.<br />
You all recall that in the early 1980s Australia's steel<br />
industry was an endangered species.<br />
Indeed it was nearly extinct. </p>
<p>When we came to office in 1983 we developed the historic<br />
Steel Industry Plan under which Government, industry, and<br />
unions worked as one to ensure first the recovery of the<br />
steel industry and then laid the basis for its re-emergence<br />
as a world class exporter.<br />
Last March I had the opportunity to see first hand evidence<br />
of the renewed investment confidence in the industry most<br />
strikingly, of course, BHP's $ 400 million investment in the<br />
Newcastle Steelworks that upgraded the rod mill and bloom<br />
caster, the world's largest.<br />
At that time I was also aware of the new attitude of<br />
co-operation and consultation that accompanied the new<br />
capital investment.<br />
Since March the Newcastle Steelworks Development Agreement<br />
has come into effect the most extensive program of<br />
workforce consultation ever undertaken in the steel<br />
industry. Through consultation, investment and improved flexibility in<br />
work practices, this agreement will lead to greater<br />
efficiency and productivity co-operation that will<br />
underpin the continued success of Newcastle's steel<br />
industry. Today, as a result of the reinvigoration of the steel<br />
industry to which we have all contributed, the Australian<br />
steel industry is less inclined to view export markets as a<br />
threat than as an opportunity for growth and<br />
diversification. There are too many doom-sayers and knockers who doubt<br />
Australia's capacity to compete on world markets. They<br />
should come to Newcastle and see what you are doing,<br />
together, to compete in the markets of the world and to<br />
win. There is good news too in that the Federal Government, in<br />
consultation with steelmakers, has negotiated a more<br />
favourable outcome under the USA's Voluntary Restraint<br />
Arrangement for steel imports.<br />
The VRA has been an irritant to Australia's steelmakers but<br />
under the new arrangements, which we hope will be signed<br />
soon, Australian steel exports to the US should grow sharply<br />
over the 30 month restraint period to about double those we<br />
had previously. This could translate into additional export<br />
sales in excess of $ 200 million a highly favourable<br />
outcome for our steel producers and Australia. </p>
<p>Delegates, Sometime in the next few months the Government must face an<br />
election to win its fourth term of Office. As we go into<br />
this election, wages policy and industrial relations will<br />
stand at the heart of the differences between ourselves and<br />
the Opposition a point not lost on the trade union<br />
movement and employers alike.<br />
Effective industrial relations requires that all parties<br />
understand that their legitimate aspirations can best be met<br />
when negotiations are conducted in a spirit of constructive<br />
co-operation.<br />
Over the last seven years, under the auspices of the Accord,<br />
the Government and the trade union movement have given life<br />
to this fundamental truth.<br />
The Accord partners can justifiably be proud of the many<br />
lasting benefits that have been delivered for Australia and<br />
Australians. With a level of industrial disputation nearly 60 per cent<br />
lower than under the previous government, the widespread<br />
acceptance of the need for a responsible wages policy has<br />
achieved an environment conducive to a dynamic process of<br />
growth and change.<br />
As a result, the Accord has fostered the creation of over<br />
1.6 million new jobs since 1983 and unemployment has been<br />
slashed from double digit levels that prevailed when we took<br />
office to around 6 per cent today.<br />
The restraint and responsibility demonstrated by Australian<br />
working men and women has been reciprocated by substantial<br />
improvements in the social wage. Through:<br />
the introduction of Medicare, a universal, fair and<br />
secure national system of health cover;<br />
the massive expansion of child care places;<br />
increases in Family Allowances and the inauguration of<br />
the Family Allowance Supplement; and<br />
S significant cuts in personal income tax rates;<br />
we have sought to ensure that the basic living standards of<br />
ordinary Australians have been enhanced.<br />
We have also transformed superannuation from a rare<br />
privilege for the well-off few to a real and effective means<br />
for ordinary workers to augment their retirement income and<br />
thereby improve their future living standards. </p>
<p>Indeed, the Government's first initiative of award based<br />
superannuation has witnessed a dramatic increase in<br />
coverage. Now nearly three-quarters of all workers have<br />
access to secure, portable and substantial superannuation.<br />
Ultimately all employees covered by awards will have such<br />
success. Delegates, The history of the Accord has demonstrated conclusively the<br />
advantage of achieving change through co-operation and<br />
consensus rather than confrontation.<br />
For this reason, the Government will continue to use the<br />
Accord as the foundation for structural adjustment and<br />
labour market reform.<br />
If we are to make Australian industry more productive,<br />
competitive and capable of generating sustained economic<br />
growth, while at the same time expanding opportunities for<br />
individuals and improving the quality of their work life,<br />
the success of the Government's labour market reform program<br />
is crucial.<br />
The process is well advanced and much has already been<br />
achieved. Successive National Wage Case decisions have given impetus<br />
to a fundamental overhaul of outdated award structures.<br />
Award re-structuring has presented us with a challenge to<br />
achieve better paid jobs and jobs with a better future,<br />
through the development of career paths with an increased<br />
emphasis on training and skills acquisition and development.<br />
A major investment of time and effort has been undertaken in<br />
the planning and development phases alone. Now we face the<br />
even more daunting challenge of instituting practical<br />
changes at the workplace level.<br />
Our collective commitment to this process will be essential<br />
if we are to realise the potential benefits to the fullest.<br />
For that reason and before this audience I want to<br />
acknowledge the progress that has been forthcoming from<br />
workplaces all over the country. I can assure you that the<br />
benefits that will accrue as a result of these historic<br />
changes will make the process of adjustment more than<br />
worthwhile. Integral to the success of labour market reform is the<br />
process of remoulding union structures at the enterprise<br />
level. </p>
<p>The Government is doing its part through the Workplace<br />
Reform Program. I am pleased to see that Newcastle is<br />
leading the way; later this week my colleague and local<br />
Federal member, Alan Morris, will be opening the Hunter<br />
Workplace Resources Centre, to assist individual enterprises<br />
establish effective work practices.<br />
For too long, Australian industry has been hampered by the<br />
fragmentation of craft based unions. Inflexible working<br />
practices and frequent disputes over demarcation have too<br />
often been the result.<br />
So I want to see open lines of communication maintained<br />
between unions, particularly where there is common coverage<br />
of skills. Wherever a ' community of interest' can be<br />
established at the industry level, union amalgamations<br />
should be feasible. This process can be reinforced at<br />
enterprise level by unions establishing a single bargaining<br />
unit such as a joint committee for negotiations with<br />
their employer.<br />
In this respect I commend the FIA's own Council for its firm<br />
stand in support of the proposal to amalgamate the FIA with<br />
the Australian Workers' Union. On that score, I wish<br />
National Secretary, Steve Harrison and his fellow Council<br />
members all the best in their campaign.<br />
As Steve has correctly pointed out in a recent edition of<br />
' Labor News', " the days when rigid barriers controlled the<br />
workplace, based on traditional precepts of what work can be<br />
done by particular classes of employees, have vanished".<br />
The bottom line is this by unifying coverage within the<br />
workplace we are able to circumvent the wasteful and time<br />
consuming occurrence of demarcation disputes, and we can<br />
open up new opportunities for employees to pursue a more<br />
flexible and fulfilling career structure.<br />
Gone are the days when an Ironworker may have started out in<br />
the industry as a sweeper or tradesmen's assistant and then<br />
be forced to remain in that one position for much of his<br />
working life.<br />
My friends, I would finish by simply saying this we are<br />
now entering a critical phase in our labour market reform<br />
program and indeed in the life of the Accord.<br />
The Opposition has attempted to throw down the gauntlet.<br />
While the mind of the public has no doubt been confused by<br />
the Opposition's various altered positions on industrial<br />
relations, the fundamental thrust remains the same. </p>
<p>Their original policies called for an end to centralised<br />
wage fixation. But that was seen by everyone, especially<br />
employers, as a straightforward desire to return to the<br />
1981-82 turmoil of confrontation.<br />
To placate the employers, Senator Chaney last Friday sought<br />
to reverse the thrust of Opposition policy by claiming that<br />
industrial tribunals will remain a major force in<br />
regulating wages for the foreseeable future."<br />
Senator Chaney essentially stated that workers whose wages<br />
are set by the Commission would suffer large cuts in real<br />
wages. But, in an attempt to keep some link with their earlier<br />
policies, the Liberals have kept a role for opting out<br />
through so-called voluntary agreements.<br />
So while trying to convince employers that real wages will<br />
fall, they still have this profound uncertainty in relation<br />
to the nationwide wage outcome. With opting out, as Andrew<br />
Peacock has said, " who's to know" how overall wages will be<br />
determined. In fact, the combination of the prospect of large wage cuts<br />
in the centralised system plus the promise of opting out for<br />
the industrially strong will see a return to the<br />
irresponsible, adversarial and confrontationist attitudes so<br />
prevalent under the Fraser Government.<br />
The malaise of industrial disputation and the disease of<br />
mass unemployment would strike down the Australian economy<br />
once more.<br />
Coalition policies will see the abandonment of the consensus<br />
based approach to industrial relations. Their undisguised<br />
aim is a progressive dismembering of the strength of the'<br />
union movement.<br />
This is the road that Andrew Peacock would, admittedly in<br />
his case unwittingly, lead Australia down.<br />
Collectively, we in the labour movement have the<br />
responsibility to ensure that this challenge is resisted.<br />
In the same way that Newcastle has united as a community, to<br />
overcome the adversity of nature's wrath, so must we rally<br />
nationally, to guard against the man-made catastrophe that<br />
would ensue from the pursuit of the Opposition's illcons<br />
idered policies.<br />
May I wish you all the very best in your deliberations at<br />
this conference. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
