<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23009</transcript-id>
    <title>Visit to Indonesia</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/09/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I will visit Jakarta, Indonesia, from 30 September to 1 October at the invitation of President Yudhoyono.</p>
<p>I will be accompanied by the Minister for Foreign Affairs, the Hon Julie Bishop MP, and the Minister for Trade and Investment, the Hon Andrew Robb AO MP, as well as a delegation of senior Australian business people.</p>
<p>The Government is determined to ensure that Australia’s foreign policy is focussed on our region, including the relationship with Indonesia and other countries in our neighbourhood.</p>
<p>The relationship with Indonesia is one of our most important.  Australia and Indonesia are close friends and neighbours who share democratic values.  Our countries face common challenges, and we have a common interest in building a stable and prosperous region.</p>
<p>Our bilateral relationship with Indonesia is one of Australia’s most broad-based, spanning business, education, defence, security and people-to-people links.  Indonesia is an important commercial partner for Australia, with two-way trade valued at $14.6 billion and Australian investment in Indonesia valued at $6.8 billion in 2012.  But the Government believes there is much scope to deepen and broaden relations.</p>
<p>Our countries cooperate closely regionally and globally, including as fellow members of APEC, which Indonesia is chairing this year, the East Asia Summit and the G20, which Australia will chair in 2014.</p>
<p>I will join President Yudhoyono for a one-on-one meeting, before being joined by members of our respective Cabinets to discuss priority bilateral interests, including ways to strengthen economic relations between Australia and Indonesia.</p>
<p>I have invited a 20 member business delegation to accompany me for the Jakarta visit. The business leaders represent key Australian export, trade and investment sectors.  The delegation sends a clear message that the Australian Government and Australian businesses are keen to tap the potential for stronger economic ties that exists between the two nations.</p>
<p>During the visit, I will address a breakfast meeting of business leaders from both countries and will lay a wreath at the Kalibata Heroes Cemetery.</p>
<p>It is my hope that this visit establishes a convention for all future incoming Prime Ministers to make Jakarta their first port of call overseas.  It would send a clear signal to the region that relations with our nearest neighbours are the most critical to Australia’s future.</p>
<p>27 September 2013</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
