<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8861</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE AUSTRALIAN MINING INDUSTRY COUNCIL ANNUAL DINNER</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/05/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008861.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 7. May. 93 14: 31 No. 004 P. 01/ 07<br />
' Asr zic 4"<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY T11 E PRI MN' ~ 1N ISTER, TitE [ ION P J KE~ ATING, Mip<br />
ADDRESS TO illlEAUSTRALIAN MINING INDUSTRY COUNCIL<br />
ANNULAL DINNErR<br />
6 N1AY' 19,9,<br />
1E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Thank you vciy mu1Lch, Campbel and congratulat Ions to Peter Barnett oil his election<br />
as President of AMIC over the next two years. Ladies and gentlemen, well thank you<br />
for having me along here tonight to sp~ eak to you.<br />
I have had a very long asSOCiation Awith ALM1C twenty years this year, in fact, and<br />
barring the last, I suppose six or seven years, qu) ite a close association as many of you<br />
probably know. For nearly a decade I was the Shadow Minister lbr minerals and<br />
energy and I emerged from the shadows in 1983, of course, to becomne Treasurer,<br />
leaving that particular interest not behind, but to one side for others to handle. But I<br />
have always had a great regard for the industry and a great respect for its capacity to<br />
earn for Au~ stralia and to play a role as Australia's, at least equal to any other, leading<br />
and competitive industry.<br />
Campbell's made tonight a number of challengs flor me. He has got me in running<br />
races on wet tracks and all sorts of things fie has given a big challenge to<br />
Governments in this country and I am -sure that we have all taken note, Richard Court,<br />
and Marshall Perron, 1 am1 sure have triken nlotes at the table as well. But there are<br />
challenges for all of uis and 1 think, certainly the Government looks forwvard to the<br />
challenge's which C'ampbell mentioned, but they are also challenges f1or the industry, I<br />
think, to acknowledge that much has changed and moved favourably for it and also the<br />
challenge to take advantage of the environment which is now here.<br />
SO Much has changed and the Governmient has done a great deal. The mrninn industry<br />
has been internationally competitive, buit the g1reat agent for change in the 80 s was no~ t<br />
the private sector of'AuIstralia, it was the public sector. That's the truth of it. It took<br />
Australia firomn basically an inidustrial backwater to a moudern country again, started to<br />
open it uip. That change has continued and muILch Of it. Of course, has been a benefit to<br />
the mining industry. ' Ihere wats a time when you used to talk to ining companies and<br />
. they Would say, look we are quite elflcient, we are at least, in terms of best practice, </p>
<p>7. May. 93 14: 31 No. 004 P. 02/ 07<br />
2<br />
up with other companies around the world, price is not bad, but profits are lousy. The<br />
profits are lousy for two reasons, because the exchange rate was wrong and because<br />
wages were too high. These were the things which were holding the industry back,<br />
and both of those very major variables were dealt with in the 1980s, and the cost of<br />
that adjustment was borne by the community at large to set the industry up to become<br />
an internationally competitive world player.<br />
When the Government dc-regulated the exchange rate in the early 1980s the<br />
adjustment burden of that change had to be borne by the community and wage earners<br />
in particular, because we knew the exchange rate was substantially over valued and<br />
when it finally fell to recover our compctitiveness that shill to inflation, in inflation,<br />
which was about 5 per cent had to be cut from wages and the burden of that fell on<br />
wage and salary earners, and the political burden of that fell on the Government. Not<br />
just the Government but the trade unions, and of course given the fact that we couldn't<br />
have accommodated such a change as easily as perhaps we did without fiscal policy<br />
and without tax cuts So in the 1980s we produced these fast fiscal surpluses, while at<br />
the same time paying $ 5 and $ 6 billion tax cuts to take the inflationary surge from<br />
wages to see that the ieal exchange rate was competitive to see that the mining<br />
industry could keep its head luapn d earn profits from its own efficiency.<br />
Now, one can't just put in one's pocket changes like these and say the track has been<br />
pretty soggy, I mean the track has been pretty good for a long time. We have had our<br />
soggy spots, but one of then wasn't in macro-economic policy where that huge<br />
change, and you can see it now, commodity prices have fallen in the last year of so, the<br />
exchange rate has gone down, it has equilibrated and I think if you look at the<br />
adjustment in commodity prices via the exchange rate it is about 1 per cent over the<br />
year. In other words, you have got a mechanism now that is working for you which is<br />
maintaining your competitiveness and you are doing it in a wage environment where<br />
the wage share in the economy today, the average of the 1960s and the profit share is<br />
all ready at this stage of the business cycle at the average of the 1960s, and where we<br />
have seen a substantial shift in profitability, indeed, profitability, net profits in the<br />
December quarter were 75 per cent above levels of a year ago. So profits are<br />
recovering, inflation is low, we have broken the back of Australian inflation The great<br />
threat to the mineral industries competitiveness, the greatest threat, a desperate out of<br />
line infation rate has been brought into line at substantial cost to the community and of<br />
course that means working people in general<br />
Not only that, but the one thing, the one claim that the mining industry used to make in<br />
the years when I had close associations with it was that Governments take the monkey<br />
of tariffs, off the mining industry's back. Now, of course, that never happened until a<br />
Labor Government came along From 1988 through to 1991, and then the adoption of<br />
phasings from 1991 through to 1996.97 will see the tarilf wall in Australia<br />
substantially reduced to an average manufacturing tariff of 5 per cent by 1996-97 and<br />
commensurately lower tariff rates for the plan areas of the economy like motor<br />
vehicles, textile clothing and footwear So, in terms of setting the industries agenda,<br />
seeking to have in ollice a Government which first gave it a competitive exchange rate<br />
mechanism broke the back of inflation, carried the huge adjustment costs of<br />
competitiveness like a ball and chain around its neck, and then smashed the tariff wall </p>
<p>TEL: I 7. May. 93 14: 31 No. 004 P. 03/ 07<br />
3<br />
down, they are the things that the mining industry in the ' 70s used to dream about, and<br />
they were all done.<br />
Now, Campbell was waxing lyrical here about whether political expediency will return,<br />
well let me tell you this, Campbell, there was nothing politically expedient sitting with<br />
18 per cent interest-rates three months from an election, I can tell you. There is<br />
nothing politically expedient about bringing down tariffs in a recession. But I am quite<br />
sure you are referring to things like Coronation Hill. Coronation Hill became a totem<br />
issue for the mining industry, where in fact the things that mattered, I think, beyond<br />
Coronation Hill, that is, the things that mattered in terms of the big macro picture of<br />
competitiveness, whether it be by way of exchange rate wages or inflation, other<br />
competitiveness issues generally. These are the things which have had greater weight<br />
and I think people in the industry know that. Coronation Hill had its problems, as a<br />
mine, frankly you could tit it in your eye, the size of it, in terms of the size of<br />
Australia's mining produce it never really mattered, it was some of the principles in<br />
there about how it was treated and whether in fact it was a place that should have been<br />
reserved because of Aboriginal interests. I don't really think that expediency is an issue<br />
in Australian public policy today. I think this Government has been prepared to take<br />
issues on which othci Governments haven't. and not only take them on but continue to<br />
go through them.<br />
One of the other things that Campbell put to us, will our tax regime be adapted to be a<br />
truly world competitive one? Well we have just introduced legislation this week to<br />
reduce the company tax rate from 39 per cent to 33 per cent. When I became<br />
Treasurer in 1983 the company tax rate was 46 per cent and there was a 60 per cent<br />
marginal tax rate on distributed income So, there was 78 cents of tax paid in every<br />
dollar of company income. That today is 33 per cent or if you distribute 47 per cent.<br />
So, 78 to 47 if you distribute, but for private companies as well as public companies<br />
they are no longer forced to distribute they can retain earning in a business, so a<br />
business could retain 67 cents of every dollar of company income after tax today and<br />
before a distribution where that was 22 cents years ago. Now that is a very large<br />
change, and coupled with that of course is dividend imputation. Dividend imputation<br />
is a huge tax break for domestic investors. What it essentially has done is make the<br />
company tax a withholding tax for domestic investors If anyone at an AMIC seminar<br />
in the ' 70s said, I will tell you what else we will do, not only will we give you a<br />
competitive exchange rate, but we will knock tariffs over, we will get real wages down<br />
and profits up, we will radically change our industrial relations scene, we will remove<br />
the double tax on dividends, well I amn quite e sue tlht everyone would have fainted at<br />
the tables. But lthioe things have been done and I think dividend imputation is a great<br />
reform and it has been a great thin tfor the companies.<br />
I just tonight picked up just some graphs of the capitalisation of some of the major<br />
companies in the period, in 1983-84 BHP was capitalised at $ 3 billion, today it is<br />
capitalised at $ 23 billion. So someone is doing right somewhere and I don't think it<br />
was all the BHP Board's doing. CRA was capitalised at $ 2.7 billion, today it is nearly<br />
$ 8 billion. Western Mining, all those lefties down there, they were capitalised at $ 1.1<br />
billion and they are at $ 5 billion, peaked at $ 7 billion in ' 87, but held most of it and<br />
have sort of travelled in the area of $ 4 to $ 5 billion since. Now part of that is the<br />
. enhanced profitability of industry, the enhanced competitiveness of the industry which </p>
<p>cr . Y H -Ll T in; 9 a x n o v v r v<br />
4<br />
has come of course through investment and good management, but it has also come<br />
through macro-economic policy, it has largely come through macro-economic policy,<br />
and that dividend imputation and that more attractive share price, attractive<br />
profitability for shareholders took our stock market index from about 1200 after the<br />
stock market crash back to about 1500 and it sort of oscillated in that 1500 now to<br />
1700. So, par of that market capitalisation is dividend imputation which is another<br />
leading tax change. We have got a 10 per cent investment allowance there for projects<br />
over $ 50 million, halfofthe projects in the $ 130 billion of registered projects are<br />
actually mining projccts. There is a 10 per cent investment allowance for projects over<br />
million, there is another 10 per cent investment allowance for those projects, that's<br />
both under $ 50 million and over $ 50 million, but for any over $ 50 million it is 20 per<br />
cent and we have got now a very competitive schedule of depreciation, I think it is<br />
competitive as anybody we trade with. Which sees, for instance, forty year assets<br />
written off in 15 years, 20 year assets written off in 7, 5 year assets written off in 3<br />
years. So rapid acceleration, a 33 per cent company rate, full dividend imputation, an<br />
investment allowance of 20 per cent, I don't know what else we have to do for you,<br />
Campbell, in terms of a tax regime which is truly world competitive. This is, in OECD<br />
terms, outrageously comlprtitive. In Asia-Pacific terms very competitive, I think we<br />
are one ofthe very few countries that has a dividend imputation regime.<br />
Now, as well as that, you quite correctly pointed out that the Government needs to<br />
keep the progress up, in terms of micro-economic reform, and I agree with you, I think<br />
that is one of our challenges, it is one of the challenges we all face, it is certainly one<br />
we face and I am quite sure that Richard, and Marshall Perron, who are with us tonight<br />
would agree it has won the States faith as well. But much has been done and we are<br />
seeing for instance in our waterfront reform program productivity in our ports have<br />
been boosted by 127 per cent in recent years. Telecoms productivity has increased by<br />
98 per cent over the last five years, reforms to electricity generation and transmission<br />
have seen productivity increased by 41 per cent over seven years, and more is<br />
happening, we are trying to put together an East Coast electricity grid so that<br />
industries can get the benefit of that coal seam down the East Coast of Australia. We<br />
have set up a competitive modelling in telecommunications with Optus and now a third<br />
cellular mobile carrier. We are continuing of course with water front reform and we<br />
have now got OECD crew manning levels, or actually better than OECD crew<br />
manning levels, on our ships. So, that change is continuing and in the course of this<br />
Parliament we expect to do more about that as well, and of course the largest perhaps<br />
of those changes in the micro-economy is in labour market reform, which you correctly<br />
identified, and in that we are now conducting a comprehensive consultation on a<br />
reform package to consolidaec our gains there That is, to spirit along enterprise<br />
bargaining so that we can see productivity, the production of productivity and the<br />
sharing of productivity between prolils and wages, where we can see that<br />
accomplished as an enterprise where it couldn't be accomplished from the decision of<br />
the central wage bench. The central wage bench will be there for the weaker areas of<br />
the labour market to be setting appropriate minimums, but in the other areas of the<br />
economy, which is most of them, we hope to see a structure for enterprise bargaining<br />
go through. That will mean that employees and owners of businesses will be able to sit<br />
down and do something interesting and clever to make the business better, and tonight<br />
at the table, Campbell, was telling me of his own e\ perience at Renison Tin Mine in<br />
Tasmania where the same thing has happened, that very thing has happened between </p>
<p>*'^^^ ilyepy~ Ii. t<br />
his management and his employees to see a large shift in productivity. This is<br />
occurring acuoss the country but there is not enough of it and we want to speed the<br />
process up. But it not though. people are saying I noticed my colleague, the Leader of<br />
the Opposition, chiding me yesterday, saying, well you are following us on that. Well I<br />
haven't followed John on many things, and I am not following him on labour market<br />
reform because what the Coalition had in mind was basically a single wage contract,<br />
individual wage contracts, what we have got in mind is the collective bargaining of the<br />
employees of an enterprise with the owners and operators of an enterprise. It is a<br />
wholly different thing. You could never get that cohesion and sense of common goals,<br />
shared goals, and common commitmenis while each person is basically sliced off<br />
individually into a common law contract. It is not the same, and it won't produce the<br />
same results. But it is important to get the problems ofa business identified and to<br />
have them repaired and the make the business more efficient and that can really only be<br />
done on the spot. It can't be done by someone at a hearing in one ofthe central<br />
business districts of the country, and that's why I think the progress now, the<br />
opportunity now, now we have got inflation low to be able to lock that low inflation in<br />
and with high levels of productivity. not only keep it down but also enhance profits on<br />
the way through. So, I think, this is one of the areas where we do want to keep that<br />
progress up<br />
We have been trying to facilitate major projects, and we have got a unit in my<br />
Department which has been involved in expediting projects worth over $ 4 billion in its<br />
first year of operation, and we have been quite successful there I think, and that<br />
coupled with the investment allowance has brought a number of projects forward and I<br />
think we are going to make progress on them, but more needs to be done to<br />
consolidate them.<br />
The other important issue. I think, is the question of Mabo and where it goes. I have<br />
said to Campbell and his colleagues who saw me last week with APEA and the<br />
National Farmers Federation that I think Mabo is a distinct opportunity for Australia,<br />
and one that should be pursued ambitiously. That is something now which the<br />
Government is seeking to do. That is, to talk to all the stakeholders, the organisations<br />
I just mentioned, as well as the Aboriginal community itself, and to see that we can<br />
reach a regime which will be one which is such that we can put to the States at the<br />
Council of Australian Governments in June or July some proposals where we can<br />
advance the whole establishment of a regime to do justice to the High Courts decision.<br />
There is a bit of a view in the industry that this is something the Government has<br />
brought on and it is something the Government is quite happy to deal with, to wrestle<br />
with, it's a decision ol' the I ligh Court of Austiralia of a case which was heard over<br />
many years and the High Court has turned over the concept of Terra Nullius and has<br />
said there is a native title right in common law, it hasn't said what the title is, how it<br />
should be established, who has the title, or how it may be used or exploited, and we<br />
are as a Government saying, well look, we will try and establish a regime here, but we<br />
have to talk to all the stakeholders, and they are principally the States, the industries,<br />
pastoral, mining, etc and of course the Aboriginal community. This won't be easy, but<br />
it will require a mature set of judgements to reach a package which I think is possible<br />
and which will do more in the event for a true reconciliation between the Aboriginal<br />
and non-Aboriginal communnities in this country than perhaps any other thing has the<br />
immediate opportunity of so loing So, we have already started in those negotiations<br />
49 </p>
<p>TEL 7. May. 93 14: 31 No. 004 P. 06/ 07<br />
6<br />
and we are continuing, but we are of course in entirely new territory with this, there is<br />
no structure at all, it has got to be all put into place, and the High Court has only but<br />
given us clues as to what, that is, beyond saying that there is a title, a native title, given<br />
us only clues about what they think the character of the title should be.<br />
So, it is not going to be an easy matter, and it is not going to be a matter where<br />
sloganeering has any place, or incantations, because that could be a pretty expensive<br />
exercise, I think, for all of us. But again, in a consultative, cooperative environment<br />
between ourselves and the States, yourselves, the pastoral industries and the<br />
Aboriginal community itself, I think we can do a great deal.<br />
Let me just perhaps close and sum up on a few of these points. In this year we expect<br />
mineral commodity exports to increase by 9 per cent to a record high of almost $ 31<br />
billion. Total new capital in\ vestment we expect in this year to reach a record of about<br />
billion and over the next five years the AB ARE forecasts the total value of mineral<br />
commodity exports will increase by 22 per cent in real terms and the production of<br />
metallic minerals will increase by 25 per cent. So, commodity exports this year up by<br />
$ 9 to $ 31 billion and total capital investment reaching records of about $ 5 billion.<br />
That is not too bad, a pretty good result, and the key thing is, I think, to keep all those<br />
elements and competitiveness in there so that we can maintain this kind of an effort.<br />
This is what the Government is committed to and of course as you know this week I<br />
had the pleasure of seeing Prime Minister Miya7awa in Australia and that raises the<br />
other prospect of Australia finding itself in an even better position in this part of the<br />
work, bearing in mind 72 per cent of our exports go to the Asia-Pacific area, that we<br />
have a unique opportunity I think with the region, with APEC, this body which we are<br />
now using in a fledging way to develop an open liberalised set of markets in this area,<br />
the interest in APEC by the United States, Japan, China, Canada and most of the<br />
countries of South East Asia, it gives us an opportunity to perhaps find a place for<br />
Australia, an enhanced place, again, not just for manufactured exports or services, but<br />
also for our traditional commodities such as mining. Campbell made the point that we<br />
are also shipping products to the old world and I think that says a great deal about the<br />
entrcpreneursllip and competitiveness of the industry that that is so, but we have<br />
always tended to be most competitive in the area of our immediate region and the<br />
possibilities of us finlding belter markets in this part of the world, are I think, have the<br />
potential to be quiet substantially enhlanced if we kick tile foreign policy and trade balls<br />
in the right way. So, I think that is another challenge we could perhaps add to<br />
Campbell's challenges as well.<br />
All in all could I say that I have always has a great respect for the mining industry. In<br />
the 1970s when I first had contact with it, apart from some segments of our agriculture<br />
industries it was the only internationally competitive industry. It lead the way in<br />
developing new markets in new areas of financing. it had the entrepreneurship the rest<br />
of the country needed In those days we had people like John Stone giving us the<br />
dismal lesson that you couldn't have a malnuflacturing sector sitting beside an efficient<br />
primary export secito that was part of the Treasury orthodoxy of the day. Well I don't<br />
think it was the Treasury I think it was his, but it was his anyway. Of course as you<br />
know in the end commodities couldn't cut the mustard. When John Howard finally<br />
toddled offinto Opposition in 1983 we were running a current account deficit of 6 per<br />
cent of GDP, because e t terms of trade have shifted so dramatically on us that the </p>
<p>TL-7. May. 93 14: 31 No .004 P. 07/ 07<br />
' 7<br />
world wasn't paying us the prices for raw materials it used to pay us twenty years<br />
earlier, and we lefl it too late to adjust Australia Without a fair bit of pain. But we are<br />
now a long way LhroULgh that adjustment task and we can now have an efficient<br />
primary expoi-tirig sector sitting beside an etlicient manufacturing sector and effcient<br />
tertiary and serv'ice seetoirs So thlt dismnal legacy of'those views has now passed there<br />
is no more Gregory Iflisis tryinlg to rocket our exchiinge rate oil the back of the<br />
mineral industry while ninlcuighas been CutI to pieces. We have got all these<br />
things musch more nicely in balance Lcause thle country. thle Government, thle<br />
industries and the community have had the Courage to face the challenges and meet<br />
them. We are a long way down tile road. We have got a long way to go.<br />
But this Government is goin", to Use its mandute to advance it further and it will be<br />
doing it in those areas which do mnatter in the miicro-economy, in wages, in thle<br />
maintenance of a lo~ v inflation rate ard doin-all those sensible things to facilitate<br />
project developmnt. be it in the Iiining or in other sectors of Lhe economy.<br />
Could I again thanlk you l'ur haviniig ine a ) ln tonighit. I appreciate this contact with<br />
the industry, I thought it % vas a good opportuniity so closely following thle election to<br />
come along at Campbell's invitat ion. I am pleased to be here and say that we will be<br />
keeping thce dialog~ ue with the induIstry open, perhaps more fulsomnely in thle first<br />
instance on Mabo, which I think is a huge challenge for all of us and will test our<br />
ingenuity, I ami certain. Thank you very much for having mie, I ani very pleased to be<br />
here in the comipany of my colleagules, Richard Court and Marshall Perron.<br />
Thank you.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
