<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4786</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT IN RELATION TO ARTICLE IN THE BULLETIN</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004786.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 2* AUGUST 1978<br />
STATEMENT IN RELATION TO<br />
ARTICLE IN THE BULLETIN<br />
I have been reluctant to make this statement, for it is my<br />
wish to protect the confidentiality of discussions between<br />
Ministers. I believe this is absolutely essential to the<br />
working of good government. However, the gross distortions<br />
of fact contained in the Bulletin article, widely repeated<br />
since, demand that this statement be made, and the Minister<br />
for Finance, Mr Robinson, has agreed that I should make it.<br />
I categorically deny that I requested Mr Robinson to cast<br />
doubts on his evidence to the McGregor Royal Commission or<br />
to say that that evidence was not a perfect recollection or<br />
that it was based on uncertain, vague or hazy memory.<br />
The facts of this matter are as follows:<br />
on 7 and 8 August discussions took place between Ministers<br />
concerning the findings of the Royal Commission.,<br />
In the course of these discussions Mr Robinson stated that his<br />
then recollection was that I had been informed on 17 January<br />
of the fact of a telephone coversation between Senator Withers<br />
and the Chief Electoral Officer, but not of the contents of<br />
that conversation.<br />
I asked Mr Robinson, if he was sure of his recollection, to<br />
write me a note.<br />
Mr Robinson thereafter re-read the transcript of his evidence<br />
before the Royal Commission and concluded that in his opinion<br />
a note would not add anything to it.<br />
In these circumstances, when Mr Robinson informed me of this<br />
conclusion I agreed with him that this should be the end of<br />
the matter.<br />
Before re-reading the transcript, Mr Robinson did dictate a draft<br />
note. It was never signed or sent. I saw it for the first<br />
time today. To put this matter to rest, the draft is being<br />
made public and is attached to this statement. </p>
<p>NOTES AS DICTATED BY THE HON. ERIC ROBINSON MP,<br />
ON 8 AUGUST 1978, SYDNEY<br />
DRAFT<br />
My dear" Prime Minister,<br />
I refer to my evidence given to the Royal Commission<br />
regarding a conversation, held on the 17 January between<br />
yourself, Senator Withers and me. My recollection of<br />
that conversation, which took place in your office during<br />
the luncheon adjournment of Cabinet was that during a<br />
discussion lasting approximately 15 minutes, a number of<br />
matters were discussed.<br />
These included my concern about continuing press reports<br />
of allegations made against me regarding re-distribution<br />
by. Mr Cameron. The matter of Mr Cameron' s declaration of<br />
polls' speech and the question of unrest amongst Queensland<br />
Liberal Parliamentarians and suggestions of meetings held<br />
during the Christmas New Year break about alleged electoral<br />
malpractice in Queensland.<br />
During that conversation I recall Senator Withers, amongst<br />
a number of comments made about the general allegations,<br />
making reference to a telephone call that he had made tothe<br />
Chief Electoral Officer, Mr Pearson.<br />
I do not recall any specific detail of that conversation<br />
being offered. In fact I was not aware myself of the specific<br />
content of that telephone call until Mr Pearson gave evidence<br />
at the Royal Commission about Senator Withers' telephone call<br />
to him and the action that he, Mr Pearson, took because of it.-<br />
000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
