<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11084</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          INTERVIEW WITH LEIGH MCCLUSKY          AND TONY PILKINGTON          RADIO 5AA                                     </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/11/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Republic referendum, interest rates, Melbourne Cup</p>
<p>E&amp;OE.............</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister John Howard, a very good morning to you.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Good morning, how are you, Leigh?</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Very well. Prime Minister, could I ask you, the yes case is saying that</p>
<p>   on a day like - and it's opportune that we speak to you on Melbourne Cup</p>
<p>   Day - they're saying this is exactly the sort of day that would make or</p>
<p>   should make Australia focus on a future and that, they say, is a future</p>
<p>   that should be as a republic. What do you say?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I say that Australians are going to enjoy Melbourne Cup Day irrespective</p>
<p>   of the sort of system of government they have. I think people who try and</p>
<p>   associate days like Melbourne Cup Day with one or other side of a political</p>
<p>   argument are really missing the point. They're also misunderstanding their</p>
<p>   Australia. If I know Australians they'll go to the Melbourne Cup, they'll</p>
<p>   go to their parties, they'll participate in their office sweeps and they</p>
<p>   won't be asking their friends and their work mates how they're going to</p>
<p>   vote on Saturday. They'll be respecting the fact that we have different</p>
<p>   views on that. But, at the end of the day, we are all Australians together.</p>
<p>   So, can I just politely say to the yes campaigners, in voting national folk</p>
<p>   occasions and national festivals like the Melbourne Cup in aid of either</p>
<p>   side of the debate is silly.</p>
<p>  PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, you looked stunned on television last night when obviously</p>
<p>   somebody from overseas said that if you were to lose the campaign, if the</p>
<p>   yes vote were to get up on the weekend, would you resign, I mean, you genuinely</p>
<p>   looked surprised at the question and you took a while to answer it. If,</p>
<p>   indeed, the yes vote did get up, do you think that would weaken your position</p>
<p>   personally at all?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, the reason I took a moment to answer it was that there was a delay</p>
<p>   on the satellite. You must understand that. Well, I was surprised at the</p>
<p>   question. It was a silly question. The answer to your question, Tony, is</p>
<p>   no. Just remember the history of this. I, despite my support for the current</p>
<p>   system, consistent support, always indicated to the Australian people where</p>
<p>   I stood. Despite that I promised before I became Prime Minister that I would</p>
<p>   personally hold a convention and if clear support for a model emerged from</p>
<p>   that convention I'd put that model to the Australian people for a vote before</p>
<p>   the turn of the century. And that is exactly what I've done. I've delivered</p>
<p>   on that promise. But I have never disguised the fact that I, personally,</p>
<p>   am opposed to change. I have allowed members of the Parliamentary Liberal</p>
<p>   Party a free vote and I make no apology for that. I think it was the right</p>
<p>   thing to do and I think the debate has been conducted, in the main, with</p>
<p>   a great deal of civility. And so the answer to your question is, whatever</p>
<p>   verdict the Australian people deliver on Saturday, and I hope they vote</p>
<p>   for the present system and I'm urging them to do so, but whatever decision</p>
<p>   they take I will, of course, accept it. And it doesn't make any difference</p>
<p>   to my position within the Government at all.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, would it be fair to say that there is - and obviously there are</p>
<p>   some people who feel very passionately about this as an issue but there</p>
<p>   are others who I think are, a) confused and b) increasingly disappointed</p>
<p>   by the fact that the whole thing seems to have become terribly politicised,</p>
<p>   that we've got former politicians, good, bad and otherwise, from both sides</p>
<p>   now doing these terribly patriotic, hand-on-heart, this is what I think</p>
<p>   you should vote and why. Do you feel that the Australian public is almost</p>
<p>   saying, look, I don't want to know, I know we should want to know, but just</p>
<p>   back off, let us actually make up our own minds?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I guess there's an element of that but you get that in any election campaign.</p>
<p>   What I've personally tried to do is present a reasoned argument. I didn't</p>
<p>   get involved in the debate in any detail until last week and I delivered</p>
<p>   a reasoned argument.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Well, in principle, Mr Howard, what is your main objection, what is the</p>
<p>   one thing that says to you, we don't need to and we should not change?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Because the present system has worked brilliantly and it's given us great</p>
<p>   stability.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  What of the argument where they say, but hang on, we've got to move into</p>
<p>   the future, that, you know, we've got to cut the shackles?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, you're asking me what is my main reason and, I mean, I've given you</p>
<p>   my main reason. Now, I don't think that argument about moving into the future</p>
<p>   and cutting the shackles is sufficiently persuasive for us to take the risk</p>
<p>   in moving away from a system we know works. What interests me about this</p>
<p>   debate is that we've had a lot, we've had monumental attempts by the yes</p>
<p>   proponents to argue that their model is an improvement on the present system.</p>
<p>   I think deep down most people in this country, even those who intend to</p>
<p>   vote yes, acknowledge that the present system is very stable and predictable</p>
<p>   and has given us great security. And this is not a debate about who is the</p>
<p>   better Australian. There are passionate Australians on both sides of this</p>
<p>   debate. This is not a debate about the Australian identity. This is a debate</p>
<p>   about what is the better system. I mean, this idea, which is implicit in</p>
<p>   much of the yes propaganda, that you're really not being a full-on Australian</p>
<p>   unless you vote yes, I mean, that is nonsense. And my main reason on this</p>
<p>   issue is a conservative reason. I believe in changing things that are clearly</p>
<p>   broken and clearly in need of change. And I've argued, as you know, to change</p>
<p>   our tax system, to change our industrial relations system. I've never been</p>
<p>   reluctant about arguing for change when I've thought it was good for Australia</p>
<p>   but I don't think this change is good for Australia and that's why I'm going</p>
<p>   to vote no. Now, that in a nutshell is why I'm against it.</p>
<p>  PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, at the end of the week and after the vote's taken on Saturday,</p>
<p>   when can you see this issue coming up again? Do you think it's going to</p>
<p>   be put to bed for the next four or five years and then is there any way</p>
<p>   we can say, okay, that's the end of the argument and the debate for a given</p>
<p>   period of time?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I don't think anybody can start putting periods of time on it. I think</p>
<p>   there will be a mood in the community no matter what the result not to revisit</p>
<p>   the issue for a while. Now, if there's a yes vote I don't think there's</p>
<p>   any prospect at all that there'll be a referendum, another referendum some</p>
<p>   time into the future on the question of a directly elected President. I</p>
<p>   think if there is a yes vote, well, the model that's being proposed on Saturday</p>
<p>   will be with us for a long, long, long time. I've said forever, well, I</p>
<p>   suppose you can never really define forever but it will certainly be with</p>
<p>   us for the foreseeable future. If there's a no vote, I don't think the issue's</p>
<p>   going to come back for a while but I can't sort of say forever and a day</p>
<p>   that it won't. I mean, nobody can do that. I think the mood of the community</p>
<p>   will be, whatever the outcome, that they won't want to revisit it for a</p>
<p>   while. But I can't guarantee that at some time in the future the issue wouldn't</p>
<p>   come back. I mean, nobody can. It will depend on a lot of things. And in</p>
<p>   a democracy why should you expect to? I mean, in a democracy people in governments</p>
<p>   have got a right to revisit issues if they choose and there's nothing wrong</p>
<p>   with that. I know people find, on occasions, find votes irksome and everything</p>
<p>   but, gee, isn't it better for us to be able to decide these things with</p>
<p>   everybody having an equal vote.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, talking about everybody having an equal vote, as you have already</p>
<p>   mentioned, there are members of your own party who feel passionately opposed</p>
<p>   to you when it comes to this issue of a republic. I see there is speculation</p>
<p>   today that somehow you and Peter Costello have closed ranks, you are about</p>
<p>   to freeze out Peter Reith. Well, is there a plan and secondly, given the</p>
<p>   fact that you have people who are working so closely for the Liberal Party</p>
<p>   who are at opposite ends of a scale, has your relationship perhaps with</p>
<p>   Peter Reith been damaged by his stance?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, no, it hasn't. And can I say in relation to that story I haven't made</p>
<p>   any deals with anybody. The leadership of the Government is determined by</p>
<p>   the members of the government parties, it's not determined by me or by any</p>
<p>   other individual. And I am the Prime Minister, I am the leader of the Liberal</p>
<p>   Party because my colleagues in the party chose me not because of any particular</p>
<p>   deal making capacity. I don't do deals.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Your relationship though with Peter Reith seems.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  My relationship with Peter Reith is, in fact, very good. I was on the phone</p>
<p>   to him barely 10 minutes ago discussing a range of matters. Can I just say</p>
<p>   this that strange though it is for some people in the media, I don't mean</p>
<p>   you and Tony, but others to understand - the Liberal Party has a tradition</p>
<p>   on issues like this of allowing a free vote. We are a party of conscience,</p>
<p>   we are a broad church, we do have conservatives and small 'l' Liberals on</p>
<p>   a variety of issues. And the way in which we work together effectively as</p>
<p>   a Government is that on occasions like this we recognise the reality and</p>
<p>   that is people of good conscience are going to have different views. And</p>
<p>   we have allowed a free vote and I am proud that my party has done that.</p>
<p>   Once the referendum is over, well, there won't be a free vote any more on</p>
<p>   this issue, there will be a Government position on how it's going to be</p>
<p>   handled. But in formulating that Government position around the Cabinet</p>
<p>   table and in the party room each individual member will be able to contribute</p>
<p>   his or her point of view. So if you are taking publicly a point of view</p>
<p>   now on this issue you'll be able to continue to take that issue privately</p>
<p>   but there will be developed a Government position and naturally all members</p>
<p>   of the Cabinet will adhere to that Government position. But a suggestion</p>
<p>   of, you know, people are being frozen, nobody is being frozen out or frozen</p>
<p>   in. Once the referendum is over we revert to normal and our aim from Sunday</p>
<p>   will be to resume what we have always done and that is serving the Australian</p>
<p>   people as your elected Government.</p>
<p>  PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, has the Government done any polling on the issue?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  The Government?</p>
<p>  PILKINGTON:</p>
<p>  Yes.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  The Government has not done any partisan polling on the issue now. I understand</p>
<p>   that the advertising agency in relation to the, some advertisements does</p>
<p>   what they ever do but, I mean, the Government as such has not done any partisan</p>
<p>   polling, no.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  What's your feeling on how it's going to go?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I don't know. I really.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  [Inaudible]</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No, I don't. I am wary of polls. I read the poll this morning and I also</p>
<p>   read the polls before the Victorian election.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Well, they didn't help really.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No, they didn't. Well, one of them right at the end was, to be fair, was</p>
<p>   accurate. And I think one of them, to be fair, was accurate at four weeks'</p>
<p>   out. Look, this is a very unusual issue, Leigh. People who I've talked to</p>
<p>   surprise me. I find some people I expect to be yes voters and they are not,</p>
<p>   and I find others I expect to be no voters and they are yes voters. So I</p>
<p>   just hope in the end that the undecided people who are those who are going</p>
<p>   to decide this will consider the simple proposition that if you are in doubt</p>
<p>   you should vote no. If you worry that you might be changing to something</p>
<p>   that is unknown and less safe you shouldn't take that risk. And whatever</p>
<p>   people say about symbolism, and I have not thought the arguments in favour</p>
<p>   of a symbolic change have been very strong, the reality is that this has</p>
<p>   been one of fewer than 10 nations on earth that has been continuously democratic</p>
<p>   for the whole of the 20th Century. We have through an accident</p>
<p>   and a divisive history, we have a marvellous arrangement where you have</p>
<p>   a neutral person as governor-general and as an effective head of state.</p>
<p>   And the reason that person is neutral is because that person applies the</p>
<p>   conventions and the practices of the Crown which have been developed by</p>
<p>   the hundreds and hundreds of years. And that history and the conventions</p>
<p>   arising from that history have given our system of Government a special</p>
<p>   and unique territory and I would be very loathe to risk that. And I feel</p>
<p>   quite strongly that there's a very effective, affirmative taste for hanging</p>
<p>   onto the present system. But it's not nostalgia, it's not imperial sentimentality,</p>
<p>   it is a commonsense Australian belief that we have a good system.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, two quick questions before I let you go. As you know, the</p>
<p>   Reserve Bank Board Meeting this morning, speculation about an increase of</p>
<p>   .25 per cent. Would that surprise you?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I don't talk in any way about the future path of interest rates. I</p>
<p>   am sorry, I have kept to that rule religiously since becoming Prime Minister.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Not talking about it but as a comment, would you reconsider.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No, no. I think I had better take your betting advice, it's very well put.</p>
<p>   Not talking about it but just a comment.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  All right. And in terms of today, who have you got your money on?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I have to confess that I am going for Sky Heights. I got a bit worried when</p>
<p>   I saw that it had moved into favouritism, it always makes me very nervous.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  You don't want those short price favourites.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No, no, that's right. A tough horse is always there at the finish, he's</p>
<p>   going for the double. But it does make me a little bit nervous as he has</p>
<p>   moved in to favouritism. I mean, Rogan Josh is pretty close but I picked</p>
<p>   Sky Heights a few days ago.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  So you are not a man to change your mind though are you?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, if there's a good reason put to me. If I think it's better for Australia</p>
<p>   I'll change my mind.</p>
<p>  MCCLUSKY:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, it's been a pleasure as always, thank you for your time.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Thank you.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
