<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8860</transcript-id>
    <title>RECOGNITION OF ERITREAN INDEPENDENCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/05/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008860.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
T4EL.: May. 93 10: 49 No. 010 P. 01/ 01<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
RECOGNITION OF ERITREAN INDEPENDENCE<br />
I am pleased to announce that the Australian Government has decided to<br />
extend formal recognition to Eriirea following the overwhelming vote In favour of<br />
Independence by the Eritrean people In the referendum held on<br />
23-25 April 1993.<br />
The referendum was the final stage of the peace process agreed by the<br />
Provisional Governments of Eritrea and Ethiopia In 1991.<br />
Senator Kerry Sibraa, the President of the Senate, led the Australian group to<br />
observe the recent referendum. He has confirmed the view of all the<br />
International observers that the vote was free and fair and decisively in favour<br />
of Independence.<br />
The Eritrean independence struggle has attracted the sympathy and support of<br />
many Australians and has had the strong support of the Australian Parliament.<br />
Prominent Australians, such as the late Professor Hollows and author<br />
Thomas Keneally, have also taken a personal Interest In the problems of<br />
Eritrea. in 1990, Professor Hollows Initiated a blindness prevention program to reduce<br />
the Incidence of surgically curable eye disease In Eritrea. As a contribution to<br />
this effort, the Australian Government provided funding for an intra-occular lens<br />
factory to be assembled In Wollongong and shipped to Eritrea.<br />
Australia has also provided other assistance to Eritrea under the aid program.<br />
In 1992-93 the Government will provide $ 4.3 million in emergency relief,<br />
training and development assistance through Australian non -governmental<br />
organIsatlons, and from this year Australia will also provide a number of<br />
scholarships for Enitreans under the John Crawford Scholarship Scheme.<br />
I congratulate the people of Eritrea on attaining their Independence and wish<br />
them well for the future.<br />
CANBERRA 4 May 1993 TEL </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
