<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4165</transcript-id>
    <title>FOREIGN INVESTMENT GUIDELINES - STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER AND MINISTER FOR NATIONAL RESOURCES, RT HON JD ANTHONY MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004165.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
HEDIA RELEASE FORE! IG INVESTMENT GUIDELINES<br />
Statement by the Acti--g rime Minister and Minister for National<br />
. Resources, Rt. Hon. J. D. Anthony, M. P.<br />
Recent co-ments y Sir Charles Court and Mr Bjelke-Petersen on<br />
the Government's foreign investment guidelines suggest that they have<br />
less than a complete understanding of the -maeter.<br />
The guideliens are not stifling develo zen-of mining in Australia.<br />
The Government has introduced the guidelines to give Australians<br />
encouragement and opportunity to participate in Australia's development.<br />
The guidelines, and the way they are being administered, will<br />
achieve that objective but will not hinder or delay new projects if<br />
those projects are in Australia's interests.<br />
The national Government has a clear duty to see that Australians<br />
do have this opportunity, and to ensure that the overall national<br />
interest is protected.<br />
There can be only one interpretation of the Premiers' comments<br />
that they want an " open s] ather" policy.<br />
To believe that the community would accept such a policy on foreign<br />
ownership of Australia's resources is quite unrealistic, and it is an<br />
approach which the present Government is not prepared to accept.<br />
Yet we have to make sure that our resources are utilised for the<br />
benefit of the community.<br />
New mining and energy projects could play a vital part in Australia'<br />
recovery from its present economic difficulties.<br />
The foreign investment guidelines, as made clear by Mr Lynch when<br />
he first announced them on April 1 this year, and as emphasised by<br />
3bth the Treasurer and myself since, are not rigid and inflexible.<br />
The Prime Minister also has underlined the flexibility of the<br />
guidelines in his statements in Japan.<br />
We want, as a general rule, to see at least. 50% Australian equity<br />
in new mining projects 75% in the case of uranium. ./ 2<br />
rr-</p>
<p>2<br />
But we have made it quite clear that if foreign companies<br />
genuinely try to secure 50% Australian involvement in projects other<br />
than uranium but are -nable to do so, then we will not see worhtwhile<br />
development held up.<br />
A lower level = f Australian equity will not necessarily prevent a<br />
project from proceeding.<br />
The equity requirement on uranium, subje:: to the Government's<br />
atti-tude to Dortfolio investment as outlines b-y the Treasurer and<br />
. yself on 28, is firm.<br />
As I have indicated recently, there could be an extreme case whereno<br />
Australian equity at all could be obtained for a new mining project.<br />
y--he project should and would proceed.<br />
Of course, we would seek, as appropriate, s-isactory arrangement<br />
in such cases for Australian equity to be increase: to at least<br />
at a later stage.<br />
There has never been any suggestion that the ZGvernment will appl.<br />
the guidelines in a doctrinaire way.<br />
It is significant that I have been able to quickly reach agreement<br />
on equity arrangements for three major proposed coal developments in<br />
Queensland. In the case of two of them--Norwich Park and Nebo the companie<br />
have agreed to ensure there is 55% Australian inzerest, and in the<br />
third case Hail Creek the agreed level of Australian interest is<br />
The first of these projects likely to be in a position to go ahe-.<br />
is the Norwick Park proposal of the Utah Development Company.<br />
I am sure everyone welcomes Utah's willingness to accept arrangem'<br />
S. ich will mean 55% Australian equity in this pr-tect compared with o.<br />
= abut 11% in their existing developments.<br />
Surely the Premiers do not dispute the adva.-: e to Australia of<br />
S. k-ii of arrangement.<br />
While the equity arrange-en-s have been f: r-some time, tl.<br />
Company is still having difficulty reaching a-re en-' with the<br />
Queensland Government for the project To prccei. / 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
As far as he C-oc. nwealth is concerned, there is no obstacle<br />
the project was cle re several months ago.<br />
I hope the ^ 1ueensland Government . ill soon be able to reach<br />
agreement with the company.<br />
It is a maiter for great regret that The long delays caused by<br />
the Drevious Government's unreasonable and _ realistic attitudes<br />
have called into question thesemajor new projects because development<br />
costs have increased so significantly.<br />
CABERiRA June 1976 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
