<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3518</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL WOMEN&#039;S YEAR - 4 DECEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003518.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER_] PflJEc ST. AT: MkENL NO. 394<br />
4 !) uctombor 1974<br />
INTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S YEAR<br />
The Prime Minister today tabled in the House of<br />
Representatives a statement prepared for the information<br />
of the Parliament on International Women's Year 1975.<br />
This statement indicates the priorities and<br />
considerations proposed for determining the direction of<br />
the Government's program and is intended to stimulate<br />
discussion both within the Parliament and in the community.<br />
The Prime Minister said that costed submissions<br />
so far received total around $ 3.5 million. Some of the<br />
submissions were in respect of projects which fall within<br />
the responsibility of existing government departments or<br />
other institutions. In such cases the National Advisory<br />
Committee would not act as an alternative funding agency<br />
but as a catalyst for positive response from these departments<br />
and agencies. The Prime Minister added that on the advice<br />
of the Committee the Government would be making direct grants<br />
in respect of other projects; these grants would be made<br />
progressively throughout the Year and he expected to be able<br />
to announce the first set of grants within the next week.<br />
These grants would reflect the areas of greatest need as<br />
determined by the Committee. However submissions not initially<br />
funded would be kept under continuous review during the Year.<br />
Since December 1972 this Government more than any<br />
previous national government in the history of Australia<br />
has made a conscious and genuine attempt to overcome the<br />
decades of neglect from which women have suffered, to give<br />
to women and to men the ability to freely choose that way<br />
of life best suited to them individually.<br />
International Women's Year 1975 provides an<br />
opportunity to stand back and assess what has already been<br />
achieved as well as enabling the initiation of further<br />
programs based on our deep commitment to basic human rights.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
