<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18177</transcript-id>
    <title>$18 million boost for future of manufacturing in Ballarat</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/10/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard and Member for Ballarat Catherine King today announced work will begin this month on a new centre that will provide cutting edge manufacturing training for students at the University of Ballarat.</p>
<p>The Gillard Labor Government has provided more than $18 million through the Education Investment Fund to help build the new Manufacturing Technology Training Centre in Ballarat.</p>
<p>The centre will provide specialist training spaces to help provide new skills in areas such as robotics, mechatronics and manufacturing computer animation.</p>
<p>The centre will also house labs to teach computer assisted design.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister visited the University of Ballarat today to inspect the site and meet apprentices who will benefit from the new centre when it is built.</p>
<p>The new facility will enhance the University of Ballarat's capacity to meet the training needs of the diverse and rapidly evolving manufacturing sector in western Victoria.</p>
<p>The announcement comes a day after the Gillard Government's Future Jobs Forum, which looked at further ways to position our economy for the years ahead.</p>
<p>The forum, hosted by the Prime Minister, also canvassed innovative ideas to spread the benefits of strong growth to all corners of our patchwork economy.</p>
<p>Manufacturing is the third largest category of employment in the Central Highlands of Victoria and the major driver of regional growth and development.</p>
<p>The new centre is a good example of how targeted investment will help secure a vibrant manufacturing industry and provide the jobs of the future for the Ballarat region.</p>
<p>The investment will help with the diversification of the region's manufacturing base by creating smarter, more innovative manufacturing technologies.</p>
<p>A key activity of the centre will be the training of apprentices for modern-day manufacturing. </p>
<p>Already, the University trains 200 apprentices in manufacturing and when the centre is fully operational, this number is anticipated to increase to 300.</p>
<p>These additional apprentices will be available for employment in Ballarat and throughout the region.</p>
<p>The Manufacturing Technology Training Centre will be a vital resource in maintaining, growing and leading manufacturing technology in western Victoria.</p>
<p>The University has worked closely with local industry representatives in the planning of the centre to better understand and respond to local business needs.</p>
<p>Construction of the centre is expected to commence this month and 145 jobs for local tradespeople and professionals will be created in the construction phase.</p>
<p>Since 2007, the Government has committed more than $6.2 billion in capital funding for infrastructure to support landmark investments in higher education, research and vocational education and training, as well as campus renewal, modernisation projects and improved student amenities.</p>
<p>So far 57 projects funded through the Education Investment Fund have been completed and a further 121 projects are underway.</p>
<p>This historic investment has allowed our universities and TAFEs to build state-of-the-art learning and teaching facilities equipped for the challenges of the 21st Century.</p>
<p>More information on the funding of higher education infrastructure programs can be found at:</p>
<p><a href="http://www.deewr.gov.au/HigherEducation/Programs/Funding/Pages/Home.aspx">http://www.deewr.gov.au/HigherEducation/Programs/Funding/Pages/Home.aspx</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
