<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3997</transcript-id>
    <title>LIBERAL PARTY RALLY, CROYDON PARK, MELBOURNE, SPEECH NOTES FOR HON MALCOLM FRASER MP - RALLY SPEECH - 30 NOVEMBER 1975 - AUSTRALIA NEEDS AN IMMEDIATE CHANGE OF DIRECTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/11/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003997.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 2 P. M. RELEASE<br />
LIBERAL PARTY RALLY. CROYDON PARK, MELBOURNE<br />
S! EECH NOTES FOR HON. MALCOLM FRASER M. P.<br />
RALLY SPEECH30 NOVEMBER 1975<br />
AUSTRALIA NEEDS Al IMf MEDIATE CHANGE OF DIRECTIOI<br />
AN END TO THREE YEARS OF FOOLISH<br />
INCOMPETENT GOVERNMENT<br />
ON DECEMBER 13. YOU CAN SAY WHETHER YOU WANT YOUR<br />
WAY OF LIFE TO CONTINUE OR TO DISAPPEAR FOREVER<br />
ITS TIME TO RESTORE SOUND AND RESPONSIBLE MANAGEMENT<br />
TO AUSTRALIA<br />
ITS. TIME TO BEGIN ECONOMIC RECOVERY. TO ACHIEVE<br />
PROSPERITY FOR ALL AUSTRALIANS.<br />
MR. WHITLAM IN HIS LAST NON-POLICY SPEECH TREATED<br />
AUSTRALIANS WITH CONTEMPT SUNDAY NOVEMBER 30. 19_ 75 </p>
<p>a a<br />
2-<br />
IGNORED THE PROBLEMfIS WORRYING ORDINARY<br />
AUSTRALIANS PRICES, HOUSING, STRIKES<br />
JOBS<br />
ALL MRWHITLAM SAID WAS THAT HE'D BEEN WRONGED<br />
" VOTE FOR HIM BECAUSE YOU FEEL SORRY FOR HIM".<br />
-HE IS THE FIRST PARTY LEADER IN AUSTRALIAN HISTORY.-<br />
TO MAKE. SELF PITY INTO A POLITICAL PROGRA[ MiME.<br />
,, HE DOESN'T CARE ABOUT ORDINARY PEOPLE<br />
IF HE DID, HE WOULD HAVE TRIED TO RUN<br />
* AUSTRALIA BETTER.<br />
l/ HEN OTHER AUSTRALIANS CAN'T GET A JOB HE FOUND<br />
A JOB FOR HIS SON QUICKLY ENOUGH<br />
AND BOB HAWKE IS HOLDING DOWN A SWAG OF<br />
JOBS </p>
<p>-3-<br />
WHO DO THESE PEOPLE REALLY CARE FOR?<br />
THE PEOPLE THEY HAVE BETRAYED<br />
OR THEMSELVES?<br />
HE AND HIS MINISTERS HAVE BEEN TOO BUSY GETTING<br />
THEMSELVES INTO SCANDALS AND THEN TRYING TO<br />
COVER UP TO WORRY ABOUT THE STATE OF THE NATION<br />
WHE'N WE ASKED MR. WHITLAM SOME TOUGH QUESTIONS<br />
ABOUT HIS ROLE. IN THE LOANS AFFAIR, HE SAID HE<br />
WOULDN'T ANSWER BECAUSE HE DIDN'T TRUST US.<br />
HE DOESN'T TRUST ANYONE ANYMORE'<br />
DOESN'T TRUST ALL THOSE MINISTERS HE SACKED<br />
TELLS US HE DOESN'T TRUST THE GOVERNOR GENERAL </p>
<p>-4-<br />
NOW THAT THE QUEEN HAS WRITTEN THAT THE GOVERNOR<br />
GENERAL HAD EVERY RIGHT TO ACT AS HE DID<br />
HE PROBABLY DOESN'T EVEN TRUST THE QUEENI<br />
HE CERTAINLY DOESN'T TRUST THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE<br />
WHENt. PARLIAMENT SAID HE HAD TO FACE THE PEOPLE.<br />
HE TRIED TO RULE WITHOUT PARLIAMENT..<br />
HE TRIED TO TAKE AUSTRALIA THE FIRST<br />
STEP TOWARDS DICTATORSHIP.<br />
HE IS'THE FIRST PRIME MINISTER WE HAVE EVER HAD-WHO<br />
SAID THAT AN ELECTION WAS UNDEMOCRATIC,<br />
NOW HE IS POSING AS THE GREAT DEMOCRAT,<br />
WHO ARE THE PEOPLE WHO. ARE APPEARING ON THE SAME<br />
PLATFORMS AS THE LABOR PARTY THESE DAYS? I. I. 77<br />
I </p>
<p>REMEMBER THE DAYS WHEN THEY TRIED TO HIDE<br />
THE UNITY TICKETS?<br />
-NOW LABOR PARTY LEADERS ARE APPEALING<br />
WITH COMMUNIST UNION LEADERS ON PUBLIC<br />
PLATFORMS PARADING AS DEFENDERS OF DEMOCRACY<br />
HE WANTS TO GET RID OF THE SENATE BECAUSE THE...<br />
SENATE PROTECTS AUSTRALIA AGAINST SOME OF THE:<br />
MOST DANGEROUS LEGISLATION EVER INTRODUCED. I<br />
-THIS LEGISLATION WOULD HAVE ESTABLISHED:<br />
* A GIANT GOVERNMENT PURCHASING MONOPOLY WHICH<br />
COULD FORCE LABOR'S POLICIES. ON ANY BUSINESS<br />
WHICH DEALS WITH THE GOVERNMENT,<br />
A POWERFUL NATIONAL POLICE FORCE WHICH COULD<br />
POSE A SERIOUS THREAT TO CIVIL LIBERTIES, r </p>
<p>-6-<br />
THESE BILLS, AND OTHERS LIKE THEf, ARE A THREAT<br />
TO AUSTRALIAN DElOCRACY.<br />
AND THE MAN WHO SUPPORTS THOSE BILLS SAYS HE IS<br />
DEFENDING DEMOCRACY.<br />
HE SAYS HE WILL STAND ON HIS RECORD.<br />
HE IS STANDING ON HIS RECORD BECAUSE HE HOPES<br />
AUSTRALIANS WON'T SEE IT WITH HIM STANDING ON IT.<br />
WHICH RECORD IS HE STANDING ON:-<br />
RECORD UNEMPLOYiENTI HIGHEST UNEHPLOYiENT S. IICE<br />
DEPRESSION.<br />
: RECORD INTEREST RATES-HIGHEST SINCE FEDERATION,<br />
RECORD STRIKES WORST EVER -1$ 256 MILLION IN<br />
WAGES LOST THROUGH STRIKES.<br />
RECORD INFLATION WORST PRICE RISES IN OUR HISTORY. 2:<br />
i </p>
<p>6 A<br />
NEW ZEALAND HAS JUST THROWN OUT ITS LABOR GOVERNMENT<br />
WITH A LANDSLIDE TO THE NATIONAL PARTY,<br />
THERE HAS BEEN A SWING OF. MORE THAN EIGHT PER CENT<br />
AGAINST NEW ZEALAND LABOR, AT ONE STAGE LAST NIGHT<br />
THERE WAS. EVEN-A POSSIBILITY THAT THE NEW. ZEALAND<br />
LABOR LEADER MR. ROLLINGS WOULD LOSE HIS OWN<br />
ELECTORATE OF WALLACE..<br />
THE LATEST COUNTINGS THIS MORNING INDICATES THAT THE<br />
SNATIONAL PARTY1WILL HAVE 53 OF THE 87. SEATS INITHE<br />
NEW ZEALAND PARLIAMENT, THAT IS A MASSIVE CHANGE<br />
FROM A LABOR GOVERNMENT WITH A MAJORITY OF 23 SEATS<br />
BEFORE YESTERDAY'S ELECTION,<br />
BOTH LEADERS. IN NEW ZEALAND HAVE AGREED THAT THE. STATE<br />
OF THE ECONOMY INCLUDING AN INFLATION RATE OF<br />
APPROXIMATELY 15 PER CENT WAS UPPERMOST IN THE VOTERS<br />
MINDS. I~. i<br />
il..<br />
i-I </p>
<p>-6BI<br />
HAVE SENT A MESSAGE OF CONGRATULATION TO. THE<br />
NATIONAL PARTY LEADER MR. MULDOON TODAY,<br />
THE NEW ZEALAND RESULT REVEALS OVERWHELMING<br />
REJECTION OF A SOCIALIST PARTY WHICH SHOW ED' IT<br />
COULD NOT MANAGE A MODERN ECONOMY.<br />
HOWEVER IT SHOULD BE REMEMBERED THAT THE ECONOMIC<br />
SITUATION RESULTING FROM THE MISMANAGEMENT OF A.<br />
SOCIALIST GOVERNMENT LAS _ NOQTAS.. BAD IN. NEW<br />
ZEALAND AS IT IS IN AUSTRALIA UNDER A SOCIALIST<br />
PARTY.<br />
NOT ONLY HAVE THE SOCIALISTS MADE A BIGGER ECONOMIC.<br />
MESS IN AUSTRALIA BUT NEW ZEALAND HAS NOT SUFFERED<br />
THE DISHONESTY DECEIT AND DECEPTION IN GOVERNMENT.<br />
THAT-WE HAVE EXPERIENCED IN AUSTRALIA<br />
THE LESSON IS THAT IN BOTH COUNTRIES LABOR PARTIES...<br />
HAVE PROVED TO BE. INCOMPETENT,<br />
LI~ L </p>
<p>-6CNEW<br />
ZEALAND SWUNG TO LABOR IN 1972 AND MASSIVELY<br />
AGAINST LABOR IN 1975. I AM LOOKING FORWARD TO THE<br />
SAME RESULT IN AUSTRALIA ON DECEMBER 13. </p>
<p>-7-<br />
MR HAYDEN NOW HAS THE GALL TO SAY WE HAVE<br />
STOLEN HIS BUDGET.<br />
IF HE SAYS THAT AGAIN I WILL HAVE TO TAKE<br />
OUT A WRIT AGAINST HIM<br />
FOR DEFAMATION OF CHARACTER<br />
ILNALL-HIS CAMPAIGNS OF DISTORTIONS AND ATTEMPTS<br />
TO DECEIVE THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE, MR WHITiAM<br />
HAS MADE ONE ACCURATE STATEMENT OF FACTS HE<br />
OT KW AYTHIG ARO TTHE ECOKIOMY, I.<br />
IWHAT A RECORD TO BE STANDING ON.<br />
ONE OF THE MOST DISGRACEFUL RECORDS IN OUR HISTORYI<br />
HOW MANY HERE WI-l BE VOTING FOR THISRECORD<br />
HOW MANY HERE WIM B VOTING FOR A RETURN TO<br />
PROSPERITY AND SECURITY?<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE WILL KNOW WHAT TO DO<br />
ABOUT THIS RECORD,<br />
RESPONSIBIITY USTRALIA NEEDSA 0VMFNTh1EITI OF ITCrREL i'l" i i<br />
i~ i..<br />
L </p>
<p>-8-<br />
A TRPAI TA NFFD A GOVFRMFNT THAT REALLY<br />
CARFS ABOUT PFOPIF<br />
AUSTRALIA NEEDS A GOVERNMENT THAT UNDERSTANDS<br />
HOW AUSTRALIA'S PRIVATE ENTERPRISE ECONOMY WORKS.<br />
WE CAN ATTACK RISING PRICES, WE. CAN START<br />
EXPANDING JOB OPPORTUNITIES AGAIN<br />
IF WE START NOW<br />
THE ENDLESS GOVERNMENT EXTRAVAGANCES AND<br />
WASTE OF THE LAST THREE YEARS WILL BE ENDED.<br />
. LABOR'S. EXTRAVAGANCES HAVE BEEN PAID FOR. BY THE HIGHEST<br />
TAXES IN OUR HISTORY<br />
LABOR DIDN'T HAVE THE COURAGE TO RAISE<br />
TAXES OPENLY<br />
IT USES INFLATION TO PUSH PEOPLE INTO.<br />
HIGHER AND HIGHER TAX BRACKETS<br />
SINCE LABOR CAME TO POWER AVERAGE PERSON<br />
NOW PAYING ANOTHER MONTHS WAGES. IN TAXES i. </p>
<p>9-<br />
WE WILL IMPLEMENT MAJOR REFORf1S OF PERSONAL INCOFIE<br />
TAX TO PUT AN END TO LABOR'S TAX RIP-OFF<br />
I<br />
i. I. BEGIING I rEX. T YEARS ' BUDGET WE WIL L FULLY.<br />
INDEX PERSONAL INCOME TAX FOR INFLAT-ION OVER<br />
3 YEARS. IF YOUR INCOME RISES JUST TO 1:<br />
KEEP PACE WITH RISING PRICES YOU<br />
WONT PAY A BIGGER PROPORTION OF YOUR<br />
INCOME IN TAXI<br />
WILL STOP GOVERNMENT TAI( ING [ ORE<br />
OF PEOPLE'S EARNINGS<br />
WILL MAKE GOVERNMENTS MORE HONEST<br />
IT ALS ANOUNCED A NUMBER OF OTHER TAX<br />
REFORMS WE WILL INTRODUCE L I. </p>
<p>WILL TAKE SPECIAL ACCOUNT OF SINGLE<br />
INCOME FAMILY<br />
FOR SINGLE PARENT FAMILIES,. OR FAMILIES WHERE<br />
ONE PARENT IS AN INVALID WE WILL<br />
INTRODUCE A SPECIAL CHILDCARE REBATE<br />
LABOR'S TAX CHANGES PENALISE PEOPLE WHO"<br />
W ANT TO DO. THINGS FOR THEMSELVES WE<br />
WILL GET RID OF THE INJUSTICES IN LABOR'S<br />
TAX SCALES<br />
WHERE ANl ESTATE OR PART ' OF IT PASSES BETWEEN<br />
A HUSBAND AND WIFE, ESTATE DUTY WILL ALSO<br />
BE CHANGED TO GIVE AN INCREASED TAX<br />
EXEMPTIOI. i<br />
OUR TAX REFORMS WILL EASE THE PRESSURE FOR EXCESSIVE<br />
WAGE AND SALARY INCREASES. </p>
<p>11<br />
THEY WILL HELP US GET OUT OF THE VICIOUS WAGE/ PRICE<br />
SPIRAL LABOR WAS NOT PREPARED. TO MAKE THESE REPORiS BECAUSE IT<br />
iNEEDED HIGHER AtD HIGHER-TAXES TO-FINAiNCE ITS SCHEMES.<br />
. LABOR'S TAX BURDEJ HAS FALLEN4 NOT JUST. OiJ INDIVIDUALS<br />
" I BUT ALSO ON BUSINESSES. N,<br />
SMALL BUSINESS Ii PARTICULAR HAS BEEN BADLY DAMAGED<br />
BY LABOR PROVIDES 2 OUT OF EVERY 5 JOBS<br />
IF WE'CAN HELP SMALL BUSINESS WE CAN OPEN UP A LOT OF<br />
JOB OPPORTUNITIES . ElWILL CHANGE.: THE TAX RULES WHICH OPERATE.<br />
UNFAIRLY. AGAINST SMALL BUSINESS AND PRIVATE<br />
COMPANIES<br />
Ir I i.<br />
i ' I c I </p>
<p>Ii 12<br />
RETENTION ALLOWANCE WILL BE INCREASED<br />
SHAREHOLDERS ' IN PRIVATE COMPANIES WILL'<br />
HAVE OPTION TO BE* TAXED. AS A* PARTNERSHIP<br />
TO MINIMIZE DOUBLE TAXATIOilOF PRIVATE<br />
COMPANY TAX.<br />
WE WILL EXAINE ' THE MASS OF LABOR IMIPOSED<br />
RULES. AN1D REGULATIGiS AND ABANDON THOSEW.: WH. ICH<br />
DAMAGE PROSPERITY.'<br />
WE WILL SUSPEND QUARTERLY TAX COLLECTIONS<br />
. OF COMPANY. TAX. FOR THE PERIOD OF PRESHNTTE<br />
CRISIS 40/ 10' INVESTMENT ALLOWANCE!<br />
RELAX CONDITI'ONS-ON CO NVERTIBLE SECURED'<br />
DEBENTURES I. : 1<br />
I </p>
<p>-13-<br />
SHOULD BF MA JOR NATIONAL OBJCTIVE TO ENCOULRAGE<br />
AL THOSF WHO ISH TO U0 SO, T Q* DflIEffEDLABOR<br />
ALIOST MANAGED . TO EXTINGUISH AUSTRALIAN<br />
DREAM OF HOME OWNERSHIP<br />
WIDENING DEPOSIT GAP<br />
HIGH REPAYMENTS<br />
SHORTAGE OF RENTAL ACCOMODATION<br />
WE WILL INSTITUTE HOME SAVINGS GRANT<br />
$ 1 FOR 3, OVER 2 YEARS<br />
MAXIMUM GRANT $ 2,000<br />
ROLE OF HOUSING LOANS INSURANCE CORPORATION WILL<br />
? BE EXPANDED TO ASSIST MIDDLE LOW INCOME<br />
EARNERS BRIDGE DEPOSIT GAP COOPERATION OF<br />
LENDING INSTITUTIONS WILL BE GAINED.' .1<br />
I </p>
<p>INITROUCTION OF FLEXIBLE MORTAGE<br />
REPAYMENTS IN EARLY YEARS<br />
IN EARLY YEARS REPAYMENTS WILL BE LOW<br />
f-tA4S44Ei-INCREASING AS HONEBUYERS<br />
INCOME INCREASES<br />
SEEX TO ENSURE THAT WOMEN SINGLE,<br />
SSEPARATEDI OR DIVORCED SHOULD HAVE<br />
SSAME ACCESS AS MENTO HOME FINANCE<br />
C ' I ESTABLISH PILOT SCHEME IN COOPERATION WITH<br />
STATE/ LOCAL GOVERNMENT TO PROVIDE PERSONAL'..,<br />
LOANS TO LOW TO MODERATE INCOME EARNERS<br />
TO ENABLE THEM TO IMPROVE THEIR HOUSING<br />
CONDITIONS. THIS WOULD IAINTAIN BOTH STOCK OF<br />
HOUSING AND ALLOl-. PEOPLE TO REMAIN IN<br />
NEIGHBOURHOOD WHERE THEIR FRIENDS LIVE.-<br />
q </p>
<p>PLICY flN HOUSING PART OF OUR GENFIRAL POLCY<br />
OF GETTING ErPHASIS BACK ON PEOPILE<br />
WE ARE APARTY THAT BELIEVES IN THE INDIVIDUALS<br />
RIGHT TO. CONTROL HIS/ HER OW( N LIFE EVERY INDIVIDUAL<br />
EVERY AUSTRALIAN OLD AND NEW, RICH AND<br />
POOR, COUNTRY DWELLER OR CITY RESIDENT<br />
ALHA'Y'E A RIGHT TO SELF-RESPECT' 1<br />
UR 1PHILOSOPNY ! OF FREEDM, OPPORTlIUI uIYAlI CE~ i<br />
,,_ ORfTHE INDIVIDUAL 1WlL GET AUSTRALIAM-O VJIQNINAGA1.<br />
ILE HOICE<br />
INCREASING. CONTROL OVER OUR LIVES BY<br />
K POLITICIANS AND CIVIL SERVANTS 0 ' I<br />
-i:<br />
i I </p>
<p>16<br />
MORE AND MORE POWER TO CANBERRA<br />
RISING UNEMPLOYMENT<br />
RISING PRICES<br />
GREATER FREEDOM FOR ASTRALIA S -IRICH. A~ D.<br />
POOR.-TO CONTROL THE I R OWN LIVES.....<br />
-ORE INFLUENCE TO LOCAL LEVELS<br />
GOVERNMENT CLOSE TO PEOPLE<br />
RESTORE NCENTIVES<br />
RETURN TG PRSERITY.-JOBS, PRICESTABILITY,<br />
OP. PORTUNITIES 3K1_ i: i<br />
DEMOCRACY OR SOCIALISM<br />
VOTE FOR FREEDOM ON DECEflBER .13<br />
e<br />
OR<br />
.1 I iii </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
