<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8527</transcript-id>
    <title>STATE BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP SERBIA AND MONENEGRO - IMPOSITION OF MANADTORY UNSANCTIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/06/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008527.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 53/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
SERBIA AND MONTENEGRO IMPOSITION OF MANDATORY UN<br />
SANCTIONS<br />
Australia welcomes the decision by the United Nations<br />
Security Council in Resolution 757 to impose a range of<br />
mandatory sanctions against Serbia and Montenegro. These<br />
sanctions include a trade embargo excluding food and<br />
humanitarian items but including oil, restrictions on the<br />
movement of financial assets, a ban on cultural, sporting<br />
and scientific cooperation, a ban on air links and a<br />
reduction in Belgrade's diplomatic representation.<br />
The UN has taken this decision in view of the failure of<br />
Serbia and Montenegro to abide by earlier Security<br />
Council demands to cease interference in the internal<br />
affairs of Bosnia-Herzegovina. The international<br />
community has been appalled at the senseless loss of life<br />
and suffering resulting from those actions.<br />
The Government is moving expeditiously to implement the<br />
UN decision. Ministers and departments are now working<br />
on the details of implementation, with decisions to go<br />
before the Executive Council tomorrow.<br />
The Yugoslav national airline, JAT, which flies out of<br />
Australia twice a week, will have its services suspended<br />
from this week. Australia has already downgraded its own<br />
diplomatic representation in Belgrade. Cuts to the<br />
Yugoslav diplomatic and consular presence in Australia<br />
will be introduced.<br />
Since the beginning of the break-up of the old Yugoslav<br />
federation last year, Australia has consistently called<br />
for all the disputing parties to exercise maximum<br />
restraint and work towards a negotiated settlement.<br />
Regrettably, the fighting has continued. The attacks on<br />
civilians in Sarajevo have led to the further tragic<br />
loss of innocent life. </p>
<p>The imposition of sanctions is intended to make Belgrade<br />
and its allies modify their behaviour. We hope this will<br />
open the way to a resolution of territorial and communal<br />
differences, thereby bringing to an end the suffering of<br />
all involved in the conflict, including the Serbian<br />
people themselves.<br />
The Government is aware of the anguish and uncertainty<br />
felt by all those in Australia who have relatives and<br />
friends in the areas affected by the fighting. The<br />
Government commends the restraint shown by local<br />
communities in Australia, and urges them to maintain<br />
their patience. I assure these communities that<br />
Australia will continue to work with other countries<br />
towards a lasting and just resolution of the Balkan<br />
conflict. CANBERRA 1 June 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
