<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2324</transcript-id>
    <title>SENATE CAMPAIGN 1970 - TV AND RADIO TALK NO 2 BY THE PRIME MINISTER MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/11/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002324.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
12 NOVEMBER, 1970<br />
SENA T E C A M P AI G N 1970<br />
TV AND RADIO TALK NO. 2 BY THE PRIME MIiISTER<br />
MR. LOHN GORTON<br />
( To be broadcast by ABC and commercial TV channels at 8. 30 p. m.<br />
local time on Thursday 12 November and by the ABC Radio Network<br />
at 7. 15 p. m. E. S. T. Friday 13 November.)<br />
EMM B A R G 0 8. 30 PM. THURSPAY </p>
<p>When I becamne Prime Minister a little less than three years ago, I spoke of<br />
my wish to help the old and the ill and the handicapped. Now it is undoubtedly true<br />
that a great deal remains to be done in this field, a very great deal. Bu* It it Is also<br />
true much has been done.<br />
We have done a number of things, and if you will bear with me ! or a moment,<br />
I will outline some of them.<br />
We have removed the fear of the cost of long illness in hospitals. Our Health<br />
Scheme has removed the fear of the cost of expensive operations, or expensive<br />
specialist attention.<br />
It is a scheme, moreover, which provides that the community will pay insurance<br />
for low-income families, and it is a scheme under which the contributor pays, in<br />
general, less, and receives, in general, more, than was offered under Labor's<br />
scheme. We have brought in the Tapered Means Test, under which pensioners who can<br />
earn, or who have saved, can receive some of the benefit of their self-help<br />
without losing their pension entirely.<br />
We have brought in a Home Care Programme for the care of aged persons, or<br />
others with special needs, in their own homes.<br />
We are providing $ 5 million a year to the States to build low rental housing<br />
for pensioners. We are providing capital for buildings and equipment for homes for<br />
handicapped children.<br />
We have raised pensions for TPI repatriation pensioners by $ 8 a week, or<br />
more than 25 per cent.<br />
And we have increased the base rate of penisions by $ 2.50 a week for a single<br />
pensioner and $ 4 a week for married pensioners, during a period when the Cost<br />
of Living Index shows a rise of $ 1 a week.<br />
In fact we have raised benefits, or taken entirely new initiatives in more than<br />
different areas of social welfare.<br />
As a result, social welfare now makes up the second greatest item in our<br />
Budget, and will cost this year 800 million, which is a 25 per cent increase on<br />
the Budget of two years ago.<br />
But we still must overcome the problem of long-term illness in nursing homes<br />
as distinct from hospitals. We still must redeem our promise to help low-income<br />
earners with young families. We need to initiate a scheme for pre-school care for<br />
the children of working mothers. And we must continue to improve the lot of the<br />
base rate pensioner, but without losing sight of the needs of other area-" of social<br />
welfare. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
We will do these things as soon as they can be done with financial responsibility.<br />
I have not changed the aim I had when I became Prime M. nister, and I believe<br />
that what we have done in a short time is evidence that we shall continue with the<br />
task. Australia must and will win the war on poverty. We shall not win it in one<br />
battle or in one year. It must be fought on many fronts. It will take time and it<br />
will take effort from all Australians, for after all, it is only from the production of<br />
Australians that Governments can divert resources to these ends. But my<br />
Government is determined we shall win it, and I believe I can claim that the record<br />
shows we have advanced.<br />
Indeed, in this as in other fields, I think that I can truly say to you what we<br />
promise we perform.<br />
Goodnight. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
