<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18707</transcript-id>
    <title>Supporting Indigenous families and women in the East Kimberley</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/07/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard today formally opened the new Wyndham Early Learning Activity Centre in Western Australia, funded through a $1.7 million grant from the Australian Government under the East Kimberley Development Package.</p>
<p>This purpose-built facility delivers a great new space and playground areas for the Wyndham Early Learning Activity Centre to deliver a range of highly regarded community programs, with a strong focus on supporting parents and early learning opportunities for children.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister was also pleased to announce $100,000 funding to help Indigenous women build leadership skills and improve their wellbeing. </p>
<p>The centre will use this funding to establish a community garden and teach Indigenous women about gardening and growing healthy food, in partnership with the Kimberley Training Institute.</p>
<p>The centre will also teach women about how to prepare healthy meals and educate their children about the benefits of healthy eating.</p>
<p>Other activities include a family day with arts and craft and a sewing group where women can learn how to make items for themselves and their homes.</p>
<p>As well as teaching new skills, these activities will also provide the women with an opportunity to meet new people and make friends.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister visited the centre today to see firsthand the work they have been doing to support Indigenous families in the East Kimberley.</p>
<p>Wyndham Early Learning Activity Centre is one of 10 organisations across Western Australia which will share in more than $800,000 in Gillard Government funding for Indigenous Women's Grants in Western Australia in 2012-13.</p>
<p>The Government's investment will help these organisations to deliver a wide range of training programs, information sessions and workshops, including in retail and business administration training, leadership workshops, computer training, health and nutrition and an anti-bullying program.</p>
<p>These programs and workshops will help up to 630 Indigenous women to develop skills in business, finance, leadership, and health and wellbeing. </p>
<p>Indigenous women will have the opportunity to further develop their skills and knowledge, giving them a sense of pride and purpose, and the ability to use these new skills and knowledge in the community and at home.</p>
<p>This funding forms part of the Government's long-term efforts to overcome decades of underinvestment, and continue to improve the lives of Indigenous Australians. </p>
<p>Organisations in Western Australia                                          Funding (up to)</p>
<p>Wyndham Early Learning Activity Centre Inc                                        $100,000</p>
<p>Paupiyala Tjarutja Aboriginal Corporation                                              $100,000</p>
<p>Pilbara Indigenous Women's Aboriginal Corporation                               $100,000</p>
<p>Marninwarnikura Fitzroy Women's Resource Centre (Aboriginal Corporation)                                                                                         $170,000</p>
<p>Geraldton Streetworks Aboriginal Corporation                                        $95,000</p>
<p>Yawaru Jarndu Aboriginal Corporation                                                    $80,000</p>
<p>Kiwirrikurra Council Aboriginal Corporation                                              $52,128</p>
<p>Beananging Kwuurt Institute                                                                  $34,100</p>
<p>Dumbartung Aboriginal Corporation                                                       $38,100</p>
<p>Langford Aboriginal Corporation                                                             $32,800 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
