<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7499</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF SATELLITE HOOKUP INTERVIEW WITH JOHN HORFGAN, PACRIM CONFERENCE, HONG KONG, 22 FEBRUARY 1989+</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/02/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007499.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF SATELLITE HOOKUP INTERVIEW WITH JOHN HORGAN,<br />
PACRIM CONFERENCE, HONG KONG, 22 FEBRUARY 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: I have just returned from a visit to the region. I<br />
visited Korea, Thailand then Pakistan and India. In each of<br />
those countries that I visited I witnessed the benefits of<br />
the reduction in tension that is being associated with the<br />
dialogue between the United States and the Soviet Union and<br />
also between the Soviet Union and China.<br />
we have a situation now where in Korea the new leadership of<br />
President Roh who may I say I think is an extremely<br />
distinguished and able leader is not only leading his<br />
country towards democracy now but is also opening up<br />
dialogue with the North with North Korea and with the<br />
socialist countries while of course retaining the firmest of<br />
alliance relationships with the West.<br />
Now that is extremely important because it means that we can<br />
look that region at the reduction of tension and with<br />
the reduction of tension comes the opportunity for greater<br />
trading opportunities. So I think the Korean peninsula is<br />
looking much better than at any stage in the period since<br />
the beginning of the 1950s. of course there's an extremely<br />
strong and growing economy.<br />
But Thailand is extraordinarily interesting. There we have<br />
a situation where it has emerged as one of the most rapidly<br />
growing economies in the region over 10 per cent last year<br />
similar expectations for the future a country which is<br />
now taking a very prominent role in the dialogues and<br />
discussion involving the resolution of the Kampuchean<br />
situation.<br />
Thailand is positioning itself not merely in those processes<br />
but in the firm belief, which I think is fairly solidly<br />
justified, that we will see a resolution of the Kampuchean<br />
problem before the end of this year. Thailand will be well<br />
positioned to participate in what it sees as the opening up<br />
of the new markets of Laos, Cambodia and Vietnam itself and<br />
certainly I think all enterprises around the region and all<br />
countries around the region that are looking to the future<br />
should be seeing Thailand as a very important centre of<br />
economic development itself and also well positioned to take<br />
advantage of the new opportunities in the region immediately<br />
adjacent to it. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM ( cont): Now of course I went from there to Pakistan and<br />
India and there we have again the optimism associated with<br />
the withdrawal of the Soviet troops from Afghanistan there<br />
is still going to be a bloody mess in Afghanistan one way or<br />
another but the superpower rivalry has essentially<br />
diminished and the opportunities I think are now better for<br />
a constructive relationship between Pakistan and India than<br />
they have been for a very long period.<br />
The personal relationship and chemistry between Prime<br />
Minister Bhutto in Pakistan and Rajiv Ghandi in India is<br />
very good and I believe that there is reason to hope that as<br />
they see themselves able to contemplate a more amicable<br />
relationship that we may in time see a reduction in defence<br />
outlays in both those countries, the greater emphasis<br />
therefore upon their own internal development, and that in<br />
turn of course has great importance for the region.<br />
So that is a summary of my assessment of the region. The<br />
region now ( is) not merely the most economically dynamic<br />
region in the world, which we're all aware of, but also a<br />
region which offers even greater hope for the future as we<br />
see these reductions in political tension which have so<br />
bedevilled parts of the region now for too long.<br />
It was within that framework John and ladies and gentlemen<br />
that I made the observations that I thought the time had<br />
come when we should in fact try and give greater substance<br />
to what has been over a period now a time where there have<br />
been calls for greater regional cooperation. I think the<br />
point ought to be made and understood that if you look at<br />
this region, trade within the region, between countries in<br />
the region, there's about twice what it is as their share of<br />
total world trade and that certainly for my country,<br />
Australia, is true that trade in 87/ 88 with the Western<br />
Pacific region constituted just under 50% 48.6% and if<br />
you're taking North America, 66.7% of all our trade was in<br />
that region.<br />
Now I have made the suggestion that the time has come when<br />
we ought to look at how we can have a sort of organisation<br />
which will make possible greater consultation, effective<br />
consultation, between the countries in the region and I<br />
suggested an OECD type model not necessarilly it would be<br />
exactly that but to distinguish it from a bloc.<br />
I mean I'm not looking at the idea of a trading bloc in the<br />
region but I think if we get a mechanism whereby we can<br />
understand more consistently what's happening in each of the<br />
economies in the region then we'll all be able to conduct<br />
our own policies better. We'll be better placed I think to<br />
bring influence to bear upon the rest of the world to ensure<br />
the maintenance of a free multilateral trading system and </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM ( cont): we'll also be better established it seems to me<br />
to see on the examination of our own economies and<br />
understanding the complementarities of our resources and<br />
capacities how we may best be able to improve our own<br />
situations and the situation and of the region as a whole.<br />
I got a good reaction to that suggestion and we will try and<br />
process the discussions now for the rest of this year to see<br />
whether there may be the possibility of a ministerial<br />
meeting later this year to then look at what possibility<br />
there is for the establishment of such an organisation.<br />
Now summing it all up John and ladies and gentlemen let me<br />
put it this way. There has been a lot of talk as we know<br />
over recent years about the 21st century being the Pacific<br />
century. I believe that that is sensible talk. The<br />
evidence of the present sustains that prediction for the<br />
future. But it's not going to be something which will just<br />
happen automatically or we won't maximise the opportunities<br />
of that Pacific century just by sitting back and allowing<br />
things to go ahead. I think we've got to understand the<br />
total inter-dependence we have, understand the great<br />
potential complementarities we have and work hard at<br />
assisting ourselves in a sense by assisting one another,<br />
intermeshing our economies more effectively than we do to<br />
this stage. If we do that we have the opportunity now in a<br />
world which at no point in the nuclear age has been better<br />
poised to talk optimistically about being a world and a<br />
region living at peace. So the politics are good, the<br />
economic potentials are enormous. I feel it's an exciting<br />
time to be a leader in this region and I'm certainly very,<br />
very proud of the fact that Australia more and more is<br />
seeing itself as part of this region.<br />
HORGAN: Mr Hawke, we have delegates here at PACRIM from 34<br />
countries in the region and they have given me in advance<br />
some questions to put to you. In May the world will witness<br />
the first Sino-Soviet summit in 30 years. What do you see<br />
of significance for the Pacific region flowing from the<br />
prospect of Russia and China opening this historic dialogue?<br />
PM: The first thing to say John is that we shouldn't be<br />
afraid of it. I think if you examine the past and analyse<br />
the present to try and read the future the right conclusion<br />
to which to come is this, that when that break occurred in<br />
1969/ 60 between the two communist giants, in one sense it<br />
was an irreversible decision. By that I mean that I don't<br />
think we in our lifetimes or in the foreseeable future are<br />
going to see a resumption of a situation where the Soviet<br />
Union and China will be allies, but they will be friends and<br />
they will be economic cooperators. That is good for the<br />
Soviet Union and China and importantly it's good for the<br />
region. If you look at the two speeches that were made by<br />
Mr Gorbachev in Vladisvostok in 1986 and last year in<br />
Krasnoyarsk, what Mr Gorbachev was saying then can really be<br />
divided into two parts. He was making a political ploy, if </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PM ( cont): you like, to try and talk about greater<br />
political cooperation. We haven't yet seen a great deal of<br />
evidence some, but not a great deal yet to flesh out the<br />
intentions of Vladivostok and of Krasnoyarsk. But,<br />
importantly, what Mr Gorbachev is flagging is the desire to<br />
orient Siberia in the Soviet far east into a greater<br />
economic relationship with our region. I think that is to<br />
be welcomed. We alreay have in China as you know the<br />
establishment of the Pacific economic zones there,<br />
significant economic progress in China. They are baulking<br />
at this stage at taking the reform process further. The<br />
implementation of price reform is a serious political<br />
problem but I think the basic thrust of change in China is<br />
irreversible. Now, if we have a situation where the two<br />
giants are in fact going to strengthen their own economic<br />
performance, which is what we want to see, and do it in a<br />
way which wants to see greater cooperation with our<br />
countries in the region, that's good, because we have in the<br />
region the technology, the expertise, the capital to be of<br />
assistance to their plans for development. So I welcome the<br />
summit, I have taken the view consistently, I think probably<br />
I've been at the forefront of world leaders going back in<br />
regard to the changes in China in recognising their<br />
importance and asserting their irreversibility. I therefore<br />
welcome the fact that the rapprochement, the essentially<br />
economic rapprochement between China and the Soviet is going<br />
to mean, I think, a lessening of political tensions and the<br />
overwhelming evidence of that is the decision they've<br />
obviously made to secure resolution of the Kampuchean<br />
conflict. So I think, summing it up, the summit will<br />
confirm not merely a reduction in tension between them but<br />
it will provide a cement for a lessening of tensions in the<br />
region, including the Korean peninsula as one part,<br />
Kampuchea as another, but it will also create the<br />
environment, I think, for great economic opportunities of<br />
development both within and between the two countries and<br />
for us in this region. So in total I welcome the summit and<br />
I think we all should.<br />
HORGAN: Thank you very much for that comment on the<br />
Russia/ China summit. Another question, and you have touched<br />
on this a little bit in your address, maybe you could<br />
expand. Last month you called for the formation of an Asian<br />
based trade group loosely modelled on the OECD. Can you<br />
tell us why you advocate such steps and what they could lead<br />
to for the region's traders, businesses and nations?<br />
PM: Yes, I to some extent touched on that in my comments.<br />
Just let me flesh it out a bit more. As I say, it's not the<br />
first sort of observation of this type that's been made<br />
although I think I've probably concretised it a little bit<br />
more. The important point to re-emphasise John and ladies<br />
and gentlemen is this, and it's very important that people<br />
understand it. I am not arguing for the creation of a<br />
trading bloc. There is no person and certainly no nation<br />
more than myself and my country committed to not merely the </p>
<p>PM ( cont): but the development of a strong free<br />
multilateral trading system. So what I see as one of the<br />
results of the formation of some sort of consultative<br />
mechanism along the OECD model is not merely the internal<br />
benefits that will derive from that because the time for<br />
insular economic programming and policy making is past. No<br />
country in our region if it's sensible and properly attuned<br />
to the realities of this world can think that it can just<br />
make its own economic policy without knowledge of and<br />
understanding of what's happening in the region. So the<br />
basic thing that I'm about in what I've been putting is the<br />
creation of an organisation which will enable us to get the<br />
greatest benefit from knowledge and understanding of what<br />
one another is doing. That's why I've sort of used the OECD<br />
type model. But I also believe that if we can come together<br />
in this way we can say to North America and we can to say to<br />
Europe, look, we are the fastest growing dynamic region in<br />
the world, we're not a threat to you, we want to have a<br />
world trading system within which we can all benefit and I<br />
think that's one external benefit of the formation of this<br />
grouping that I'm talking about. At the same time within<br />
the region we can look at what are the possibilites of the<br />
lowering of barriers within the region that do exist and I<br />
think that's very important. As I've said John and ladies<br />
and gentlemen in my opening remarks, there are a lot of<br />
complementarities between the economies of our region and it<br />
just seems to me that the formation of some sort of<br />
organisation of the type that I'm talking about would enable<br />
us in a concentrated continuous analytical way to maximise<br />
the opportunites of those complementarities. In other words<br />
we'd all be better off if we created, I think, the mechanism<br />
for understanding what we're all doing. We'll make better<br />
policies in each country if we understand what the others<br />
are doing and will maximise the opportunities for growth in<br />
the region as a whole.<br />
HORGAN: We have the satellite now for another two minutes,<br />
this is probably a tough question to end on, but your<br />
Government is turning Australia towards an open market to<br />
face global competition. Just briefly, how are you doing<br />
this? PM: Firstly, I'm trying to change the attitude of<br />
Australia, that is to make them understand that this nation<br />
of sixteen and a half million people in a world of five<br />
billion has got to construct itself and have the attitudes<br />
that relate to that world. It will never be able to be<br />
island fortress Australia. We will condemn ourselves and<br />
our future generations if we have that attitude. So what<br />
are we doing? I have with my colleagues created a movement<br />
towards a more outward looking Australian economy. we have<br />
floated the Australian dollar, we've deregulated the<br />
financial system, we have very very signifcantly liberalised<br />
the foreign investment guidelines and we have run a fiscal<br />
policy which has very signficantly reduced the call of the<br />
public sector on the savings of our country so that we can </p>
<p>-6-<br />
PM ( cont): release resources to the private sector. Just<br />
last May we had a 30% reduction in tariffs and the<br />
attitudinal change in Australia may be judged by the fact<br />
that Australians accepted, almost welcomed that as compared<br />
to back in the 1970s when there was a 25% reduction and it<br />
was the end of the world. So we are in those macroeconomic<br />
senses doing those things which are creating a more outward<br />
looking economy, we're reforming a microeconomy, we're<br />
making the infrastructure more competitive, better able to<br />
service the Australian economy. In this way we are going to<br />
make Australia outward looking, competitive and make it in<br />
my words more enmeshed in the region.<br />
HORGAN: Thank you Mr Hawke. May I express to you in<br />
conclusion on behalf of all the delegates here from 34<br />
countries how pleased we are and our sincere gratitude for<br />
you being part of our symposium and making such a<br />
significant contribution.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
