<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2275</transcript-id>
    <title>SWEDISH GIFT TO MARK B-CENTENARY YEAR</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002275.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SWEDISH GIFT TO MARK BI-CENTENARY YEAR<br />
Presentation by His Excellency, Mr Per Anger,<br />
the Swedish Ambassador, at Parliament House,<br />
Canberra, A. C. T. 21 AUGUST 1970<br />
~ pech~ y hePrime Minister. Mr john Gorton<br />
Your Excellency, Parliamentary Colleagues, Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
Tis with pleasure that I accept, on behalf of the<br />
Australian Gove:: -nment, this gift from Sweden, and I would ask<br />
you, Sir, to convey . xur appreciation and thanks to your Government<br />
and people. We are delighted that a nation which had associations<br />
with our beginninigs 200 years ago should be honouring our Bi-Centenary<br />
in this way. Today's ceremony is well timed. It is 200 years<br />
ago tomorrow 22 August 1770 that Captain Cook landed on<br />
Possession Island and made claim to what was later called New<br />
South Wales. The engravings on this crystal plinth remind us<br />
of the botanical and zoological discoveries of that great Swedish<br />
botanist, Daniel Solander, who was with Cook on his historical<br />
voyage of discovery along Australia's Eastern coastline.<br />
Even at that time, of course, Sweden was already<br />
a highly civilised country and had laid the foundations for that<br />
craftsmanship for which it is renowned,<br />
Most Members ind Senators are familiar with the<br />
Orrefors vase which was presented to this Parliament by the<br />
Swedish Chamber of Commerce to commemorate the opening of<br />
Parliament Hou!: 2 in 1927. This plinth makes a splendid companion<br />
piece. / 2<br />
tN r </p>
<p>-2-<br />
And it is a mark of our developing interest, Sir,<br />
that in a week or two an Australian Trade Fair will open in<br />
Stockholm, you: x capital city. I hope this Fair will help to<br />
stimulate Sweden's interest in Australia, just as this ceremony<br />
today will help : o stimulate our interest in Sweden.<br />
We are glad that you are sharing our history<br />
with us in this way and with such an elegant gift. We thank you,<br />
Sir, and we tharnk your Government. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
