<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16113</transcript-id>
    <title>Press Release with Minister for Infrastructure and Queensland Minister for Main Roads $190M Road Project to Support Townsville&#039;s Growing Economy  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/09/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister Kevin Rudd today turned the sod on Townsville's $190 million Port Access Road, up to two years earlier than originally anticipated.</p>
<p>The Australian and Queensland governments are each contributing $95 million to link the Flinders and Bruce Highways to the Port of Townsville  -  a project which could help attract up to $10 billion worth of investment to the region.</p>
<p>“The early start on this vital project was only made possible by the decision to bring forward $20 million as part of our first Budget,” Mr Rudd said.</p>
<p>“We took this decision because we recognise the importance of 21st century transport infrastructure to the region's rapidly growing economy.”</p>
<p>The road is now scheduled to be completed by the end of 2011 or early 2012.</p>
<p>The Port of Townsville handles 10 million tonnes of freight a year  -  a figure that's expected to triple over the next 20 years  -  and supports up to 7,000 direct and indirect jobs.</p>
<p>Minister for Infrastructure Anthony Albanese said improving access would allow major industries, such as livestock, sugar and mining, to move goods to and from the Port more quickly and safely.</p>
<p>Currently, road trains are required to break down into single trailers on the outskirts of Townsville before accessing the port via semi-suburban roads.</p>
<p>The new road will allow them to drive to the port directly without having to remove their trailers, significantly increasing efficiency and reducing costs.</p>
<p>“Residents living near the Port of Townsville have long been calling for better road infrastructure,” Mr Albanese said.</p>
<p>“This project will greatly improve their quality of life by reducing the amount of noise, dust and vibrations caused by heavy vehicle traffic.”</p>
<p>The road will be delivered in two stages  -  the Stuart Bypass (Stage 1) and the Eastern Access Corridor (Stage 2). The contract for Stage 1 was recently awarded to the Abi Group/Seymour Whyte Joint Venture.</p>
<p>“The Port Access Road project demonstrates the Government's commitment to providing North Queensland with high-quality, well-planned roads,” Mr Rudd said.</p>
<p>“Improving the links between existing freight routes and major export points like the Port of Townsville is vital to Australia's future prosperity and national productivity.”</p>
<p>The Rudd Labor Government's plans for North Queensland also include:</p>
<p>     * $55 million to duplicate the 5 kilometre Douglas Arterial from University Drive to Upper Ross River Road to four lanes, with planning already underway;</p>
<p>     * $110 million to duplicate 7 kilometres of the Bruce Highway from Vantassel Street to Flinders Highway to four lanes;</p>
<p>     * $90 million to realign about 4 kilometres of highway on the northern side of the Cardwell Range, including a rail overpass, widening the road and adding overtaking lanes to boost safety;</p>
<p>     * $60 million to build up to 30 new overtaking lanes between Sarina and Cairns, a 60 per cent increase for this stretch of the Bruce Highway; and</p>
<p>     * Flood immunity works around Tully and between Townsville and Cairns.</p>
<p>This financial year the Rudd Labor Government will invest $3.2 billion in nation-building road and rail projects, including more than $500 million to make an early start on 45 election commitments such as the Townsville Port Access Road.</p>
<p>Queensland Minister for Main Roads, Warren Pitt, welcomed the Prime Minister and Minister Albanese to Townsville for the sod turning.</p>
<p>“This is a much needed piece of work for the community of Townsville and is long overdue,” Mr Pitt said.</p>
<p>“This joint project is another sign of the commitments of the Australian and State Governments to building vital infrastructure across Queensland.”</p>
<p>The state contribution is part of the Queensland Government's $16.2 billion commitment to roads over the next five years.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
