<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9313</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER , THE HON P J KEATING , MP LAUNCH OF &quot;AUSTRALIA REMEMBERS - 1945 - 1995&quot; AUSTRALIAN WAR MEMORIAL,CANBERRA, 14 AUGUST 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009313.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
LAUNCH OF " AUSTRALIA REMEMBERS 1945 1995"<br />
AUSTRALIAN WAR MEMORIAL, CANBERRA, 14 AUGUST 1994<br />
1 am very pleased to be here once more at the Australian War Memorial.<br />
I don't think I have been to any public building more than this one in the<br />
past two and a half years.<br />
This is understandable enough. World War 11 is fifty years away and we<br />
have had a series of commemorations not just here in Canberra, but in<br />
Darwin, Kokoda, the Coral Sea and Thailand. And in Great Britain and<br />
France just a couple of months ago.<br />
But the Memorial has been doing more than merely observing the<br />
passing of these anniversaries. Their Initiative has brought me here for<br />
the inauguration of the Vietnamn Memorial, the Entombment of the<br />
Unknown Soldier and the Children of the Holocaust exhibition.;<br />
I have been deeply honoured to participate in these occasions, and like<br />
everyone else, deeply moved.<br />
This Memorial is one of Australia's great public institutions: a<br />
storehouse of our collective memory and an icon of our faith.<br />
It does its job superbly and for that, obviously, a lot of credit has to go to<br />
the leadership and staff.<br />
Yet I'm sure those same people would agree that there Is something at<br />
work in the Australian community which makes their job easier.<br />
For the fact is the sentiment that emerged from Gallipoli, the Western<br />
Front and the Middle East in the First World War, does live on.<br />
TEL: Huq 4 9 : 21 No .003 F 1 -' 0j </p>
<p>TEL: 1 u. 94 9 : 2 INO.-003 P'. 02/ 04<br />
2<br />
The nation has no forgotten. In fact, I have grown quite certain that the<br />
tradition of Anzac ' will inspire and unite us through the next century no<br />
less than It has in this.<br />
The national response to the Entombment of the Unknown Soldier alone<br />
suggests that new generations will find in the legend of Anzac powerful<br />
symbols for their own faith. For an enduring Australian faith.<br />
Our celebrations of the fiftieth anniversary of VP Day and VE Day will<br />
express that faith and we hope will significantly strengthen it among<br />
young Australians.<br />
The generation we will commemorate and thank was a heroic one.<br />
They were born of the Australians who had endured World War I and<br />
the Great Depression, and who had been denied so many of life's<br />
opportunities by those tragic events. From where we stand we might be<br />
tempted to think it understandable if they had lost their belief in Australia<br />
and humane and democratic values.<br />
They didn't. They fought a war in defence of the country they loved, and<br />
they bequeathed to their children the opportunities which they had been<br />
denied. They were nation builders.<br />
Our freedom was their legacy: the robust democracy we enjoy, the<br />
security, the marvellous continent which is ours, the unequalled personal<br />
freedoms. But they left us more than that. They passed on a tradition and a faith<br />
for us to live by the Ideals of courage and sacrifice, the principles of<br />
mateshlp, and the conviction that wherever we come from on this vast<br />
continent, whatever divides us, we are Australians. By their example<br />
they taught us about the ties that bind us, and our common cause.<br />
And by the same example they compel us now, not just to remember<br />
them, but to pass on the lesson to our children.<br />
We hope that the commemorative events we plan for next year will do<br />
this. We also hope, of course, that at the end of these celebrations<br />
Australians will have a much more thorough appreciation of the War<br />
itself and the nature and extent of Australia's Involvement.<br />
Today I launch " Australia Remembers 1945-1 995": a program of<br />
activities that will culminate on August 15 next year, the fiftieth<br />
anniversary of the final peace. </p>
<p>TEL: 15. Au9.94 9: 21 No. 003 P. 03/ 04~<br />
3<br />
It is a substantial program which I hope will engage the attention and<br />
involvement of all Australians, which will honour our veterans and all<br />
those others who served In non-military roles, and which will deepen our<br />
understanding of events which so profoundly shaped the story of<br />
Australia. The focus of the program will be on Australia and Australians: the<br />
veterans of battles like those In the Middle East and Greece and Crete<br />
and In the air war over Europe: and those who fought in the Pacific War,<br />
the war to save Australia from Invasion.<br />
We will remember their service, and the grief of those they left behind.<br />
We will remember all those who lost their lives and those who lost the<br />
ones they loved.<br />
We will remember those who served at home in factories and on farms<br />
that generation of Australians who stoically endured the dislocation of<br />
their lives and the hardships which the War necessitated.<br />
We will remember the great achievements and the great spirit of the<br />
times. We will also remember those who came from war torn Europe to make<br />
their lives here, and who by doing so made all our lives so much richer.<br />
When I opened the Children of the Holocaust Exhibition here at the<br />
Memorial earlier this year, one of the survivors told me that she had<br />
made her home In Australia because it was as far away as possible<br />
from the terrible events she had witnessed.<br />
Over the next year we will celebrate the contribution such people have<br />
made to Australia. And we will re-affirm our faith in Australia as a place<br />
which has opened Its heart and mind to people seeking refuge from<br />
wars in many parts of the world.<br />
I hope " Australia Remembers" will add to our nation's understanding and<br />
confidence about our place In the world and our capacity to play a<br />
creative and humane part in It.<br />
I hope it will encourage us to recognise how important It Is for a nation to<br />
believe in great ideals to have them at the forefront of our ambitions.<br />
And I hope It will help us recognise how important it is to believe in<br />
ourselves. </p>
<p>I EL 4<br />
We want to involve every Australian community. We want all<br />
Australians to be touched by it.<br />
All who contributed to winning the war and making the peace and all<br />
who benefited from those triumphs.<br />
We want Australian women involved as never before in such a<br />
commemoration. The great sentiment which this Memorial embodies must never be<br />
allowed to drift away from them, or any group of Australians.<br />
If those ideals are to continue to provide inspiration and faith for<br />
Australians in the twenty first century the story must belong to every one<br />
of us as the peace which came in 1945 belonged to us.<br />
Thank you 15. Aug .94 9: 21 No. 003 h. U </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
