<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9161</transcript-id>
    <title>UNITED NATIONS CONVENTION ON CLIMATE CHANGE TAKES EFFECT</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009161.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
/ 0<br />
[ Embrpr. j iUntil. M<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
UNITED NATIONS CONVENTION ON CLIMATE CHANGE TAKES EFFECT<br />
I welcome the commencement today, Monday 21 March, of the United<br />
Nations Climate Change Convention.<br />
This marks the beginning of the next phase of concerted international action<br />
to mitigate the potentially adverse effects of climate change.<br />
Australia shares the genuine concern of other countries about this major<br />
issue, a concern reflected in the extraordinarily speedy negotiation of this<br />
convention. Parties to the convention will act within their own boundaries and share in<br />
actions extending beyond national borders.<br />
Scientific and economic research, limits on greenhouse gas emissions,<br />
education and information programs, and planning for any possible adverse<br />
effects of climate change will make up a large part of the world's concerted<br />
action.<br />
Australia's response recognises that action must take place within the<br />
framework of a sustainable Australian economy and a competitive trade<br />
position, as well as protecting the environment.<br />
Australia has been a leader in this field. We were among the first nations to<br />
develop and begin implementing an action plan, the National Greenhouse<br />
Response Strategy.<br />
The State and Territory Governments co-operated with the Commonwealth<br />
Government in developing a national Strategy that allows for change within<br />
the context of changing international conditions.<br />
It is significant that parties to the UN Convention agree to review their<br />
commitments in the light of the best scientific and economic information until<br />
the objective of the Convention is met. More is being done in Australia than<br />
the original Strategy demanded, and more will be done.<br />
Since the Strategy was adopted in 1992, the Commonwealth has developed<br />
an inventory of greenhouse gases, adopted a guaranteed excise-free period 21/ 94 </p>
<p>for alternative fuels, and initiated a study of the opportunities and strategies<br />
for a biomass-derived energy industry.<br />
At the recent Council of Australian Governments in Hobart, the States and<br />
Territories agreed to work for national markets in gas and electricity that will<br />
be more competitive. By increasing efficiency in generating energy, such<br />
markets will reduce the nation's demand for new generating capacity and<br />
thereby provide for more responsible use of finite resources of fossil fuels.<br />
This Government has always recognised the environmental and economic<br />
interests at stake in climate change.<br />
Australia will continue to be actively involved in future negotiations, and will<br />
continue to protect and advance those interests.<br />
CANBERRA March 1994 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
