<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10256</transcript-id>
    <title>MEET THE PRESS</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010256.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Fax from 6162733784<br />97 122MEDTA I RELEASE'P. 1/ 1<br />M) M EDIA RELEASE<br />* Cw A3I 1i1 i<br />IVJEETTHE<br />Network TEN presents an exclusive feature length interview with JOHN<br />HOWARD in this week's edition of MEET THE PRESS, Sunday March 2 at<br />8: 30am,<br />On the anniversary of his first year in Government. JOHN HOWARD will<br />discuss the achievements of his Party and their plans for the year ahead.<br />GUEST: JOHN HOWARD<br />PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA<br />PRESENTER: PRESS: PAUL BONGIORNO<br />JULIE FLYNN<br />RADIO 2UE<br />MALCOLM FARR<br />THE DAILY TELEGRAPH<br />A full transcript of the program will be placed in the press gallery boxes by<br />12 noon Sunday March 2, 1997.<br />Please feel free to extract whatever material is appropriate, acknowledging<br />MEET THE PRESS, NETWORK TEN.<br />For further information, please contact:<br />SIMON WEST<br />Executive Producer<br />( 02) 310 4934 Privete<br />( 018) 119 645 Mobile<br />A cn l T It A TT i1 O Tu O 0 15. B T I11 I' U . T O N SW<br />T i L O 2 1 44 10 F A X 4 10 3 P O B o x 1 0 O t ITr N S W 1 0 0 7<br />1 0 0 1<br />' DC, 1001<br />F3/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 1 V</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704 83/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 2<br />MEDIA MONITORS<br />MEDIA MONITORS ACT PTY LTD<br />* A 2' Xenfxlo A venu. K fisPtQ ACT 2oCO4. AuSt( r.. i TIen ; n. n 0 ia 233 Ficsimni ILL i 23') 5244<br />CHANNEL TEN ' MEET THE PRESS 02.3.97 08.30<br />Subject: i/ v John Howard<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD: Good morning and weklcoie. One year ago, Loday.<br />Australian v: oters ended the longest period of Labor<br />government since Federation. It was a stunning victory<br />for the John Howard-led Coalirion. capitalising on<br />Community perceptions that the Keating administration<br />was out of touch with the mainstream, and promising the<br />battlers a new government \ vouldn't ignore [ heir fears<br />and aspirations.<br />Toda, the Prime Minister meets the press. On the<br />panel. Julie Flynn, Radio 2UE and NM1alcolm Farr. the<br />Daily Teleei_ h.<br />Thanks for joining us. M\ lr Howard.<br />A pleasure.<br />I guess we better say ' Happy first birthday'.<br />Yes, it's great.<br />Agery Repami For pavate resewth and no to be d1Ucn* Uced. Lvy tiort made to ensure Aeuray<br />for am bcndwt of o" clicnts but no legal cW otr tcponsibliy Is taken fuw cnoix or a lons.</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />PAUL BONGIORTNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO: Now. I believe before we get down to serious business.<br />that you acually met the real Placido Domingo last<br />night. I did. What's nmore I presented him with a little gift on<br />behalf of the promoters. It was quite an experience.<br />I don't suppose y'ou want to say who your favourite<br />tenor is. do you?.'<br />It was a good show. I'll he diplomatic. It was a very<br />good show.<br />Well. I guess onto other maters..<br />From three tenors to the three journalists.<br />That's right. yes. Well. I noticed reading the number of<br />press interviews you've given in recent days for the first<br />anniversary. that there is no doubt that one of the<br />achievements of the first year was the passing of the<br />Telstra le-islation. and it's no secret that that legislation<br />passed because of Mal Colston defecting from Labor,<br />becoming an Independent.<br />Now. Labor is convinced that Colston is vitally<br />important to you. Just how grateful are you to him?<br />083/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 3</p>
<p>Fax from 616273370483/ 83/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 4<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />JULIE FLYNN:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />JULIE FLYNN: Well. naturally we're grateful for the support of Brian<br />Harradine and a1l Colston in getting the legislation<br />through. Of course we were. I mean. after all. we did<br />win a huge majority at the last election. Because of the<br />v'azaries of the electoral system. we don't have control<br />of the Senate. So -whyw ouldnt you be grateful if you<br />can Let Ehe support ot a couple of Independents. I<br />mean. let's not he sort of mince words about that.<br />Of course we were grateful. but that doesn't alter the<br />fact that in relation to the expense allowance dispute<br />that's goinzio n at the present time. the more it will be<br />allowed to run its course.<br />Well. how big. though. do you feel you're indebted to<br />him? 1 mean. do you owe him in a big way?<br />Well. not owe in the sense that the law is going to be<br />bent. Last time that le had these problems were under a<br />Labor goveniment...<br />That's right.<br />and an administrative solution was found. You've<br />promised to raise the standards that that government<br />applied. Would you be prepared to take it further than<br />they did?</p>
<p>Fax from 616273370483/ 83/ 97 14: 43 Pg:<br />JOI-LN HOWARD: Well, what we are going to do is to allow the law to run<br />its proper course in relation to him and in relation to<br />anybody else against whom allezations are made.<br />I mean. vtouIl be aware that some allegations have been<br />made about a couple of other members. One of them<br />won't be a member for much longer. He's resigning.<br />But they will be allowed to run their course those<br />investigations. That means. of course, that all of the<br />men involved are entitled to a presumption of innocence.<br />And let's understand that the Labor Party is on a<br />destruction mission as far as Colston is concerned.<br />They're out to get him. The fact that they may have<br />sort of had administrative solutions, which is a<br />euphemism for perhaps turning a blind eye. some might<br />think, it doesn't alter the fact that now they feel quite<br />free to have a go at hirn. We're going to just allow the<br />law to take its course.<br />We're not going to show him any favouritism. but<br />equally we're not going to be bulldozed into the sort of<br />rolling him out. so to speak, simply because the Labor<br />Party and some media hysteria have suggested that we<br />might. I mean, we'll let the thing be investigated<br />properly and the law run its course.<br />I mean, that's the assurance I give you. He won't be<br />shown any favours, but equally we won't allow the</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />MALCOLM FARR:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />MALCOLM FARR:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD: 83/ 83/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 6<br />Labor Party's malicious, vengeful campaign against him<br />dominate an objective. considered examination of his<br />position. Whatever the Labor Party's motives, it could be in the<br />end that they are routing out a rat someone who's been<br />rorting the taxpayer.<br />Well. there well. yes well. they're your words-I<br />mean. you....<br />It could be. I mean the end result will be that the<br />taxpayer will he saved.<br />Well, that's very colourful language and it gets a line,<br />but doesn't alter the fact that he like anybody else who's<br />entitled to a presumption of innocence that is our<br />system and people should await a proper consideration.<br />My position is simple....<br />Prime Minister....<br />Hang on. My position is simply this. that the law<br />should be allowed to run its course. He's not going to<br />be done any favours, but he's not going to be subject to<br />any persecution. And the other thing I want to say is<br />that the great bulk of members of parliament, the<br />overwhelming majority on both sides are honest and<br />scrupulous and utterly above board in relation to their</p>
<p>Yax from 616273370403/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 7<br />MALCOLM FARR:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD: expense allowances, and it makes them as mad as<br />hornets when stories get around about allegations of<br />rorting because it gives a false impression.<br />The great bulk of NIPs are decent. hard-working, honest<br />men and women on both sides vho are trying to do a<br />job for the community.<br />Do the public believe that?<br />Well. to the extent of the public doesn't believe it. I<br />think the members of parliament are done an injustice<br />and I feel that my obligation as Prime Minister to speak<br />up for all of them, on both sides not only my own<br />colleagues, but also the very honest, hard-working<br />people in thle Labor Party as well. who do the right<br />thing according to their own values and beliefs.<br />Prime Minister. one of the excuses, if you like. that the<br />former Labor government gave was that there was some<br />advice they claim that would he hard to nail Senator<br />Colston with any sort of criminal activity. Now there is<br />the perception that too much....<br />Well. you ought to go and ask Senator Evans and Mr<br />Beazley about that. I don't know anything about what<br />happened in government 13 years ago-I was in<br />Opposition then.</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />PAUL BONGIORINO:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />SULIE FLYNN: But that brings me to today In the sense that the<br />perception is tha[ at thec Federal level there is too much<br />trust of poiltcians for their TA and other allowances,<br />chat thie s%-sem isn't Ei~ hE enou~ lh. and that at the end if<br />the day Senator Cotston Is found not to have done<br />anVthiiia criminai. the perception is out there that he has<br />been rorcin,-,. I inean, w. e saw on television this week<br />the chauffeur car and the self-drive car.<br />An English Jurist once said that if there was no instinct<br />for honour, you couldn't legislare it. And no matter<br />what sy'Stem-yoCu havte, there wvill always be somebody<br />and I'm not suggesting ihere's anybody at the moment<br />there alwauys mnight be somebody who'll try and<br />manipulate it.<br />But I repeaL. I think the great bulk of people in the<br />Parliament on both s&gt; ides are hard-working and honest<br />and scrupulous, and I feel some sympathy for them in<br />thle senlse Ehat the collective tzood name of the show is<br />sometimes put into unfair disrepute.<br />A question from Julie Flynn.<br />Prime Minister. you've used your authority a-s Prime<br />Minister this weekend to raise the issue of gambling and<br />gambling taxes. But the States are arguing that you've<br />cut their funding and rejected calls from people like Jeff<br />Faxtrot : 6167330403/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 8</p>
<p>KaK Iron blbZYJJY74<br />JOHN HOWARD; 83/ 83/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 9<br />Kennett for a review of the tax base. you leave them<br />with no choice.<br />Oh. come on. Look. States always say the Federal<br />Government gives them insufficient funds. What I<br />expressed concern about was the fact that there's<br />growing evidence that there are a lot of people in our<br />community who can't afford to do so. are losing large<br />amounts of money gambling.<br />The figures I've got indicate that in the last financial<br />year, net gambling losses in Australia were about S9.4<br />billion, and that's about 2 per cent of GDP. Now. I'm<br />not a wowser. I don't care if other people gamble, but I<br />do express some alarm about the social consequences of<br />people who can't afford to do so, getting into personal<br />family and financial distress as a result.<br />I wouldn't like to see<br />made at the weekend.<br />saturation level as far<br />are concerned.<br />JULIE FLYNN: more facilities that's the point I<br />I think we're up here: we're at<br />as gambling facilities in Australia<br />But don't the States have a point that they're not<br />because you won't look at restructuring the tax base, or<br />their fixed share of Commonwealth revenues, that<br />gambling is one form of getting revenue in gambling<br />sin taxes, it you like?</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />JOHN HOWARD;<br />PAUL BONGIORINO:<br />JOHN HOWARD: Well. you know. tile States could took at their<br />expendhiures and there art other revenue-raising devices<br />available ito States. That is an easy, if I may say so. it's<br />an easv excuse and gambling. of course mass<br />gamblina was introduced years and years and years ago<br />in som-e parts of Australia. and because it has spread<br />more rapidly and the introduction of large casinos and<br />the like have heen the inodern manifestation.<br />Now. I amn not conderrning it is such. I think it would<br />be absurd Of Me to dO that, hut wvhat I am expressing<br />concern about is that taken LO excess. many people are<br />left in personal and financial ruin as a result. And that<br />is only adding to societies complications and to distress<br />and difficulty for peouple in the community.<br />Are you sayZing you don't accept the States' argument<br />that their iax base is so eroded that they'v'e got no other<br />option? And I mean. it's one thing to say that you're<br />bemnoaning-it-. isn't it fair enough to say ' Well. what.<br />can vou do about it, if you don't wanc it to expand'?<br />Imean. you can't if you're a State. you can't have it<br />both ways. You can't sort of say ' Well. I want all the<br />independence to do what I like and make my own<br />spending decisions, and the Peds can't tell us what to<br />do', and vet if something goes wrong or you're short of<br />a dollar, you always blame the Federal Government.<br />Fax ro3 6167330403/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg:</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733784<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD;<br />JULIE FLYNN:<br />JOHN HOWARD: 03/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 11<br />Now for time immemorial in our system. States have<br />sort of blamed the Federal Government whenever there's<br />a shortfall. Some of chose criticisms are from time tO<br />time justified. What we are endeavouring to do in cooperation<br />with the States is to end areas of duplication.<br />and I hope the States ; are as keen as we are to end areas<br />of duplication.<br />Well. Premier Kennett apparently doesn't think you're<br />going fast enough or hard enough in that area.<br />Well. it'll he very interesting to see the reaction of the<br />States. this year. in respect of proposals that have been<br />put to end areas of duplication. I mean. I congratulate<br />the Victorian Government in handing over its industrial<br />relations authority to the Federal Government. It'd he a<br />very good idea if that were duplicated, and I'd be<br />interested in a two-way trade.<br />There are some things that I think the States can do<br />better than we can, but equally there are some things we<br />can do better. And you've got to be realistic about what<br />can be achieved in this area.<br />Such as?<br />I don't believe you're ever going to totally reverse the<br />sort of relative fiscal roles of the Federal Government<br />and the States. I think you can make improvements at</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />JULIE FLYNN:<br />JTOHN HOW. ARD: 03/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 12<br />the margrin, but I think this i'athat you're voing to<br />[ urn evervthinu on its head is a hit of' u pipe dream.<br />There has been sOme criticism of your first year. that in<br />faict vou have been. i( anvdhing. too cautious and tax<br />reform and health reform are the two key areas that are<br />nominated. isn't, this whole argumnent between ( he States<br />and the Commnonwealth over the tax base also a<br />reflection of the fact that you've said you wvill not look<br />at broadeniti-the tax base neXt E<br />Well, wve made a promise in the election campaigin that,<br />we would not introduce a GST in our first term. Now.<br />it* s no good people saying ' Well. look, yes, we're aware<br />of that, but what about tax reform' I mean, we made a<br />promise. We looked the Australian people in the eye<br />and said ' We w. ill not have a OST in our first term.'<br />Now uoainst that backutround. it IS hypocritical of people<br />to run around saving ' What are you doing about tax<br />retorm?' when w~ e made a promise to the Australian<br />people before the election that we wouldn't do it.<br />Now as far as the pace of reform generally is concerned,<br />if we hadn't been in a minority in the Senate, we'd have<br />changed the industrial relations system nine months ago.<br />The benefits ot' that would now be flowing through to<br />the small business community.</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />MALCOLM FARR:<br />JOHN HOWARD: The unfair dismissal laws would have disappeared nine<br />months ago. not six weeks ago. And a lot of the<br />benefits of our program that will only be felt in the next<br />six or nine months would have been well and truly felt,<br />absorhed. and would have been working as a henefit of<br />that sector long before now.<br />A question from Malcolm Farr.<br />Prime Minister, you said a spirit of compromise is going<br />to be needed to work out the Wik problem. Are you<br />confident that your National Party colleagues are<br />prepared to come up with a compromise?<br />Well. I'm confident that there's a willingness on the part<br />of everybody in the Government to try and see if there's<br />an agrccd solution that can he reached. I'm not<br />confident that we can have that agreed solution, but I'm<br />trying very hard-<br />I've had extensive discussion with the Aboriginal<br />leaders, with the miners and the farmers. I've had them<br />all together in the one room for three or four hours, and<br />I'll be talking to some of them again next week as I did<br />last week. And I'm trying very hard to see if we can<br />reach an agreed outcome.<br />There's a good spirit abroad, but.... 03/ 83/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 13</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733784<br />MALCOLM FARR:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />MALCOLM FARR:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />MALCOLM FARR;<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />JULIE FLYNN:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />JULIE FLYNN: It didn't seem it when Premier Borbidge yeSterday said<br />some High Cuourt judges were dills about history.<br />Well. that in a sense is a little bit separate from the<br />spirit that's cedeid to reach an ugreed outcome.<br />You say\ you're not confident at this stage.<br />I've -ot no talse illusions about how hard it's going to<br />be. and there's no point in getting false expectations up.<br />But I am trving. by including evervbody in the<br />discussions. to see if I can find the common ground for<br />an agreed outcome. If I can't. tlihen I' 11 be making some<br />recommendations to my colleaues.<br />Legislative.... Well. whatever you do. there'll be some leislation<br />required. It's a question of how extensive.<br />Hendv Cowan yesterday said that National Party<br />constituency has given up on the Liberal Party coming<br />up with a solution....<br />Well, that's just Hendy trying to get a headline, really.<br />and that it should simply be extinguishment of native<br />title. 83/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 14</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />JOHN HOWAkRD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD; I've spoken to the only National Party Premier in<br />Australia. quite extensively, last week. and that's the<br />Premier of Queenisland. Rob Borbidge. for whom I have<br />enormous respect. and I mean he's fiercely defending<br />thle interests of his constituents, but fies also adopting. I<br />think,. a very sensible approach. He's searching to see if<br />there is a basis for ail a,_ reed outcome which will<br />properly protect thie interesis of farmers in Queensland.<br />So. I think that sort of utterly final declaration from<br />somebody contributes nochin'a at all to the debate.<br />But when you talk compromise. isn't the problem that<br />you're asking one group. tile Aborigines. to compromise<br />a riL-hc?<br />Yes, but those who argue that nothing should happen in<br />the wake of the \ Vik decision. are asking the pasroralists<br />of Australia to give up something that they have seen as<br />a right for 200 years. I mean, when their leases were<br />issued year after y'ear all around Australia. nobody<br />talked about native tite. because it didn't exist. Now,<br />it's a question of I mean. in a sense the Wik decision<br />retrospectively altered the wvhole basis on which pastoral<br />leases in this country have been issued.<br />So. you've got a collision of perceived<br />therefore, to talk of compromise is<br />unreasonable for the Aborigines than it<br />farmers or the miners. And this idea that rights and.<br />no more<br />is for the<br />compromise<br />Farxo6 m16 733643/ 1034/: 9473 Pg:</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />MALCOLM FARR:<br />JOHN HOWA. IRD: involves Imposirng solely obligations on the Aborigines.<br />inisreads what has happened Inl[ tie wake of' the Wvik<br />decision to the perceived rights of farmiers and<br />pastoral isis in particular.<br />Do you see this Hiuh Court as quite deliberately sending<br />the Gtweriiineiu a in11sa1z t 4ti. theC court, wants the<br />Government to 11ove a11011-a hit quicker'!<br />Well, what I have said Is that there is a perception in the<br />commnunity and this is not necessarily related to one or<br />other decision there's a perception in the community<br />that Somne people In thle judicial area think the role of the<br />courts 1now is it) sort of jolly governments along where<br />thley, perceive governments hiaven't moved quickly<br />enough1. NOW. Call I ma1ke! it clear that I have the utmost<br />respect for tie in~ eurity of the High Court. I make no<br />complaints about their commitment to their work or to<br />their responsibilities, Like any other Australian citizen,<br />I have the right to disagree with or criticise a particular<br />decision. I was disappointed in the Wik decision. It would have,<br />in my view, been more in conformity with what<br />everybody was told in 1993. if the High Court had held<br />that pastoral leases extinguished native title. I mean,<br />that's what Paul Keatinv-said. it's what all the farmers<br />Far3xo/ 6u01 36/ 79373 64 14: 43 Pg: 16</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD: believed: it's what man\, Aboriginal leaders<br />acknowledg. ed. and it was contained in a recital of the<br />Native Title Act. Now that in a sense has created the<br />dilIem ma.<br />Now, I accept that wvhat the High Court has said<br />decla res the lwas it is at present But as I've said on<br />probably 20 occasions. che Parliament hias Elie right at<br />any' tiMe Lhat if it thinks it is in Australia's interests to<br />alter the law aS currently interpreted.<br />Now thiat represents a correct statement of the<br />interaction of the legislature and thie executive with the<br />judiciary, It respects the role Of tlie High Court. but it<br />asserts the superior right. Of Parliament to change the law<br />as interpreted and declared by the High Court if it thinks<br />that is in Australia's interests.<br />Mr Howard. there's news overnight that 150<br />mercenaries have landed on the Papua New Guinea<br />island of Boueainville. Isn't this a slap in the face to<br />our diplomatic efforts to prevent. this happening, and<br />what now can Australia do about it"<br />Well. there are a number Of Options that we'll be<br />looking at, and I don't want to go into them any further<br />at this stage. We expresscd our view about it. We'll<br />continue to express our view about it. This is not a new<br />problem. The previous government had a similar<br />Faxf1ro6 233743/ 1034/: 9473 Pg: 17</p>
<p>Fax from 6162733704<br />PAUL BONGIORLNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD: difficulty w ithj papua New Guinea. It really is against<br />that country's miedium and long-term interests to use<br />mercenaries TO Wipe ourC tile BRA.<br />The only % kav k ou vaii solve Thai problem is by genuine<br />negotiationi. We've put chat ito the Prime N\ tinister of<br />New Guinea repeatedly. WV'll continue to do a number<br />of rhinas ito trv and hrinL, home io the PNG Government<br />the fully of tile course ( in which we believe that<br />gYovernrnnt is now embarked. And I understand ilhac<br />view is shared by New Zealand. by the United Stares.<br />by the UK. by other Pacific Island countries. It's a<br />difficult issue an1d I<br />Well. there only seeil to be 1% V0 Options. do there nor?<br />Either w,, e dit something about our aid what we give<br />them: or perhaps even some sort of military<br />inherv entioll*?<br />Welt, it's not the sort of issue where one should make<br />sort of over-Ehe-shoulder comments on the run. You're<br />dealing With a very sensitive area of international<br />relations and something is right on our doorstep and<br />somethingy that the rest of the world sees Australia as<br />having a particular responsibility for.<br />But you're also dealing with an independent coumtry,<br />and you have the sensitivity that a former colonial<br />power. so to speak, telling a former colony what it<br />Fax1œ 6ro2~ 3 3743/ 0134/ 9: 74 3 Pg: 18</p>
<p>Fax f rom~ 6162733704<br />JULIE FLYNN:<br />JOHIN HOWARD: 83/ 03/ 97 14: 43 Pg: 19<br />thinks it ouft to be. That always raises natural<br />sensitivies. And Australia and New GUinea are no<br />different from any other tw. o countries that had that<br />relationship. Asecond jury has just uwarded dainages, to William<br />lvll-an? a survivor of the \\ w-, ager disaster, You<br />aave a public coritnment to investigate the<br />Commonwealth's iutack on. or challenge to that. Will<br />vou continue to challenae this man who now has only<br />three weekS to 1iVe? WVill your government....<br />Well. I will be lookinVI atl that m1atter tomorrow. It is a<br />very difficult and sensitive issue because of the tragic<br />circumstances in which Mr McLean now finds himself.<br />But the other side of it is that w,. hat happens to him has<br />enormous precedent implications for hundreds of people<br />who were on the Melbourne.<br />Bear in mnind that % Mr McLean wxas on the Melbourne,<br />hie wvas not on the Vovagzer. And it opens up a whole<br />new sort of area of potential liability involving tens of<br />millions of dollars. And I'm totally sympathetic to his<br />personal situation. but I have a responsibility to the<br />people wiove paid the taxes that might ultimately fund<br />( he Lens of millions of dollars of compensation claims, to<br />look to their interests as well. So. I'm trying to get a<br />balance of the two.</p>
<p>PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO:<br />JOHN HOWARD:<br />PAUL BONGIORNO: 03/ 83/ 97 14: 43 Pg:<br />It sounds like you don't have much room to move,<br />though. Well. it's one of those difficult issues because the optics<br />of it are awful. People say ' Gee. you're hard-hearted<br />and everything. The poor man is dying.' All of that is<br />true. but the implication of just giving a tick to that is<br />that the taxpayers could be up fur tens and tens of<br />millions of dollars in circumstances that they may not<br />regard anywhere near as meritorious as Mr McLean.<br />Prime Minister. we are running out of time. Just very<br />briefly, of your deputy that is Treasurer Costello and<br />Peter Reith, Leader of the House. which of the two, do<br />you think, is performing better?<br />They're both performing brilliantly. Look, I think Peter<br />Costello is a tremendous Treasurer, and I think Peter<br />Reith has done a great job as IR. and I think they'll<br />continue to contribute mightily for the Howard<br />government for at least a decade into the future.<br />Okay. Thank you very much to our guest today. Prime<br />Minister John Howard. and to our panel.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
