<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3727</transcript-id>
    <title>NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER FOR THE OPENING OF COLIN GARLAND&#039;S EXHIBITION OF PAINTINGS, KINGSTON, JAMAICA, 1 MAY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/05/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003727.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER FOR THE OPENING<br />
OF COLIN GARLAND'S EXHIBITION OF PAINTINGS<br />
KINGSTON, JAMAICA, 1 MAY 1975<br />
1. NUMEROUS ARTISTS HAVE SOUGHT INSPIRATION IN BEAUTIFUL<br />
ISLAND SURROUNDINGS. ONE THINKS OF GAUGUIN IN TAHITI,<br />
OF DONALD FRIEND IN BALI. IN THE SAME COMIPANY,,<br />
I TRUST, WE SHALL THINK( OF COLIN GARLAND IN JAMAICA.<br />
2. HE IS NOT THE FIRST AUSTRALIAN ARTIST TO MhAKE HIS<br />
NAMERAND ENHANCE HIS COUNTRY'IS NAME, ABROAD. NOLAN<br />
AND BOYD ARE GOOD EXAMPLES. IT WAS WITH GUY MARTIN BOYD,<br />
A MEMBER OF THAT CELEBRATED FAMILY, THAT GARLAND BEGAN<br />
WORKING WITH CLAY AT THE AGE OF 14 IN SYDNEY.<br />
THIS EXPERIENCE, AND HIS FORMAL TRAINING AT THE<br />
EAST SYDNEY TECHNICAL COLLEGE, LAID THE BASIS OF<br />
HIS CRAFTSMANSHIP.<br />
3. WHEN HE WAS 22 HE CREATED THE TINTOOKIES A CELEBRATED<br />
PUPPET FAMILY BELOVED BY THOUSANDS OF AUS-[ ZALIANS.<br />
FIRE DESTROYED THE PUPPETS AND THEIR THEATRE FOUR<br />
YEARS AGO. THE TINTOOKIES TOURED WIDELY IN ASIA<br />
UNDER THE DIRECTION OF PETER SCRIVEN. THUS GARLAND'S<br />
WORK IS FAMILIAR IN TWO REGIONS ASIA AND THE CARIBBEANREGIONS<br />
OF GREAT IMPORTANCE IN THE COMMONWEALTH AND OF<br />
GREAT IMPORTANCE To AUSTRALIA, No ONE HAS DONE MORE TO<br />
DEVELOP THE CULTURAL TIES BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND HER<br />
FRIENDS AND NEIGHBOURS. 1 / 2 </p>
<p>HE FIRST CAME TO JAMAICA IN 1962, STAYED THREE YEARS<br />
AND WENT TO LONDON, WHERE HE HELD EXHIBITIONS IN<br />
1964 AND 1965. HE HELD AN EXHIBITION AT THE MACQUARIE<br />
GALLERY IN SYDNEY IN 1966. THE PULL OF JAMAICA WAS<br />
TOO STRONG, HOWEVER. GARLAND RETURNED AND HAS NOW<br />
LIVED HERE FOR NINE YEARS, PAINTING AND TEACHING AT<br />
THE JAMAICAN SCHOOL OF ART. HE WAS AWARDED A GRANT<br />
BY THE WEST GERMAN GOVERNMENT 10 TOUR GERMAN ART<br />
CENTRES, INCLUDING WEST BERLIN, AND IS GRATEFUL TO<br />
THE PRESENT GERMAN AMBASSADOR TO JAMAICA, HIS EXCELLENCY<br />
MR KURT SCHMIDT, FOR HELPING HIM SECURE THIS<br />
OPPORTUNITY,<br />
COLIN GARLAND LIVES A ROUSSEAU-LIKE LIFE-STYLE IN A<br />
HOUSE HIGH IN YOUR BEAUTIFUL MOUNTAINS WHERE THE<br />
DISTANT SEA, FLOATING CLOUDS, BIRDS AND ANIMALS ARE<br />
HIS CONSTANT COMPANIONS. HE HAS IMMERSED HIMSELF<br />
IN JAMAICAN LIFE AND HISTORY, SEVERAL OF HIS PAINTINGS<br />
BEING CONNECTED WITH THE MORANT BAY REBELLION OF<br />
1865. I BELIEVE YOU HAVE LIVING HERE IN JAMAICA A<br />
CONSIDERABLE 20TH CENTURY ARTIST. I AM PROUD OF<br />
HIS AUSTRALIAN HERITAGE AND AM DELIGHTED TO DECLARE<br />
HIS EXHIBITION OPEN, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
