<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5071</transcript-id>
    <title>QUEENSLAND STATE COUNCIL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/06/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005071.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PROVPhE UUNISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 16 JUNE 1979<br />
QUEENSLAND STATE COUNCIL<br />
The past few days in Queensland have been exciting for me<br />
because this State is very much on the move in the great<br />
new mining areas. The Government's policies of the last<br />
three or four years gave given confidence to investors<br />
and provided markets for products of Queensland mines.<br />
The problems are the problems of growth and problems of<br />
development. And they are the kind of problems we want.<br />
In Queensland, moving out into the pastoral areas in the<br />
West of this State, those people who three or four years<br />
ago had no hope for the future, who despaired at what the<br />
next year might bring, now have confidence for the 19801s.<br />
Rebuilding their assets, receiving good prices, with the<br />
policies of the Government working for their advantage,<br />
and for Australia's advantage, is again an exciting thing.<br />
Queensland is coming alive under the combined policies of<br />
the State and Commonwealth Government.<br />
I would like to look at the objectives we have for Australia.<br />
In the daily application of policy and in the decisions<br />
that have to be made we can lose sight of the major<br />
objectives. We can lose sight of our broad purpose.<br />
We can lose sight of what it is all about.<br />
But we need to kecall 1975: with an economy destroyed;<br />
with unemployment up by almost 200,000 in one year alone;<br />
with manufacturing industry in despair; people on the farms<br />
in the pastoral areas had no hope for the future, because<br />
of iuif-llation, and because markets had been lost. At a time<br />
of growing oil crisis throughout the world, oil search in<br />
Australia stopped dead in its tracks. This was because of<br />
the deliberate policies of the previous Government.<br />
The dollar was in difficulty, again because of the policies<br />
of that Government.<br />
Now in 1979, a great many things have been changed for the<br />
better. Great progress has been made in this State and in<br />
other parts of Australia. There has been remarkable recovery<br />
in many industries. Private employment has grown for the<br />
first time for seven or eight months that is the best record<br />
for many, many years. Manufacturing industry is experiencing / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
a great move forward and investmnent has risen. In the home<br />
market our manufacturing industries are getting a better<br />
share of the market. A recent survey of the Metal Trades<br />
Industry has shown that employment, on their surveys, was up<br />
nearly five per cent in M-arch, compared to a year earlier.<br />
In manufacturing industry, employment has started to grow again.<br />
There have been great iiew developments in the petrochemical<br />
industry, and engine plant developments of great size in the<br />
motor industry.<br />
In export markets, manufacturing exports were up by nearly<br />
percent in the December quarter 1978, over the same<br />
quarter of the previous year. That is because of the improved<br />
comoetitive base of Australian industry, which is now able<br />
to get out and sell, able to capture markets that had earlier<br />
been lost.<br />
Following the decline in the rural industries, there has been<br />
great resurgence in the beef industry. This means so much<br />
to the State of Queensland, and to the small country towns,<br />
after the depression of recent years. Why did we have that<br />
Depression? In 1974 we lost all our market in Japan. A market<br />
of 120,000 tonnes was cut to nothing in the next year because<br />
of policies that had been pursued in Austrlaia. At the same<br />
time, markets in Europe were lost. The Government of the day<br />
sat with that loss, and did nothing about it. Now, because<br />
markets have been regained, because inflation is much lower<br />
than it was, there is a great resurgence in the beef industry.<br />
This affects large parts of Australia, giving confidence for<br />
the years ahead.<br />
The wheat industry has had a good year. The wool industry is<br />
strong, and we have been increasing the floor price. Reserve<br />
stocks are lower than they have been some people are even<br />
saying they are too low. Prices have been moving strongly.<br />
Remember, when the industry needed help in 1973 and 1974, the<br />
then Government sought to reduce the reserve price by 50 cents,<br />
a great contrast with today's policies which are now building<br />
confidence in that industry.<br />
There have been. difficulties in the sugar industry because of<br />
duinoping by Europe** on world markets. At the same time, as we<br />
move to improve the logistics of that situation, we have been<br />
given the first indications in recent days that the European<br />
commnunity may well consider joining the International Sugar<br />
Agr-emet, provided the U. S. A. also does. That is the first<br />
tizea there has been a prospect of a sensible,-world-wide<br />
agreement for many,. many years.<br />
Many other parts of the rural industry are also doing better<br />
than for a very, very long time. I am not going to say that<br />
the rural industries have never had it so good. Somebody else<br />
said that, and he said it at a time of a very real depression.<br />
But we can say with complete accuracy that rural industries are<br />
very much better than they were. The prospects for the future<br />
can give people in the beef, sheep, sugar and in other elements<br />
of the rural industry cause for confidence as we move into the<br />
1980' 1S. / 13 </p>
<p>-3<br />
The great mining industry is also coming alive after the dismal<br />
years from 1972 to 1975, when there was hardly a new project<br />
started in this State or in any other part of Australia. Now<br />
we have $ 2 billion dollars of investment in the coal industry.<br />
Over the last two or three days, with Senator Kathy Martin,<br />
Senator David McCubbin and Dr. Llew Edwards, we saw what was<br />
happening great new developments, new investments, which<br />
are going to add to the jobs in this State, going to add -to<br />
the capacity of rural towns, going to add enormously to the<br />
export wealth of Queensland and of Australia. They result<br />
from policies pursued over the past three or four years.<br />
To see the new mines of Gregory, Blackwater and Norwich Park<br />
being developed and opened up, to see the great drag-lines<br />
operate, is exciting indeed. It brings to life the cold hard<br />
statistics of investment in Australia, which, just as a<br />
statistic, tend to be slightly meaningless and slightly lifeless.<br />
To talk to the people working in those industries, to see<br />
the growth and development of new towns, to see the port at<br />
Hay Point all of these things bring to light what is<br />
happening in Australia. Exports of black coal in 1975 were<br />
worth $ 830 million. This year they are worth $ 1510 million,<br />
with prospects of great expansion in the future. It is not only<br />
coal. In bauxite alumina and aluminium, there is nearly<br />
$ 2 million of expansion in many different places right around<br />
Australia. By 1985 a ten-fold rise is projected in aluminium<br />
exports again a great story of confidence, great story of<br />
investment, a great vote of confidence in the policies being<br />
pursued by your Government.<br />
In oil, great developments are taking place. In the preceding<br />
period oil search was stopped because of foolish policies<br />
that killed incentive at a very time when we needed to undertake<br />
a much greater search to improve our own self sufficiency.<br />
This year sufficient exploration wells will be drilled to ensure<br />
the best result, even at the lowest end of the estimates, for<br />
seven years or more.<br />
That again means we can point to the 1980' s with confidence.<br />
As a result of our policies, the balance of payments is<br />
improving, strengthening the value of the dollar very greatly<br />
indeed.<br />
Now none of this happened by accident. People sometimes say<br />
that in the rural industry there was a market upturn, that<br />
wou~ ld have happened anyway. But if there had been some market<br />
u; Dzurn overseas, while costs were rising at 30% a year as<br />
occurred in 1974, Australia's pastoralists and farmers would<br />
still have been sent bankrupt. Indeed, those markets overseas<br />
did not just occur. They came about as a result of our deliberate<br />
trade policies.<br />
We have got inflation down and we are going to keep on the<br />
policies that will pursue that path, vigorously and firmly.<br />
We have controlled expenditure. It is very easy for State<br />
governments or organisations right around this Commonwealth<br />
to suggest that we the Commonwealth should spend more, as though<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
we are some kind of cargo cult, as if we just have to wave a<br />
wand, and find the resources to meet those requests. They<br />
heed to understand that what we spend as a Federal Government<br />
we have to take from all of you, and from hundreds of thousands<br />
of other people like you, in taxation. Certainly if people<br />
want higher taxation, governments can spend more. But I seem<br />
to detect the view around that people also want lower taxation.<br />
Just as a family has to match its expenditure to its revenue,<br />
to its wages and its earnings, so too does a Nation, or else<br />
it will get into trouble. The longer it spends more than it<br />
earns, the longer it believes it can spend money that it does<br />
not have, that it has not produced, the more it will get into<br />
tro-dole.<br />
We are going to make sure that our expenditure is approximately<br />
matched with what we can collect from revenue. Our public<br />
service is nearly 60,000 less than it would have been had the<br />
policies of our predecessors stayed in force. In absolute<br />
terms the public service is over 12,000 less than when we<br />
took office. I think it is the first time there has been a<br />
continuous and sustained reduction in the public service of<br />
any government of the Commonwealth.<br />
Dr Llew Edwards advises me that there has been a ceiling in the<br />
Queensland Public Service for the last couple of years. But<br />
wit-h that exception I believe that the Public Services of some<br />
States are still growing quite dramatically. And so it may be<br />
that some attention needs to be put in that direction.<br />
What we have done has involved rigorous, difficult and often<br />
tough, and in the short term at least, unpopular decisions.<br />
But we need to understand again that when people ask things of<br />
government, they are asking us to spend something of yours.<br />
There is not much difference between asking us and putting<br />
your head over the fence and asking your neighbour. I believe<br />
people should not ask things of government which they are not<br />
prepared to ask their neighbours to support as well. By asking<br />
us you are only doing so by proxy, and we need to understand<br />
that. As a result of the last three years there is a much<br />
greater understanding throughout the Australian community that<br />
Government expenditure, State, Commonwealth and Local has to<br />
be reasonable and has to be restrained. I am quite convinced<br />
thL-at-Government c n only govern well if it is prepared to<br />
undertake a quite rigorous application of priorities, to make<br />
sure that taxation dollars are spent where they are most needed<br />
in the national interest, and to assist people who are less<br />
fCcr=-= ate tLhan others.<br />
There are still continuing problems. Wle have to work at the<br />
problem of the continuing deficit. That has been reduced<br />
substantially in relation to the size of the economy, but it<br />
is still too high, compared with what we would like. There<br />
are some things which we need to understand, which make it<br />
difficult to reduce all elements of government expenditure.<br />
Ten years ago we had 168 pensioners welfare recipients for<br />
every 1,000 people in the workforce. Today that same 1000<br />
people in the workforce have to support a much greater number<br />
of welfare recipients, about 270 instead of 168, largely </p>
<p>5<br />
because of an ageing Australian Population. The demand for<br />
additional expenditure goes on inexorably as more people go<br />
in-to over-age brackets. In addition to that, when there has<br />
been a slack time in the economy, additions to revenue lag<br />
behind recovery. The lag is perhaps about 18 months to two<br />
years behind the recovery in the economy itself, and that again<br />
puts pressure on a government's deficit.<br />
Sometimes it is necessary to trim the sails to-adjust various<br />
elements in the economy. We need to understand that does not<br />
represent a change of policy. It represents a maintenance of<br />
policy, maintenance of the steady path we have set ourselves<br />
at the outset. Our new mini budget was one of such adjustment.<br />
I make no apology for it, although all of us would have much<br />
Preferred it not to have been necessary. There were many changes<br />
after the August Budget adding to inflationary pressures. The<br />
wheat harvest was great for wheat producers, but bad for the<br />
money supply. Beef prices are good for beef producers, but<br />
again bad for the Consumer Price Index. The disturbances in<br />
Iran were much greater than expected and increased the oil<br />
prices. Capital inflow is something that we want, but again<br />
bad for the money supply. So, while there are many good<br />
effects from these changes, at the same time they have to involve<br />
some counter action by the Commonwealth to maintain its downward<br />
thrust against inflation. It would have been totally irresponsible<br />
to have policies that would have resulted in tax cuts involving<br />
something over a $ 1,000 million applying from the 1 July.<br />
As much as we would have liked that, and much, as I am sure<br />
you and others would have liked that, it would have been an<br />
addition to the inflationary pressures around Australia which<br />
would have damaged confidence, investment and the future of<br />
Australia, which would have done damage to the main thrust<br />
of our policies. That has to remain our first and foremost<br />
obligation to maintain our steady path<br />
One thing that has contributed a great deal to the recovery<br />
over the last two to three years are the trade policies and the<br />
trade offensives sometimes the trade brawls, at least in<br />
terms of negotiation that we have had recently. I can<br />
remember when we first decided to negotiate with the European<br />
Community, when we first decided as a government that it was<br />
just not good enough for Australia to sit back and say we will<br />
tak'e whatever Europe dishes out. It was not good enough to<br />
say that we are not going to argue for access to their markets,<br />
that we are going to accept it, because they are great and<br />
powerful, because they have 260 million people and what can<br />
14~ zmil lion people do about it. When we first decided to take<br />
on Europe, there were people who said " Oh, look we shouldn't<br />
do that. We won't succeed". But Australia has. The critics<br />
said we were a little country. They said we were a country of<br />
no account, that we should ignore the most affluent and the<br />
largest single market that the world has seen. Well, we decided<br />
we could not ignore that market. We decided that we had to<br />
negotiate. I can well remember when I began those negotiations<br />
in Brussels. It took four hours of determined argument even<br />
for them to concede that they would negotiate with us about<br />
the problems. On that occasion, they initially rejected our<br />
right to negotiate, our right to be consulted, our right to<br />
put our point of view. But the point was won. Negotiation / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
has continued. There has been an initial agreement between<br />
their priLncipal negot-iater, Dr Gunderlachand Vic Garland,<br />
which indicates a considerable degree of success.<br />
This does not mean that the market suddenly has become<br />
totally open. But the door is ajar. This is a basis from<br />
which we can work to the future, a recognition that we have a<br />
right to challence their market, and a recognition at the<br />
same time of the export subsidies totalling about $ 12 billion<br />
a year, which often compete against our direct interests<br />
in other markets. Sometimes their export subsidy on sugar<br />
was worth more to them than the total price our sugar farmers<br />
getl in Queensland. We had to be concerned with these issues.<br />
However, the agreement that has been negotiated, opens the<br />
door-, and gives us a base to work on. It is accepted that<br />
ther-? e will be continuing consultations into the future. All<br />
in all, the negotiations have been a significant success.<br />
In t -he United States we have won much greater certainty for<br />
our great primary exports, much greater certainty for our<br />
beef exports, than ever before. In Japan, where in 1974<br />
under the previous government a market of 120,000 tonnes was<br />
cut to nothing, there have already been painstaking negotiations.<br />
The final details of the settlement with Japan, when revealed,<br />
will show that that market is also secured into the future.<br />
Wit1-h other markets such as Korea, it means that our great<br />
primary exporters can look to the future. There is more<br />
certainty about the access they need to affluent markets<br />
around the world than I think they have ever had in the<br />
history of Australia. And none of that would have occurred<br />
i-F it hadn't been for the trade offensive by Doug Anthony<br />
and myself, and Vic Garland and their officials arguing for<br />
our interests in many different countries.<br />
We also need to look at the world we live in . Because Australia,<br />
above all countries, is vastly dependent upon world trade and<br />
access to markets, what is happening in the economies of<br />
Europe and North America is important to us.<br />
Sometimes we might have been too optimistic about the way<br />
other major significant countries would be managing their<br />
ow., n economies. We might have been too optimistic for there<br />
being a greater reduction in inflation in the major countries<br />
of ' Europe, the United States, and therefore greater growth<br />
in markets and in world trade than there has been. Since the<br />
es--ai! at'-ion into higher rates of inflation right around the<br />
worldCA in 1973, the normal rate of growth in world trade has<br />
been halved. For the preceding 20 years there was an improvement<br />
of about eight percent a year. Since then it has run at<br />
four percent per year. From that one change alone you can<br />
see much of the problem of unemployment in many advanced<br />
countries. We might have believed that the policies and<br />
rhetoric of past summit conferences, involving the seven<br />
largest economies, would have had more results than in fact<br />
they have had in overcoming inflation. / 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
But that has not been the result. In North America, in the<br />
United States, inflation is over 10 percent and rising;<br />
in Canada it is over 10 percent and rising; in the United<br />
Kingdom it is nearly 11 percent and as a result of their last<br />
Budget they themselves are predicting over 17 percent.<br />
In Germany, inflation is still low by our standards, although<br />
at six percent it has doubled. Australian inflation is<br />
around eight percent with pressures to move it up. With this<br />
high rate of inflation the Western system of trade and payments,<br />
upon which the prosperity of Europe and North America and<br />
many other countries including Australia depend, is plainly<br />
unde2r threat. Because with this inflation, there will not<br />
be an adequate market growth to overcome the problems and<br />
difficulties of unemployment.<br />
That therefore places a great deal of importance on the<br />
sur-mmt conference -to be undertaken in Tokyo. I have no<br />
doubt1 that the conference will devote a great deal of time<br />
to energy problems. It might well be called the energy<br />
surimit. But that is still not the most important problem<br />
in front of that conference. Inflation is even more important.<br />
The summit countries are great and powerful. 600 million<br />
people who are the wealthiest and the most powerful, the most<br />
tech. Lnologically advanced that the world has ever seen. What<br />
they do in the management or mismanagement of their own<br />
dcm. estic affairs plainly affects all of us, for good or for ill.<br />
Past summits have produced statements, but there has not<br />
always been action to follow those statements. This summit<br />
needs concerted follow-up action to bear down on world inflation<br />
much more vigorously than has been the case in the past.<br />
So far I believe there have been two countries that have taken<br />
action against inflation Germany and Japan. I am personally<br />
honeful that the United Kingdom might join those two and argue<br />
to strengthen the anti-inflationary courses. This would help<br />
to move all countries to a much more vigorous approach. we will<br />
have to wait and see the results. But what then of Australia<br />
against this environment. Our inflation is lower than much<br />
of Europe. It is lower than North America and it is not moving<br />
up as much as theirs. That means our industries are becoming<br />
more competitive instead of less, as was the case during our<br />
previous period of inflation, when our inflation was above<br />
ofMost other countries. If our inflation is relatively<br />
less then our home export markets will be secured and I believe<br />
expanded. I-e als have other great advantages because of our mineral<br />
wealth coke and coal, iron ore, bauxite and nickel. We are<br />
a great country to attract investment. We have many commodities<br />
that the world nations need and for which they will be looking<br />
to Australia as a source of supply.<br />
Because the world needs energy, and because we have coal and<br />
natural gas, we have the capacity to move through difficult<br />
periods and to improve the Australian economy, even while the<br />
world economy istelf is pretty sluggish, even while it is<br />
not doing well. Because we are a more attractive source of<br />
/ 8 </p>
<p>S -8-<br />
supply, and because we are a more reliable source of supply<br />
than many other countries, we are getting there and in fact<br />
receiving more than might otherwise be regarded as Australia's<br />
fair share of world investment. This is because of our<br />
political stability. I believe great world investment will<br />
continue in Australia even if there is relatively low growth<br />
in world trade and in world markets.<br />
For all these reasons Australia has many advantages. We can<br />
weather whatever difficulties there might be in world trade<br />
and the world economy, as long as we keep the wit and the<br />
will and the determination to arrange our affairs well and to<br />
continue with the policies of recent years. In this great<br />
design, I have not got the slightest doubt that we shall<br />
succeed in making Australia an even better and an even greater<br />
nation. But governments cannot do it all. We can set the course, we<br />
can set the rudder fair, but all Australians need to take up<br />
the opportunities that result. We can set the economic<br />
climate for investment and for profit. But it is you who need,<br />
to invest, it is you and other Australians who make the<br />
profits. We can negotiate markets but it is our producers<br />
who have the task of exporting, who must provide the goods<br />
to fill the markets. Wle need to recognise clearly the<br />
li'mits of Government action, the role of governments and<br />
th--e role of private enterprise. Government can open the door<br />
for opportunities, but it is private enterprise that must<br />
exploit and develop them.<br />
Scme things that governments do stimulate and encourage<br />
activity within a country, but if a government goes too<br />
far, it can stifle and destroy. We cannot make all decisions<br />
for all Australians, and we should not try to. Men and women<br />
have to seek their own destiny and make their own futures.<br />
Wle need to recognise the inevitable pressures on government<br />
to spend more and to resist that with a total determination.<br />
Our expenditure must be linked with those things we can<br />
finance responsibly.<br />
And in our philosophy we want to encourage the free spirit and<br />
enterprise of the Australian people, to promote independence<br />
development. So often governments have raised false<br />
expectations. They have led people to believe -that governments<br />
should do it all, with no effort by people themselves. That is<br />
the way I believe that many once vibrant nations have taken,<br />
to' -he-r almost total destruction.<br />
Our task has been to rebuild Australia's strength, to encourage<br />
independence. Our Liberal vision is of a vigorous imaginative<br />
people with pride and achievement, unequalled in achievement,<br />
unequalled in opportunity. We are the custodians of that<br />
freedom, we are the custodians of that opportunity. Our policies<br />
are st-eady, our resolution is firm and our conviction absolute.<br />
With faith in our hearts we shall succeed and boldly advance<br />
Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
