<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8352</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT THE  OPENING OF THE TELECOM AUSTRALIA THEATRE AUSTRALIAN WAR MEMORIAL CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/11/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008352.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>lW~ fl AtnATN~ q1 ThT. T7' PV PMRARM~ En UINTIL. DELIVFRY<br />SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />OPENING OF THE TELECOM AUSTRALIA THEATRE<br />AUSTRALIAN WAR MEMORIAL<br />CANBERRA 11 NOVEMBER 1991<br />Dame Beryl Beaurepaire,<br />Ben Humphreys<br />Brendon Kelson, Director of Australian War Memorial<br />Mel Ward, Managing Director Telecom<br />Your Excellencies<br />Distinguished Guests<br />Ladies and Gentlemen<br />The Australian War Memorial is a unique institution not just<br />in this country, but in the world.<br />It is not simply a museum, though it is a museum. It is not<br />simply a memorial, though it is a memorial. It is not a<br />tomb, though all the Australians who died in war are present;<br />here. The Australian War Memorial contains all those things<br />museum, memorial and mausoleum and more. It is, to quote<br />John Curtin at the opening of this extraordinary building<br />fifty years ago today, " the sanctuary of Australian<br />traditions." A sanctuary where C W Bean the father of the Memorial said<br />we should " feel the presence of the dead", where we would<br />find their " relics and records" close by, and where we would.<br />find understanding through knowledge. In Bean's inspired<br />view this was the most profound way to commemoration and<br />remembrance. I<br />Their spirit would be here, because unlike most other<br />countries we know their names. -Although Australia returned<br />just one body home in World War One, we had no need for a<br />tomb of the unknown soldier, for we know who they were and<br />we remember them.<br />Bean read the words of an Australian soldier, dying alone in<br />a muddy hole in France in the First World War and kept them<br />as motivation through the long years it took to establish<br />this great shrine. The soldier wrote, " At least in<br />Australia they will remember me."</p>
<p>On this Remembrance Day, at this opening of a new page in<br />the story of' the Australian War Memorial, it is fitting that<br />we should remember what those Australian traditions are,<br />what the Australians whose names are fixed forever in bronze<br />died for: liberty, democracy, the rule of law, national<br />sovereignty and peace.<br />In 1991 those traditions, which are not so uniquely<br />Australian that we have not wanted to share them, are as<br />important as they ever were.<br />We have seen over the past two years that those traditions<br />are what people all over the world demand as well in<br />Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union, in Africa, Asia<br />and South America.<br />This year, Australians have again served with distinction in<br />war, to defeat aggression in the Gulf.<br />Australians are still serving overseas, under the United<br />Nations in the Western Sahara.<br />Before this year ends, Australians will be serving in<br />Cambodia, under the United Nations, to underwrite a peace<br />settlement which Australian diplomacy has been instrumental<br />in achieving..<br />No one can overlook the poignancy of the opening of the of<br />this Memorial fifty years ago, on the eve of that massive<br />struggle in t~ he Pacific which did so much to shape Australia<br />and its regio~ n.<br />The Pacific War was the greatest crisis in our nation's<br />history, and we emerged from it much changed. In its way it<br />was a rite of passage as fundamental as Gallipoli.<br />For if Gallipoli gave Australians a sense of our identity as<br />a nation, the Pacific War brought us to understand our<br />location as a. nation, and our destiny as a part of the Asia-<br />Pacific region.<br />It marked the decisive turning point of the colonial era in<br />Asia, and the emergence of the complex community of<br />independent nations which are today our neighbours and<br />friends. It also marked the final chapter of our own colonial era,<br />and the foundati6n of our unique partnership with the United<br />States a distinctively Pacific relationship which has<br />grown to reflect our increasing acceptance of the Asia-<br />Pacific region as the place where we live.<br />It is fitting that today's ceremonies are the first of a<br />series on which, over the next year, Australians will look<br />back with that vividness which an anniversary brings to the<br />events of fif-ty years ago.</p>
<p>There will be a series of special events to mark particular,<br />dates; the fall of Singapore, the bombing of Darwin, the<br />Battle of the Coral Sea, and the Kokoda Trail. The<br />Government wrill participate fully in these events.<br />I plan to be! in Darwin in February to commemorate the first<br />bombing raid.; in the Coral Sea in May to commemorate the<br />great naval battle which laid the foundations for allied<br />control of the Pacific Ocean; and on the Kokoda Trail later<br />in the year to remember those great battles in which<br />Australians turned the tide of the Japanese march.<br />In marking these anniversaries, we will be recalling not<br />only the sacrifi ces made by Australians in defence of their<br />country, but also the sacrifices of our allies, particularly<br />the United States. Each year the anniversary of the Coral<br />Sea has been an occasion for the US and Australia to<br />remember the fire in which our alliance was forged.<br />This year it will be a special opportunity to look back on<br />fifty years of co-operation and partnership, and look<br />forward to the continued growth and evolution of this<br />relationship over the challenging years ahead.<br />With this in mind a Coral Sea Commemorative Council has been<br />established under the chairmanship of Sir Eric Neal,<br />bringing tog-ether many eminent Australians to co-ordinate<br />and develop commemorative activities. The Council aims not<br />only to remind Australians and Americans of the momentous<br />events of fifty years ago, but also to encourage them to<br />look to the future of that relationship in the twenty-first<br />century. I am honoured to be Patron, with my friend the<br />American Ambassador Mel Sembler and I give the Committee my<br />full support.<br />Over the coming year we will also be remembering the<br />sacrifices o: E other allies in the defence of Australia. I<br />would mention in, particular the Dutch forces which fought<br />here. The government has recently agreed to contribute to<br />the erection of a memorial in Canberra to those forces.<br />And in these commemorations we will also remember the<br />Japanese, for7 whom the Pacific war was such an appalling<br />tragedy, and such an important rebirth. We will remember<br />not just the Pacific war a war often of great ferocity and<br />cruelty but also the regeneration of Japan after the war<br />and its extraordinary development as an economic power and<br />partner for Australia, and also, increasingly, as a valued<br />political partner in regional afid international affairs.<br />As we move, ever more rapidly it seems, towards the twenty<br />first century it is right that we should remember how far we<br />have come in this great country, who made the ultimate<br />sacrifice that has permitted us our achievements, and<br />reflect for et moment on where we are going.</p>
<p>Nothing is more constant than change: that was true fifty<br />years ago, when John Curtin spoke here, and it is true<br />today. Curtin had to look to a re-orientation in Australia's<br />foreign policy, to putting the economy on a war footing.<br />Fifty years on we have look at those things again.<br />The Australian War Memorial has also had to face the squalls<br />of change, right from the day it was opened. Conceived as a<br />memorial to World War One, this Memorial was of course,<br />opened in World War Two and necessarily had to incorporate<br />a second generation of sacrifice.<br />The story of the way the Memorial has coped or not, with<br />change over the past fifty years, and with the troubled time<br />between 1917, when Bean first thought of the Memorial, and<br />1941 is told in Michael McKernan's fascinating and moving<br />history, Here Is Their Spirit.<br />Suffice to say here that an institution which had not<br />changed with the times would not have been able to<br />commission and publish such a warts and all work.<br />The Australian War Memorial of 1991 is quite different to<br />the one opened in 1941. It has not in any way betrayed the<br />ideals of Bean it has expanded and enhanced them. Bean<br />looked for the best way, artistically and technically, to<br />display the relics and records to their best advantage.<br />He would, I am sure, be delighted and proud that such a<br />splendid venue as the Telecom Australia Theatre would be<br />available for the screening of the Memorial's moving picture<br />heritage. Especially as Bean had encouraged two photographers, Frank<br />Hurley and Hubert Wilkins, to try their hand at moving<br />pictures, an infant artform at that time.<br />Their work, some of which has been shown during the<br />Memorial's recent film festival, is a vivid, almost haunting<br />reminder of the terrible ravages of that war in France and<br />Gallipoli. John Treloar, Bean's friend and director of the Memorial<br />from its inception until his death in 1952, commissioned<br />kilometres of film during World War Two to the extent that<br />the Memorial collection contains some 4000 titles with about<br />1000 kilometres of footage.<br />For many years this magnificent -collection of film material<br />was available to only a few scholars who were able to use it<br />in the Research Centre.<br />Regrettably the great majority of Australians were denied<br />access to an important part of their heritage.</p>
<p>Through the generous support of Telecom Australia that has<br />now changed. I congratulate Telecom in joining forces with<br />the War Memorial in this major project and the Memorial<br />Council and management for the enterprise shown in arranging<br />for this important partnership.<br />I began by saying that the Australian War Memorial is a<br />unique institution more than a museum, more than a tomb,<br />more than a gallery, more than a research facility more<br />than a simple memorial. It is all of those things.<br />Over the past fifty changing years it has become a place of<br />pilgrimage until it has nearly one million visitors a year.<br />While I suppose some of those visitors simply come here<br />because it is one of the places on the tourist trail in<br />Canberra, I am sure that none leave here without learning a<br />little bit more about our Australian history, our collective<br />memories and our stories about being Australian.<br />The Telecom Australia Theatre will make a substantial<br />contribution to this living history.<br />It now gives me much pleasure to formally declare open the<br />Telecom Australia Theatre.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
