<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8629</transcript-id>
    <title>PARTIAL TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, POWERDHOUSE MUSEUM, SYDNEY 25 AUGUST 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/08/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008629.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STEL: 25. Rug. 92 17: 42 No. 016 P. 01/(<br />
3 7<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARTIAL TfRANSCR1PT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J.<br />
KEATING, MP DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, POWERHOUSE MUSEUM, SYDNEY,<br />
AUGUST 1992<br />
Q: We're having a bit of problems here trying to understand<br />
how Chineae boat people are getting into AuStrala and it<br />
Seems Auutralian journalists have a better Intelligence<br />
service then Foreign Affairs and the Indons. Can you explain<br />
that a bit more?<br />
PM: Well I don't know. I think obviously we have a widely<br />
spread news service that is going to pick up information in<br />
other countries and that may reach here before local<br />
Surveillanco produces these things.<br />
Q: Mr Keating, are you concerned about the level of the<br />
Australian dollar?<br />
PM; I'm not out here for a comment about that, one of you<br />
saold something about the Liberal's immigration policy.<br />
Q: Are you happy with the immigration level or would you<br />
like to see a out?<br />
PM: We think that the immigration program's important. We<br />
think that in reducing the level in recent years to around<br />
80,000 we have taken account of economic circumstances and<br />
we've appropriately taken account. But I'm very very<br />
ooncerned about the attitude the Liberal Porty has taken. I<br />
think Mr Howard's hijacking of the immigration polloies of<br />
the coalition that is pushing Mr Ruddock to one side and<br />
demanding that the intake be cut is I think confirming the<br />
general contempt that Dr newson holds for the ethnic<br />
communities In this country. That is he says<br />
multioulturaleim is a mistake. He thinks, Mr Howard thinks<br />
that the intake should bo out dramatically. Wlhat they're<br />
saying, not even subtly, Is that they don't believe in the<br />
migration program, they think multioulturalism is a mistake,<br />
and they basically have nothing but disregard for the ethnic<br />
communitiee.<br />
Q; Why don't you want to talk about the dollar or the<br />
finoncial markets?<br />
PM; ecause I just don't talk to doorstops about the<br />
exchange rate ever, and at doorstops in particular. </p>
<p>TEL: 2<br />
Q: Prime Minister, on the interest Withholding-tax, is that<br />
definitely on the agenda or Is this Just a toing and froing<br />
because there's a problem with your Budget, Belling it?<br />
PM; Well what is on the agenda is that John Hewson's got a<br />
billion tax hike. That's over half the existing income<br />
tax revenue. Revenue raised is $ 49 billion; he wants to<br />
raise nearly $ 30 billion from a consumption tax. We'll give<br />
the Australian people a thirty per cent tax rate without a<br />
consumption tax, and we'll do It from a strong fiscal<br />
policy. The things we announoed last week are basically to<br />
keep the tone on fiscal policy. Now he's got exactly the<br />
same problem. You understand if fiscal policy in 95-6 is<br />
difficult for us, It would be similarly, were he to be in<br />
office, difficult for him. So it We've got to 90y where<br />
we're goiig to raise two billion, so to must he. He must<br />
voy how he would make fiscal policy more receptive to the<br />
tax cuts, that is more able to carry the tax cuts. Aud so<br />
the responsibility is for him not to keep secret his 9genda<br />
for tightening fiscal policy in 95-6, but most particularly<br />
to tell us how in the hell ho' going to fund $ 13 billion<br />
worth of tax outs when all the consumption tax money's spent<br />
on payroll tox and petrol.<br />
ENDS 25. Pug. 92 17: 42 No. 016 P. 02/( </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
