<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3676</transcript-id>
    <title>VIETNAMESE CHILDREN</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/04/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003676.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
* Jj,, AUSTHAL1A<br />
PRM MOHNISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 481<br />
3 April 1975<br />
VIETNAMESE'CHILDREN<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr ' Whitlam, said today that the<br />
Government of the Republic of Vietnam had agreed to<br />
facilitate arrangements for Vietnamese orphans to come<br />
to Australia. In a special message to State Premiers, Mr Whitlam<br />
repeated his appeal for the States to finalise as<br />
expeditiously as possible decisions on applications for<br />
permi ssion to adopt Vietnamese orphans. Children would<br />
be flown from Saigon to Australia by the R. A. A. F. as<br />
soon as the States gave certain guarantees about their<br />
adoption and child welfare procedures in relation to the<br />
orphans who would go to their States.<br />
In his message to the Premiers, Mr Whitlam said:<br />
" The Australian Government is in close touch with<br />
the Government of the Republic of Vietnam through the<br />
Australian Embassy. That Government has now advised my<br />
Government that it is prepared to facilitate arrangements<br />
for the exit of orphan children. There is, however, as yet no<br />
precise figure on the number of children in Vietnam for<br />
whom Australia is intended as destination. We also have<br />
advice that in some cases children will not be accompanied<br />
by documentation normally required for adoption. I am<br />
however in the present critical circumstances prepared<br />
to accept this situation. There remains one further<br />
problem: that-we have no way of guaranteeing prior<br />
to the orphans'departure that their physical and medical<br />
condition will be such that they will necessarily be<br />
accepted by adoptive families. In these circumstances,<br />
therefore, I need your assurance that in the event that<br />
children destined for your State are not chosen for<br />
adoption by approved families your State will nevertheless<br />
receive those children and guarantee their accommodation<br />
and care..." " I should be grateful, therefore, for your agreement<br />
that you will receive the number of children for whom<br />
there are approved families whatever their condition and<br />
that you concur in my Government's action in wajvivA<br />
the normal medical requirements. </p>
<p>4_ -2-<br />
I w'julJ. also be grateful if your State authority responsible<br />
tr adoption couIld mai. ntaiii clos; e liason with the<br />
/' Lt ral ian p. tment o L,. ibor ind Immigration in your<br />
tLe in the norm^." vryV for overseas adoption cases.<br />
L or an. wil for its part, proceed as<br />
qiuickly s r. idc keep in touch with the<br />
situation in Vietnam Lhrough our Department of Foreign<br />
Affairs." TOWNSVILLE CANBERRA FAMILIES APPROVED AND AWAITING CHILDREN<br />
FROM SOUTH VIETNAM FOR ADOPTION<br />
NEW SOUTH WALES<br />
VICTORIA QUEENSLAND SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
WESTERN AUSTRALIA<br />
TASMANIA 100 2<br />
D4 f<br />
TOTAL<br />
FIGURES FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF LABOR AND IMMIGRATION AS AT 0. 2/<br />
APRIL 3, 1975. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
