<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5078</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS INTERVIEW: PRIME MINISTER AND PETER NOLAN, ACTU SECRETARY, INTERVIEWED BY RICHARD CARLETON, NATIONWIDE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/06/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005078.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT 119 JUNE 1979<br />
PRESS INTERVIEW:, PRIME MINISTER<br />
AND PETER NOLAN, A. C. T. U. Secretary, INTERVIEWED BY<br />
RICHARD CARLETON, NATIONWIDE.<br />
RICHARD CARLETON<br />
We'll come to the last-minute discussions in a second, Sir,<br />
but to use your words, this futile dispute, and from that, I<br />
think one could possibly draw this futile stoppage on Thursday.<br />
on Friday morning in what way is Australia going to be a better<br />
place as a result of that futile exercise?<br />
PETER NOLAN<br />
Well let's put it in these terms, that we didn't ask for this<br />
diszu-te, we didn't design it but we've got a situation on our<br />
han: ds, where you can't get any sense out of the Western<br />
Auszralian Governm~ ent. Notwithstanding that we've been persisting<br />
over the last week or so, to try and get to a situation of<br />
stec , o; rig back. Even to the extent where Bob Hawke is in contact<br />
with the Premier and his reaction to it was that he couldn't do<br />
anthing about it, that he'd refer it back to the Cabinet in<br />
Western Australia and they considered their position, or<br />
re-considered their position and the only thing we got out of that<br />
was the direction from the Prime Minister to say that the facts<br />
should be known. Now, we've got some reservations about the facts,<br />
but that's the sort of reaction we've been getting for the last<br />
week, that's the sort of reaction the West Australian Trades and<br />
Labor Council's been getting for some time in that State.<br />
RICHARD CARLETON<br />
Mr Nolan we're all Australians in this together. How, on Friday<br />
morining, to repeat the point, how on Friday morning are we going<br />
to be a better place as a result of this futile exercise?<br />
PETER NOLAN<br />
Well, i-f we come to that situation, or if we have to go through with it.<br />
We've made the treat now, I suppose, we'll carry it through. Will<br />
Australia be a better place? I would hope that if that sort of<br />
action doesn't assist the Western Australian Government's thinking,<br />
on z: ulling back from the position that they've placed Australia<br />
in and. I Put this blame squarely with the Western Australian<br />
Government, then I suppose we'll see continuing action until we<br />
break this sort of stupidity that the Western Australian<br />
Gz-7ernm-ent_ is going on with, because what we're up against is a<br />
finda. ental problem, is if we allow a situation to exist in the<br />
State of Western Australia, or for that matter, any other State<br />
of Australia, then the Australian Trade Union Movement won't be<br />
worth a butt.<br />
RICHARD CARLETON<br />
Mr Nolan I detected just a twinge of doubt in your words there,<br />
used if I think a couple of times, is there a possibility that<br />
Thursday will be called off? / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
PETER NOLAN<br />
Well I'm hopeful, I've only just heard that there's going to be<br />
last-minute discussions in Western Australia. I don't know how<br />
far they get up the track there but certainly, I'll be having<br />
discussions with fellow-officers in Canberra tomorrow.<br />
RICHARD CARLETON<br />
You are coming to Canberra tomorrow, are you?<br />
PETER NOLAN<br />
Yes, I've only just made those arrangements in the last few<br />
RICHI: ARD CARLETON<br />
This is at Mr Fraser's invitation?<br />
PETE? NOLAN<br />
Yes, and we'll be carrying on discussions with the Cabinet,<br />
hopefully to try arnd avoid this sort of situation that's going<br />
to exist in Australia, from Thursday on, because Thursday is not<br />
a once situation because it could develop into all sorts of other<br />
actions being taken by the Trade Union Movement.<br />
RICHARD CARLETON<br />
Now what do you expect Canberra and Mr Fraser to do, to placate<br />
you?<br />
PETER NOLAN<br />
Well, we've had those sorts of discussions with, or I have had<br />
discussions with the Prime Minister and also the Acting Minister<br />
for Industrial Relations and I'm told at that stage they couldn't<br />
intervene and I accept that situation. But I believe that they<br />
co-ald be more positive in talking with -their colleagues in<br />
Western Australia to try and bring about a resolution of this<br />
particular problem.<br />
R 7 1HARD CARLETON<br />
Wha7-, do you want Mr Fraser to give Sir Charles Court a beat<br />
about the ears, so to speak?<br />
Well, I'm not putting it in that sort of childish terms. But I<br />
thi. nk they could be more direct, more positive in their approach<br />
than what they have been up to date.<br />
RICHARD CARLETON<br />
Like what? / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PETER NOLAN<br />
Just trying to talk some sense into the West Australian<br />
Government and the Cabinet. Because what we're saying is<br />
we're not asking themn to drop the charges, I think we've gone<br />
past that at the present moment but if we can get a clear<br />
undertaking. As I've said on several occasions over the last<br />
two or three days, if we get a clear undertaking from the<br />
Western Australian Government that on the first day of sitting<br />
on the next Session of the Western Australian Parliament, that<br />
they intend to amend the Police Act, to remove those obnoxious<br />
words, as we see -them, then I believe that we can get to a<br />
settlement of this sort of a situation that we're facing up to<br />
on Thursday.<br />
R-ICHiARD CARLETON<br />
Mr -Nolan, in his Office in Parliament House an hour or two ago,<br />
Mr ?' Iraser said that he did not believe that the A. C. T. U. really<br />
thcu~ ht that its right, or unionists right to assembly was under<br />
threat by virtue of this West Australian Legislation. Is that<br />
the way it is?<br />
PE= R NOLAN<br />
That:' s not entirely true because what has happened in Western<br />
Australia and I don't think I've got time to go through<br />
eve ry detail. What did happen was that a meeting was held and<br />
even the Police in Western Australia who are carrying out the law<br />
and I've got no complaints with the Police, but how that Act and<br />
how those provi S4ons have been carried out Western Australia since<br />
it came in 2 years ago, when the Trade Union Movements saw,<br />
foresaw the problems it could create so far as the Trade Union<br />
Movements concerned was rubbished at that time by the Court<br />
Government in saying that this would never happen. We find that<br />
the Police have been administering the law over there on the<br />
basis that if the Trade Union Movement wanted to have a March<br />
and that's what they were concerned about, Marches. They weren't<br />
concerned about meetings and that being * the spirit of the<br />
Legislation, hcw it was being carried out in Western Australia,<br />
we f'ind then that a meeting being held in a country town in<br />
Western Australia, where Laurrie Carmichael is invited at the<br />
last, minute. We find then, you know this is the whole basis of<br />
the thing is that-we find then that the action being taken<br />
aaffst aTrade Unionist, not two, as has been reported by the<br />
medi-a but in fact ] 3 Trade Union officials of varying political<br />
persuasions. CARLETON<br />
Mr Nolan, I thank yo u very much indeed for your comments. I<br />
invite you, if you wouldn't mind to just remain in the Melbourne<br />
Studios for a few moments and if I could now introduce from<br />
Canberra now, the Prime Minister and suggest to you Mr Fraser,<br />
in explaining that you've been fishing on a holiday and thank<br />
you very much for coming in, suggest to you that Mr Nolan put<br />
forward a very reasonable sort of case there, would you<br />
like to respond to what he said? / 4 </p>
<p>4-<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I think Mr Nolan, in many conversations I've had with him and I<br />
hope this doesn't condemn him, is a very reasonable person who<br />
likes to deal with a matter on its merits. But on the advice that<br />
I've had I think this whole matter now has got far beyond the<br />
particular dispute which first caused it. I'M not seeking to<br />
defend a particular law but I think -that as I've been advised<br />
some explanation, or a particular explanation ought to be given.<br />
Well over 500 applications have been made under the law and as<br />
I'm advised all granted, many of them to the Trade Union<br />
Movement and the Labor Party. I think overwhelmingly, anyway<br />
because the Trade Union Movement and to the Labor Party granted.<br />
On this case, as I'm told, officials said you know, can we have<br />
a ma.-rch, or have a meeting and was told that they should apply in<br />
wri1ting and as I'm advised that application in writing wasn't<br />
and that's the only thing that you know,-if that had occurred<br />
th; anr this whole wretched business would not have arisen.<br />
RD TiCA RD CARETON<br />
Such a petty thing though, such a petty thing bringing the nation<br />
to a stop.<br />
PP22, MINISTER<br />
Well, exactly but you know, why wasn't that application made in<br />
w-riting? Now if that's a correct interpretation of the facts,<br />
it seems-apparently under the law that it has to be made in<br />
writing but not imuch in advance, it can be done much at the last<br />
minute aand it Seems to me that one needs to ask why didn't<br />
somebody write out on a bit of paper, we want--<br />
RICHARD CARLETON<br />
But that's all behind now Sir what Thursday?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
That was still a petty thing, not making that application in<br />
writing and whether that was decided or not, I don't know but<br />
I do need to say that the decision taken by the Australian<br />
Council of Trad e unions in support of industrial action, which<br />
could on a continuing basis lead to bans on the export of major<br />
C= EC Itie" s,, thweh ich could, at request of the Unionists in<br />
Western Australia, lead to concerted bans on the State of<br />
Wa-stern Australia.<br />
RT~ ARDCARLET ON<br />
No one doubts -the seriousness of it, one's looking for a solution.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Well, exactly but I think it needs saying that those actions are<br />
far out of proportion to the nature of the dispute itself and that<br />
needs to be kept in mind because I really don't believe that<br />
anyone thinks that the right of assembly, the right to meet and<br />
the right to march is under threat in Australia. </p>
<p>RICHARD CARLETON<br />
Mr Nolan seems to be saying though Sir, that if you can produce<br />
for him a promise from Sir Charles Court that on the first day of<br />
the Sitting of the Western Australian Parliament this provision<br />
will be removed that then there's no need for the disaster on<br />
Thursday. PRIME MINISTER<br />
That's a commitment that one would have to get out of the Western<br />
Australian Government. Sir Charles Court has said that the<br />
provision will be reviewed and it seems to me that that statement<br />
has passed through the air and has not been given due weight.<br />
I've also indicated of course, that I would believe that there<br />
is going to be a dabate in the Western Australian Parliament<br />
abcat it because if the Government doesn't initiate one the<br />
Cpzos~~ oncertainly will.<br />
RICEA-? D. CARLETON<br />
Put vourself in the position of a Union Leader who is going out<br />
to his Members and saying well, Sir Charles Court has said that<br />
he'll review this matter so therefore we shouldn't go on strike<br />
on Thursday. From-i Mr Nolan's point of view and from the<br />
membership of the point of view, they want Sir Charles<br />
Court to say that it's going to be withdrawn. Now if you can<br />
produce that, you save the nation.<br />
PRTME MINISTER<br />
Now, wait a minute. That may well be so, but there are some<br />
otlh-er aspects of this. Threats have been made of a very real<br />
kind and its not always the best way to get a result out of a<br />
Government. It's not always a responsible use of power to<br />
indicate that you intend to use the undoubted power that Trade<br />
Unions have and I believe that one of the results of the<br />
general public and the tens upon tens of thousands of trade<br />
urnionists that a weapon has been used against Australia and<br />
against the pecple of Western Australia in particular, which is<br />
out of all proportion to the nature of the dispute and I think,<br />
ncw but wait a minute, wait a minute.<br />
-2 -n RD CARLETO<br />
Let me correct your grammar there Sir, is to be used, hasn't<br />
been used yet it's-going to be used unless you step in.<br />
T S 7~'<br />
No, not unless I step in. It's a question of. No, this is one<br />
of the things we're talking about tonight. So many people<br />
believe that the Commonwealth has power to resolve industrial<br />
disputes when very often that power resides in the hands of a<br />
State Government and not in the Commonwealth and you need to<br />
understand that this is the position at the moment and I believe<br />
that the Trade Union Movement has done itself irrepairable harm<br />
by seeking to involve the whole of Australian major export<br />
industries and maybe the possibility of a very real ban on trade<br />
and commerce with Western Australia as a result of this particular / 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
dispute and I don't for one moment wish the union movement that<br />
harm but on my judgement the people of Australia will believe<br />
that a weapon of massive proportion is being used and the<br />
original dispute does not in any sense merit that.<br />
RICHARD CARLETON<br />
It can be stopped though Sir, if you would produce from Sir<br />
Charles Court a promise to withdraw this legislation as Mr Nolan<br />
just said.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
You also know quite well, that Sir Charles Court is not in<br />
Australia and Sir Charles has said that this matter resides in the<br />
hand's of his own Cabinet in Perth. Now, I think that it would<br />
have been very much better if people could have stood back a little,<br />
it'= worth noting that there was going to be a massive dispute<br />
on ursday anyway. The AMSWu and other major unions, MetalWorkers<br />
Uni: n was having a major dispute on a wage case and they decided<br />
to do that anyway. To defy Arbitration and to say look we want to<br />
supcrt it by industrial muscle when they ought to be going to<br />
the Arbitration Commission and putting their case there and that<br />
the . erits determine the issue and not industrial strength. So<br />
there was going to be a major dispute on Thursday involving many<br />
people right around Australia in any case.<br />
RT-ARD CARLETON<br />
The opportunity is there to kill two birds with one stone?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Oh look, do you think that the Metal Workers won't continue with<br />
their dispute?<br />
RICHARD CARLETON<br />
It would look pretty silly if they went out this Thursday after<br />
getting a promise to withdraw the law.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Well, I think you've got to understand that the processes of<br />
r. ev i hn ave to be undertaken and Western Australia has indicated<br />
qu; t-e plainly that it is going to. Peter Durack, our Attorney-<br />
General will be talking with Mr Metcalfe, Western Australia<br />
co Dt as soon as Mr Metcalfe comes back from overseas. He<br />
w have had these discussions earlier. Well, sometime during<br />
the course of tomorrow, I'm not sure what time his plane gets in.<br />
Those discussions will have taken place earlier if Mr Metcalfe<br />
had been in Western Australia but he wasn't and so the Commonwealth<br />
Government I have had discussions with Mr. O'Neil and Ian Viner has had<br />
many discussions with Mr. O'Neil on this particular issue. / 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
PRIME MINISTER ( continued)<br />
But again, I come back -to the point, the weapon that is being<br />
used is out of all proportion to -the nature of the dispute,<br />
to the nature of the complaint. Against the background of<br />
the Metalworkers and one or two other unions wewere going to<br />
have a national stoppage anyway on Thursday. It makes one<br />
wonder whether or not there aren't some people almost take a<br />
delight in this. I know quite well that Mr. Nolan is not he<br />
said he doesn't want a dispute and I accept that totally and<br />
absolutely. C APT. F TO0N<br />
I will come back to Mr. Nolan in a few moments sir, but just<br />
may end off our segment by asking you; what is your<br />
Government doing to stop the petrol disaster that is about<br />
to i-nCHict itself, or now inflicting itself on N. S. W.<br />
PR-MIN ISTE R<br />
Well, a number of things are happening. There will be a meeting<br />
between the Chafil-ian of the N. S. W. Industrial Commission and<br />
Sir-! John Moore, the Chairman of the Arbitration Commission,<br />
tororrow.<br />
CARLETON Mr. Wran though?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Oh Wi th our consultation and all the rest. This matter is<br />
under Federal jurisdiction. It's basically under the State<br />
jurisdiction, I said Federal. But the dispute has arisen<br />
because as I am advised both the N. S. W. State Government and<br />
the State AWU want certain elements of the Kurnell oil Refinery<br />
worker's case to be under the N. S. W. jurisdiction.<br />
CA. PLETON<br />
What are you doing to solve it? What are doing to get the<br />
petrol flowing?. You are the leader of the country.<br />
I th. ink you need to let people understand what the basis of the<br />
tat is because a particular union, the State AWU,<br />
w-e e er the State jurisdiction and are defying the<br />
determinations that have been made so far that the whole oil<br />
industry ought to be under the Federal jurisdiction. Now the<br />
Commoonwealth very strongly supports that because we believe<br />
that having a State jurisdiction and a Federal jurisdiction<br />
cutting across industries makes no sense whatsoever. I had<br />
earlier written to Premiers on matters that were related to this<br />
but today the Commonwealth decided that we should put to the States,<br />
to the trade union movement and to employers, whether or not<br />
there should not be a referral of powers to the Commonwealth so<br />
that in the future there could be one industrial jurisdiction. / 8 </p>
<p>8<br />
PRIME MINISTER ( continued)<br />
It could be done for a trial period of three years if<br />
people like, because there have been many disputes caused<br />
by jealousies between a jurisdictions, people leap-frogging,<br />
people in the State jurisdiction getting a higher award,<br />
people in the Federal jurisdiction therefore being aggrieved.<br />
CARLETON That does nothing to get petrol flowing in N. S. W. tomorrow though?<br />
PR1._ E MINISTER<br />
This-doesn't do anything to help get petrol flowing in N. S. W.<br />
tomC:-row. This situation may well never have arisen if<br />
Mr. Wran had not given moral support to the State AWU to break<br />
ou-cf the Federal jurisdiction. He knows that very well indeed.<br />
No-w, hat doesn't help for tomorrow. But if there is going to<br />
be ptrol flowing in N. S. W. it is the State Government that has<br />
emer-ency powers in these circumstances. It is the State<br />
Government that is using those emergency powers to ration petrol,<br />
who could be using those emergency powers although I believe<br />
that should wait until the hearing which is tomorrow afternoon<br />
at 2: 00 o'clock who could be using and maybe should later on<br />
be using those emergency powers to get people back to work.<br />
There are 400 people in a State union that are holding the<br />
whole of the State of N. S. W. to ransom. I haven't heard Mr. Wran,<br />
at any point, say, throw the weight and moral authority of his<br />
Government against those 400 people holding up the whole State<br />
of N. S. W.<br />
CARLETON Apart from the long-term referral question, whi:-h is a big and<br />
complex issue, for the immediate problem in N. S. W. though is it<br />
the case that your are impotent?<br />
P_ RIU MINISTER<br />
The power is within the N. S. W. jurisdiction, yes it is. It is<br />
within Mr. Wran's emergency powers. He understands this and<br />
he knows it. Again, I believe the tragedy is that over a<br />
-icant period the N. S. W. Government has given its moral<br />
support to a breakaway section to try and break out of the<br />
Federal jurisdiction which would lead, even within N. S. W. itself,<br />
s-. e o the i-ndustry under the Federal award and some of the<br />
i-_ 3-try under a State . award. That in itself would have the<br />
seeds of discontent and disruption for one moment the<br />
Federal people would be ahead, the State would fight to catch<br />
up and they would jump ahead and there would be continual<br />
disturbance in a very important industry. Now, we've even tried<br />
to assess, to see, to what extent it might be possible to help<br />
N. S. W. from other parts of the Commonwealth, but petrol supplies<br />
are tight right around Australia and that means if any State<br />
was to help to get extra petrol into N. S. W. it would probably<br />
have to use its own emergency powers, impose rationing in its<br />
own State, to divert supplies to N. S. W. / 9 </p>
<p>9<br />
CARLETON Mr. Fraser, I thank you on that point, and I am going to go<br />
back to Melbourne, but could I just ask; are you going back<br />
fishing tomorrow or not?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I think that might well be doubtful. There will be discussions<br />
tomorrow morning with Peter Nolan and such other of his<br />
colleagues as he wants to bring to Canberra with him. Ian Viner<br />
and one or two others of us will be involved in that.<br />
There will be another meeting of Federal Cabinet tomorrow<br />
afternoon, certainly those Ministers that are available or<br />
presant today, to assess the situation again tomorrow afternoon.<br />
Ta:-_ e at the moment is on that houseboat in Eildon, and whether<br />
I get back there or not at the moment I think is very much<br />
ocen to doubt. 000---<br />
( MR. NOLAN INTERVIEWED FOLLOWING INTERVIEW WITH MR. FRASER)<br />
A. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
