<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5294</transcript-id>
    <title>THE WOOL DISPUTE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/03/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005294.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-1,, USTRA<br />
PRIME MINISTER A~ A<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY,-14 MAR 118<br />
THE WOOL DISPUTE<br />
The Government, woolbrokers and growers met today for<br />
a very full dicusssion concerning the damaging and critical<br />
wool industry dispute involving the Storeman and Packers<br />
Union. The organisations represented were the Wool Council of<br />
Australia, the National Farmers Federation, the Australian<br />
Woolselling Brokers Employers Federation and the National<br />
Council of Woolselling Brokers of Australia.<br />
In the discussion today, everyone agreed that the industry<br />
needed to maintain its determination to uphold the arbitration<br />
system and to ensure that the dispute was resolved as soon as<br />
possible.. Everyone at the meeting agreed not to accept the blackmail<br />
being pursued by the Storernen and Packers Union. As a result,<br />
the parties camne to a number of specific agreements, which<br />
would be applied progressively from the beginning of the next<br />
working week, Monday 17 March, unless an agreement resolving<br />
the dispute was reached over the weekend. In this context,<br />
the meeting noted that a conference called by the Conciliation<br />
and Arbitration Commission would be meeting tomorrow to discuss<br />
these matters. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
The brokers told the Government that present circumstances,<br />
in which the normal roster of sales had been disrupted since<br />
before Christmas, would make it necessary to cease forthwith all<br />
woolstore operations unless the strike in Melbourne and Sydney<br />
ceased immediately and normal work resumed in all woolselling<br />
centres. Amongst the reasons given was the absence of effective<br />
international buying support as a result of the forced cessation<br />
of sales. The point was also made -that it had become increasingly<br />
difficult to ensure satisfactory standards of clip preparation<br />
because of the current dispute.<br />
The brokers agreed that if the dispute still continued<br />
after the weekend, they would withdraw, the facility of deducting<br />
union dues and would withdraw over-award payments. The<br />
brokers also said that they would continue with the<br />
preparation of the case for deregistration. The Government<br />
said that as soon as that case was lodged it would give full<br />
support. The meeting put to the Commonwealth Government that it<br />
should bring down export regulations which would enable it<br />
to control the export of raw wool. -The purpose of those<br />
regulations would be to make sure that the industry as a whole<br />
had a unified approach to the dispute, having regard to the<br />
gross disruptions to normal trade that had occurred. The<br />
Government, for its part, undertook to prepare those<br />
regulations speedily. The regulations would be ready by next<br />
Tuesday. The Wool Council of Australia, the National Farmers<br />
Federation, the Australian Wool Selling Brokers Employers<br />
Federation, the Natonal council of Woolselling Brokers of<br />
Australia, and the Government, recognised that this request to the<br />
Government, and decision by the Government, would bring the </p>
<p>9. whole industry to a halt, pending a resolution of the<br />
dispute. The Government and the organisations represented at<br />
today's meeting all mutually supported, and were committed<br />
to maintaining, all the foregoing measures.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
