<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9213</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP, INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN, &quot;A CURRENT AFFAIR&quot; CHANNEL 9, WEDNESDAY, 4 MAY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/05/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009213.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN, CURRENT AFFAIR", CHANNEL 9,<br />
WEDNESDAY, 4 MAY 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: we've had nearly a couple of million job _ growth in the 1 980s and we<br />
have held those jobs, but we didn't grow enough jobs to take<br />
everybody up and we have lost some as well. We lost some jobs,<br />
largely we kept the 1980s employment gains, but what happens in<br />
every recovery is that the new entrants to the work force are rarely the<br />
long-term unemployed.<br />
RM: Now, you have got to live with this, of course, you said back in 1983<br />
you said that you inherited the worst recession in 50 years with three<br />
quarters of a million people unemployed. Now we have got almost a<br />
million unemployed.<br />
PM: Yes, but in those days we had a work force of 6 million and now we<br />
have got a work force of 8 million. So we have put 2 million jobs in<br />
during the period, Ray. Now, sure unemployment is too high and the<br />
economy is now growing reasonably strongly and we have seen nearly<br />
a quarter of a million jobs created this year. But, the problem is as in<br />
the 1 980s, the people who go into those jobs are not the long-term<br />
unemployed. Someone who has been out of work a year or eighteen<br />
months starts to lose their self esteem and their confidence and the<br />
employers think that they are not employable. So, this is focussed to<br />
pull them up and give them a chance.<br />
RM: Well, you talk in this paper of half a million out of work by the turn of<br />
the century, is that the figure for the hard core unemployable?<br />
PM: No, we are saying that if we do nothing there will be 300,000 people,<br />
long-term unemployed still out of work by the turn of the century<br />
which is too much.<br />
RM: The figure is half a million. </p>
<p>PM: We are looking at the prospect of getting to 5 per cent unemployment<br />
by the end of the century.<br />
RM: And with the normal rise in the work force that would be about half a<br />
million wouldn't it?<br />
PM: No, it would be much more. It would be well over one million, Ray.<br />
RM: All right, how does that sit then if you accept that more than a million<br />
are, in fact, going to be out of work, how does that sit.<br />
PM: No, sorry, well over one million jobs will be created to get down to<br />
around 5 per cent by the end of the century.<br />
RM: And is that figure about 300,000 out of work by the end of the century<br />
or 500,000?<br />
PM: Well, 5 per cent of the work force then would probably be about<br />
500,000 4 to 500,000.<br />
RM: PM, how does that set then with you claim that in fact every Australian<br />
who wants a job can have one?<br />
PM: Well, it is the time people are in the pool, Ray. Let me give you an<br />
idea about this. By the time we got to the end of the growth phase of<br />
the late 1980s we still had unemployment of about 6.5 per cent, but the<br />
average duration in the pool was only a few weeks. I think three<br />
weeks on average from memory. The problem we have got here is a<br />
long tail of people who have been forgotten. They have lost their<br />
esteem, their skills and their job readiness. This is about picking them<br />
up, intensively case-managing them, training them and placing them in<br />
a job.<br />
RM: All right, but again with respect, to say that every Australian who wants<br />
a job can have one under this program doesn't it sound a bit like Bob<br />
Hawke's ' no child in poverty in 1990'?<br />
PM: No, what we are saying is that the aim should be that if we can grow<br />
the Australian economy quickly enough that we ought to be able to<br />
take up more than just simply new entrants to the work force. We<br />
ought to be able to buy down, wear down, the pool of unemployed.<br />
RM: This is as you say, if this is the best of all possible worlds, if business,<br />
if unions, if the unemployed work with you and if we don't have a<br />
disaster.<br />
PM: Yes, but remember what we are doing here. We will be case<br />
managing, we'll have somebody in the CES or a private case </p>
<p>management business case managing personally over half a million<br />
individual people.<br />
RM: How is that possible without an army of public servants?<br />
PM: Well, there will be a lot of people involved in that, I wouldn't say there<br />
would be an army involved. There will be a lot involved, but unless<br />
you actually take somebody in and talk to them, know about their<br />
personality, about their qualifications, about their work experience,<br />
about their education, it is not really possible You see in a rigid<br />
national system which to some extent is what we've had, somebody<br />
who turns up at a CES counter, say somebody 45 years of age, might<br />
have two or three children, he's just been caught up in a system and it<br />
doesn't really find out their skills and place them properly.<br />
RM: But we accept that and it is a dreadful situation for those men and<br />
women in that situation, but 300,000 people have got to have<br />
individual case management.<br />
PM: 500,000.<br />
RM: 500,000 individual case management.<br />
PM: Next year 504,000.<br />
RM: All right, what about the training wage you talk about. How much is<br />
that going to be?<br />
PM: That will be decided in the next week or so with the ACTU. There are<br />
three principal elements to this Ray. There is a job compact for the<br />
unemployed of 18 months or more. Then we have got two things on<br />
the youth side:-the Youth Training Initiative for young people<br />
unemployed under 18. We-Nil-case mana ge . every young person<br />
unemployed under 18. That is, every young person in this country<br />
who is under 18 years of age and unemployed, we'll pick them up and<br />
speak with them, train them and case manage them. The other<br />
element is Entry Level Training. We are going to start vocational<br />
preparation in Years 11 and 12 at school. That is, away from school<br />
on the job training during school years Years 11 and 12 and the<br />
training wage is an attempt to engage another 50,000 trainees and<br />
also pull kids in from their last school years and skill them.<br />
See, the great change Ray, I think, people need to remember, is when<br />
you and I were teenagers there were many jobs for unskilled people<br />
to 20. That is all done today by computing equipment. The sort of<br />
industries, the clerical jobs, and a lot of the message carriers; all that's<br />
gone. So, now what we have to do is regard 1 5-19 as a period of<br />
vocational preparation. We want 95 per cent of kids completing<br />
secondary school by the Year 2000. </p>
<p>4<br />
RM: All right Prime Minister, let me just get specific for a moment then. We<br />
had last night we spoke to a man in Launceston who heads the<br />
Unemployed Workers Union. He has been on the dole for ten years.<br />
Have a listen to what he said and tell me how the White Paper is going<br />
to effect him. The fact is that the jobs just aren't out there and it is about<br />
time you know, I just get sick of playing the game and<br />
pretending, going along with this fiction that the jobs are out<br />
there if only I knew how to write a better job application letter or<br />
I knew how to apply for a job. I was trained for one of these<br />
jobs that didn't exist.<br />
RM: But would you do any job? Get fair dinkum, would you<br />
do any job if someone rang up tonight?<br />
No, I wouldn't just do any job. No, bugger it. Why should I?<br />
I mean, I'm not going to do a job that pays terrible wages or has<br />
got terrible conditions. I am a human being, I'm not a slave.<br />
RM: Prime Minister, you have said today that you are going to get tough.<br />
Will he have a choice or will he have to take the job you give him?<br />
PM: He will be a job compact person. He would be intensively case<br />
managed, there would be a training course recommended for him and<br />
there would be a job subsidy and if he doesn't take the job, under this<br />
proposal there is a reciprocal obligation on the part of the unemployed<br />
person to take any reasonable job offer.<br />
RM: Or he goes off the dole?<br />
PM: There is a set of penalties then where then he loses so many weeks<br />
for the first time he refuses and a greater number of weeks for the<br />
second time and it goes on in that vein.<br />
RM: It is not up to him to decide whether he accepts the wages or the<br />
conditions. He has to take what he is given finally?<br />
PM: Well, he has got to take what he is given because what he is given will<br />
be, because of the case management something that will suit him and<br />
if he is unskilled, I mean probably his reason for not being able to find<br />
a job is because the economy has changed from an economy that<br />
used to have unskilled jobs and many of them, to an economy now<br />
which has got many more skilled jobs.<br />
RM: He says in fact, he lives in Launceston and he says there are no jobs<br />
in Launceston. If you find a job in Burnie or Hobart would he have to<br />
go there? </p>
<p>PM: No, this would be one that is within reasonable distance of where one<br />
lives.<br />
RM: But, there are hundreds of country towns around Australia like this.<br />
You say that most of the jobs are going to come out of the private<br />
sector. They say these country towns, I'm sorry, there just aren't any<br />
jobs.<br />
PM: There is never going to be an evenness of jobs right throughout the<br />
country Ray, but in every classic recovery particularly where you have<br />
got a high profit share in the economy and wages set right which we<br />
have now we will get employment growth we have already seen it<br />
as a quarter of a million jobs this year as the economy starts to pick<br />
up. Now, there will be a lot of aggregate employment, but will these<br />
people be part of it and the answer is without this no, they won't be.<br />
RM: All right, on behalf of 950,000 unemployed Australians I wish you good<br />
luck.<br />
PM: Thank you very much, Ray.<br />
RM: Thank you Prime Minister, very much.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
