<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2050</transcript-id>
    <title>SECOND VISIT TO US 1969 - SYDNEY - RETURN PRESS CONFERENCE BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON, ON ARRIVAL AT MASCOT AIRPORT - 14 MAY 1969</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/05/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002050.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
% IEW8 DEf4A.<br />
4BR A V0 SECOND VISIT TO US 1969<br />
SYDNEY<br />
RETURN PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME<br />
MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON, ON ARRIVAL AT MiXC OT<br />
AIRPORT. 14 MAY 1969<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I am not going to be able to tell you anything much. You<br />
realise that, of course, because I will be making a statement to<br />
Parliament and I won't be answering questions concerning the trip<br />
until I have made the statement.<br />
Q. Will there be any surprises, Sir, in your report to<br />
Parliament?<br />
PM: Oh, I don't think so. I hope it will be of interest.<br />
Q. When will you be making your report, Sir?<br />
PM: I am going to try to make it tomorrow night.<br />
Q. How would you describe the visit, Sir?<br />
PM: Well, it was hectic but I believe it was well worthwhile for<br />
a number of reasons which I will be putting before Parliament.<br />
Q. Is it too much to expect an explanation of your Waltzing<br />
Matilda statement?<br />
PM: Why, does it need an explanation?<br />
Q. Well can you tell us what the thinking was at the time<br />
you. made that statement?<br />
PM: My thinking is that Australia has always supported a<br />
resistance to armed aggression, has always supported attempts to<br />
raise material standards of living of the people in the world and 1<br />
would be surprised if anybody thought we shouldn't continue to support<br />
that.<br />
Q. Sir, can you tell us the topics you discussed while you<br />
were with President Nixon? </p>
<p>-2<br />
PM: No. I don't think I should do that either at this point of<br />
time. This is' really a bit awkward because after all I have only<br />
just got back. I have to report to Parliament and I will list all the<br />
topics we discussed and what we said about them and then it will be<br />
a subject for debate.<br />
Q. I am certain Parliament wouldn't mind if you told us how<br />
you wrenched your back horse-Wiing?<br />
PM: I didn't wrench my back horse-riding. . I will tell you<br />
exactly what happened. I had a couple of pressmen up there. Of<br />
course they are all very good men pressmen but there were a<br />
couple of pressmen up there who said " Can we come and have a<br />
drink with you before dinner one nigheand I said, " Yes So they<br />
came and had a drink before dinner and I said, " I've got a bit of a<br />
stiff back. I was riding a rather rough horse today. The next<br />
thing I know I had fallen off the horse and broken my back. and<br />
whatever it is, you've read it:<br />
Q. Sir, while you were away, Senator Fulbright said that<br />
he had no doubt that any US Sena tor would be able to get into either<br />
Woomera or Pine Gap bases. These bases have been denied to<br />
Australian MPs. Have you any comment on this?<br />
P M: No comment.<br />
Q. What was your opinion of this man who is so critical of<br />
the Vietnam war?<br />
PM: Well, I had met him before and I like him. He is a very<br />
forthright sort of a man and it is a pleasure to be forthright back to<br />
him.<br />
Q. Sir, will any US Senators be able to get into these bases?<br />
PM: I couldn't tell you ' that at this stage.<br />
Q. Did President Nixon tell you what he is going to tell the<br />
nation today, Sir?<br />
PM: No, but he will be doing this today, I believe.<br />
Q. Before your official statement?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
Q. H-ave you had any advice, Sir, of anything he is going to<br />
say in it? ,3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
PM: Oh, I think it miould interest Australia but 1 don't believe<br />
it would be anything terribly significant at this point, but I haven't<br />
yet seen it.<br />
Q. Prime Minister will your report to Parliament cover only<br />
your discussions with President Nixon or also, for example, your<br />
discussions with Mr Laird on the Fill?<br />
PM: The Fli will form~ a part of the statement.<br />
Q. Broadly, Sir, how would you sum up your tour as<br />
successful or more successful than you had hoped?<br />
PM: I don't know that it is for me to sum it up. I believe it<br />
was successful. It is for other people to assess it themnselves. I<br />
think it was successful. Indeed, I believe that the statement issued<br />
by the President alone was a fairly successful outcome in the<br />
reaffirmation and underlining of the ANZUS Treaty.<br />
Q. Did you have any disappointments, Sir?<br />
PM: No, I don't think so.<br />
Q. Were there any ma tters that will have to be followed up<br />
in subsequent talks with the President? Were there any things<br />
that were left incomplete by these talks?<br />
PM: I think probably not followed up in subsequent talks with<br />
the President. There are obviously technical matters vmh ich will<br />
have to be followed up.<br />
Q. Any indication when President Nixon might be able to<br />
tour Australia, Sir?<br />
PM: No definite indication, but I hope next year.<br />
Q. Any plans at this stage for returning to the White House?<br />
PM: Gosh no. Listen, I think in this last year approximately<br />
a year I've been to New Zealand, I've been around Asia, I've been<br />
to America, I've been tp England, I've been to America, I've been<br />
to America again. I have just had thirty hours flying back. I would<br />
just as soon stay here for a while.<br />
Q. Sir, to get back to this question of visits of US politicians<br />
to these bases. You said you were unable to tell us at this moment.<br />
Is that because the whole thing was / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PM: No, I can't tell you at this moment.<br />
Q. Sir, do you believe the W altzing Matilda statement will<br />
be politically damaging to you as it was with Mr Holt with his " All<br />
the Way with LBJ"?<br />
PM: No. In fact I would be quite pleased if somebody from<br />
the Opposition, for example, got up and said they didn't believe<br />
that Australia ought to resist aggression, and they didn't believe<br />
Australia ought to go along with people improving material standards<br />
of living. Australia has never reneged from doing this sort of thing<br />
before and I don't see why it should now.<br />
Q. Did it come as a shock to you, Sir, that there was another<br />
major fault with the Fill?<br />
PM: 1 don't know which one you are talking aboutl </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
