<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6019</transcript-id>
    <title>ASSEMBLY OF LIGHT FIELD GUN AT BENDIGO</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/02/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006019.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIMVE MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SATURDAY, FEBRUARY 12 1983<br />
ASSEMBLY OF LIGHT FIELD GUN AT BENDIGO<br />
I am pleased to announce that Bendigo is to become the lead<br />
factory for the manufacture of parts for, and assembly of,<br />
the Army's new Light Field Gun Project Hamel.<br />
Hamrrel involves production of a towed field gun and is the<br />
largest project since Australian manufacture of the<br />
pounder during the 1940s. It involves the manufacture<br />
under licence of a British designed light gun to replace<br />
the existing 1930 vintage 105 mm Howitzer.<br />
The Minister for Defence Support, Mr Ian Viner,<br />
recently announced that the Ordnance Factory in Bendigo<br />
would establish the capability to manufacture major<br />
sub assemblies of the gun and would build and test two<br />
pre-production weapons. That work is already in hand.<br />
As the lead factor for Hamel, Bendigo will arrange the assembly<br />
of 73 guns for the Australian Army from parts made here and<br />
by sub-contractors.<br />
As significant as this project may be, my Government has other<br />
plans for the Bendigo factory.<br />
Ian Viner recently announced that the Naval Dockyard at<br />
Williamstown had been invited to tender for the construction<br />
of two follow-on destroyers of the FFG class.<br />
As part of the Government's policy to maximise Australian<br />
content, the Ordnance Factory at Bendigo will have the<br />
opportunity to become heavily involved in sub-contract work.<br />
Some of the special items of equipment which would involve<br />
the Ordnance Factory are machining of the propeller shaft and<br />
hub. This shaft work will be identical with previous shafts made<br />
at Bendigo for installation in earlier vessels of this type.<br />
Negotiations with Oto Melara of Italy for a licence to build<br />
the 76 nun gun mounts for the follow-on destroyers are close<br />
to finality. These mounts would be manufactured here in Bendigo.<br />
Negotiations are also proceeding with a number of United States<br />
companies to obtain offset work against equipment which would<br />
be supplied by those firms.<br />
It is also expected that this work would include parts for the<br />
guided missile launching system, handling and support equipment<br />
for gas turbine engines and ships generators as well as parts<br />
for small calibre weapon systems. Some of this work would come to </p>
<p>Light field gun 2 12/ 2/ 83<br />
Bendigo. Bendigo would also become involved as a sub-contractor to the<br />
Naval Dockyard in fabricating and madoining work directly associate8<br />
with ship construction. This commitment of the Government<br />
to the Ordnance Factory not only helps ensure its future and<br />
the jobs of the people working here, but facilitates up-grading<br />
of a number of areas of defence technology. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
