<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40841</transcript-id>
    <title>Statement on Indulgence – Terror attack on London</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/03/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Mr Speaker, this morning Australians woke to the shocking news of a terrorist attack at Westminster - an attack on the Parliament, on police, on citizens.</p>
<p>Mr Speaker, it was an attack on Parliaments, freedom and democracy everywhere in the world.</p>
<p>Westminster is rightly known as the mother of parliaments - almost every element of our Parliamentary tradition is modelled on the Parliament of the United Kingdom.</p>
<p>It is the birthplace of our free, parliamentary democracy and the rule of law which sustains it.</p>
<p>When the Palace of Westminster was under attack from the Nazis in 1943, Churchill described the House of Commons as “the citadel of British liberty; it is the foundation of our laws…able to face the possibility of national destruction with classical composure”.</p>
<p>Consistent with this, Prime Minister Theresa May has said that Parliament will resume tomorrow. This will ensure, as Churchill went on to say, that the House of Commons will continue to play “its part in all its broad freedom in British public life”.</p>
<p>We send our heartfelt condolences, especially to the families of the victims, including the police officer murdered by the terrorist as he attempted to enter the Houses of Parliament, and we wish all those injured a full recovery.</p>
<p>Our heartfelt sympathy and resolute solidarity is with the people of the United Kingdom with whom we stand today, as we always have and always will, steadfast allies in freedom’s cause.</p>
<p>And as the Speaker noted we acknowledge the presence of her Excellency, the High Commissioner of the United Kingdom, Menna Rawlings, in the House today. Your Excellency, you have our full sympathy, solidarity and support.</p>
<p>At this stage, Mr Speaker, it appears that four people were killed by the terrorist and around 40 injured – including a woman who resided in South Australia.</p>
<p>Our agencies and our High Commissioner, with whom I have spoken several times, are engaging with the United Kingdom counterparts as the investigation continues.</p>
<p>We praise the quick action of the first responders and all those who came to the aid of the injured. In one example, the British MP, Tobias Ellwood, whose brother had died in the Bali bombings in 2002, in the frantic minutes after the attack, desperately attempted to resuscitate the critically injured police officer who subsequently died as a result of the murderous attack upon him by the terrorist.</p>
<p>This act of heroism is just one of the extraordinary stories that are emerging from this tragedy.</p>
<p>As Prime Minister May said, so powerfully and in language we know reflects the values of Australians as much as it reflects the values of Britons - those first responders rushed towards the danger, at the same time as they called on citizens and civilians to flee.</p>
<p>Australians should be reassured, Mr Speaker, that our agencies are today, as every day, working relentlessly and tirelessly to keep our people safe. We are very alert to the vulnerabilities of places of mass gathering and open spaces and the risk of relatively unsophisticated attacks like that perpetrated in London. We have experienced them in Australia, most recently and tragically in Melbourne.</p>
<p>Keeping Australians safe is our highest priority. It is our most solemn, our supreme obligation.</p>
<p>My Government has and will continue to provide our agencies with the resources and the powers they need at home to protect us and the powers they need to ensure that our armed forces have the ability to kill the terrorists in the field, whatever they may be doing.</p>
<p>But we must be clear eyed about the risk - it is real, and that is why the terror threat level has been set at probable since September 2014.</p>
<p>We work very closely with all our allies including the United Kingdom.</p>
<p>Our relationship, our strategic, our security relationship with the UK is as close as it could be and we have work with many other partners around the world.</p>
<p>Now the aim of the terrorist, Mr Speaker, is to prey on vulnerability and divide us. But we will never let the terrorists win – not on the battlefield, not here at home – we will never change the way we live.</p>
<p>And as I have said before, including when we launched our Multicultural Statement on Monday, Australia is the most successful multicultural society in the world.</p>
<p>A necessary precondition for our harmony is national security - a resolute determination to defend our nation, our people and our values.</p>
<p>Security is the foundation on which our freedoms have been built and maintained.</p>
<p>The fact that we are a secure, diverse, well integrated nation, means we confront these challenges from a position of strength and unity.</p>
<p>And that is why I am so confident when I say that our people are our greatest assets – all 24 million of them. People with much diversity but united as patriotic Australians, proud of our nation - multicultural, safe, secure and free with a shared destiny.</p>
<p>As Prime Minister Theresa May said earlier this morning, the values of British Parliament “command the admiration and respect of free people everywhere.”</p>
<p>And so they do because they are our values too.</p>
<p>We stand, all of us, with the United Kingdom comforted that we share those values – they’re ours - freedom of speech, democracy, the rule of law. We will never give in to terror. We will never stop fighting for our hard-won freedoms and standing resolutely side-by-side with free nations that fight for freedom too, by our side.</p>
<p>Thank you Mr Speaker.</p>
<p><strong>[ENDS]</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
