<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3969</transcript-id>
    <title>Date for Elections and Fraser Ministry</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/11/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003969.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>12 November 1975</strong></p>
<p>The Prime Minister, the Hon. Malcolm Fraser M. P. announced today that the Governor-General had agreed that elections for both Houses of Parliament would be held on Saturday 13 December 1975. The Prime Minister also announced that the Governor-General had sworn-in a Ministry to carry on the affairs of Government, at a ceremony at Government House Canberra.</p>
<p>Mr Fraser said: "following the simultaneous dissolution of the Senate and the House of Representatives by His Excellency, the Governor-General on 11 November 1975 I proposed, and the Governor-General agreed to the following timetable for elections to be held on Saturday, 13 December 1975 for both Houses of Parliament.</p>
<p>Issue of Writs:</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Monday, 17 November 1975 – in New South Wales, Tasmania, Queensland, Victoria, and Northern Territory</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Friday, 21 November 1975 in South Australia, and Western Australia</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Nominations Close:.-Friday, 28 November 1975.</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Polling: Saturday, 13 December 1975.</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Return of Writs: by Thursday, 22 January 1976.</p>
<p>His Excellency, as I understand, informed all State Governors of the timetable and has sought their agreement to it in connection with the election of Senators."</p>
<p>The Prime Minister also said that on his recommendation, the Governor-General had appointed the following to hold the offices mentioned after their respective names and to administer the Departments connected with such offices:</p>
<p>The Right Honourable J. D. Anthony, M. P. to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Overseas Trade and<br />Minister for Minerals and Energy.</p>
<p>The Honourable P. R. Lynch, M. P. to be Treasurer.</p>
<p>The Honourable I. McC. Sinclair, M. P. to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Agriculture and<br />Minister for Northern Australia.</p>
<p>Senator the Honourable R. G. Withers to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Special Minister of State,<br />Minister for the Capital Territory,<br />Minister for the Media and<br />Minister for Tourism and Recreation.</p>
<p>Senator the Honourable I. J. Greenwood, Q. C. to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Attorney-General and<br />Minister for Police and Customs.</p>
<p>Senator the Honourable R. C. Cotton, to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Manufacturing Industry and<br />Minister for Science and Consumer Affairs.</p>
<p>The Honourable P. J. Nixon, M. P. to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Transport and<br />Postmaster-General</p>
<p>The Honourable A. S. Peacock, M. P. to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Foreign Affairs and<br />Ministor for Environment.</p>
<p>The Honourable D. L. Chipp, M. P. to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Social Security,<br />Minister for Health and<br />Minister for Repatriation and Compensation.</p>
<p>The Honourable D. J. Killen, M. P. to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Defence.</p>
<p>Senator the Honourable T. C. Drake-Brockman, D. F. C. to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and<br />Minister for Administrative Services</p>
<p>Senator the Honourable J. L. Carrick to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Housing and Construction and<br />Minister for Urban and Regional Development.</p>
<p>The Honourable A. A. Street, M. P. to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Labour and Immigration.</p>
<p>Senator the Honourable M. G. C. Guilfoyle to be</p>
<p style="margin-left:36.0pt;">Minister for Education.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister said that Mr Anthony  would be the Deputy Prime Minister and that  Senator Withers had been appointed Vice-President of the Executive Council.</p>
<p>In accordance with the undertaking given to the Governor-General, the policies of the previous Government would be implemented and new policies would not be introduced, until an election was held.</p>
<p>" We will, of course, during the election campaign be announcing the policies that we believe to be appropriate for the revival of Australia to bring responsibility and a sense of proper behaviour to Australia's affairs", Mr Fraser said.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
