<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9727</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING, MP NATIONAL PRESS CLUB CANBERRA THURSDAY 24 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009727.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
*** CHECK AGAINST DELI VERY***<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
NATIONAL PRESS CLUB CANBERRA<br />
THURSDAY 24 AUGUST 1995<br />
It's nice to be back.<br />
You may have picked up a comment the other day to the effect that Australian<br />
politics was becoming risk-averse even gutless.<br />
You will understand my outrage at this slur upon my profession.<br />
Keen to defend its reputation, a couple of lively issues notwithstanding, I<br />
decided to come down to the National Press Club and deliver a speech.<br />
Not one of these headland speeches you've been hearing being decidedly<br />
non risk-averse, I am more inclined to the headlong speech.<br />
Or to put it another way, I would like to share with you some thoughts on<br />
where our country is going. What is good and what needs to be improved.<br />
How we might retain the good and make the improvements.<br />
There are several places I could start: with those economic data in the back<br />
pages of The Economist, for instance, where Australia continues to outshine<br />
many of our OECD counterparts in economic fundamentals and is placed<br />
among the top brigade in forecasts for growth.<br />
It is easy to take comfort from the data, notwithstanding the current account<br />
deficit which we must and will correct. The data shows that Australia is doing<br />
very well.<br />
And we should draw satisfaction from that.<br />
Our initiatives have generally been effective. We have got the economic<br />
settings pretty well right. And our approach to the economic and social<br />
equation has been, I think, largely vindicated. </p>
<p>But to draw a sense of satisfaction is not the same as drawing a sense of<br />
complacency. If I have learned one big thing in the past decade, it is that reform never stops<br />
you never entirely get out of the woods, there is always one thing more or<br />
two, or three or even four things.<br />
You never really get to the last chapter. You might sometimes imagine that<br />
you are approaching it and that when you get over the next hill you'll see the<br />
words, " The End", emblazoned in a clear blue sky.<br />
But it doesn't happen. I said up in Roma the other day It's a bit like farming.<br />
You fix the tractor and the generator goes on the blink. You get through a<br />
drought and you have to deal with a flood.<br />
Sometimes it does boil down to simple endurance.<br />
The modern economic contest is a long distance race a very long distance<br />
race. It is like the modern marathon, it gets faster and faster. But unlike the<br />
marathon, it has no finish line.<br />
I agree with what John Prescott had to say on Tuesday. I wish I didn't. I wish<br />
I could say all the reform was over and that we don't need to change any<br />
more. But we do. We need the culture of " continuous initiative" which<br />
John Prescott talks about.<br />
We need it in government, our education system, our public service and in<br />
our businesses.<br />
It is a condition of success in the modern world.<br />
But we should remember that it is also a measure of our success.<br />
The reason we have to go on is that we have come so far already. Far<br />
enough to be a player. Far enough to enjoy some of the rewards and get<br />
within view of greater ones. Far enough to know our potential and our<br />
strengths and weaknesses.<br />
I mentioned marathons: I think there's a lesson to be learned from watching<br />
marathons, and listening to former marathon runners.<br />
They all talk about not losing rhythm up hills and down, over cobblestones,<br />
round corners, through the pain, through the drinks station you have to keep<br />
the same steady stride and your eyes fixed.<br />
You have to keep mind and body and soul together. </p>
<p>When they are together, keeping up is almost mechanical. When they begin<br />
to fall apart, the consequences are rapid and dramatic.<br />
In no tir~ ne you drop out of the leading pack. And very few ever make up the<br />
ground again.<br />
I think this is something like the position we are in. On our own initiative,<br />
talents and hard work, we have joined the leaders.<br />
And we have to stay there. If they go faster we have to go faster.<br />
We have to keep our stride.<br />
If we are to keep up, we need to continuously improve.<br />
If we are to continuously improve, we have to keep everything together.<br />
The basics which have got us this far have to stay in tune.<br />
And by this rather circuitous route I come back to the last time I spoke at the<br />
Press Club. You will remember it was in connection with Working Nation<br />
the Government's White Paper on Employment, Industry and Regional<br />
Development. I remember copping a bit of criticism for comparing it with the White Paper of<br />
the 1940s it was a shameful boast in the eyes of some people.<br />
But it was a more than fair comparison. In fact, if only because contemporary<br />
Australia is a more complex place, Working Nation had to be a statement of<br />
broader dimensions and far greater detail than its counterpart of fifty years<br />
ago.<br />
And it was as much a defining document. It was as much a statement of this<br />
Government's philosophy as the White Paper of 1944 was to the<br />
Governments of reconstruction which Curtin and Chifley led. I hope it will be<br />
as much a stamp of our ambition and achievement.<br />
Working Nation was about keeping mind, body and soul together. I think I<br />
said at the time that it addressed the great issue of unemployment with a cool<br />
head and a warm heart.<br />
It addressed problems which were both specific to Australia and endemic in<br />
contemporary western economies and societies. It addressed them with a<br />
view to maintaining the balance in this country between economic efficiency<br />
and social justice indeed we sought the means to make those two goals<br />
complementary. </p>
<p>As Australian policy had been right through the eighties, Working Nation was<br />
different to the orthodox model of economic liberalisation the model adopted<br />
in a number of other countries and by our opponents.<br />
It took the view that we could be competitive and still look after those on the<br />
margins. We could compete with the best in the region and the world, and<br />
yet maintain our egalitarian values and preserve our social cohesion.<br />
Working Nation was a document for its time, and it was a very good one, I<br />
believe. It has made life easier and opportunity greater for countless<br />
Australians. It will make Australia both more productive and fairer. It will help<br />
preserve the fabric of our communities and families. It is serving hundreds of<br />
thousands of Australians now, and it will still be serving them for a long time.<br />
Working Nation did not suddenly drop from the clouds. Its provenance was<br />
the whole period of reform from 1983. It addressed the imperatives facing us<br />
in the 1 990s, yet it was part of a policy story which includes financial<br />
deregulation and tariff reform, reforms in training and education, the<br />
progressive introduction of a sophisticated social wage, the Accords in<br />
summary, a policy record which reflects Australia's dual commitment to<br />
economic liberalisation and social fairness.<br />
Working Nation built on this story and the philosophy underlying it.<br />
It took a position on long term unemployment which not everyone shared, but<br />
which was logical, moral and consistent with Australia's traditional values.<br />
For all these reasons it will make Australia stronger.<br />
With Working Nation we were not ahead of our time, but we were ahead of<br />
most other countries; among them the United States, where Robert Reich and<br />
many commentators these days complain of a destructive imbalance between<br />
economic and social goals.<br />
Working Nation now seems like a long time ago. You might ask why I'm<br />
reviving it today.<br />
Particularly as one of the weekend columnists wrote that there is no value in<br />
these big policy statements any more? No political value at least.<br />
But of course Working Nation is still operating. It's out there in Australian<br />
communities now.<br />
And there is profound value in major policy statements, including political<br />
value. Policy is the means by which the lives of individuals, families and<br />
communities are shaped. It is the means by which we shape the character<br />
and the future of the nation. </p>
<p>It is the purpose of political life, the only worthwhile measure of political<br />
success, and by far the most significant measure of the worth of politicians<br />
and parties.<br />
It is also the best way to get elected.<br />
I remain in no doubt that, however long they might suspend their judgement,<br />
Australians always make policy their principal measure.<br />
When they judge the Government sometime next year, they will judge it on<br />
the basis of policy. Whatever you the media or we the politicians might think<br />
about our ability to read or influence their views, one way or another the<br />
ultimate test Australians apply will be a policy test.<br />
It is essential to good democratic government that we explain our actions,<br />
that we listen to what people are thinking, that we understand what they are<br />
going through.<br />
And that we are prepared to adjust our strategies when the interests of the<br />
people demand it.<br />
But it's equally essential that we don't confuse the product with the marketing<br />
of it.<br />
Of course we can be criticised for failing to " sell" policies as well as we might<br />
I've no doubt that the criticism is often justified. But don't tell me that what<br />
Australians want most in their lives is another salesman. Don't tell me that's<br />
what they want in their Prime Ministers.<br />
We can also be criticised for not hearing the complaints of large numbers of<br />
Australians and I think very often that criticism is justified too. But don't tell<br />
me that all Australians want from their Government is a good listener.<br />
I've said it a few times good governments listen, but so do bad<br />
governments. In our modern political culture I think we should resist what might well be a<br />
real temptation to confuse good government with good radio and television.<br />
They are not the same.<br />
The essence of good government is not in the listening or in the talking but<br />
in the thinking and the doing.<br />
It was not public relations or spin doctoring which caused total employment to<br />
rise by 380,000 in the year to June, by 680,000 since April 1993. Primarily it<br />
was policy. It was thinking and doing. </p>
<p>It was not PR which provided nearly 400,000 Australians with case managed<br />
assistance to get employment or training, or a 20 per cent fall in the number<br />
of long term unemployed: or a fall of more than 25 per cent among young<br />
long tern unemployed. It was policy. It was thinking and doing.<br />
When Working Nation was delivered, all of us here were in no doubt about<br />
what was the most important issue facing the country it was unemployment.<br />
No one needed reminding about the devastating effects of unemployment on<br />
individuals, families and communities.<br />
None of our imaginations needed prompting when we thought about the<br />
difference between having a job and not having a job.<br />
We all knew that jobs are far and away the best means of distributing wealth<br />
and opportunity; that they are the best defence against alienation and<br />
delinquency; the best measure and the best source of family and community<br />
prosperity and cohesion; the best form of crime prevention; the best<br />
investment a government can make.<br />
I don't think we've forgotten. Even though we've had unprecedented job<br />
growth and a fall in the unemployment rate among the highest in the OECD, I<br />
don't think we have decided that the problem has gone away. I think we still<br />
know that nothing counts as much as jobs.<br />
Yet there has been a shift. Not in those communities where unemployment is<br />
still very high, or in the families where breadwinners or children are still<br />
unemployed. Not among those administering programs or dealing with the<br />
consequences of unemployment.<br />
But in the places where opinion is made, jobs have dropped down a rung or<br />
two on the ladder of what matters. They should stay on top.<br />
As long as jobs stay at the peak of our national ambitions we will know that<br />
we are keeping body and soul together.<br />
We will know that as a community we have kept faith with the spirit of change<br />
in the past decade, and indeed with what we think of as our national<br />
character and traditions.<br />
And that is the best way to succeed.<br />
The effort to marry economic efficiency to social justice and cohesion has<br />
been the means by which we have reached the leading group of nations.<br />
You have to ask -why change it? </p>
<p>If a consensual incomes policy, a partnership between the union movement<br />
and the Government is delivering progressive economic, social and industrial<br />
relations reform if it is a vehicle of our progress why would you ditch it in<br />
favour of a conflict model?<br />
Why change stride?<br />
If the Accords have helped substantially deliver sustained productivity<br />
increases since 1983; a 60 per cent decrease in working days lost in strikes<br />
compared to the previous period and, in the last 12 months, the lowest<br />
number of strikes since records were first collected in 1942; employment<br />
growth of 4.8 per cent in the past year and 2.3 per cent on average since<br />
1983; economic growth which, at 3.7 per cent, one of the highest in the<br />
OECD; and an inflation rate currently less than 3 per cent why would you be<br />
ditching the Accord?<br />
Why, when the Accord has helped create the culture in which change can<br />
take place, in which the imperatives of competitiveness have been<br />
recognised, in which enterprise-based agreements are becoming the norm<br />
and worker superannuation is laying the foundations of a national savings<br />
program why would you ditch it?<br />
The essential contribution of the Accord has been as an inflation mechanism<br />
in which the union movement has delivered wage restraint to help ensure<br />
buoyant employment outcomes and, through this, sustained increased in<br />
household incomes. The effect has been an increase in per capita real<br />
disposable household income of 19.7 per cent since 1983.<br />
Each employment target has been met, underlying inflation has been<br />
reduced, and at the same time Australia has been opened up to international<br />
trade and regional growth.<br />
All of this without industrial disputes and with protection for the most<br />
economically and socially vulnerable.<br />
Why, when you have an effective inflation mechanism in the form of the<br />
Accord, would you ditch it and leave yourself with only monetary policy to<br />
control prices?<br />
You keep the monarchy and you ditch the Accord! It is an amazing<br />
perspective on contemporary Australia.<br />
If we accept that social cohesion and social justice are desirable ends in<br />
themselves, traditional national ambitions and essential aids in the economic<br />
progress we have been making why would you be threatening cuts of<br />
between 5 and 10 billion dollars in government outlays? </p>
<p>It is also reasonable to ask why you would expect anyone to believe that cuts<br />
of this magnitude will not include cuts in government programs in income<br />
support, health, education, and transport for instance.<br />
And why, when the evidence is plain that globalisation and new technology is<br />
tending to increase earnings inequality everywhere, would you compound the<br />
problem in Australia by cutting into the social wage we have built over the<br />
past decade?<br />
In the United States over the 1980s, 70 per cent of the rise in average family<br />
incomes has gone to the top 1 per cent of families; and in the same period<br />
the average real income of the bottom 20 per cent of income distribution has<br />
fallen by 10 per cent.<br />
In Australia very substantial increases in income support broadening the tax<br />
base, introducing fringe benefits and capital gains taxes, reducing the lowest<br />
marginal tax rate to 20 per cent and increasing the tax-free threshold have all<br />
mitigated the tendency towards unequal income distribution. As a result, the<br />
gap is nowhere near as wide in Australia as it is in the United States.<br />
At the same time, the introduction of Medicare, large increases in funded<br />
educational participation, the expansion of child care, targeted public sector<br />
housing and, now, improved income in retirement through superannuation<br />
none of which are taken into account by the usual studies or international<br />
comparisons all narrow the gap in income distribution.<br />
If a sophisticated social safety net is keeping Australian society together<br />
through a period of profound and pervasive change why would you tear<br />
holes in it?<br />
Why would you make the US labour market model Australia's model, even as<br />
the US Labour Secretary is lamenting its inadequacy?<br />
To fix the Current Account? To make an impact on our external debt?<br />
Because they are doing it in New Zealand?<br />
But in New Zealand since they introduced individual contracts in 1991,<br />
productivity has increased by only 1 per cent per annum. In Australia, it has<br />
increased by over two and a half per cent per annum in the same period.<br />
No one in the Government believes that every step we have taken has been<br />
the right step, any more than we believe that all our problems as a nation are<br />
behind us.<br />
We know that the figures indicating that Australia has moved beyond the<br />
realms of recovery into a sustained period of growth do not translate into<br />
ease and comfort for every household and community. </p>
<p>We know that the confidence in Australian sharemarkets, and among<br />
commentators like Chris Caton and Don Stammer, is not felt generally around<br />
the country at the moment.<br />
Don Stammer has been reported as saying that he expected " a long lasting<br />
upswing" that " will take us through to at least... .2000".<br />
The Australian said recently that we may be experiencing " the healthiest<br />
recovery the nation has had". But we know that it does not feel that healthy<br />
in a lot of Australian homes.<br />
We know that there is a lot of uncertainty around. And that there are a lot of<br />
people preying on this uncertainty.<br />
Perhaps this is where we need that capacity for endurance I mentioned.<br />
The Government could do with it to deal with the modicum of frustration<br />
anyone feels when hard won and long sought after success is interpreted as<br />
something much less.<br />
Much more importantly, Australians need it as we all come to terms with an<br />
essentially new kind of Australian economy: an economy in which we have<br />
sustained growth without inflation not a boom, not an environment in which<br />
we substitute inflation for savings, but low inflation sustainable growth.<br />
The uncertainties which people feel are not unique to Australia. In the US<br />
and elsewhere, there appears to be wide concern about the income<br />
distribution gap; about frustrated personal aspirations and inadequate<br />
personal security.<br />
I have talked about the income gap in Australia and I might add the<br />
observation that in Australia the rich are not yet building private roads for<br />
themselves, or employing private police forces and establishing, for all intents<br />
and purposes, a new species of feudalism.<br />
They have not had a government in the past 10 years willing to encourage<br />
the growth of an exclusive and exclusivist oligarchy and an underclass<br />
condemned to permanent and increasing impoverishment.<br />
We have liberalised the economy to encourage opportunity and create<br />
wealth. But we have also pursued a fair social equation and kept alive the<br />
sense of commonwealth.<br />
International comparisions create a context in which our problems can be<br />
better understood, but I know they are small comfort for real insecurities.<br />
Nevertheless, I think that with each successive quarter of growth confidence<br />
will slowly return. We can also reasonably expect a steady improvement in<br />
confidence as the current account begins to improve. </p>
<p>It will take a while for the real and lasting benefits of the reforms to<br />
superannuation to be appreciated, but they will be. And there is genuine<br />
reassurance for all Australians in them they mean greater comfort and<br />
security in retirement and they mean a savings base, and in due course a<br />
savings culture, for the nation.<br />
That sense that the recovery will be short lived can only be laid to rest by<br />
time. The fears about the current account and our external debt will start to<br />
fade as the deficit declines and Australians become aware that solving the<br />
problem is within our reach.<br />
And of course it is.<br />
It is within our reach because of the action we have taken on both the public<br />
and private savings.<br />
We have taken the decisions to restore the Budget to surplus.<br />
As Treasury has shown, the changes to superannuation will lift private<br />
savings by around 4 per cent of GDP over time.<br />
Together, these initiatives mean less reliance on foreign borrowing in fact,<br />
considerably less.<br />
I would very much like to see develop a new phase in the economic<br />
consciousness of Australians. I know it has undergone a remarkable<br />
transformation in the past decade, but I would like to see another one. And I<br />
think it will happen.<br />
Over the next two or three years I believe Australians will not only recognise<br />
that we have entered a period of prolonged growth, but rapidly come to insist<br />
that we stay on this sustainable low inflation path.<br />
I believe we will see a savings culture quickly emerge. And among the<br />
elements of that culture will be a recognition that we will only succeed by<br />
saving and investing wisely, making maximum sustainable use of our<br />
resources, continuing to work hard and committing ourselves to the path of<br />
continuous improvement.<br />
I think John Prescott can feel confident about Australia's capacity to reach<br />
what he calls " champion" status.<br />
The fact is, Australia has already embarked on a process of continuous<br />
improvement at a national level. </p>
<p>There are a multitude of new, well-managed quality firms in Australia which<br />
were born and have thrived because of the internationalisation of the<br />
Australian economy. They were raised in the knowledge that no matter how<br />
good tley are today in their product and their process, they must be better<br />
tomorrow. And the Government is keeping pace. We know we have to both encourage<br />
innovation in the private sector and practice it ourselves. We also know that<br />
the public is understandably cynical when governments talk about their<br />
achievements and their work practices.<br />
But we have kept up the pace of reform and we will maintain it.<br />
This year we negotiated the eighth Accord. Each Accord has built on the<br />
preceeding one. Each one has been designed to meet contemporary needs.<br />
We have maintained the progress in opening Australia to international and<br />
regional economies and improving those environments for trade. From<br />
those first financial reforms of long ago, through the tariff reductions, APEC<br />
and the vision of free trade in the Asia-Pacific we have kept up the pace.<br />
We have progressed from protectionism and industry assistance, through the<br />
adjustment plans for particular industry sectors we have today; to the notions<br />
of innovation, investment facilitation and seeding growth through assistance<br />
to small and medium-sized enterprises which govern our modern industry<br />
policy.<br />
Above all, we are developing the skills of our people which is the foundation<br />
of all successful industry.<br />
One Nation was a great leap forward. Working Nation, and to no small<br />
extent, the cultural policy, Creative Nation, consolidated the gains. The<br />
statement on innovation in industry that we will deliver later this year will<br />
maintain the pace.<br />
We will continue to back our judgment. We will continue to follow an<br />
Australian path to international success.<br />
We take the view that government needs to put a marker out beyond current<br />
best practice, so we are not playing catch-up.<br />
It is a rare government that meets with total private sector approval and we<br />
don't go seeking it.<br />
But we do seek partnerships, common goals, a cooperative spirit. We talk to<br />
business a great deal. We exchange ideas. </p>
<p>But governments have independent roles and capacities. If they do their job<br />
diligently and with a passion, and have no hang-ups about their role, they can<br />
help industry build its competitiveness, they can help it enter international<br />
market places, they can help it win.<br />
Our worst critics will concede that this Government has done a great deal to<br />
translate regional free trade from economic fantasy into a real political<br />
prospect. I think industries therefore, have reason to feel confident that we<br />
count their interests as our own which is to say as part of the national<br />
interest. I began by talking about policy and I will end by it.<br />
I don't mean I will give you the full checklist since 1983. I won't even give you<br />
a resume since 1992.<br />
But I want to say this much.<br />
The big policy statements those big, non risk-averse statements from<br />
One Nation through to this year's Budget, have at their heart something more<br />
than meeting the interests of the sectors of the economy and population<br />
which they specifically address.<br />
I think there is more to them than the effect they have in, say, kick-starting the<br />
economy and creating new national infrastructure as One Nation did; or<br />
creating a stimulus for regional development, as Working Nation did; or a<br />
new deal for Australia's creative artists and industries as the cultural<br />
statement did.<br />
I think, beyond the practical effects we seek from them, good policy<br />
developments pick up on forces at work within the country: I mean things as<br />
intangible as collective needs and ambitions, emerging ideas and<br />
perspectives and they give them concrete force. They give them expression<br />
in the life of the nation.<br />
And the life of the nation should be healthier for it.<br />
I see policy as a process of national reinvigoration and reinvention. I see it<br />
as a process of national character building.<br />
Among the many things One Nation did, I hope, was give expression to the<br />
sentiment that is always there in hard times the fellow feeling, the sense that<br />
we are stronger when we stick together. And in so far as it succeeded in<br />
doing this, I hope the feeling will last us right through the decade.<br />
Working Nation, I believe, gave expression to an Australian sensibility as old<br />
as the nation itself that employment is a birthright and the unemployed<br />
should not be left behind. That this is a fair country and properly a pioneer of<br />
social democracy. </p>
<p>13<br />
I hope Creative Nation will prove to have tapped a vein of creativity and<br />
national pride; that the Native Title Act will be seen in time as an expression,<br />
not of dur collective guilt, but our collective sense of justice and<br />
responsibility; and that before the end of the century the initiative that we<br />
have taken with the Republic will give voice to an Australian spirit and<br />
identity. John Prescott said on Tuesday night " A country must be able to constantly<br />
renew itself if it is to offer its people rising standards of living and larger<br />
opportunities." He said he wanted " A culture of continuous initiative".<br />
I have never welcomed a speech by an Australian business leader more than<br />
this one.<br />
Especially after all the talk about risk-averseness. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
