<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22895</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop at the Superdome, Sydney </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/09/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Andrew Gaze's appointment to the position of flag bearer for the Australian Olympic Team</p>
<p>E&amp;OE……………………………………………………………………………………</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think it’s a wonderful choice. Andrew is a magnificent representative, he represents everything- there’s the family tradition there. He’s competed in so many Games before. He’s obviously a great personality. He has a humility and passionate excitement about the honour that’s been given to him. And I thought the absolutely exuberant, wonderful, the excited way that he reacted was just so heart warming and just demonstrates that he’s the right choice.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>It’s not too often the Prime Minister gets a hug is it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, well I don’t mind! But more importantly I think nineteen million Australians would have wanted to hug him for his spontaneity.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Have you ever been kissed by a six foot seven bloke before?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh now don’t ask me personal questions!</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you yourself seem very excited as the big day draws close.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am. I think I am expressing a collective national excitement. I wandered around Sydney on Monday morning, I did some shopping, and everybody is so engaged and friendly. It’s almost as if for the next few weeks we’re going to be living in a slightly different world, and I think we are. And I that’s terrific because Australians do love their sport, they do see this as a great opportunity to show the world what a fantastic country we have.</p>
<p>And these young men and women here tonight - the uniforms, incidentally, are fabulous, they’re the best Olympic uniforms I’ve seen yet and I’m very delighted that I’ve been honoured and given one – it’s terrific.</p>
<p>But I think the spirit of this, of tonight and the excitement which is obviously being reflected around the community now is what everybody feels.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Any predictions of how many gold medals we’ll win?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look I don’t get into that. I wish them well, I love them all and I hope it’s pile!</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
