<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5241</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE, 4 TREASURY PLACE, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/01/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005241.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT TUESDAY, JANUARY 22, 1980<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, 4 TREASURY PLACE, MELBOURNE<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I will say something first and then I will read a text of the<br />
letter that is being delivered to the Olympic Federation later today.<br />
First I would like to remind you all of the significance of<br />
Afghanistan, why we are concerned and why it is different.<br />
It is a watershed. It does represent the first significant use<br />
of Soviet troops outside what had been accepted as the Soviet<br />
sphere of influence. Czechoslovakia and Hungary, tragic and<br />
horrible as they were, were both in the accepted sphere of<br />
influence of the Soviet Union in Eastern Europe.<br />
Afghanistan was a different case. It was a non-aligned country.<br />
But that did not protect Afghanistan from attack, and that, I<br />
believe, says something to all members of the non-aligned movement.<br />
So, it is a new situation. Now, that does not represent a return<br />
to the cold war. That was a different time and that is past. we<br />
do go into the 1980s with the international scene gravely and<br />
seriously troubled with difficulties of a kind that we hoped had<br />
been put behind us a long, long while ago.<br />
It does not help to use the rhetoric, the language of the past.<br />
That is why I say quite specifically, the period ahead of us<br />
does not represent a repetition of something that occurred once before.<br />
It will be different if, for no other reason that it is in a<br />
different decade and time has gone on very significantly. But it<br />
is also different for one or two other reasons. Over all of this<br />
period, the Soviet Union has been spending about 12 per cent of<br />
its Gross National Product on arms and3 armaments, a very large<br />
expenditure indeed, of a kind I believe that has probably not<br />
been matched by any other count3-y 7 certainly not matched by any<br />
of the democracies.<br />
So, they have been improving the quality, the effectiveness and.<br />
the range of their armaments in both conventional and nuclear fields.<br />
That is a different situation where in the past, during what was<br />
called the cold war and what was known as the West our alliescertainly<br />
had nuclear superiority, and much more nearly<br />
conventional quality than might now be the case.<br />
That again means that it involves a different situation, and as<br />
we believe as we have said, a more dangerous situation. So, there is<br />
a clear-need for us to consult with our regional friends and<br />
partners and also a need for us to consult with major party<br />
principals, the principal actors on the stage the United States<br />
and the United Kingdom in particular.<br />
Andrew Peacock is not going to South East Asia, to India and Pakistan,<br />
and I am not going -to the United States and to the United Kingdom<br />
with any grand design or with a plan to put. We are going to<br />
achieve an exchange of ideas and views on a matter of the utmost<br />
seriousness to all of us: to all people who want to support the<br />
independence of nations, the independence of states, free from / 2<br />
co 0/ </p>
<p>-2<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
domination by others. That is really what it is all about.<br />
So it is for consultations, for an exchange of views, helping to<br />
build a consensus amongst all of those who want to support the<br />
independence of states. If Australia can contribute something<br />
to that, then so we ought.<br />
I have already said that the weight a nation of 14 million people<br />
can put into the scales is very obviously limited, against the<br />
weight that the United States or Europe combines, through NATO,<br />
through the Common Market, can put into the scales is obviously<br />
very significantly limited. But that does not remove the obligation<br />
for Australians to do what Australians can on a matter which is of<br />
vast importance and which could be of infinite importance to our<br />
children and to the people who will live and will want to make their<br />
homes and bring up their families in Australia down through<br />
the generations.<br />
So, consultation alone is the purpose of why we are going overseasto<br />
help to build, if we can, that consensus of independentlyminded<br />
nations.<br />
Now, quite plainly in the discussions today there was a-significant<br />
exchange of views, not only in relation to Andrew Peacock's visit.<br />
He is expecting Cabinet's views to be sent to him. There were<br />
preparatory discussions yesterday between the Foreign Minister,<br />
myself and senior officials, the Defence Minister~ also Michael<br />
MacKellar who is accompanying me to the United States and to<br />
the United Kingdom. There will be confimatory advice going to<br />
Andrew Peacock in relation to that. There was obviously a good<br />
deal of discussion about the nature of the talks that will take<br />
place in Washington and later in London.<br />
One of the matters that we discussed considerably, concerned the<br />
Olympic Games, and I want to reaa you. the text of a letter, shortly,<br />
that will be sent to the Australian Olympic Federation. It sets<br />
out the totality of our view, and I believe it does it in clear<br />
and concise terms. But, before doing that, I want to issue a y7arning<br />
and a plea please don't treat the Olympic Games, itself, as the<br />
issue. The issue is the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan. That is<br />
the thing that is important. That is the kind of thing which we<br />
want tosee is not repeated, and cannot be repeated, anywhere else,<br />
anwhere around the world. The Olympic Games, as events have turned,<br />
has a relationship to that. Yet the Olympic Games themselves are<br />
not the issue. The issue is Afghanistan and the invasion. And so,<br />
please, I hope you can remember that.%<br />
Now, the text of the letter that will be sent to the Secretary of<br />
the Australian Olympic Federation:<br />
I am writing to advise you officially of the Government's views on<br />
the holding of the Olympic Games in Moscow. You will be aware that the<br />
Government takes the most serious view of the Russian invasion of<br />
Afghanistan, and regards it as a grave threat to world peace and to<br />
all independent nations. It also believes that the great majority<br />
of Australians would want their Government to express in strong terms'<br />
our complete opposition to the actions of the Soviet Government. ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
The Government considers that one of the most telling<br />
ways in which the opposition of Australia and other independent<br />
nations to the Soviet actions can be expressed, particularly to<br />
the people of the is by an effective boycott of the<br />
1980 Olympic Games in Moscow by the Olympic Committees of<br />
those nations.<br />
President Carter has recently written to the United States<br />
Olympic Committee urging it in consultation with other<br />
National Olympic Committees to advise the International<br />
Olympic Committee that if Soviet troops do not fully withdraw<br />
from Afghanistan within the next month, Moscow will become an<br />
unsuitable site for a festival meant to celebrate peace and<br />
goodwill. In the event that Soviet troops did not withdraw within<br />
that time he urged the U. S. O. C.. to propose that the Games be<br />
transferred or cancelled.<br />
Our Government takes a similar view and I am writing on its<br />
behalf to ask that the Australian Olympic Committee join with<br />
U. S. O. C. and other National Olympic Committees to express to the.<br />
International Olympic Committee the strong view that if Soviet<br />
troops do not withdraw as suggested, Moscow will become unsuitable<br />
as a site and that the Games should be transferred to another<br />
site or sites or be cancelled for this year.<br />
It is the Government's belief that the Australian Olympic<br />
Committee, our Olympic athletes and our people will fully understand<br />
its reluctance to propose such a serious course but it is quite<br />
satisfied that in the event of the continued occupation of<br />
Afghanistan by the U. S. S. R. an effective boycott of the Games<br />
will bring home to the Russian Government and people, perhaps<br />
in a way no other step could, the great seriousness in the eyes<br />
of independent nations of the steps the U. S. S. R. has taken.<br />
I would also like to assure you of the Government's continued<br />
support of the principles underlying the Olympic Games. This year<br />
the Government has agreed to ton tribute $ 700,000 to the Olympic<br />
appeal and a cheque for the balance of $ 500,000 will be handed<br />
over later this week. Whatever happens it is the earnest wish of<br />
the Government that these monies be used to give cur athletes<br />
the opportunity to pursue their excellence in sport and engage in<br />
peaceful competition with the athletes of other countries. It is<br />
difficult to do this in a country where the Government of that<br />
country has so recently violated the basic principles upon<br />
which the peace and goodwill of nations depends.<br />
It is equally our earnest wish that all possible steps be taken<br />
to preserve and enhance the Olympic ideal, and the<br />
Australian Olympic Committee can be sure of the Government's<br />
full support for its endeavours to that end. Olympic Committees<br />
around the world will no doubt be studying with great seriousness<br />
all the options available. One option, particularly for the<br />
longer term, would be a permanent site in Greece for the<br />
Olympic Games. If that were the desired outcome, this Government<br />
would support it, including with an appropriate financial<br />
contribution. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Question* It is very hard to tell exactly whether or not inaudible<br />
any sort of boycott of the Olympic Games?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well, this letter will be handed around so you can judge, quite<br />
exactly for yourself. We are taking the view, similar to that<br />
which President Carter took with the American Olympic Comimittee,<br />
and that is; we are saying that if the Russians stay in<br />
Afghanistan, Moscow will become an unsuitable site for the 1980<br />
Olympics and in that event, we would be urging the Australian<br />
Olympic Committee, along with the United States Olympic Committee,<br />
and that of any others that can be so persuaded to seek to transfer<br />
the Olympic Games to another site or sites. We have also said<br />
quite plainly, that an effective boycott of the 1980 Olympics<br />
in the circumstances that have unfolded, could well bring home to<br />
the Soviet Union and people, the seriousness of the action that<br />
they took and the strength of the opposition of independent<br />
nations more clearly than any other single act.<br />
Trade sanctions in all these matters can be very important, but,<br />
the Moscow Olympic Games are going to be highly visible to all<br />
the Russian people. It was clearly the objective of the Soviet<br />
government to have all the Russian people know and understand<br />
that the athletes of all the nations of the world were coming to<br />
Moscow, to Russia to pay homage might be too strong a word<br />
but, by their coming, to pay their respects to the Soviet Union<br />
as hosts to the 1980 Olympics. But if that were not the fact, if<br />
there were to be an effective boycott, then the message would<br />
get home to the Russian people and to the Russian government, very<br />
effectively indeed.<br />
And with the President having announced his decision in relation<br />
to it, and with the Australi~ n government having taken the serious<br />
view that it has of these particular matters, we believe we need<br />
to support that-stand.<br />
Question Supposing Australia's athletes and the Olympic Committee don't agree<br />
with the Government and want to go to Moscow? What would be the<br />
Government's attitude then?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well, let's see what happens to the response that has been put.<br />
But I had noticed even on the news screens tonight that some<br />
athletes who are now training and obviously wanting to test their<br />
skills against the athletes of other countries, have been saying<br />
that they believe the appropriate thing would be for the Games<br />
to be transferred to another country in the circumstances that<br />
prevail. I believe that those athletes who have already stated<br />
that kind of view and quite a number have been asked are really<br />
putting matters first which are of great importance to Australia<br />
and to their families; putting them above what must be a<br />
tremendous ambition, a tremendous hope, and a tremendous test for<br />
them of all the time and effort that has gone into becoming<br />
an Olympic athlete. </p>
<p>5<br />
Question Would Canberra withdraw finance?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No. I said quite plainly that I wouldn't. That is in the letter<br />
that I read out. It could be used for other purposes, but it will<br />
be handed over, it will be in the hands and the responsibility<br />
of the Olympic Committee. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
