<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6753</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER AT INTERNATIONAL HOUSE, MELBOURNE, 1 OCTOBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/10/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006753.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JAUSTRLIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRI1ME MINISTER<br />
AT INTERNATIONAL HOUSE,<br />
MELBOURNE, 1 OCTOBER 1985<br />
Warden, Chairman of Council<br />
Distinguished Guests,<br />
Students, I was particularly delighted to be invited to officially<br />
open this dining hall in International House and in so<br />
doing to honour Sam, who was Warden of the College from<br />
the early days of its establishment and construction.<br />
Residential colleges have traditionally had a special<br />
place in university life, and an institution such as<br />
International House has, of course, a particularly<br />
significant contribution to make on the campus of<br />
Melbourne University, serving the needs of both overseas<br />
and Australian students. Like most colleges or halls of<br />
residence, the services it provides to all its residents<br />
extend beyond simple material needs, with students<br />
benefitting from the personal interest, support and<br />
assistance college tutors are able to give them.<br />
Just as importantly, residents are also able to learn<br />
from each other. The informal daily contact of all<br />
residents permits a cross fertilization of cultures and<br />
of ideas. Through this kind of opportunity Australianstudents<br />
are able to broaden their knowledge and<br />
understanding of overseas countries and other lifestyles<br />
and philosophies. Overseas students, in turn, gain a<br />
deeper appreciation of the Australian way of life, and<br />
feel less isolated in our country because of this<br />
interaction.<br />
I believe this kind of exchange is important in terms of<br />
its impact both on academic and on personal development.<br />
This is a personal view which I formed years ago when I </p>
<p>I believe this kind of exchange is important in terms of<br />
its impact both on academic and on personal development.<br />
This is a personal view which I formed years ago when I<br />
was a student at the University of Western Australia.<br />
It was then that I realised the need and advantages of a<br />
residence designed specifically to house overseas and<br />
Australian students, to the benefit of both groups.<br />
Although my early attempt at raising funds for a similar<br />
residence in Perth in the early fiftijes did not come to<br />
fruition, it has not lessened my belief that residences<br />
like International House act to promote excellence in<br />
education as well as better understanding between<br />
countries.<br />
This striving for excellence is a feature of the<br />
Australian education system which my Government is<br />
determined to foster and-develop. The need to maintain<br />
and improve the quality and relevance of Australia's<br />
education system together with the goal of increasing<br />
participation, have shaped the actions taken by my<br />
Government in the education area.<br />
In talking of the relevance and quality of education, I<br />
am not denigrating the traditional role played by<br />
universities as the repositories of knowledge in our<br />
society. Universities have, over the centuries,<br />
provided the focus for the development of intellectual<br />
thought and rigor and for concentrated research into<br />
the manifold issues affecting humanity. Rather, I<br />
believe that the university system has a very<br />
substantial responsibility, and very much to offer in<br />
the years ahead, in consolidating and building upon the<br />
gains we, as your Government, have made to Australia's<br />
economic and social fabric.<br />
Our concern for the quality and relevance of education<br />
has led the Government to initiate inquiries into<br />
tertiary education by the Commonwealth Tertiary<br />
Education Commission under its Chairman, Hugh Hudson,<br />
and into primary and secondary education, under<br />
Professor Peter Karmel. These reports are providing the<br />
Government with a basis for ensuring that the resources<br />
going to education are used most effectively in the<br />
years ahead.<br />
The recent Budget, building on that of 1984, clearly<br />
demonstrates our commitment to education. Despite the<br />
difficult budgetary circumstances and other competing<br />
priorities for funds, funding for universities and<br />
colleges of advanced education has increased by 2.8% in<br />
real terms in 1985. We shall continue to increase our<br />
funding in 1986 and 1987. </p>
<p>Many of you are no doubt aware that the Government has,<br />
over the past year, undertaken a major review of its<br />
overseas student policy. Details of this were announced<br />
earlier this year but it is worthwhile recapitulating<br />
some of the major features, which will be of particular<br />
concern to many associated with International House,<br />
both tutors and students.<br />
Under the new policy the Government will continue to<br />
determine the overall. numbcr of overseas students who<br />
are able to study in Australia, but at a level which<br />
will be subject to regular review. In addition, the<br />
number of overseas students at any tertiary institution,<br />
and in any course, will be fixed within specific limits.<br />
Wfhile we would like to be able to accommodate many more<br />
overseas students, these controls represent a realistic<br />
balance between Australia's role and responsibility as a<br />
member of the regional eommunity of nations, and our<br />
responsibility to respond to the increasing home demand<br />
from students seeking tertiary qualifications.<br />
This new policy will guarantee continued access for<br />
students from neighbouring countries to Australian<br />
education facilities, while providing for a more even<br />
distribution of overseas students over the range of<br />
institutions and courses of study available in<br />
Australia.<br />
An important element of the new policy, not least from<br />
the perspective of students, is the new level of<br />
overseas students charge. As you will be aware, we have<br />
decided that fees should increase progressively, towards<br />
the level of 45% of the total cost of courses. We<br />
consider that this level of charge represents a<br />
reasonable contribution by overseas students towards the<br />
cost of their education, costs which are otherwise borne<br />
by Australian taxpayers.<br />
I hasten to add, however that Australia will of course<br />
continue to meet all the charge for students sponsored<br />
under overseas aid arrangements and from developing<br />
countries, who comprise the majority of overseas<br />
students.<br />
With the aim of improving access for overseas students,<br />
and simplifying administration, the overseas Student<br />
Office has been established to provide a " one stop shop"<br />
or point of contact. The Overseas Student Office is<br />
also responsible for policy advice to Government, and<br />
will draw upon the collective wisdom offered by the net.;<br />
Australian Council for Overseas Students. I personally<br />
believe that this reform is long overdue and I am sure<br />
that those of you from overseas who have battled with<br />
various Government agencies would agree. </p>
<p>Perhaps the most signi ficant aspect, potentially, of the<br />
new overseas student policy is the decision to allow<br />
universities and CAEs to market courses at full cost to<br />
overseas students either in Australia-or overseas.<br />
These places will allow an important new avenue for<br />
access to education oppportunities. These places will<br />
be additional to those under existing arrangements.<br />
The guidelines for these courses have been developed<br />
largely to allow institutions to test the waters in<br />
regard to these activities, to see whether courses can<br />
be run competitively and to establish the real level of<br />
demand. They provide for orderly development to take<br />
place, while safeguarding Australian students' access to<br />
the continued provision of high quality education.<br />
The marketing of courses-overseas also has the potential<br />
to contribute to the growth of the education system as<br />
we know it, to expand employment opportunities and<br />
Australia's overall export performance.<br />
But benefits cannot be measured in simple dollar terms.<br />
The intangible benefits greater understanding of<br />
cultures, of increasing our abilities to listen and to<br />
learn and to work co-operatively for the good of<br />
humanity these are some of the benefits which provide<br />
the basis and the hope for future peace and progress in<br />
our world.<br />
Australia does not seek an exaggerated role for itself<br />
in efforts to address the major issues bedevelling world<br />
order. We have a realistic appreciation of the limits<br />
to our own influence. Nevertheless our foreign policy<br />
is making a constructive and realistic contribution to<br />
peace and prosperity in this part of the world.<br />
Our future must be seen as being predominantly with, and<br />
determined by events in, the region of Asia and the<br />
Pacific. Australia's destiny is inextricably linked<br />
with this region, the fastest growing and most dynamic<br />
part~ of the world economy and to which most of the<br />
overseas students in International House will return.<br />
The Labor Government has made it clear from the time of<br />
its election the importance it attaches to Australia's<br />
relations with ASEAN. We value the association as one<br />
of the most effective and lively regional organisations<br />
anywhere in the world. We will continue to seek to<br />
expand political, economic and other forms of<br />
co-operation with ASEAN.<br />
B * ill Hayden and I have attached great importance to<br />
developing understanding and support with our<br />
col! trpart in South Fast Asia. W~ ha%' e ! Dnth v.-isitod </p>
<p>the countries of the region on a number of occasions and<br />
have welcomed leaders from these countries to Australia.<br />
The close political relationship we have enjoyed with<br />
the ASEAN countries is progressively being broadened to<br />
areas such as trade. The process of regional trade<br />
consultations, the latest round of which was held last<br />
month in Seoul, is giving real substance to the growing<br />
regional sense of shared economic and trading interests.<br />
And all countries of the region, including Australia,<br />
have much to gain by being part of such a dynamic growth<br />
region.<br />
Secondly, the Governn'ent has given a new dimension, a<br />
new priority, to arms control and disarmament issues a<br />
priority unpredecentel in Australia. I know that these<br />
issues are of great concern to you, and particularly to<br />
our nation's youth. I would in particular mention the<br />
initiative we took in 1983 to launch the concept of a<br />
nuclear free zone in the South Pacific. It is a matter<br />
of considerable gratification that the text of a treaty<br />
was endorsed at the recent South Pacific Forum at<br />
Rarotonga and that it has been signed by nine regional<br />
countries. This Treaty and the overwhelming support for it which<br />
has been expressed by the countries of the South Pacific<br />
Forum will bring greater-pressure to bear on the French<br />
to end their totally unacceptable nuclear testing.<br />
The French continue to maintain that their nuclear tests<br />
at Mururoa are quite safe. But the logic of this<br />
argument, is that if these tests are as safe as is<br />
claimed they should be conducted in France, and not in<br />
Australia's back yard.<br />
Thirdly, it is appropriate that, at this institution,<br />
which bring together students of diverse ethnic,<br />
religious and cultural background, I should mention our<br />
policies on racial tolerance and equality.<br />
Just as we stand resolutely against any manifestation of<br />
racism in Australia, we reject international policies<br />
which seek to entrench racial injustice.-This<br />
Government, like the Whitlam and Fraser Governments<br />
before it, stands at the leading edge of international<br />
opposition to the abhorrent system of apartheid, the<br />
only institutionalised form of racism in the world.<br />
We want to see that system abolished and an orderly,<br />
peaceful process of change introduced in South Africa<br />
which could lead to the emergence of a genuinely<br />
multi-racial society based upon universal adult<br />
suffrage. In the words of Bill Hayden, we want to see </p>
<p>South Africa brought to its senses, not its knees.<br />
I shall be exploring ways of furthering this process at<br />
the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting in the<br />
Bahamas later this month.<br />
Among the options we shall explore will be the<br />
possibility of mandatory economic sanctions being<br />
adopted by the United Nations. But at the same time, we<br />
believe that comprehensive measures by Australia alone<br />
or by a limited number of countries are self-defeating<br />
and probably counterproductive. To date, the necessary<br />
international consensus for mandatory sanctions withuniversal<br />
compliance does not exist.<br />
If the world community is to achieve its aim of seeing a<br />
peaceful transition of South Africa to a multiracial<br />
Society based on universa l adult suffrage it is<br />
critically important that trained South Africans will be<br />
available to take over the responsibilitites of the<br />
transfer of power in that country.<br />
Without fanfare and without political rhetoric the<br />
Commonwealth, through the Commonwealth Trade Union<br />
Council and the Commonwealth Fund for Technical<br />
Cooperation has been engaged for a number of years in<br />
helping to train South African students and workers for<br />
this task. We shall be encouraging increased efforts by<br />
the Commonwealth in this field.<br />
We shall also be seeking enhanced cooperation through<br />
the Commonwealth in areas where Commonwealth links have<br />
not been as developed as much as they could in the past<br />
in the field of employment and labour, youth and women<br />
and development. In these fielcds progress is vital in<br />
all societies, whether in relatively prosperous<br />
countries like Australia or in poorer countries like<br />
Tanzania or Swaziland.<br />
In closing, I would like to say simply I look forward to<br />
a continued association with you as International House<br />
continues to serve the academic and international<br />
community. I am honoured to have the opportunity of<br />
naming this building " Dimmick Dining Hall", in memory of<br />
Sam who contributed so largely to the foundation of<br />
International House.<br />
I know that there will be many long and memorable hours<br />
of discussions of debate and of laughter in this, " The<br />
Dimmick Dining Hall".<br />
Thank you. kr </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
