<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>25</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA AND THE LONDON CONFERENCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1952</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000025.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~ c / qp-<br />
AUSTRALIA AND THE<br />
LONDON CONFERENCE.<br />
The Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon.<br />
R. G. Menzies, M. P.,<br />
reports to the Australian people<br />
on the work of the London<br />
Economic Conference. By Authorif<br />
L F. JomNmSo. Commonwealth Government Printer. Canberra.<br />
( Printed in Australia.) </p>
<p>WHAT CONVERTIBILITY MEANS.<br />
Full convertibility," says Mr. Menzies, " will exist when<br />
the pound can be freely converted into other currencies at<br />
whatever may be the prevailing rate of exchange.<br />
It clearly cannot be reached in one stride. There must be<br />
intermediate stages as our trading position and our reserves grow<br />
stronger. What we have done is to agree, in some detail, on the<br />
procedures to be followed to reach an intermediate stage.<br />
They depend, not only on the success of our own efforts,<br />
but also on close and specific co-operation with European<br />
nations and the United States of America.<br />
You will understand at once that delicate negotiations will be<br />
required, and that meanwhile it would be quite impossible to<br />
publish the precise terms or even the outline of our proposals.<br />
But I can assure you that they are clear cut and constructive,<br />
and that if success is attained we will be much nearer to that full<br />
trade, commerce and intercourse between the nations which was<br />
once a refreshing and stimulating aspect of our lives, and which<br />
we all hope to restore." </p>
<p>" What strengthens sterling will<br />
strengthen all of us in the Commonwealth.<br />
It will increase the flow of<br />
goods. It will help the international<br />
investment. It will help to get us out<br />
of the atmosphere of emergency and<br />
restrictions, and serve to add to the<br />
prosperity and raise the living standards<br />
of the peoples of the world.<br />
" We are all proud to think that<br />
we have between us immense resources,<br />
not only in material things<br />
but also in courage, patience and<br />
resolution. With these rich endowments,<br />
and common friendship and<br />
understanding, we can not only<br />
deserve success, but command it." </p>
<p>The London Economic Conference in November-December,<br />
1952, was the most important of its kind for twenty years. There,<br />
the member nations of the British Commonwealth pooled their<br />
expert knowledge and experience and agreed on lines of policy<br />
designed to restore the convertibility of sterling and promote the<br />
trade and prestige of the Commonwealth in world affairs.<br />
Despite illness, the Prime Minister, Mr. Menzies, led the<br />
Australian delegation to the Conference. Afterwards, he took<br />
prompt steps to inform the Australian people what he had done<br />
in their name.<br />
This booklet contains the essence of what he said in broadcasts<br />
and statements immediately the Conference had ended. </p>
<p>NOT A " CRISIS CONFERENCE.<br />
The London Conference was not a "* crisis conference. It<br />
was convened for four purposes, each of them related to long-term<br />
policy and designed to ensure steady progress towards the development<br />
of resources, the promotion of production and trade, and the<br />
ultimate achievement of convertibility of currencies.<br />
The attainment of this goal will, by widening markets and<br />
stimulatin-g the flow of international investment, vitally assist<br />
further development, production and trade.*<br />
In other words, the nations represented at the Conference were<br />
seeking positive policies, moving away from artificial restrictions<br />
and towards greater freedom in the movement of goods and money.<br />
The four purposes were<br />
A frank and full interchange of ideas, policies, and<br />
experience, enabling each of the eight governments<br />
represented to review their own internal policies and<br />
to learn what the other governments were themselves<br />
doing in the financial and economic field.<br />
The formulation of a set of principles action upon which<br />
would assist in the gradual elimination of restrictions<br />
by the promotion of development and trade.<br />
The discovery of ways and means of increasing public<br />
and private investment calculated to assist adequate<br />
trade and payments balances.<br />
The preparation of specific plans for achieving convertibility,<br />
limited at first, but ultimately complete, so as<br />
to break down the exchange barriers which now cause<br />
a serious interference in trade between the dollar and<br />
sterling areas. </p>
<p>AUSTRALIAN MANUFACTURERS REASSURED.<br />
The countries represented were seeking common policies, not<br />
entering into legal commitments, secret or otherwise. Nor did<br />
any country give undertakings as to how it should handle its<br />
internal problems of development.<br />
For example, any suggestion that Australian manufacturing<br />
is to be cut back, or that the search for improving<br />
living standards is to be modified or abandoned, is quite<br />
untrue. On the contrary, each government represented saw in the<br />
overall design the real and valuable means of increasing production<br />
all round and so earning and saving dollars as to make convertibility,<br />
when it comes, a permanent thing and not a precarious<br />
step depending on precarious reserves.<br />
The interchange of ideas, policy, and experience was both<br />
detailed and valuable. Budget policies, aiming at balance or<br />
surplus, were remarkably similar in all countries. The need for<br />
a careful control of credit as an anti-inflationary measure was<br />
accepted by all.<br />
You will not need to be told by me that all forms of antiinflationary<br />
action such as taxation, credit controls, and import<br />
controls,, tend to be unpopular. Sometimes, in our own countries,<br />
people are tempted to believe that in such matters governments<br />
are either heartless or capricious. It is for this reason that I want<br />
to point out, at this Conference, all the Commonwealth countries<br />
not only agreed that counter-inflationary measures should be<br />
resolutely pursued, but also agreed that unless this was done it<br />
was idle to think that more active international trade and the convertibility<br />
of sterling could be achieved. </p>
<p>All governments were concerned about the burden olf<br />
taxes but the obligation of defence expenditure, especially<br />
since Korea, and the need to resort to tax revenues for<br />
some portion of public works has in all cases limited<br />
capacity to reduce taxes.<br />
In each one of the eight countries represented, problems like<br />
our own are being encountered and there is a close similarity in<br />
the methods which are being employed.<br />
The long-range principles evolved by the Conference were<br />
unanimously agreed upon. Briefly, they were:<br />
A resolute continuation of anti-inflationary policies, including<br />
control of credit, with of course such flexibility of application<br />
as new circumstances may require.<br />
Investment policies designed to secure a sound balance of<br />
payments position by encouraging the movement of Capital<br />
info industries producing additional exports or reducing<br />
the demand for dollar imports in particular.<br />
Development policies giving high priority to works calculated<br />
to increase production, strengthen competitive power in<br />
overseas markets, maintain employment and so provide a<br />
real foundation for increased living standards.<br />
These principles are not a mere form of words. They are<br />
completely opposed to the foolish notion that needed Capital can<br />
be secured by an inflationary use of central bank credit. The<br />
Conference states plainly that<br />
" Inflationary conditions frustrate the progress of<br />
sound development, both by increasing its cost<br />
and by destroying the savings necessary to finance<br />
it. Moreover, they damage the -external balance<br />
by stimulating excessive imports and by diverting<br />
to internal use goods which would -otherwise be<br />
available for export.". </p>
<p>POLITICS MUST BE FORGOTTEN.<br />
Great emphasis must be placed on the special character of the<br />
development to be aimed at. In Australia this presents great<br />
difficulties, for, while the Commonwealth has voluntarily accepted<br />
great financial responsibilities, including huge budget liabilities,<br />
the works programmes are largely under the exclusive control of<br />
the States. I will take an early opportunity of inviting the States<br />
into conference on this vital point.<br />
Politics must be forgotten. Special local interests must<br />
give way to the national need for improving our section of<br />
the sterl[ ing area's balance of payments. Unless we can<br />
really concentrate on works of the indicated character, we<br />
will hinder the accomplishment of an overall scheme which<br />
is of such immense importance for our future.<br />
Ways and means of increasing public and private investment<br />
were considered from two angles. First, it was recognized that<br />
our domestic savings are our first and principal asset. Increased<br />
savings will result from stability in the value of money ( antiinflationary<br />
action), increased production and improved overseas<br />
balances, and fiscal policies which encourage savings.<br />
We have here a challenge to the national conscience and<br />
good sense. There can be no easy promise of sudden<br />
results. We must, following the example of some foreign<br />
countries, make a vigorous effort for production. The<br />
increased individual production which has been noted<br />
during the past twelve months is proof that it can be done.<br />
Increased production will tend to reduce costs and to stabilize<br />
prices and money values. With the arrest of rising costs, tax<br />
reductions will become more practicable. With stable prices and<br />
lowering taxes, savings will be encouraged. </p>
<p>But to use central bank credit, not increased production, as a<br />
means of reducing taxes would be simply to aggravate inflation<br />
and so destroy the whole foundation upon which improved trade<br />
and convertibility of currencies clearly rest.<br />
COMMONWEALTH-STATE CO-OPERATION<br />
VITAL. Discussion also occurred upon how overseas Capital could be<br />
secured. Australia's greatest periods of development have been<br />
appreciably financed from overseas. Eight million people can<br />
scarcely hope to finance the development of a huge continent.<br />
I. Two new sources of overseas finance were evolved. The<br />
United Kingdom Government will make sterling<br />
available to the International Bank for sterling loans<br />
to British Commonwealth countries. Whether this<br />
will offer any benefit to Australia will depend<br />
entirely upon whole-hearted Commonwealth-<br />
States co-operation. For the International Bank<br />
will lend only upon projects which answer to the<br />
test of improving the balance of payments. Even<br />
then, it will lend only the overseas exchange content<br />
of any project, leaving a large proportion-representing<br />
local expenditure-to be financed in Australia. We<br />
must therefore marshal our resources and deal with<br />
public works on their merits.<br />
2. The other new source of finance is the new Finance<br />
Corporation which is being formed in London. We<br />
do not yet know how much new money this may<br />
mean, or on what terms, but we do know that it<br />
will not find money except for works which possess<br />
the necessary character and significance. </p>
<p>AUl of this can be sumnmed up by saying that we may,.<br />
in due course, be able to get outside assistance for public<br />
works. But we will get none unless we are prepared to<br />
put first things first, and prefer some irrigation scheme<br />
which will produce more food for export rather than some<br />
suburban railway.<br />
Specific plans for moving towards convertibility were prepared.<br />
Their formulation in fact occupied a large proportion of our time.<br />
They will require full co-operation by the nations of Western<br />
Europe and by the United States of America. Until discussions<br />
have occurred on the highest level, these plans obviously cannot<br />
be published. We all thought that they held great promise of<br />
reaching a new era in international trade. Even in what must<br />
be at first a limited form, they will hold great advantages, for<br />
directly or indirectly they will tend to increase our earnings of<br />
covetble currencies and so strengthen our international tradin<br />
position.<br />
AUSTRALIAN POLICIES SOUND.<br />
A fair summing up of all this is that eight Commonwealth<br />
Governments met, in a non-party atmosphere, without pressure<br />
from any sectional interest, to work out ways and means of moving<br />
away from restriction of produc tion and trade and towards freedom<br />
and expansion, which are what the world needs.<br />
We agreed that freedom cannot be got without effort, effort by<br />
governments, by employers, by employees. We agreed that vast<br />
defence expenditures and the maintenance of what has been called<br />
the welfare State make such demands upon public revenues<br />
that we are all confronted by high taxation or galloping inflation<br />
( itself the harshest of all taxes) unless production and trade can be<br />
tremendously increased.<br />
It was to the means of securing that increase that we devoted<br />
our minds and secured a notable measure of agreement. </p>
<p>If I have not come back home with a series of cut-and-dried<br />
proposals for Australia to carry out, it is for the very good reason<br />
that our plans and efforts inside Australia are our responsibility,<br />
and not for others to decide. But unless we are prepared to<br />
play our part in positive measures for world prosperity,<br />
we will let down our friends, and we will damage ourselves.<br />
The London Conference made it clear that our own financial<br />
and economic policies have been both appropriate and<br />
sound. But we must do better. We must earn and save more<br />
capital. We must not waste capital, for it is scarce. Sound and<br />
developing manufacturing will save us imports. Expanding primary<br />
industries will give us more exports, will save dollar expenditure by<br />
other Commonwealth countries, and will help to build up those<br />
international reserves which will help the convertibility of the<br />
pound and encourage the trade of the world.<br />
There is nothing either spectacular or easy about all this. But<br />
it is good common sense; the common sense of eight British<br />
nations and I am sure that Australia will respond to it. </p>
<p>COMMONWEALTH ECONOMIC CONFERENCE COMMUNIQUE.<br />
1. The Commonwealth Economic Conference, which ended to-day, was<br />
convened with the aim of concerting measures for increasing the economic strength<br />
of the Commonwealth countries, including the Colonial territories, and creating<br />
conditions in which their peoples can play their part in securing prosperity and<br />
contentment for themselves and for the world.<br />
2. In recent years the sterling ares has been faced with recurrent economic<br />
crises which have forced its members to take emergency measures of trade and<br />
exchange restriction. These measures were necessary but they have inevitably<br />
tended to frustrate the long-term economic expansion on w~ hich our hopes and<br />
opportunities for the future are founded. This was recognized at the January<br />
meeting of Commonwealth Finance Ministers. The measures taken in accordance<br />
with the conclusions of that meeting have, however, enabled the present Conference<br />
to decide that a more positive policy can now be adopted, both by the Commonwealth<br />
countries themselves and in concert. with other friendly countries, to<br />
promote the expansion of world production and trade.<br />
3. The Conference agreed that Commonwealth countries would work together<br />
to achieve certain broad common objectives. They have no intention of seeking<br />
the creation of a discriminatory economic bloc rather, their object is, by<br />
strengthening themselves, to benefit the world economy generally.<br />
Accordingly the following principles were agreed upon as governing the<br />
approach to the whole range of subjects under discussion<br />
Internal economic policies designed to curb inflation and rises in the<br />
cost of living should be steadily followed.<br />
Sound economic development should be encouraged with the object of<br />
increasing productive strength and competitive power, providing<br />
employment and raising the standards of life.<br />
A multilateral trade and payment system should be extended over the<br />
widest possible area.<br />
4. The application of these principles will require individual action by Commonwealth<br />
Governments, co-operation among them and international action with<br />
other trading nations and existing international organizations.<br />
INTENAL MEASURE.<br />
All Commonwealth Governments have agreed to persevere in their efforts to<br />
curb inflation. Inflationary conditions frustrate the progress of sound development,<br />
both by increasing its cost and by destroying the savings necessary to finance it.<br />
Moreover, they damage the external balance by stimulating excessive imports and<br />
by diverting to internal use goods which would otherwise be available for export. </p>
<p>6. An adequate and stable external balance must be a first objective for all<br />
governments. Failure to achieve this means repeated crises, a continuously rising<br />
cost of living, a constant threat to employment and failure to develop resources<br />
effectively. The Conference welcomed the improvement which had taken place<br />
in the balance of payments both of the individual sterling area countries and of<br />
the sterling area as a whole, following upon the conclusions reached by Commonwealth<br />
Finance Ministers at their meeting in January, 1952. It noted with<br />
satisfaction that the sterling area would achieve balance with the rest of the world<br />
in the second half of this year. It was, agreed, however, that this achievement,<br />
while reassuring, was only the first step towards a stable balance for the sterling<br />
area. Policies were agreed upon for 1953 which, it is hoped, will lead to further<br />
improvement in the reserves during that year. Nevertheless, while there has been<br />
steady improvement, the level of the reserves is as yet too low to warrant any<br />
substantial relaxation of the restrictions on imports from outside the sterling area.<br />
7. The Conference considered the extensive restrictions which some countries<br />
of the sterling Commonwealth have needed to impose upon imports from the<br />
United Kingdom and other Commonwealth sources. There was agreement that<br />
restrictions imposed because of balance of payments problems should be relaxed<br />
as the external financial position of countries improved. In considering the whole<br />
problem the governments concerned would have clearly in mind the difficulties<br />
which the restrictions have raised for the export industries affected.<br />
8. The economic and social objectives of the Commonwealth countries,<br />
individually and in association, depend upon their ability to produce and supply<br />
under competitive conditions an expanding flow of exports. There was therefore<br />
general agreement in the Conference on the vital need to expand the earning power<br />
of all sterling countries.<br />
9. Development Policy.-Throughout the Commonwealth there is wide scope<br />
for expanding the production of the essential supplies which the whole world<br />
needs-food and agricultural products, minerals and engineering products-and<br />
improving the means for transporting them. This development of the basic<br />
essentials has on occasion been impeded by other development of a less sound and<br />
permanent kind, which has overtaxed the countries' resources and has failed to<br />
contribute to the building of economic strength. The Conference agreed that in<br />
sterling area countries development should be concentrated on projects which<br />
directly or indirectly contribute to the improvement of the area's balance of<br />
payments with the rest of the world. Such projects should strengthen the economy<br />
of the countries concerned and increase their competitive power in world markets<br />
and so, by improving their balance of payments, bring increasing prosperity to<br />
their peoples. In some countries of the area, however, development plans have </p>
<p>been or are being made to provide for some basic improvement in the standards of<br />
living, which is a necessary foundation for further economic development. Some<br />
social investment is also urgently needed in the more developed countries, certain<br />
of which have rapidly increasing populations. The Conference recognized the<br />
need in such cases for these types of investment.<br />
To enable development to go forward a sufficient flow of savings must be<br />
provided in the countries undertaking the development and also in other countries<br />
which are ready to invest their savings there. The amount of savings which will<br />
he available from external sources will at best be small in relation to the size of the<br />
development programmes of countries of the sterling Commonwealth, and it is<br />
therefore essential that these countries should themselves adopt policies which<br />
increase the flow of savings-although this is inevitably a slow process for countries<br />
with low incomes and little margin above the basic needs for existence. The<br />
process of development will itself increase income and increase the flow of savings.<br />
11. The United Kingdom is the traditional source of external capital for Commonwealth<br />
investment and has special responsibilities in the Colonial territories.<br />
The United Kingdom Government are determined that the flow of capital from<br />
London for sound development throughout the Commonwealth shall be maintained<br />
and increased. This will only be possible if the United Kingdom can sustain the<br />
necessary level of internal savings and can achieve a surplus on overseas account<br />
additional to that required to meet its heavy existing commitments.<br />
12 The United Kingdom Government have, however, undertaken to make a<br />
special effort to provide additional capital for Commonwealth development by<br />
facilitating the financing of schemes in other Commonwealth countries which will<br />
contribute to the improvement of the sterling area's balance payments. The<br />
Conference took note that the United Kingdom Government would wish, before<br />
making any of this additional finance available for Commonwealth development,<br />
to be sure that the country concerned was itself devoting an adequate part of its<br />
resources to investment designed to improve the sterling area's balance of payments<br />
and was ready to make a sufficient contribution towards the particular scheme in<br />
question, to ensure that both countries had an interest in seeing that it was carried<br />
through as efficiently and economically as possible.<br />
13. The Conference welcomed the proposal by a group of important financial,<br />
industrial and commercial concerns in the United Kingdom to form a company<br />
to further development in other countries of the Commonwealth and the Colonial<br />
Empire. It was pleased to note that an announcement by this group is being issued<br />
to-day. The Conference also welcomed a statement by the United Kingdom<br />
representatives that the United Kingdom Covernn ent intend to discuss with the </p>
<p>International Bank for Reconstruction and Development arrangements to give<br />
-effect to their decision to make sterling available for lending by the Bank for<br />
Projects designed to improve the sterling ares's balance of payments.<br />
14. The Conference recognized the important contribution which investors<br />
, outside the aterling area. particularly in the United States. can make to economic<br />
development in the sterling area and agreed that every effort should be made to<br />
create conditions which would encourage such investment. It further agreed that<br />
all sterling area governments should strive to attain this by reducing such obstacles<br />
-as controls over the movements of capital across the exchanges. The United<br />
Kingdom Government have reviewed the right, which is now enjoyed by residents<br />
outside the sterling area who have invested capitsl in approved projects in the<br />
United Kingdom and Colonial Empire since Ist January. 1950, to transfer their<br />
capital across the exchanges. At present this right only extends to the sterling<br />
equivalent of the initial investment. Thc United Kingdom Govemnment informed<br />
the Conference that they have decided that henceforth it shall extend also to<br />
capital profits. Commnodity Policy.-The Conference recognized that there was no one<br />
universal remedy for the problem of instability of prices for primary commodities.<br />
Each commodity must be considered on its merits, in the light of the conditions<br />
prevailing at the time and the circumstances must determine what form of<br />
arrangements would be appropriate. The Conference agreed that violent fluctuations<br />
and an uneconomic level of prices for primary commodities were against the<br />
interests of consumers as well as producers.<br />
All Commonwealth Governments are therefore ready to co-. operate in considering,<br />
commodity by commodity, international schemes designed to ensure<br />
stability of demand and prices at an economic level. They also recognize the need<br />
for an agreed procedure for calling together the governments concemned to consider<br />
emergency action in the event of rapidly developing conditions of surplus or<br />
shortage of commodities entering into Internationsl trade.<br />
16. Imperial Preference.-There was general recognition at the Conference of<br />
the value of existing preferences.<br />
On the initiative of the United Kingdom a discussion took place on a proposal<br />
that all Commonwealth countries should join in seeking release from the no new<br />
-preference rule in the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade and<br />
-this United Kingdom proposal was supported by the representatives of some<br />
-countrses. The representatives of other countries felt that such an approach would<br />
not advance the agreed objective of restoring multilateral world trade and the<br />
Conference was therefore unable to support it. </p>
<p>All Commonwealth Governments agreed, however, to co-operate with the<br />
United Kingdom Government in an approach to the other contracting parties to.<br />
the G. A. T. T. to meet particular difficulties arising on the United Kingdom tariff.<br />
The object would be to enable the United Kingdom, consistently with the basicprovisions<br />
of the GA. T. T., to continue the duty-free entry for Commonwealth<br />
goods notwithstanding any increases that might from time to time become necessary<br />
in duties designed to protect domestic industry and agriculture in the United<br />
Kingdom. The Commonwealth Governments also agreed to consider sympathetically<br />
certain special tariff problems affecting the Colonies.<br />
INTERNATIONAl. ACTION.<br />
17. Resolute action in accordance with the conclusions recorded above will in<br />
itself do much to strengthen the economies of the sterling Commonwealth countries.<br />
But this is not enough. Action in a wider sphere is also necessary. The Conference.<br />
therefore agreed to seek the co-operation of other countries in a plan to create theconditions<br />
for expanding world production and trade. The aim is to secure international<br />
agreement on the adoption of policies, by creditor and debtor countries,<br />
which will restore balance in the world economy on the lines of Trade not Aid<br />
and will, by progressive stages and within reasonable time, create an effective:<br />
multilateral trade and payments system covering the widest possible area.<br />
18. Trade.-The plan envisages positive international action for the progressiveremoval,<br />
as circumstances permit, of import restrictions imposed for the purposeof<br />
bringing a country's external accounts into balance. Action will be required'<br />
by both creditor and debtor countries. The rate of progress in removing discrimination<br />
will depend upon the advance towards equilibrium between the United.<br />
States and the rest of the world.<br />
19. The sterling Commonwealth countries will not all be able to removerestrictions<br />
at the same time. In particular, the representatives of some countries:<br />
have emphasized that they must continue to use their exchange resources in the<br />
manner which enables them to carry out their planned development programmes:<br />
most effectively, and that they are likely to continue to need import restrictions<br />
for this purpose.<br />
Finance.-The Conference agreed that it is important, not only for the<br />
United Kingdom and the sterling area but also for the world, that sterling should'<br />
resume its full role as a medium of world trade and exchange. An integral part<br />
of any effective multilateral system is the restoration of the convertibility of sterling.<br />
but it can only be reached by progressive stages. The achievement of convertibility<br />
will depend fundamentally upon three conditionsthe<br />
continuing success of the action by sterling Commonwealth countries:<br />
themselves, as outlined above </p>
<p>the prospect that trading nations will adopt trade policies which are<br />
conducive to the expansion of world trade:<br />
( d the availability of adequate financial support, through the International<br />
Monetary Fund or otherwise.<br />
21. Procedure.-It is proposed to seek acceptance of this plan by the Governments<br />
of the United States and of European countries, whose co-operation is<br />
essential, and to work as far as possible through existing international institutions<br />
dealing with finance and trade.<br />
22. The timing of the successive stages of this plan cannot be decided at<br />
present. This can only be judged as the necessary conditions are satisfactorily<br />
fulfilled. 23. Conclusion.-The Conference is happy to be able to present this account<br />
of the confident understanding which exists between members of the Commonwealth<br />
and the wide measure of agreement which they have been able to achieve<br />
over the whole range of economic policy. The aims of their co-operation are<br />
entirely consistent with their close ties with the United States and the members<br />
of the Organization for European Economic Co-uperation. The Commonwealth<br />
countries look outward to similar co-operation with other countries, not inward<br />
to a closed association. It is their common purpose, by their own efforts and<br />
together with others, to increase world trade for the mutual benefit of all peoples.<br />
London, December, 1952.<br />
By Authorit7-L F. JoHNs-roN, C'wealth Govt. Printer. Canberra.<br />
-04.-1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
