<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3950</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE, ALICE SPRINGS, 1 NOVEMBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/11/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003950.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE, ALICE SPRINGS<br />
1 NOVEMBER 1975<br />
PRIME MINISTER: commitment that we have, the Labor Government<br />
said that it would create a fully electea ' Legislative Assembly:<br />
it's done that. It said that it would produce votes for<br />
Territorians in the Senate: it's done that. We have done in<br />
our three years more for the Constitutional and political<br />
development of the Territory than had happened-in the previous<br />
three-quarters of a century. So obviously we are going to get<br />
on with it. But one can't give a timetable, all that I can<br />
point out to you is -that we have carried out these other promises<br />
as promptly as was possible. There was a very great deal of<br />
obstruction as regards the-fully elected Legislative Assembly.<br />
And still more as regards representation in the Senate. But we<br />
overcame it, we carried out the promise, we will carry out this<br />
other promise.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Whitlam. on the subject of the half Senate el-ection<br />
now, you are hopeful that you'll get two Labor Senators in there.<br />
, What happens if you don't get two Labor Senators in there?<br />
How will this help the balance of power?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh well, it would be very much the same as it is<br />
now. See, in ordinary circumstances one would expect that the<br />
Government and the Opposition, whichever Parties they are, would<br />
get one of the Senators from the Northern Territory, and one of<br />
the Senators from the Australian Capital Territory. I believe,<br />
however, that in the present circumstances there are good prospects<br />
of the Labor Senate, candidates both getting up. That would<br />
require two-thirds of the votes. And why I say that I believe<br />
there are good prospects of this, is because in the Northern<br />
Territory more than any part of Australia there is damage to the<br />
people's welfare and the general economy of the region through<br />
the Senate's going on strike. That is, the Senate is holding<br />
up $ 439 million being provided for the Territory in this Budget.<br />
And the other reason why I believe that we will poll so well in<br />
the Senate is that the Liberal Senators and the Country Party<br />
Senators, all of them, without exception, voted against the<br />
Northern Territory getting Senators. And it was a Country Party<br />
Premier, Mr Bjelke-Petersen, who challenged the Bill when it got<br />
through, in the High Court. So wherever it's been in the Joint<br />
Sitting for instance, all the Country Party and Liberal members,<br />
in the Senate and in the House of Representatives, from every<br />
State, voted against the Territory having Senators. Now I think<br />
people will be outraged by the Senate's denial of Budget Moneys<br />
for the Territory and will be outraged by the Liberal and Country<br />
Parties' resistence to the Territory having Senators. That ought<br />
to be to the advantage of the Labor Party, which wants to get<br />
the Budget through, which has wanted the Territory to have Senators.<br />
QUJESTION: Could we just isolate the Territory for one second.<br />
We have a Legislative Assembly which is fully elected but there<br />
is not one Labor member on that Assembly. Do you see this as an<br />
anti-Labor indication?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I believe that was an utterly exceptional<br />
circumstance. I would have no doubt that at the next time there<br />
is an election for the Legislative Assembly we'll do very much<br />
better; we might win. Because the Country Party members of the<br />
Legislative Assembly, I think one much acknowledge, are a pretty<br />
indifferent bunch. They've not been impressive. </p>
<p>t-the whole week and they didn't call him.' And they didn't call<br />
him because they knew that they'd get no change out of him.<br />
IThat is there was nothing to embarrass me. Now I say Mr Fraser's<br />
been found out because people now-see that he is an impetuous,<br />
as impatient, as greedy, as improper as Mr Snedden. And Mr Fraser<br />
has been led astray by his Country Party confederates and by the<br />
newspaper proprietors.. Now you'll never change the minds of<br />
these Country Party confederates. They will, that tail will<br />
wag the Liberal dog as long as the Liberal dog doesn't have a<br />
better head'than Mr Snedden or Mr Fraser. The newspaper<br />
proprietors, with one exception, have changed their minds.<br />
The Country Party will never change its mind and the other people<br />
whose advice Mr Fraser takes have changed theirs. He's left<br />
high and dry. He's been found out. He did wrong. And people<br />
see it. And he will go the way that Snedden went. Sad but true.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, back to the south road, considering that-you ' ye<br />
made a promise or given a timetable, the last time that you were<br />
approached on the topic, would you care to do that again, to say<br />
that providing you were staying in power, how long would it take<br />
for the south road to be sealed?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This will come up in the triennial roads<br />
legislation which we were hoping to bring in before the end of<br />
this year.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, we had Mr Anthony and Country Party Leaders here<br />
this week, last week sorry, and you're here this week;<br />
Mr Bjelke-Petersen is coming next week. Does this mean that there<br />
is already a p-ee-Senate campaign on-in the Territory?<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER: I'm coming here because I've had an engagement<br />
for some months in Port Augusta tomorrow morning, Sunday the<br />
2nd of November. And in view of the present circumstances I<br />
thought that instead of getting to Port Augusta on Saturday night<br />
directly from Canberra or Sydney, I'd spend the day at Alice<br />
Springs on the way. After all I was in Alice Springs about<br />
three months ago. I've been to Alice Springs and the Territory<br />
more often than any Leader of the Liberal Party or the Country<br />
Party, Federal or State. You might think that this is an unfair<br />
comparison because I'm now doing over the fifth successive Federal<br />
Liberal Leader. But during the time that Holt was Prime Minister<br />
and then Gorton, and then McMahon and during the time that<br />
Snedden was Liberal Leader, during the time that Fraser has been<br />
Liberal Leader, in every case I've been more often to the<br />
Territory than any of them. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
