<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3856</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, FOR THE OPENING OF THE FILM AND TELEVISION SCHOOL, NORTH RYDE, NSW, 22 AUGUST 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003856.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THlE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, QC, MP,<br />
FOR THE OPENING OF THE FILM AND TELEVISION SCHOOL,<br />
NORTH RYDE, N. S. W., 22 AUGUST 1975<br />
1. 1 give full credit to John Gorton for recognising the<br />
needs of the Australian film and television industry.<br />
We agree on the need to develop an industry of world<br />
standard. We agree that a flourishing film and TV<br />
industry is possible only with a pool of expert trained<br />
technicians and craftsmen, of creative producers, directors<br />
and scriptwriters. That is what this school is providingalong<br />
with lectures, seminars, workshops and information<br />
on all aspects of film and TV production for those involved<br />
in the industry.<br />
2. It is seven years since a school such as this was f4 rst<br />
proposed at a UNESCO seminar on film and TV training<br />
at the University of N. S. W. I am proud that my Government<br />
was able to follow up these initiatives and establish<br />
the Film and Television School as an independent statutory<br />
authority in 1973. The School has the same status as a<br />
college of higher education. Eight months ago you invited<br />
me to open the first full-time three-year course of -the<br />
School. 1 regret that I was not able to be with you on<br />
that occasion, but I know that the first courses have<br />
successfully begun. It is a very select group -only 24<br />
stu~ dents a year it's smaller than the Cabinet -but<br />
those men and women have been carefully chosen and will be<br />
trained to the highest standards of excellence, of professionalism.<br />
3. Professor Toeplitz and your Council have recognised the<br />
essential truth that the Australian film and TV industry<br />
can only survive and prosper by producing works of<br />
international quality. There is no room for mediocrity.<br />
Here you have the very finest equipment and technical<br />
facilities; by 1980 you will have a permanent new<br />
building at Macquarie University. But none of these things<br />
will be of" much value if the standards of professional<br />
training are inferior. The success of this School<br />
depends, not only on cultivating a technically stimulating<br />
atmosphere, but on attaining and insisting upon rigorous<br />
professional standards in all your work. Technical<br />
competence in film production is only apparent by its<br />
absence; its presence is taken for granted. Too often in<br />
Australian productions in the past we have been aware of<br />
a certain clumsiness, a certain roughness at the edges.<br />
It is difficult to pin down but we can recognise it.<br />
True excellence of style and technique must be taught and<br />
learnt the hard way. In film and TV productions it involves<br />
collaboration by many different people with many different<br />
skills. Here in this school you will have the benefit<br />
of working together and getting used to the discipline of<br />
working together. That is an essential part of the training<br />
this School provides. ./ 2 </p>
<p>4. Films and television are the authentic art forms of<br />
the 20th century the most popular, and therefore also<br />
the most representative art forms, and those most<br />
closely attuned to the thoughts and feelings of the<br />
people. The problem is that they involve technical<br />
resources and expenditures beyond the reach of individuals<br />
or even of substantial private companies. Writing and<br />
painting and composing were solitary arts and could be<br />
practised in penury, but films and television require<br />
heavy investment and advanced technology. In the days<br />
when the technology was relatively simple and investments<br />
were modest Australia could afford a successful, and<br />
indeed flourishing, film industry. Overseas markets<br />
were limited, but the overheads were such that costs<br />
could be recouped and profits made from local exhibition.<br />
This is no longer the case. For years we heard demands<br />
and appeals for a viable film industry in Australia.<br />
These hopes were not fulfilled because Governments were<br />
never prepared to accept any responsibility for film<br />
production. It is only now that Governments are playing<br />
their part by subsidising film production and supporting<br />
their own production agencies. We now recognise that in<br />
a small or medium-sized country maintaining film<br />
production is like running an orchestra or an art gallery;<br />
it has little chance of succeeding without Government<br />
support. I am not suggesting that a profitable private<br />
industry is impossible. I am suggesting that without<br />
Government support a profitable industry is difficult<br />
tc establish and unlikely to succeed. moreover, it is only<br />
with Government support that films can be produced for<br />
a minority audience. There is less pressure on film<br />
makers to4-c onform to cosmopolitan and frequently debased<br />
standards of popular taste. There is more scope for a<br />
distinctively Australian style.<br />
We can all take satisfaction for the success of many<br />
recent Australian films. We have seen a healthy expansion<br />
of the Australian film industry in recent years. This has<br />
been due in large part to the involvement of governments.<br />
The Australian Government, as you know, has established,<br />
the Australian FiLm Commission as a statutory authority<br />
to Promocte a healthy Australian film industry. The<br />
Commission will incorporate Film Australian ( the Government's<br />
film production unit) and the Australian Film Development<br />
CorporatiLon -another offspring of the Gorton Government.<br />
The Corporation this year committed about $ 1.5 million<br />
to Australian film projects.<br />
6. The Labor Party is committed to a high level of Australian<br />
content in television production. We have established<br />
the Australia Council as an independent authority with its<br />
Film, Radio and Television Board to supervise Australian<br />
Government assistance to film and -television projects. And<br />
now we have a fully-fledged Film and Television School to<br />
produce the qualified men and women that the industry will need.<br />
I am delighted to be with you to perform this opening<br />
ceremony. I congratulate the director, Professor Toeplitz<br />
and the council and staff of the School on the excellent start<br />
it has made. I am confident that it will make an indispensable<br />
contribution to the development of film and -television<br />
in Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
