<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19247</transcript-id>
    <title>$777 Million for Renewed Effort to Close the Gap in Indigenous Health</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>The Australian Government has announced $777 million to fund its share of a renewed National Partnership Agreement on Closing the Gap in Indigenous Health Outcomes for a further three years to 30 June 2016.</p>
<p>This funding will ensure indigenous Australians continue to benefit from improved health services and support our commitment to close the gap on indigenous disadvantage.</p>
<p>In particular, our health funding will help us achieve our commitment to close the gap in life expectancy between indigenous and non-indigenous Australians within a generation, and to halve the gap in mortality rates for indigenous children under five within a decade.</p>
<p>The Australian Government will ask the States and Territories to also continue their investment to renew the National Partnership Agreement.</p>
<p>Under the current National Partnership Agreement, due to expire on 30 June 2013, governments provided $1.58 billion over four years to improve access to health services for indigenous families and communities.</p>
<p>The Australian Government provided $805.5 million over four years for this initial agreement.</p>
<p>Our renewed funding of $777 million over three years is an increase over previous per annum expenditure.</p>
<p>The Australian Government will continue to work with indigenous people and health services as we implement the renewed agreement.</p>
<p>As a result of our investments in indigenous health, we are seeing improvements.</p>
<p>This year's Closing the Gap report showed that local health services were helping to lead a comprehensive approach to chronic disease management, encouraging people to undergo health checks and follow ups.</p>
<p>In 2011-12, 65,501 health assessments were provided to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people aged 15 and over, a 34 per cent increase from 2010-11.</p>
<p>There are also more primary care workers in indigenous and mainstream health services to help meet the increase the uptake of health services by indigenous people.</p>
<p>While this work is encouraging we know there is more to be done.</p>
<p>We need sustained investment and effort to continue the momentum and ensure continued progress.</p>
<p>The renewed NPA will complement the proposed National Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Health Plan which has been the subject of extensive stakeholder consultations over the last several months. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
