<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3315</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA - 2 JULY 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/07/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003315.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
2 JULY 1974<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, first I can inform you of some<br />
appointments. The Government has decided to appoint Mr Philip<br />
Evatt, B. Sc., as a Judge of the Australian Industrial<br />
Court; Mr Justice Starke of the Victorian Supreme Court and<br />
Mr John Dixon of Melbourne to the Board of Trustees of the<br />
Australian War Memorial; and Brigadier A. B. Stretton as<br />
Director-General of the Natural Disasters Organisation. The<br />
brigadier will be promoted to major-general. Cabinet has also<br />
approved the re-appointment of Mr J. L. Burke, barrister, and<br />
Mr M. Dempsey, accountant, as members of the Taxation Board<br />
of Review. Mr Walsh can give you biographies of the gentlemen<br />
concerned. Mr Walsh will also give you press statements concerning<br />
appointments to the Industries Assistance Commission. I'll<br />
just briefly mention the persons involved. Mr Peter Westerway<br />
is to be a commissioner and, after the act has been amended<br />
to permit the ceiling on the number of appointments to be<br />
raised from the present nine to eleven full-time commissioners,<br />
Mr Frank Pascoe will be appointed as the tenth commissioner.<br />
He was recently appointed as associate commissioner for the<br />
inquiry into the clothing industry and, as you know, he is<br />
the president of the South Australian Chamber of Manufactures<br />
and now the first president of the amalgamated Chamber of<br />
Manufactures and Chamber of Commerce of South Australia, and<br />
he is deputy president of the Associated Chambers of Manufactures<br />
of Australia. There are some other associate commissioners<br />
who have been appointed. Dr Melville for the inquiry into the<br />
financing of rural research; Mr Fisk for the inquiry into<br />
the dairy industry and rural reconstruction; Mr J. Poulton<br />
for the inquiry into paints, varnish and lacquers; Mr Kevin<br />
Brown for the inquiry into electrical machinery and equipment.<br />
Mr Colin Grace, whose present term as an associate commissioner<br />
expires on the 16th of this month, has been re-appointed on<br />
a temporary basis in order to finalise a number of inquiries<br />
on which he has been engaged, and the acting Premier of New<br />
South Wales has agreed to make the services of Dr Dunn of the<br />
New South Wales Department of Agriculture available for the<br />
inquiry into the financing of rural research, subject to<br />
certain administrative arrangements being satisfactorily<br />
concluded. Here again, if you want the biography of the<br />
appointees, Mr Walsh can give them to you.<br />
Cabinet yesterday received the Cochran Committee report<br />
on labour market training. We are getting it printed as soon<br />
as possible and expect to be able to table it next week.<br />
Similarly, we are trying to get copies printed as soon as<br />
possible of the report by Mr Justice Woodhouse of the New<br />
Zealand Court of Appeal and Mr Justice Meares of the New<br />
South Wales Supreme Court into the national compensation and<br />
rehabilitation scheme. You'll remember that was appointed at<br />
the beginning of last year and last March its charter was<br />
extended to cover compensation and rehabilitation for sickness<br />
in general, not merely for people injured on the roads or in<br />
factories or in the home. That also we hope to be able to<br />
table and thus publish next week.<br />
Are there any questions you would like to ask me? ./ 2 </p>
<p>QUESTION: We received a cable from Cairo which says in<br />
part: " The Palestine Liberation Organisation welcomes the decision"-<br />
welcomes, Sir, is the word " of the Australian Government to<br />
allow it to open an information centre in Sydney' I ask, has<br />
the Government in fact granted such permission and have you<br />
any comment to make on the whole question?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Government has received no approach on this<br />
matter at all. It knows nothing other than it has read in the<br />
newspapers on it.<br />
QUESTION: Does your silence on the attack by Senator Brown<br />
on Mr Marshall Green indicate, as has been suggested, your tacit<br />
approval of what he said?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think you're putting such an allegation to<br />
me so directly and promptly so that I can refute it. I wasn't<br />
proposing to dignify or magnify Senator Brown's attack. It is<br />
a miserable in fact a cowardly thing to attack an ambassador.<br />
An ambassador cannot reply. If Senator Brown has any information<br />
which would indicate that Ambassador Green has not conducted<br />
himself with propriety in his present post it is his duty to<br />
give it to the Foreign Minister or to the Prime Minister. He<br />
has given no such information. I don't believe there is any<br />
such information. I read in the papers that he is keeping it<br />
for some rally to mark the Fourth of July. If there's any<br />
information it shouldn't be kept for an occasion like that<br />
it should have been promptly put at the disposal of the<br />
responsible minister. From what I know of Mr Green and I've<br />
known him for ten years in Washington, in Jakarta and in<br />
Canberra he is, as you all know, a singularly alert, active,<br />
articulate man. I don't believe that any member of the U. S.<br />
Congress would have any justification to criticise an<br />
Australian ambassador who had said or done in the United States<br />
what Mr Green has done in Australia. Mr Green is one of the<br />
most experienced of America's diplomats. He has had experience<br />
for over 30 years in the western Pacific. And not only did<br />
the Government approve his appointment that's obvious, of<br />
course, from the fact that he became ambassador here but it<br />
welcomed his appointment. Mr Green is a man whose experience<br />
and qualifications would have entitled him to the embassy in<br />
Tokyo or the liaison office in Peking. I believe it is a<br />
singular indication of the importance that America attaches to<br />
her relations with Australia that Mr Green was appointed to<br />
Canberra. QUESTION: Have you contacted Mr Green or caused a message<br />
to be sent to him dissociating yourself and the Government from<br />
the senator's attack?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I've seen Mr Green since, as you would have<br />
expected. I've been in Canberra some days since this. Mr Green<br />
doesn't need to be reassured of my attitude to him or his country.<br />
QUESTION: Indications are that unemployment may worsen during<br />
the last half of this year that the economic situation may worsen<br />
during the last half of this year. Do you have any information<br />
supporting or refuting these indications and what are your views<br />
and your information on the economic situation? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: You mention there are " indications". Now<br />
specify them. I know of two events which are said to be<br />
indications. One is that Leyland have put off 1,000 people;<br />
but the motor car industry is producing as many vehicles as<br />
ever. It's not the Government's fault if Leyland finds it<br />
more difficult to sell its products than other companies find<br />
it to sell theirs. The other field is in the textile industry.<br />
People who lose their jobs in the textile industries in the<br />
State capitals are, we believe, able to find other employment<br />
which they like just as well. In regional areas there can be<br />
a difficulty there, but the cure for that is not to ban the<br />
imports of textiles or to put a prohibited tariff on them.<br />
There's no need to burden the Australian consumer because of<br />
some regional difficulty. What we are doing and there has<br />
been a committee of our ministers considering it, and there<br />
is a conference pending between my ministers and State ministers on<br />
the decentralisation or regional aspects of this question for<br />
something needs to be done to improve regional developments in<br />
many areas. I notice that the Victorian Government and the<br />
Victorian Minister for Decentralisatiop have been singularly<br />
vocal in these matters, not least, of course, during the recent<br />
election campaign. Their arguments would have carried very<br />
much more weight if they had stuck to the facts. If State<br />
ministers were to specify areas of regional development they<br />
would find that the Australian Government is very happy to<br />
collaborate with them. The Australian Government is very<br />
happy to collaborate with them. The Australian Government has<br />
taken the initiative in the biggest regional development<br />
project, Albury-Wodonga. We are very happy to collaborate with<br />
other States which have designated such areas. Our attitude<br />
to Bathurst and Orange, which New South Wales has designated,<br />
evidences that; and there have been for the last dozen years,<br />
I suppose, four other areas apart from Wodonga which Victoria<br />
has designated Ballarat, Bendigo, the area of Warrnambool,<br />
Portland and Hamilton, and the Latrobe Valley. You might<br />
remember there was a debate on the Latrobe Valley in the<br />
House of Representatives a few months ago on this very point.<br />
We are very happy to collaborate with State Governments in<br />
regional development but, as in all these things, one needs to<br />
plan properly and co-operatively. We've shown that we are anxious<br />
to do this.<br />
QUESTION: I was speaking specifically of the Associated<br />
Chamber of Manufactures/ National Bank survey which indicated<br />
that something like 73% of businesses or companies surveyed were<br />
extremely pessimistic.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well those are expressions of opinion. Give<br />
me some facts. I've quoted the two that I am aware of.<br />
QUESTION: Ever since your address on Saturday night to the<br />
Industrial Relations Society, when you said that we couldn't go<br />
on with wage increases at 20% a year, there's further evidence<br />
that wage-price pressures are increasing. Is there anything that<br />
you can say now that you couldn't say then about the Government's<br />
strategy in face of this, and in particular is there anything you<br />
can say about how quiickly the Government is going to take action<br />
with so many wage negotiations currently overhanging the economy? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: No, I've got nothing to add to the prepared<br />
remarks which I made on Saturday night.<br />
QUESTION: Would you consider following or giving a lead to<br />
the lead put up by four of your backbenchers in Victoria yesterday<br />
that pay rises for M. P. s should be postponed for some time in<br />
the fight against inflation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You will remember that the Act on this subject,<br />
the Remuneration Tribunal Act, provides that the tribunal can<br />
make recommendations concerning judges' salaries and ministers'<br />
salaries and can make determinations concerning members'<br />
salaries, ministers' allowances and the salaries of first division<br />
members of the public service.-Now I'll read-what th ' e Act says<br />
on this very aspect: " If either House of the Parliament within<br />
fifteen sitting days of that House, after a copy of the<br />
determination has been laid before that House, passes a<br />
resolution disapproving of the determination, then if<br />
the determination has not come into operation... I interpose<br />
there to say that the Tribunal can fix a date for determination.<br />
Well, if the determination does not come into operation " or<br />
if the determination has come into operation, the determination<br />
shall not have any force or effect in respect of a period on or<br />
after the day on which the resolution was passed." So it's open<br />
to the Parliament, either House, to disapprove of a determination.<br />
QUESTION: If I asked for your personal opinion, would you<br />
consider following or leading<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't choose to express my personal opinion.<br />
I'm the man in the Parliament who has the highest salary. it<br />
would be very easy for me to get kudos by expressing a view.<br />
I prefer to consider this in a collective way.<br />
QUESTION: You said that Senator Brown's comments were cowardly<br />
and miserable. Do you intend to tell him so face to face?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't propose to magnify this issue. I suppose<br />
I'll speak to him. I'm not going to call him in. I don't propose<br />
to answer any further questions on this matter.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, do you disagree with Clyde Cameron's forecast<br />
yesterday that unemployment will increase?*<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I was speaking to Clyde Cameron quite a lot<br />
yesterday. I didn't hear him make that forecast. I appreciate<br />
that it's necessary to ask, Do I approve of what some particular<br />
critic or reporter or colleague has said? I wish you chaps would<br />
take responsibility for the unpleasant things which you want me to<br />
answer.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Cameron said yesterday, " I've felt for a long<br />
time that unemployment will rise."<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I didn't know he had.<br />
QUESTION: He also says, " We are in fact taking steps which<br />
are based upon the possibility that this will happen.' What steps<br />
will those be? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I believe you've already been given a statement.<br />
I think you were given a statement last night concerning the<br />
Structural Adjustment Board, for which legislation was approved<br />
yesterday, and I think you were also given information concerning<br />
the action we're going to take on the Cochrane Report which I've<br />
already mentioned to you the one about retraining.<br />
QUESTION: The question of wage indexation awaits Mr Justice<br />
Moore' s conference.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
QUESTION: Then are there any moves which will speed up the<br />
holding of the conference, which I think would take place about<br />
September?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The holding of the conference is an initiative<br />
by Mr Justice Moore, the president of the Australian Conciliation<br />
and Arbitration Commission. Clearly, therefore, it should be<br />
left to him. We said that we were happy to support that initiative.<br />
I think we've shown that, including on Saturday at the Industrial<br />
Relations Society Seminar at Surfers Paradise, where both<br />
Mr Cameron and I supported the idea.<br />
Perhaps I should have mentioned another thing about<br />
Senator Brown. I'm sorry that his statement of the declaration<br />
of the Senate poll in Victoria, of all places, took out of the<br />
papers I think, relegated t6 the third page of the Melbourne<br />
Sun, which is a pretty comprehensive medium the comments made<br />
on the same occasion, of all places by Mr McManus. I notice,<br />
not for the first time, that he said he had been offered the<br />
post of Ambassador to the Vatican. He was never offered the<br />
post of Ambassador to the Vatican. At the time that Australia<br />
established diplomatic relations with the Vatican at the time<br />
that Australia appointed an ambassador to the Vatican I was the<br />
Foreign Minister, and Senator McManus was never approached nor,-<br />
if it's not too harsh for me to say, was he ever considered.<br />
QUESTION: While we're talking about senators, does the<br />
Government intend to provide Senator Steele Hall with any<br />
increased facilities or staff? If so, why?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Senator Steele Hall hasn't written to me or<br />
spoken to me about the matter.<br />
QUESTION: I understand there was a meeting of ministers and<br />
Treasury officials at the Lodge last night. Was the tenor of<br />
that meeting optimistic that the Government would be able to<br />
both contain or reduce inflation and maintain employment and<br />
that it would be able to do both together?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It was a private meeting both before, during,<br />
and after dinner. So don't expect me to state<br />
or to repeat the views which the wide number of men there<br />
expressed. The object of it was for me to have the benefit of an<br />
exchange of views with and between the Government's senior<br />
economic advisers. And I do this not infrequently. Not as<br />
often as I'd like to, but... </p>
<p>QUESTION: Do you consider immigration more important as an<br />
instrument of foreign policy rather than one of domestic, social<br />
and economic policy?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Immigration, as far as the present Australian<br />
Government is concerned, involves people who were born overseas<br />
and who have migrated to Australia; our prime objective is to<br />
make them happy in this country, and to see that they get as<br />
good opportunity, individually and as families, as it is<br />
possible for the country to provide as their new home. I notice<br />
that you still get some references to a mass immigration program.<br />
The Government has no mass immigration program at all. Its<br />
efforts are directed to making migrants feel at home in Australia.<br />
QUESTION: How can you emphasise family reunion and yet give<br />
the Immigration Department to Mr Clyde Cameron, the Labour<br />
Minister, where the obvious orientation is going to be towards<br />
manpower needs, considering that family reunion has the least<br />
requirements for manpower policies and national need?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Mr Cameron, as Minister for Labour and<br />
Immigration, naturally has the prime responsibility for<br />
determining what the opportunities are for permanent migration<br />
to Australia that is, for people coming here who want to<br />
live here permanently and obviously, therefore, want to maintain<br />
themselves when they come here. It's quite an unreasonable and<br />
cruel thing to permit, still more to encourage, people to come<br />
to Australia as permanent residents if there aren't jobs<br />
available for them. I notice there's a great deal of speculation<br />
in the newspapers on this subject arising from fomentation by<br />
members of the old Department of Immigration when it was an<br />
individual department. It's true that that department fell down<br />
very badly in respect of Australia's urban affairs and foreign<br />
affairs, but it has got many skills which are appropriate to be<br />
retained and which will be retained in the augmented Department<br />
of Labour and Immigration. Nevertheless, there are some aspects<br />
which were left to that department and which obviously would be<br />
better handled by other departments. For instance, it has already<br />
been decided that the administration of the Immigration<br />
Guardianship of Children Act should be transferred to the<br />
Minister for Social Security; and that the administration of<br />
the Immigration Education of Children Act be transferred to<br />
the Minister for Education; and that the policy and issue of<br />
passports for Australian citizens should become the responsibility<br />
of the Foreign Minister. And other matters are being considered<br />
with the general object in mind of assuring efficiency of<br />
administration and humanity of administration.<br />
QUESTION: Have you or Mr Daly been able to reach any agreement<br />
with the-Opposition parties or their leaders on the procedures<br />
to be adopted for the proposed joint sitting of Parliament this<br />
month? PRIME MINISTER: Mr Daly at this moment is studying the Canadian<br />
federal elections, where it is expected that a result will be<br />
achieved rather more efficiently and promptly than was the case<br />
in the Australian federal election. I haven't spoken to him<br />
about this for a couple of weeks, I think. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Has the rise in the price of phosphatic rock,<br />
combined with the fall in the price of meat, given you any<br />
reason to reconsider the decison to abolish the superphosphate<br />
bounty at the end of this year?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I can only repeat that if any industry or<br />
region--. believes it is disadvantaged by the increase in the<br />
cost of superphosphate then it can make an application to the<br />
Department of Agriculture to see if there's a prima facie case<br />
for a reference by me to the Industries Assistance Commission.<br />
There has already been one successful proposition of that nature<br />
put to me by the department and one unsuccessful one. The cost<br />
of superphosphate as a fertiliser in Australia is lower than<br />
in pretty well any other country in the world. At last<br />
Australia might find it profitable, therefore, to develop her<br />
own very considerable resources of phosphate, those near<br />
Mt Isa, in the hands of Australia's greatest and most prosperous<br />
company. QUESTION: When do you propose to announce the appointment of<br />
the inquiry into security services?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'Id say in a couple of weeks.<br />
QUESTION: Do you intend to make public the findings of the<br />
inquiry some of the hearings of that inquiry?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Terms of reference, yes. Findings,. almost<br />
certainly, in respect to procedures to review decisions which<br />
are thought to have affected public servants or immigrants.<br />
Hearings, that will be up to the judges.<br />
QUESTION: If the Palestine Liberation Organisation approached<br />
the Government, does that....<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Do not speculate. Wait until the matter<br />
happens. Wait until there is such a proposition.<br />
QUESTION: The metal trades unions have said they will press<br />
ahead with new wage claims despite your call for restraint last<br />
Saturday. Do you feel that this is a legitimate stand for<br />
the unions to take at the moment and do you agree with your<br />
Labour Minister, Mr Cameron, who said yesterday the metal<br />
trades....<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Here it comes again! Do I agree with one of<br />
my colleagues? Yes, go on.<br />
QUESTION: do you agree with Mr Cameron who said yesterday<br />
the metal trades workers were only trying to keep pace with the<br />
public service?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Where did he say all these things? I spent<br />
most of yesterday morning, afternoon and night with him and he<br />
didn't say any of these things to me! There's only one person<br />
I listen to on Macquarie and he sounds more funereal than<br />
Mr Cameron. Mr Jack Devereux was at Surfers on Saturday night<br />
talking with me. He had my oration. He didn't express the view </p>
<p>to me that you attribute to the union of which he is head.<br />
I notice that an assistant secretary was reported a day later<br />
as commenting that he was not there and hadn't, at that time,<br />
received his copy of the oration.<br />
QUESTION: This week we're getting the third instalment of the<br />
long-running Bulletin serial on ASIO. Are you concerned that<br />
these documents have leaked out? Do you think they've damaged<br />
the security service or the Government? Have you asked for an<br />
inquiry on how they've leaked out and have you any results<br />
from the inquiry? And will this be one of the things being<br />
looked at by the Royal Commission?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Any of You who wants the full text of the ASIO<br />
document entitled " Croation Nationalist Movements and Activities<br />
in Australia" can get a copy of it from Mr Walsh immediately<br />
after this gathering disperses. Anybody who wants to know the<br />
titles and the dates of the other documents in this category<br />
which were prepared by ASIO can similarly get that list from<br />
Mr Walsh as soon as this gathering disperses.<br />
QUESTION: Senator Greenwood said these documents were<br />
unclassified.? PRIME MINISTER: I wouldn't be releasing this document if I<br />
were not satisfied that it was completely genuine! But even so<br />
I wouldn't be releasing it but for the fact that the Director-<br />
General of ASIO has assured me that there is no confidential<br />
material in it whatever. All the material in these articles<br />
could have been got from any bookstore, and the dates, the facts,<br />
the quotations were available in newspapers and magazines which<br />
were freely available in Australia. There is nothing in these<br />
documents which ASIO has sought or received in the course of<br />
its statutory duties. in releasing this document I am assured<br />
by the Director-General that the security of the country is not<br />
in any way jeopardised. There is no confidential information in<br />
these documents at all. Security is not involved and therefore<br />
I am making it available to you through Mr Walsh if you're<br />
interested in it. Perhaps I could refresh your memory about<br />
this in general by quoting an answer which the Attorney-General<br />
provided for our colleague, Dr Klugman. You'll see it in<br />
House of Representatives Hansard of 13 December last. Dr Klugman' s<br />
question was: " Has the Attorney-General's attention been drawn<br />
to the statement by Mr Robert Mayne, Assistant Editor of the<br />
Sun-Herald, that he was approached by Mr Peter Coleman, M. L. A.,<br />
and a senior officer of the Australian Security Intelligence<br />
Organisation to work for a magazine called Analysis and ( b)<br />
that the organisation would supply material to discredit members<br />
of the Australian Labor Party." To that the Attorney-General<br />
provided the answer " Yes". Dr Klugman also asked: " If so,<br />
who was this senior officer of the organisation and ( b)<br />
is he still in the employment of the organisation?" To that<br />
the Attorney-General answered: " The officer concerned is still<br />
in the employ of the organisation. The supply of material<br />
about individual citizens to be used in the media of which this<br />
case was an example was wholly unwarranted and outside the<br />
functions of ASIO. The Director-General of Security has informed<br />
me that some time after he assumed office he discontinued the<br />
practice of giving background briefs to journalists." The<br />
documents to which you refer were among some scores of document </p>
<p>prepared from 1962 onwards. The preparation of these documents<br />
was discontinued by ' the present Director-General of Security<br />
before the present Government was elected. The material was<br />
given to a selected number of journalists.<br />
QUESTION: Well we know the author of these documents?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. I should say the employee of ASIO who was<br />
referred to in the Attorney-General's reply to Dr Klugman is the<br />
author of all these documents. He's still in the organisation.<br />
He is there, I am sure, doing-work which does relate to the<br />
organisation. I therefore don't believe that I should mention<br />
his name.<br />
QUESTION: Do you welcome the election of Mr Percy Tucker as<br />
Leader of the Opposition in Queensland,. and are you happy with<br />
the way it comes out?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It's not up to me to express a view on a matter<br />
such as that. Whom any Parliamentary Labor Party chooses to<br />
hold office in it is entirely a matter for that party. I've<br />
known Mr Tucker, of course, for very many years. He is a family<br />
friend of mine as well as a personal friend. I'm sure I can<br />
work very effectively with him. I congratulate him. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
