<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1549</transcript-id>
    <title>ASIAN TOUR 1967 - TAIWAN - JOINT COMMUNIQUE ISSUED BY THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA AND THE COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA - 6TH APRIL, 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/04/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001549.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ASIAN TOUR 1967 TAIWAN<br />
JOINT COMMVUNIQUE ISSUED BY THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA<br />
AND) THE COMMVOMWEALTE OF AUSTRALIA 6TH APRIL, 1967<br />
At the invitation of the Government of the Republic<br />
of China, the Right Honourable Harold E. Halt, Prime Minister<br />
of the Commonwealth of Australia and Mrs. Halt, accompanied<br />
by high-ranking officials of his government, visited the<br />
Republic of China from April 4th to April 6th, 1967.<br />
President Chiang Kai-Shek, in expressing his deep<br />
appreciation for Prime Minister Holt's visit, considered it<br />
to be a significant milestone in the history of the friendly<br />
relations between the Republic of L China and Australia.<br />
Prime Minister Halt, on hi~ s part, thanked President Chiang,<br />
Vice President and concurrently Prime Minister Yen Chia-Kan<br />
and the Government and people of the Republic of China for<br />
the warm hospitality accorded to him, to Mirs. Holt and to the<br />
members of his party during the visit.<br />
During his stay in the Republic of China, the Prime<br />
Minister had the opportunity of holding a series of frank and<br />
free discussions with President Chiang, Vice President and<br />
concurrently Prime Minister Yen and other Chinese Government<br />
leaders on the world situation, particularly the situation in<br />
Asia and the Pacific and other matters of common interest to<br />
the two countries. Presideit Chiang and Prime Minister Holt reaffirmed the<br />
long-standing friendship between the Republic of China and<br />
Australia and pledged to further strengthen their co-operation<br />
in the common effort to maintain peace and security in the basis<br />
of freedom and ju--tice and to promote the oconomic prosperity of<br />
this area. President Chiang expressed thle admiration of the<br />
Government and people of the Republic of China for tho stand which<br />
Australia has taken in Vietnam an'. the significant contribution<br />
Australia has made and is still making to the fighting in Vietnam<br />
agaii-ot communist aggression. The two leaders are agreed that<br />
peace, like freedom, is indivisible and that inasmuch as Hanoi<br />
has repeatedly refused to ne gotiate for peace, no end to tho war<br />
in Vietnam is at present in sight and, theroefore, such joint<br />
effort as has been made to resist communist aggreosion, in Vietnam<br />
should be continued,<br />
Prime Minister Halt also had the opportunity of visiting<br />
the industrial centres and harbour facilities of the Republic of<br />
China. He was greatly impressed by the vitality of the people,<br />
the tremendous progress that has been made in the field of<br />
economic development and the political stability that the country<br />
enjoys under the inspiring leadership of President Chiang.<br />
President Chiang and Prime Minister Holt believe that<br />
since Asia has now become the crucial area of resistance to<br />
communist aggression, it is essential that the two countries<br />
should do their utmost to promote unity among free nations<br />
everywvhere and among member nations of the Asian and Pacific<br />
Council in particular, so that the threat to world peace posed by<br />
militant communism on the Chinese Mainland and elsewhere in Aoia<br />
can be eliminated and conditions for the promotion of the economic<br />
prosperity and social well-being for all the peoples of this<br />
area established. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
