<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3821</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S SPEECH AT OPENING OF ST FRANCIS XAVIER PRIMARY SCHOOL, LURNEA, NSW ON 13 JULY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/07/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003821.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH AT OPENING OF ST, FRANCIS<br />
XAVIER PRIMARY SCHOOL, LURNEA, N. S. W, ON 13 JULY 1975.<br />
AFTER THE TURMOIL OF CANBERRA, IT IS CURIOUSLY<br />
REFRESHING TO COME HOME TO MY OWN ELECTORATE, TO WERRIWA, FOR<br />
FRIDAY AND SATURDAY NIGHT AND SUNDAY AFTERNOON. I HAVE BEEN<br />
IN EXCELLENT COMPANY ALL WEEKEND, AS SOME OF YOU MAY KNOW.<br />
LAST NIGHT WAS THE ALL SAINTS PARISH BALL AND I HAD<br />
THE PLEASURE OF SEEING His LORDSHIP BISHOP CREMIN AGAIN. W'<br />
LAST MET AT THE BLESSING AND OPENING OF ST. BEDE'S HOME AT<br />
HURSTVILLE, WHERE HE TOLD A VERY LONG AND COMPLICATED JOKE WHICH<br />
SUBSEQUENTLY GOT RECORDED IN MY WIFE'IS MAGAZINE COLUMN.-IN<br />
WOMAN'S DAY.' TAT MORE THAN MY JOKES DO.<br />
TODAY, OF COURSE, His EMINENCE CARDINAL FREEMAN IS<br />
HERE TO GIVE HIS BLESSING TO THE OPENING OF YET ANOTHER CATHOLIC<br />
PRIMARY SCHOOL. WE LAST MET ON THE OCCASION OF THE BLESSING AND<br />
OPENING OF ST. JOSEPH'S, MOOREBANK. I REMEMBER WE TRADED<br />
OBSERVATIONS ABOUT THE TWO THOMAS MOORES THE ONE WHO ENDOWED<br />
A PROTESTANT THEOLOGICAL COLLEGE IN SYDNEY AND AFTER WHOM<br />
MOOREBANK IS NAMED, AND THE OTHER GREAT ENGLISHMAN, ST, THOMAS MOORE,<br />
AFTER WHOM SO MANY CATHOLIC SCHOOLS IN THIS COUNTRY ARE NAMED. </p>
<p>2.<br />
OPENING DAYS ARE ALWAYS A SOURCE OF IMMENSE<br />
SATISFACTION TO THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN INVOLVED IN PLANNING<br />
AND FUNDRAISING TO GET A PARTICULAR PROJECT, LITERALLY, ItOFF<br />
THE GROUND" TODAY IS NO EXCEPTION: IAM ALWAYS DELIGHTED TO BE<br />
ASSOCIATED WITH SUCH CEREMONIES, PARTICULARLY WHEN, IN THE CASE<br />
OF SCHOOLS, IT MEANS THAT A NEW SCHOOL HAS BEEN CREATED IN A<br />
RAPIDLY DEVELOPING OUTER SUBURBAN* AREA, WITH A CLEAR NEED FOR<br />
EDUCATIONAL FACILITIES TO CATER FOR THE HIGH PROPORTION OF.<br />
SCHOOL-AGE AND YOUNGER CHILDREN. IT HAS BEEN THE CONSISTENT<br />
BELIEF OF THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR GOVERNMENT THAT ALL CHILDREN<br />
ARE ENTITLED TO EVERY POSSIBLE CHANCE OF A GOOD EDUCATION, NO<br />
MATTER WHERE THEY LIV E IN AUSTRALIA. I B EL IEVE THAT WHAT WE<br />
HAVE DONE FOR EDUCATION IN THIS COUNTRY WILL BE REMEMBERED WITH<br />
GRATITUDE IN YEARS TO COME.<br />
TIME WAS, AND NOT EVEN TWENTY YEARS AGO, WHEN IT WOULD<br />
HAVE BEEN QUITE UNTHINKABLE FOR A PERSON OF MY POLITICS TO BE<br />
ASKED TO DECLARE OPEN A CATHOLIC SCHOOL. AND YET, HERE WE ARE,-<br />
CARDINAL FREEMAN AND I, -AT OUR SECOND CATHOLIC PRIMARY SCHOOL<br />
OPENING IN THIS WERRIWA ELECTORATE IN THREE MONTHS. IT IS JUST<br />
THREE MONTHS TO THE DAY APRIL 13-THAT ST. JOSEPH'S WAS<br />
OPENED. AND NOW ST. FRANCIS XAVIER'S. </p>
<p>BOTH TII; l CATIIOLIC PRIMARY SCHOOLS HAVE<br />
ATTRACTED IDENI It,\ l A/ I\ TRALIAN GOVERNMENT GRANTS OF $ 140,000<br />
UNDER THE CAP IAI ill IOR SCHOOLS PROGRAM 1973-74. THEY CAN<br />
BE SEEN AS PART t~ uI; AUiSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S VASTLY<br />
. IINNCCRREEAASSEEDD EEXXPPEENNIIgn11,1,, 1 ON EDUCATION OF ALL KINDS AND AT ALL<br />
LEVELS. THREE Yt Al: i TIIE AMOUNT OF MONEY BEING SPENT<br />
BY THE FEDERAL ( 1VII) I IJMENT ON CATHOLIC EDUCATION THROUGHOUT<br />
AUSTRALIA WAS BIAllly $ 30 MILLION, THIS YEAR IT IS THREE<br />
AND A HALF TIME:, MUCH. IT IS OVER $ 100 MILLION. NOW<br />
THAT IS VERY MlI,' 1 FilUI THAN WOULD BE REQUIRED BY AN INCREASE<br />
IN ENROLMENT OR AN INCREASE IN INFLATION IN THAT PERIOD,<br />
THE PRINCIII II THAT WE HAVE ADHERED TO THROUGHOUT,<br />
AS I SAID BEFORI, I I IAT IT SHOULD BE POSSIBLE FOR CHILDREN<br />
WHEREVER THEY LIVI WHATEVER THEIR PARENT'S MEANS, WHATEVER<br />
THEIR PARENTS 1l:-II:; 11, WHATEVER THEIR PARENTS OCCUPATION<br />
TO HAVE AS GOOD AN I IJCATION AS THIS COUNTRY CAN PROVIDE. </p>
<p>AND THE BASIS UPON WHICH WE MAKE THAT PROVISION<br />
IS PERFECTLY OPEN; IT'fS UNDER AN ACT OF PARLIAMENT. IT<br />
IS ADMINISTERED BY A COMMISSION WHOSE MEMBERSHIP IS<br />
APPOINTED BY THE GOVERNMENT OF THE DAY. IHAVE NEVER<br />
HEARD ANY CRITICISM OF THE PEOPLE, MEN AND WOMEN, BOTH<br />
LAY AND RELIGIOUS, WHO HAVE BEEN APPOINTED TO THAT<br />
COMMISSION. IT IS A VERY DILIGENT COMMISSION, WITH A<br />
VERY SERIOUS JOB TO DO. ITS RECOMMENDATIONS FOR 1974 AND<br />
1975 HAVE TRANSFORMED EDUCATION IN AUSTRALIA AND I WOULD<br />
BE ABLE TO SAY7THAT IF I WENT TO ANY STATE SCHOOL, IF I<br />
WENT TO ANY CATHOLIC SCHOOL, OR IF I WENT. TO ANY<br />
NON-GOVERNMENT, NON-CATHOLIC SCHOOL, ANYWHERE IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
THREE YEARS AGO, HAD ICLAIMED THAT IWOULD BE ABLE<br />
TO SAY THAT IN THE FUTURE, THERE MIGHT WELL HAVE BEEN A VERY<br />
GREAT NUMBER OF DOUBTING-THOMASES AMONG YOU. WHAT I SAID<br />
MIGHT HAVE BEEN RECEIVED WITH SCEPTICISM, IF NOT DISBELIEF.<br />
IBELIEVE THAT THIS AUDIENCE -SO MUCH INVOLVED IN<br />
THE PROFESSION OF TEACHING, SO MUCH CONCERNED ABOUT THE<br />
QUALITY OF EDUCATION, AND SO MUCH AWARE OF THE NEEDS OF THE<br />
YOUNG POPULATION IN OUR BURGEONING OUTER SUBURBS -KNOWS<br />
HOW MUCH WE. HAVE TRIED TO DO IN THE EDUCATIONAL SPHERE, AND<br />
HOW REAL ARE OUR INTENTIONS TO CONTINUE OUR POLICIES IN THIS<br />
AREA. </p>
<p>I HAVE VERY GREAT PLEASURE : i DECLARING OPEN<br />
ST. FRANCIS XAVIER SCHOOL. </p>
<p>AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT EXPENDITURE ON CATHOLIC EDUCATION<br />
IN WERRIWA<br />
SACRED HEART, CABRAMATTA<br />
GENERAL BUILDING GRANT<br />
RECURRENT GRANT 1974<br />
LIBRARY BOOK GRANT<br />
CAPITAL GRANT ( DISADVANTAGED)<br />
RECURRENT GRANT ( DISADVANTAGED)<br />
RECURRENT GRANT ( DISADVANTAGED) $ 200,000 45,564 3,937 6,000 5,770<br />
11,948 ALLOCATED ( 1974)<br />
( APPROVED TO<br />
APRIL 1975)<br />
( a ST. THRS'S, SADLIER-MILLEN<br />
RECURRENT GRANT 197LV<br />
LIBRARY BOOK GRANT<br />
CAPITAL GRANT ( DISADVANTAGED)<br />
RECURRENT GRANT ( DISADVANTAGED)<br />
RECURRENT GRANT ( DISADVANTAGED) ,30,770 1,697 2,000 7,520<br />
12 242<br />
OUR LADY OF MIT. CARMEL, MIT. PR'ITCHARD<br />
RECURRENT GRANT 1974<br />
LIBRARY BOOK GRANT<br />
CAPITAL GRANT ( DISADVANTAGED)<br />
RECURRENT GRANT ( DISADVANTAGED)<br />
RECURRENT GRANT ( DISADVANTAGED) ( 1974)<br />
( APPROVED TO<br />
APRIL 1975)<br />
40,446 3,500<br />
20,000 3,000 ( 1974)<br />
9,120<br />
A SPECIAL POINT OF INTEREST IS THE EXPENDITURE OF $ 9,000 ( INCLUDED<br />
WITHIN THE ABOVE-FIGURES) ON A REMEDIAL READING TEACHER BEING SHARED<br />
BY THE THREE SCHOOLS. ALL THREE. HAVE A HIGH PROPORTION OF PUPILS<br />
WITH SEVERE READING DIFFICULTIES. </p>
<p>HIGH SCHOOLS<br />
PATRICIAN BROTHERS HIGH SCHOOL, LIVERPOOL<br />
RECURRENT GRANT 1974<br />
1ST PAYMENT 1975<br />
LIBRARY BOOK GRANT $ 104,335 88,741 2,625<br />
ST. MARY'S HIGH SCHOOL, LIVERPOOL<br />
RECURRENT GRANT 1974<br />
1ST PAYMENT 1975 88,552 74,880<br />
GRANTS TO NON-GOVERNMENT SCHOOLS<br />
YEARAUSTRALIA 1970/ 71 32,508,000<br />
1971/ 72 36,236,000<br />
1972/ 73 47,755,000<br />
1973/ 74 70,163,000<br />
1974/ 75 ( ESTIMATE) $ 127,5331/" o INCREASE 11,4% 31.7% 46.9% 81.7% N. S. W,<br />
$ 12,136,000<br />
$ 13,234,000<br />
$ 17,277,000<br />
$ 24,564,000<br />
$ 45,206,000 </p>
<p>S<br />
CHILDHOOD SERVICES PROGRAM4<br />
ELECTORATE OF WERRIWA<br />
1973/ 74 1974/ 75<br />
( 1/ 1/ 74 to ( 1/ 7/ 74 to<br />
Iocation 30/ 6/ 74) 31/ 3/ 75)<br />
*.., Ition to salary costs,<br />
in pre-school centres.<br />
_,, Orthy Pre-Schoo, Holsworthy 2,747 4,572<br />
. c Village Pre-School, Holsworthy 2,031 3,312<br />
,... leburn Pre-School Kindergarten 1,656 4,622<br />
: 3jbi Kindergarten, Ingleburn 993 1,563<br />
jreen Valley Pre-School, Miller 6,170 12,966<br />
Liverpool Pre-School Centre,<br />
Liverpool 4,755 7,875<br />
Ashcroft Pre-School Kindergarten 2,674 4,668<br />
2. Contribution to salary costs, staff<br />
S in child care centres. 1972/ 73 1973/ 74 1974/ 75<br />
Ingleburn Child Care Centre,<br />
( Methodist Church) 365 4,424 3,955<br />
Ashcroft Child Care Centre,<br />
S( Methodist Church) 3,639 4,329<br />
3. Before and After School Proaram<br />
( Approved 5/ 3/ 75 under Childhood<br />
Services Program)<br />
Heckenberg Primary School<br />
equipment costs 2,370<br />
4. Child Care Centres Capital Cost<br />
( Approved under Child Care Act)<br />
Child Care Centre for 40 children<br />
aged 3-5 years Ingleburn 57,000<br />
( Methodist Church), completed<br />
operational<br />
Child Care Centre for 53 children<br />
aged 0-5 years Liverpool 200,000<br />
( Lutheran Church)-( approval in<br />
principle awaiting preparation<br />
of building plans)<br />
Child Care Centre for 40 children<br />
aged 3-5 years Macouarie Fields 180,000<br />
( Salvation Army, plans being<br />
prepared). N. S. W. Education Dept.<br />
Pre-School Centres Capital Cost,<br />
Approved in 1973/ 74 Interim Pre-School<br />
Child Care Services Program. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Double Unit Pre-School<br />
( conversion) Busby West<br />
Public School 38,555<br />
Single Unit Pre-School<br />
( conversion) Sadleir<br />
Public School 46,695<br />
Single Unit Pre-School<br />
( conversion) Canley Heights<br />
Public School 36,960<br />
Single Unit Pre-School<br />
( conversion) Lurnea<br />
Public School 44,435<br />
A number of other proposals are now being<br />
considered. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
