<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9819</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP NO ISSUES PLEASE - WE&#039;RE PROFESSIONALS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/11/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009819.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
12Q3<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
NO ISSUES PLEASE WE'RE PROFESSIONALS<br />
The Coalition's " strategy" of keeping the Australian people in the dark about<br />
policy matters for the election has today reached new heights of absurdity.<br />
The Liberals have refused to answer a straightforward question put to them<br />
by the ABC on what they see as the main issues at the next election because<br />
this " is of a strategic political nature and cannot be disclosed before the<br />
election campaign".<br />
Andrew Robb, the Liberal Party's Federal Director, has justified this insult to<br />
the Australian electorate on the grounds that the parties are playing for big<br />
stakes and it is professional and disciplined not to comment on these matters.<br />
This is despite an Adelaide newspaper report today which suggests the<br />
Liberal Party's policies for the election were " finalised and packaged at the<br />
weekend." If they're ready, why not let the public see them and make an<br />
informed assessment.<br />
John Howard and his colleagues are quite happy to engage in daily exercises<br />
in muckraking and personal abuse but do not have the honesty and<br />
intellectual depth to engage the Australian people in a debate on the kind of<br />
Australia they envisage for the future and on the policies which could achieve<br />
this. And yet, when the Government points to the ideological attitudes and the<br />
previous policies they have taken to the people as a guide to their real<br />
intentions, the Liberals simply accuse us of lying and of manufacturing a<br />
scare campaign.<br />
Mr Robb's latest excursion into the absurd only serves to increase the<br />
suspicion and scepticism with which Australians will view the Coalition's<br />
political tactics.<br />
CANBERRA 1 NOVEMBER 1995 </p>
<p>N. oa mJ QJ .1 ' VJrck t% AovC Aov,, W( 2<br />
ROB Well as we've predicted for months now, we've observed that their<br />
members, especially in tie regional seats, whoiu t1my'ie vulnetable, have been running away from<br />
Paul Koating, running a hundred miles from Paul Keating, trying to distance themselves from the<br />
Labor Party, but the irony is that everyone of those people have voted for every pioco of legislation<br />
that's gone thmgigh with the Keating Government over the last three years. They haven't opposed<br />
anything In the House. all the tax Increases. the petrol tax increase, the Medicare levy Increases.<br />
all of the biukvi piumiea, they'vu bUeri a party to It, and they're now trying to quite cynically<br />
present themselves as Independents In the electorate. Now I think that is taking the electorate for<br />
granted. EWART; That's the way politics works though, doe. n't It Are you ready to combat<br />
that? ROBB: Well, all we can do is shine a light on it. We can try and expose that. We<br />
have been saying that this is what they'll do. this Is what they're doing, we've ben saying that for<br />
months. EWART: An ABC survey of both Liberal and Labor candidates that's just Wen dull,<br />
the results of that are coming in now and the consistent answer from Liberal candidates, when<br />
they're questioned on what they see as being the issues at the next election, their answer is that<br />
question is of a strategic political nature and cannot be dis. lorsed hAfore the election campaign.<br />
Now isn't that getting a bit paranoid?<br />
ROBB: No. no, no. This is a campaign, we're playing for big stakes in this election,<br />
this is all about the future of Australia. We have to play a very professional part In the campaign<br />
that we run and the period betore the campaign, so I think R's quJite critical that we have a<br />
disciplined effort by all of our candidates across the country.<br />
EWART: But, if, as you scem to suggest, the electon campaign could be off and<br />
running any day now. Don't you need to have a bit more detail than that?<br />
ROBB: The work Is lone, and we will, as we've promised, we will release further<br />
detail and all the detail that the electuiulu iftwd tu make a Judgement between now and election<br />
day. ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
