<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7044</transcript-id>
    <title>THE INTERNATIONAL YEAR O PEACE AUSTRALIA`S CONTRIBUTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/11/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007044.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
YEAR OF PEACE<br />
AUSTRALIA'S<br />
CONTRIBUTION<br />
An Address to Parliament by the Prime Minister,<br />
the Hon. R. J. L. Hawke, M. P.<br />
28 November 1986 </p>
<p>THE INTERNATIONAL YEAR OF PEACE<br />
AUSTRALIA'S CONTRIBUTION<br />
An Address to Parliament by the<br />
Prime Minister<br />
the Hon. R. J. L. Hawke, AC, MP<br />
28 November 1986<br />
Australian Government Publishing Service<br />
Canberra 1986 </p>
<p>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE INTERNATIONAL YEAR OF PEACE AUSTRALIA'S CONTRIBUTION*<br />
CANBERRA 28 NOVEMBER 1986<br />
As 1986 draws to a close, and as the Parliament prepares to<br />
conclude its deliberations for the year, I take this<br />
j opportunity to review for the House the efforts made by the<br />
Government and the Australian community to advance the<br />
objectives of the International Year of Peace.<br />
it has been a year in which the Australian community has<br />
given vigorous and articulate expression to its desire to<br />
help build a more peaceful world.<br />
At the same time, 1986 has been a year in which Australians<br />
have been given greater grounds.-for-hope than for many years<br />
that the threat of nuclear war will be significantly<br />
diminished. EAST-WEST RELATIONS<br />
Before dealing with our national contribution to the IYP,<br />
let me say something about the international background to<br />
Australia's efforts.<br />
In a speech at the University of New England in September I<br />
said that historic opportunities existed for the restoration<br />
of stability and realistic understanding between the<br />
superpowers. There was the prospect of less suspicion and<br />
tension than had been the case for a decade.<br />
Subsequently, the renewed intensity of negotiations on<br />
nuclear and space arms found dramatic expression at the<br />
meeting in Reykjavik between President Reagan and General<br />
Secretary Gorbachev.<br />
Naturally, there was disappointment in Australia and around<br />
the world at the failure in Reykjavik to reach final<br />
agreement on the truly breathtaking set of proposals which<br />
was discussed there. We should recognise, however, that<br />
during 1986 a fundamental transformation has occurred in the<br />
nature of the superpower dialogue on security issues. The<br />
United States and the Soviet Union have begun to cut through<br />
to the very essence of the profound differences that<br />
separate them in these negotiations.<br />
Significant in this regard was the successful outcome in<br />
Stockholm at the Conference on Confidence and Security<br />
Building measures and Disarmament in Europe. This, the<br />
first East-West accord in security matters in seven * years,<br />
indicated a new determination to restore momentum to the<br />
process of arms control and disarmament after years of<br />
stalemate. </p>
<p>Significantly, the Stockholm agreement also saw the<br />
acceptance for the first time by the Soviet Union and its<br />
allies of-a system of mandatory on-site inspections to<br />
verify compliance with the information-exchange provisions.<br />
Greater openness in such matters is essential if real<br />
progress is to be made in disarmament and arms control.<br />
The road ahead will not be easy. But I have no doubt that<br />
we are on the right road and I believe there are grounds to<br />
be optimistic that the superpowers are determined to stay on<br />
it.<br />
Australia has received regular and detailed briefings from<br />
the United States on progress in these matters and the<br />
Government has taken full advantage of numerous<br />
opportunities to inject our views at the highest levels on<br />
both--sides on how progress-might be further achieved. We<br />
will continue to urge progress with all the force we have.<br />
As I have frequently said, I do not, exaggerate Australia's<br />
role and influence in these matters. But it is our firm<br />
conviction that we have the right and responsibility to be<br />
heard on issues of peace, arms control and disarmament. And<br />
we have been.<br />
Notwithstanding our differences with the United States on<br />
some issues of principle such as the Strategic Defence<br />
Initiative, the very healthy state of our relationship has<br />
enabled us to maintain a close and productive dialogue with<br />
Washington. And, while not seeking to ignore the gulf in<br />
strategic orientation and ideological perception which<br />
separates us from the Soviet Union, we have restored<br />
sensible contact with Moscow, without which any Australian<br />
arms control and disarmament policy would be meaningless.<br />
I have written on several occasions to President Reagan and<br />
General Secretary Gorbachev this year, making clear the<br />
importance that the Australian Government attaches to<br />
continued compliance with the SALT II Treaty. I conveyed<br />
our view that the Soviet Union has a case to answer on<br />
specific compliance issues, but that Australia was no less<br />
concerned at the US announcement in May that future<br />
decisions on the structure of its strategic forces would no<br />
longer be bound by SALT II limitations.<br />
We will continue to make our voice heard.<br />
In a variety of other ways, the Government has been very<br />
active in the pursuit of peace and disarmament in 1986.<br />
SOUTH PACIFIC NUCLEAR FREE ZONE ( SPNFZ-) TREATY<br />
This year marks a historic moment for disarmament in the<br />
South Pacific. </p>
<p>when the Senate passes the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone<br />
Treaty Bill and related legislation currently before it,<br />
Australia will be in a position to ratify the Treaty of<br />
Rarotonga. Our ratification will be the eighth, and will<br />
bring the Treaty into force.<br />
Not only does the Treaty represent a major disarmament<br />
achievement, it also makes a positive contribution to<br />
regional security.<br />
The countries of the South Pacific Forum have built upon<br />
existing international treaties to make a new treaty that<br />
will help preserve the South Pacific as it is today:<br />
free from nuclear weapons stationed in the countries<br />
and territories of the _ region;<br />
free from nuclear waste dumping; and<br />
with the tragic ( and we hope temporary) exception of<br />
French Polynesia, free from nuclear testing.<br />
All the countries of the region want to preserve these<br />
freedoms and that is the central purpose of the Treaty.<br />
In this context, the Government is very pleased that<br />
countries of the South Pacific, al ' ong with the United States<br />
and France, agreed in principle on 25 November to adopt the<br />
text of a Convention for the Protection and Development of<br />
the Natural Resources and Environment of the South Pacific<br />
Region ( the SPREP Convention).<br />
The Convention complements the Treaty of Rarotongars<br />
prohibition on radioactive waste dumping at sea in the South<br />
Pacific-Nuclear Free Zone.<br />
The Treaty does not seek to undermine the favorable security<br />
environment which the South Pacific enjoys. It does not in<br />
any way conflict with Australia's defence arrangements,<br />
notably ANZUS.<br />
On the contrary, the Treaty of Rarotonga seeks to build on<br />
the factors that have created and sustained the security of<br />
the region to help ensure that the South Pacific, unlike<br />
other parts of the world, does not in the future become a<br />
theatre for nuclear confrontation.<br />
The Pr-otocols to the Treaty adopted in final form by the<br />
South Pacific Forum in August this year will be open for<br />
signature on 1 December. These provide for the United<br />
States, the United Kingdom and France to apply provisions of<br />
the Treaty to their South Pacific Territories and for the<br />
nuclear-weapon states ( the United States, the USSR, the<br />
United Kingdom, France and China) to undertake not to use or<br />
threaten to use nuclear weapons against parties to the<br />
Treaty nor to conduct nuclear testing in the South Pacific. </p>
<p>It. is the Government's strong hope that all the eligible<br />
states, which have major responsibility for international<br />
peace and security, will adhere to the Protocols to the<br />
Treaty of Rarotonga.<br />
The significance of the Bill before the Senate goes further<br />
than clearing the way for the entry into force of the Treaty<br />
of Rarotonga, important though that is. For, in passing the<br />
South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone Treaty Bill, Australia will<br />
become the first independent, sovereign country in the world<br />
to make a commitment by national legislation against the<br />
nuclear weapons option.<br />
The Bill commits this and future Governments to prohibit the<br />
manufacture, acquisition and possession of nuclear explosive<br />
devices and the stationing and testing of such devices<br />
within Australia's territory. We take great pride in this<br />
stand. It is deeply regrettable that the opposition in this House,<br />
and no doubt in the Senate, saw fit to oppose this historic<br />
declaration of principle.<br />
COMPREHENSIVE TEST BAN<br />
During 1986, the Australian Government has continued to<br />
attach the highest priority in our multilateral disarmament<br />
diplomacy to the conclusion of a comprehensive nuclear test<br />
ban ( CTB).<br />
Stich a treaty would ban all kinds of nuclear tests in all<br />
environments by all countries for all time. It is a<br />
feasible and negotiable proposal whose implementation would<br />
be an important step towards preventing horizontal and<br />
vertical proliferation of nuclear weapons.<br />
Earlier this month, the First Committee of the United<br />
Nations General Assembly voted on several resolutions<br />
dealing with nuclear testing. Two of these resolutions were<br />
sponsored by Australia and both received overwhelming<br />
support.<br />
The first was the Australia-New Zealand resolution on a<br />
comprehensive test ban which reaffirms the fundamental<br />
importance of such a treaty and sets out a program of action<br />
. to achieve it. Five CTB resolutions were considered by the<br />
Committee this year. Australia's resolution, which has the<br />
best chances of contributing to a nuclear-free world,<br />
received 117 positive votes, the highest number of any of<br />
the five.<br />
The Australia-New Zealand resolution was co-sponsored by 26<br />
countries including Sweden, Canada and Japan. The United<br />
States and Blritain, who had opposed our resolution in 1985,<br />
abstained this year. Only France voted against. This<br />
excellent result reflected the international community's<br />
acknowledgement of Australia's realistic approach and deep<br />
commitment to the early, conclusion of a CTB Treaty. </p>
<p>The second Australian resolution considered this year calls<br />
on the nuclear testing states to make public each test and<br />
to provide certain data including the size of the test and<br />
the geology of the test site. This was a new initiative and<br />
the resolution received 107 positive votes. Only one<br />
country France opposed the resolution.<br />
CHEMICAL WEAPONS<br />
The abolition of chemical weapons has long been a high<br />
priority objective of the Australian Government's arms<br />
control and disarmament policies. We have made special<br />
efforts during 1986 to facilitate progress on effective<br />
international measures against such abhorrent weapons.<br />
Australia is at the forefront of international action to<br />
this end.<br />
The Australian Government is committed to the early<br />
conclusion of a comprehensive Chemical Weapons Convention<br />
which would ban the production, stockpiling and use of all<br />
chemical weapons and provide for the destruction of all<br />
existing stocks of chemical weapons and their production<br />
facilities.<br />
We have been prominent at both the diplomatic and technical<br />
levels in the negotiations on chemical weapons at the<br />
Conference on Disarmament. During 1986 Australia chaired<br />
one of the Conference's three working groups on chemical<br />
weapons which made considerable progress. We have also<br />
actively supported and participated in investigations by the<br />
UN Secretary-General into reports of the use of chemical<br />
weapons. We have instituted controls on the export of particular<br />
chemicals which could be used in the manufacture of chemical<br />
weapons. In addition, Australia convened consultations<br />
during 1986 with eighteen Western countries ( known as the<br />
' Australia Group') which have adopted similar controls with<br />
a view to co-ordinating such measures internationally.<br />
These outstanding results in the cause of peace and<br />
disarmament were only made possible by the strong and<br />
sustained commitment of the Government to achieving real<br />
progress on arms control, a field in which little can be<br />
done without detailed expertise in the issues, international<br />
acceptance of the contribution we can make and the skills of<br />
sensitive diplomacy and negotiation.<br />
The Government, from the moment it came to office, set about<br />
establishing for the first time in Australia's history, the<br />
necessary credentials for successful work in the field of<br />
disarmament. The highest credit for our success belongs to my colleague,<br />
the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Bill Hayden, whose skill,<br />
initiative and energy have won him worldwide respect and<br />
regard. </p>
<p>I should also acknowledge the efforts of our officials in<br />
the Department of Foreign Affairs, and those of our<br />
Ambassador for Disarmament.<br />
IDEALS OF THE INTERNATIONAL YEAR OF PEACE<br />
So far, I have talked about the international background to<br />
the International Year of Peace and the Government's own<br />
disarmament activities.<br />
In resolving to give its strong support to the United<br />
Nations' designation of 1986 as the International Year of<br />
Peace ( IYP), the Government reaffirmed the high priority it<br />
has consistently placed on arms control and disarmament but,<br />
at the same time, agreed with the view of the United Nations<br />
that IYP activities should not be sponsored only at the<br />
level of national governments.<br />
Accordingly, the Government sought to encourage the wide<br />
range of individuals and community organisations in<br />
Australia who had set high value on the opportunities this<br />
year offered them to express their views and make their own<br />
contribution to the debate.<br />
The search for international peace habitually attracts close<br />
attention from both cynics and utopians. Cynics say that<br />
military confrontation is inevitable and that no generation<br />
in history has been totally free from the threat of war.<br />
For their part, utopians are so eager for peace that they<br />
trust the panaceas of unilateral disarmament and<br />
isolationism, ignoring the unfortunate history of such<br />
policies. The view of this Government, however, is that to work for<br />
real peace is neither to ignore reality nor to neglect<br />
securi tv.<br />
During the ! YP, I have witnessed again and again the<br />
yearning for peace among people in Australia, especially our<br />
young people. I have heard their conviction that there are<br />
better alternatives to the threats under which we live and<br />
that there are better uses for human and material resources<br />
than the accumulation of weapons.<br />
We believe that the IYP has provided a timely opportunity<br />
for people throughout the world to find ways of achieving<br />
progress towards the peace we all seek.<br />
IYP PROGRAM<br />
The planning of the IYP program fell within the portfolio of<br />
the M'inister for Foreign Affairs, Bill Hayden, and, again,<br />
he deserves full credit for his determination that the noble<br />
idea behind the IYP was fully and appropriately celebrated<br />
in Australia. </p>
<p>To assist him in planning and implementing the program Mr<br />
Hayden appointed Mrs Stella Cornelius, the prominent<br />
community activist, as TYP Director. He also established<br />
IYP Committees both at the National level and in each of the<br />
States and Territories with members drawn from a broad range<br />
of community organisations.<br />
I should like to take this opportunity of paying tribute to<br />
Mrs Cornelius' tireless and dedicated work for the<br />
objectives of the IYP and to the members of the various<br />
committees who gave so freely of their time and energy to<br />
make the program a success. I should also like to<br />
acknowledge the generous support given to the IYP by State<br />
Governments. The Government approved a budget of $ 3.15 million for the<br />
IYP Program in Australia. These funds were divided on a<br />
roughly equal basis between three main components of the<br />
program: information and advertising;<br />
. a series of Government projects;<br />
and in recognition of the vital role of the community,<br />
$ 1,050,000 to support non-government projects.<br />
You will have seen the IYP advertisements on radio and<br />
television. Those advertisements were designed to relate to<br />
peace in all its meanings, and to counter despair and apathy<br />
with the message that, while peace is not easy to achieve,<br />
it is not impossible and every attempt at progress is a<br />
" Step in the Right Direction"<br />
The med * ia campaign was complemented by the production and<br />
wide distribution of 20,000 Peace Kits containing detailed<br />
information on Australia's role and achievements in<br />
disarm~ ament and arms control and suggestions as to ways in<br />
which local communities might participate in the program.<br />
In order to encourage better public understanding of the<br />
complexities of international arms control, the Government<br />
sponsored a number of projects, which included a series of<br />
public arms control and disarmament seminars in State<br />
capital cities and an international symposium on Seismic<br />
Verification, a vital technical precondition for a possible<br />
Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty.<br />
The Government's IYP program was officially launched by the<br />
" Overture of Peace", a concert by over 2000 NSW school<br />
students which was televised nationally in February. As an<br />
optimistic, joyful celebration of peace it was a fitting<br />
beginning to the year.<br />
That event also symbolised the strong connection the<br />
Government saw between the International Year of Peace and<br />
the.-immediately preceding International Year of Youth. </p>
<p>The enthusiasm and commitment of our young people for the<br />
goal of peace obvious at that occasion asserted itself again<br />
at His Holiness the Pope's peace rally in Sydney on Tuesday<br />
night. Just over a month ago I presented Australian Peace Awards to<br />
Australians who had made outstanding ' contributions to peace<br />
in many areas of activity. in establishing these Awards<br />
during the IYP, the Government sought to give fitting<br />
recognition to both the quality and diversity of community<br />
achievements in work for a peaceful future.<br />
These same elements were also reflected to an overwhelming<br />
degree in the non-government IYP projects organised and<br />
carried out by individuals and community organisations in<br />
every part of the country. Many of these received financial<br />
support from the Federal Government. I am also aware of<br />
many more community projects which have been mounted quite<br />
independently of any Government assistance.<br />
Non-government projects for the IYP have involved the<br />
Churches, peace groups, academics, the Aboriginal community,<br />
artists, teachers, school students, welfare organisations,<br />
ethnic groups, women's organisations, the RSL, service<br />
clubs, trade unions and many others. The projects have<br />
included conferences and seminars, theatrical performances<br />
and concerts, publications, videos, educational and research<br />
programs. They have taken place in every part of Australia,<br />
from the largest cities to the smallest rural towns.<br />
So impressive was this response to the IYP that the UN<br />
Secretary-General sent a personal message commending<br />
Australian community groups for their enthusiasm and<br />
commitment. Three UN Secretariat officials who visited<br />
Australia to familiarise themselves with our IYP program<br />
were particularly impressed with its unique combination of<br />
Government and non-government activities.<br />
It is clear from this great community response that the IYP<br />
has been a great success in Australia. Not only have<br />
Australians beccme more aware of why they should care about<br />
international events around them but they have also<br />
demonstrated their strong concern to leave the world at<br />
peace for the benefit of future generations.<br />
What has been achieved this year is a firmer basis for<br />
continuing work for peace in the future both by the<br />
Government and the Australian community as a whole. The<br />
heightened awareness of the issues and sense of<br />
responsibility for a world of peace which the IYP has<br />
generated will not end on 31 December 1986.<br />
I would like to address some concluding words to young<br />
Australians, who more than any of us, have made their<br />
concerns about peace felt this year and whose responsibility<br />
it will be in the future to shoulder the burden of securing<br />
-peace. </p>
<p>9.<br />
I have already mentioned that I spoke earlier this year to<br />
an audience at the University of New England in Armidale.<br />
Let me conclude now as I concluded then.<br />
" Do not succumb to the paralysis of despair. It would<br />
be a tragedy if our young people, in particular, were to<br />
be so weighed down at the remote prospect of nuclear war<br />
as not to care adequately about their own self<br />
development or to contribute to our society in a<br />
positive and energetic way.<br />
Seek to decode the often confusing language of arms<br />
control, its acronyms and its technical jargon. Do not<br />
allow the so-called experts to monopolise the debate.<br />
Inform yourselves fully about the difficult<br />
international issues involved. Effective arms control<br />
will only come about through incremental, careful and<br />
patiently negotiated steps. Do not become overwhelmed<br />
by pessimism at the sometimes glacial speed of progress<br />
in disarmament negotiations.<br />
Above all, do not fail to let the political leadership<br />
of this country, and of the international community,<br />
know of your desire for tangible progress towards a<br />
saner, safer world." </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
