<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12153</transcript-id>
    <title>Centenary Scholarships for Young Australians </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/03/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that one hundred young Australians have been awarded Centenary Scholarships to undertake study in a number of academic and vocational areas including science and engineering, the health professions, the arts, trades and in youth development.</p>
<p>The scholarships have been awarded by The Foundation for Young Australians in a joint one off initiative with the Commonwealth Government to mark the Centenary of Federation.</p>
<p>The Centenary Scholarships for Young Australians are worth up to $10,000 a year for a maximum of six years, and will assist young people aged 18 to 30 with academic studies and/or specialised training here in Australia, and for some recipients, at overseas institutions.</p>
<p>The young Australians awarded scholarships are from all States and Territories, and many are from regional and rural communities. They are pursuing studies and specialised training in a wide variety of fields, and include:</p>
<p>? Jason Dew from Robe in South Australia who is studying architecture at Adelaide University.</p>
<p>? Shannon Butler from Northampton in Western Australia for studies in Health Information Management at Curtin University.</p>
<p>? Tara Walker from Murarrie in Queensland who is undertaking a Bachelor of Speech Pathology degree at the University of Queensland.</p>
<p>? Carlee Thomas from Nhulunbuy in the Northern Territory to study medicine at Monash University.</p>
<p>The Centenary Scholarships are funded from a $15 million Commonwealth endowment provided to The Foundation for Young Australians when it was launched in June 2000.</p>
<p>The assessment criteria for the scholarship programme gave particular emphasis to assisting young people in an area of study or training that would be of long term benefit the Australian community.</p>
<p>In addition, priority was given to disadvantaged young people, particularly from rural and remote areas who otherwise may not have been able to pursue further studies.</p>
<p>The Foundation for Young Australians is also using the endowment to continue the important work of its predecessors, the Australian Youth Foundation and the Queen's Trust for Young Australians, as a non-profit organisation providing practical initiatives to help disadvantaged young people, and to promoting excellence and leadership.</p>
<p>The Foundation for Young Australians is contributing to a social coalition between the community, non-profit organisations, business and government, and in doing so is helping to strengthen local communities.</p>
<p>I congratulate everyone who has been awarded a Centenary Scholarship, and wish each of them well in their studies.</p>
<p>I would also like to congratulate The Foundation for Young Australians for its work on this valuable programme.</p>
<p>12 March 2001 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
