<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3750</transcript-id>
    <title>EMPLOYMENT IN QUEENSLAND</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/05/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003750.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J4) pAU ST A LL<br />
Press Release for Queensland<br />
24 May 1975<br />
EMPLOYMENT IN QUEENSLAND<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, predicted today that<br />
-the employment situation in Queensland would soon improve.<br />
He said traditionally, Queensland had higher unemployment than<br />
other States, but the present rate was unacceptably severe.<br />
He said legislation introduced last Wednesday would<br />
enable Queensland beef producers to obtain carry-on finance<br />
at 3k per cent interest.<br />
The Australian Government would make available<br />
million for this purpose in Queensland, matching the State<br />
Government's contribution.<br />
Mr Whitlam said the re-opening of the market for<br />
beef in Japan was another reason for greater confidence.<br />
Employment activity in the beef industry would accelerate as<br />
the Japanese market expanded.<br />
He said the sugar industry had enjoyed a recordbreaking<br />
year and this would improve the economic climate<br />
in many areas of Queensland, producing more jobs.<br />
The Prime Minister said that while unemployment<br />
remained at its present level thoere would be no cut-backs in<br />
relief funds provided by the Australian Government to Queensland.<br />
lie said Queensland had received more money from the RED scheme<br />
than any other State but N. S. W.<br />
The Australian Government had provided $ 29.5 million<br />
for 955 projects in Queensland. Total cost of the project was<br />
$ 33.5 million and 9,893 unemployed workers had found jobs<br />
under the scheme.<br />
Mr Whitlam said he was concerned by reports of<br />
anomalies and inefficiency in the RED scheme. He said it was<br />
up to local authorities and other sponsors to ensure the<br />
proposals they submitted were sensible and useful projects.<br />
The Australian Government did not plan individual projects but<br />
only approved those submitted to it by the local sponsors.<br />
Money was allocated to areas with the highest unemployment.<br />
It was disturbing that the State Government's own unemployment<br />
relief scheme was discriminating against these areas because they<br />
were receiving RED grants.<br />
Mr Whitlam also appealed to the State Government to<br />
maintain its own employment levels. He said there should be no<br />
basis for talk of lay offs from State Government departments. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The State Treasurer Sir Gordon Chalk had made a most<br />
thorough assessment of Queensland's needs prior to the Premiers<br />
Conference on 14 February. The Queensland Government had received<br />
$ 47.5 million all it asked for, and more specifically to<br />
maintain its own employment levels, and re-employ people<br />
who had been laid off.<br />
If lay-offs were now being predicted again it meant<br />
either that Sir Gordon Chalk had miscalculated his needs or<br />
that the funds had been used inefficiently.<br />
BRISBANE. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
