<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4096</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS - 14TH APRIL 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/04/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004096.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F76/ 68<br />
FOR PRESS 14th April, 1976.<br />
There have been consultations today involving myself, Mr. Hawke<br />
and Mr. Egerton from the A. C. T. U. and Mr. Polites of the<br />
National'Employers Policy Committee and with reference to<br />
representatives of the Wool Brokers and the Storemen and Packers<br />
Union. The Government and those parties directly involved in the<br />
consultations would hope that a resolution of the existing<br />
situation in the wool industry could be expedited along the<br />
following lines:<br />
1. It is'accepted as arguable whether the men have been stood<br />
down or are on strike.<br />
2. The Wool Brokers have withdrawn the stand down notices and<br />
work is available on existing award conditions.<br />
3. Coxitinuity of employment will be preserved for all those<br />
who resume work.<br />
4. Relevant termination conditions will be applicable where<br />
it is determined that men have been retrenched and do not<br />
wish to resume their previous employment.<br />
There is acceptance of the scope for negotiation on the<br />
question of sick leave and rest pauses in the industry.<br />
6. It is accepted also that the dispute over bale weights will<br />
proceed within the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission<br />
with an independent report being prepared by Dr. Ferguson of<br />
the University of Sydney.<br />
7. It is noted that the unions will subsequently be seeking a<br />
conference with the dumping companies on their container<br />
claims.<br />
8. It is noted that the wages claim of $ 9.10 per week is to<br />
be the subject of a hearing before Mr. Commissioner Heagney<br />
next week.<br />
9. The Government is prepared to assist the parties in any way<br />
including participation in any discussions which might be<br />
considered appropriate. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
To this end the Government requests the parties to confer<br />
as soon as possible on the basis of these points with a<br />
view to an early resumption of work and I have asked the<br />
President of the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission<br />
Mr. Justice Moore to chair such a conference. It will be<br />
held at 9.30 a. m. tomorrow. It would be open to any party<br />
to discuss any of the points covered above and the<br />
Government would have no objection to such discussions.<br />
OoO---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
