<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1581</transcript-id>
    <title>REFERENDUM: THE &quot;YES&quot; CASE - TALK BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/05/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001581.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
' I -A Embgo: 7.30 p. m. Wednesday<br />
L [ BRA 24th May, 1967.<br />
REFEREDUM: THE " YES" CASE<br />
Talk by the Prime Minister, M! r. Hirold Holt<br />
( This is the final radio and television talk by the Prime inister<br />
in support of the " Yes" cases for both referendums. It will be<br />
progr-ammed by the A. 3. C. in all states this evening.)<br />
You '-re being : sked, on May 27th, to approve two measures<br />
passed by the Nationial Parliament to ilter the Constitution. That<br />
is why the Leaders of the three main parties represented in Federal<br />
Parliament are asking you to say " Yes to both questions.<br />
First, we ask you to say " Yes" to the proposed law Uto<br />
alter the Constitution so that the number of Memoers of the hualse<br />
of Representatives may be increased without necessarily increasing<br />
the number of Sen-tors".<br />
Secondly -ie-ask you to say " Yes" to the proposed lawito<br />
alter the Constitution insofar as it affects our a1boriginal<br />
population. As to this second question, there w-is no dispute nor<br />
arrument in the Federal Parliament. It was '. dopted unanimously in<br />
both the House of Representatives and the Senate. The alteration<br />
is designed to remove from the Constitution certain words which<br />
appear o discriminate a'ainst Aborigines and to provide that<br />
Aborigines are to be counted in reckoning the popul. tion. Just<br />
-s the Parliament WILs unanimous, we expect that you will wish to<br />
vote " Yes" to this proposal.<br />
As to the first question, a case for " Yes" and a case for<br />
" No" has been sent to all electors. I hope that a. fter reading these<br />
cases the issues raised are clear in your minds and you appreciate<br />
the strength of the case for a " Yes" vote.<br />
Some may still be puzzled about wht is called the nexus<br />
between the House of Representatives and the Sena-te. It is in fact,<br />
a provision in our Cons itution which says thit the House ot<br />
Representatives cannot be enlarzed without at the same time increasing<br />
the number of Sen-ttors on a basis of one more Senator for each two<br />
added to the House of Representatives.<br />
If you siy " Yes" to the lw passed by both Houses of<br />
the Feder'Ll TFarliament, it will be possible to look at membership<br />
of the House of Representtitives and memership of the Senate as<br />
two separate matters. It will be po. sible, when tho ght necessa-ry,<br />
to enlarge the popular House; it will be possible, when thought<br />
necess-ry, to enlArge the Sen-te. But &gt;, on't ue compelled as<br />
we now are, to incrLase the membership of both the Senate an the<br />
popular House it the same time.<br />
termtermss.. That's what the nexus referendum amounts to in simple<br />
But, as well as breaking the nexus, the new law we<br />
have passed in Parliament would write into the Constitution for<br />
the first time a provision clearly restricting the rate it which<br />
the House of Representatives can grow. It will be tied to population </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Yrowth and tied to a figure of population represented by each<br />
Federal Member nearly twenty thousand greater than he represented<br />
on averae when the present size of the Parliament was fixed in<br />
1949. You should understand also that every member of the<br />
House of Representatives voted for the proposed change, and in<br />
the Senate the voting for the alteration was forty-five to seven.<br />
The authors of the " No" case tell you thit Parliament's<br />
proposal would weaken the position and authority of the Senate.<br />
This argument will not stand up. The Senate of sixty members is<br />
made up of ten from each of the six States. The powers and role<br />
of the Senate are defined in the Constitution, and nothing in our<br />
proposal would change these powers. We believe that at the moment<br />
sixty Senators can adequately discharge their responsiilities as<br />
members" of a House of Review and is a States' House. I mi. ht<br />
point out that, althouAh te Senators are elected from the individual<br />
States and members of the House of Representatives from individual<br />
electorates, all members of the National Parliament ( whether Senators<br />
or MF's) come from the States. They are all in a very real sense<br />
State men and women in a Federal Parliament.<br />
You would imagine from the " No" case that while Senators<br />
retain their State identity all the members of he popular House<br />
suddenly, upon election, cease to have any identity at all with the<br />
States they come from. This is nonsense!<br />
The authors of the " No" case don't argue the practical<br />
and common sense proposition that the link between the Senate and<br />
the popular House is clums and that it mikes for more, not<br />
fewer, parliamentarians. Tey say, in effect, " If we can't have<br />
more oenators, we'll rubbish the House of Representatives and say<br />
they are an incompetent lot anyway". This is childish.<br />
The House of Representatives the House in which governments<br />
are made is constructed upon electorates and electorates are<br />
constructed on population. They change as the population changes. They<br />
doulgrow in a reasonable way as the population grows. From time<br />
to time, since Federation, hen the population was small, the<br />
popular House has ben enlirged. By he time the next election comes<br />
round, it will have been twenty years since the size of the House<br />
of Representatives was last reviewed, and the population will have<br />
grown by fifty per cent from eight to twelve millions over that<br />
period. The time has come for ' aother look at the numbers required<br />
in the House to make it truly representative of a growing population<br />
a population conscious of the changes and developments occurring in<br />
our continent. If there is to ue any increase, a " Yes" vote from<br />
you, because of the safeguard it incorporates, will ensure that any<br />
increase must be modest.<br />
The oddest feature of the " No" case is th: t while its<br />
authors protest that we have enough parliamentarians, a " No" vote<br />
would perpetrate an out-dated system whereby if we wanted twelve<br />
more parliamentarians we would be compelled to have eighteen more,<br />
and if just by way of illustration, we wanted twenty-four more<br />
we would be compelled to have thirty-six. There is an Alice in<br />
; onderland kind of logic about this idea yet, when you strip away<br />
all the fancy talk, te authors of the case are rot really<br />
arguing for fewer parliamentarians. They are the champions of a<br />
stay-put situation guaranteeing more parliamentarians every time<br />
only a few are needed.<br />
7e, on the other hand, are asking you to vote " Yes" as<br />
a mature democracy looking sensibly it a practical parliamentary<br />
reform. It is neither sensible nor practical to keep the Senate<br />
and the House tied together like Siamese twins.<br />
CAF E 1 * 4<br />
CAER. 24 " A 1967. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
