<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19417</transcript-id>
    <title>New Data Show West Australian Schools Funding Boost</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/06/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Government</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>Every school sector in Western Australia will see their funding increase every year under the Gillard Government's National Plan for School Improvement, as shown by new data released today.</p>
<p>Government schools in Western Australia will receive a boost of around $670 million, while non-government schools will benefit from around an extra $250 million in funding over the next six years.</p>
<p>This extra investment, plus securing a better indexation rate, comes on top of existing funding for schools and will see a total public investment of about $2.8 billion in the six years from 2014.</p>
<p>The new data is based on around $920 million of extra funding on offer under Labor's plan, provided the Barnett Government signs up to the National Plan for School Improvement.</p>
<p>From the total public funding provided to WA schools over the next six years if the National Plan is adopted:</p>
<p> * 	The location loading will provide about $1.9 billion  - benefitting 83,000 students in 378 schools (35 per cent of all schools.)<br />
 * 	The size loading will provide about $770 million  -  benefitting 126,800 students in 648 schools (61 per cent of all schools).<br />
 * 	The Indigenous loading will provide about $1.1 billion for Indigenous students  -  benefitting around 27,000 students in 917 schools (86 per cent of all schools).</p>
<p>If Colin Barnett accepts the offer that will see better schools across WA, schools will benefit from around an additional $600 million in Commonwealth funding over the next six years.</p>
<p>Under the plan every school will see its funding rise year-on-year, with the biggest increases going to the schools that need it most.</p>
<p>Labor's National Plan for School Improvement will deliver:</p>
<p> * 	More one on one attention and support in the classroom for every child.<br />
 * 	Specialist literacy and numeracy programs for those children in danger of being left behind.<br />
 * 	Greater assistance for those students with disability or special need.<br />
 * 	Building the skills and knowledge of teachers and providing mentoring support for those who are new to the profession.</p>
<p>It is time for Premier Barnett and Education Minister Peter Collier to put the students of Western Australia first and sign up to the National Plan for School Improvement.</p>
<p>With 10 days to go the choice is clear. They can walk away from the offer and short-change students, or they can sign up to the new fairer funding system which will benefit every sector and every school in Western Australia.</p>
<p>This is a once in a lifetime opportunity to deliver the biggest investment in schools in generations.</p>
<p>The table below shows extra funding, per sector, under the Prime Minister's offer to Western Australia:</p>
<p>	Additional funding for Western Australian schools under the National Plan for School Improvement						$ millions					2014					2015					2016					2017					2018					2019					TOTAL							Government Schools					20					48					82					123					171					227					671							Catholic Schools					5					11					16					21					25					30					107							Independent Schools					6					13					20					27					35					43					143							TOTAL					31					71					118					171					231					300					921	</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
