<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23783</transcript-id>
    <title>Report of the Royal Commission into the Home Insulation Programme</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/09/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Government welcomes the Final Report of the Royal Commission into the Home Insulation Programme which has been received by the Governor-General from the Royal Commissioner, Mr Ian Hanger AM QC.</p>
<p>The tabling of this report delivers on the Government’s election commitment to properly investigate this policy disaster and provide the victims’ families with the answers they deserve.</p>
<p>Four young men lost their lives as a consequence of this bungled programme.</p>
<p>As well, homes were damaged or destroyed and businesses badly affected.</p>
<p>I hope this report brings some comfort to everyone affected.</p>
<p>The report’s findings are grave and its recommendations are detailed.</p>
<p>It details a litany of failures arising from a dysfunctional culture in the former administration.</p>
<p>The Government will carefully consider the findings and recommendations of this report, which is a timely reminder of what can happen if Government acts with undue haste.</p>
<p>We will provide a preliminary response by the end of the month, with a final response delivered by the end of this year.</p>
<p>The Government’s response will focus on ensuring such a catastrophic policy failure never happens again.</p>
<p>I thank the Royal Commissioner and his staff for their work.</p>
<p>I particularly thank the victims’ families who shared their anguish with the Commission.</p>
<p>An electronic copy of the Report is available at the Royal Commission website - <a href="http://www.homeinsulationroyalcommission.gov.au/">http://www.homeinsulationroyalcommission.gov.au</a></p>
<p>1 September 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
