<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4174</transcript-id>
    <title>UNION ATTITUDE TO MKU CONTRACT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004174.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MEDIA RELEASE Canberra, 28 June .76<br />
UNION ATTITUDE TO MKU CONTRACT<br />
Statement by the Acting Prime Minister, Minister for National<br />
Resources and Minister for Overseas Trade, Rt.. Hon. J. D. Anthony<br />
I have been advised that a meeting in Sydney today of<br />
representatives of unions and ACTU State Branches associated<br />
with the mining or transport of uranium decided to ask the<br />
Government, pending the report of-the Ranger Inquiry, to<br />
allow a contract by Mary Kathleen Uranium -to export in July<br />
45.4 tonnes of uranium oxide to the United States to be filled<br />
by borrowing from an overseas uranium stockpile.<br />
I have also been advised that the meeting suggested that<br />
the Government, if necessary, should underwrite the ability of<br />
Mary Kathleen Uranium to borrow from an overseas stockpile.<br />
I understand the meeting also said that if the Government<br />
issued an export licence to enable Mary Kathleen Uranium to<br />
fill the contract from its own production then all unions<br />
involved with Mary Kathleen Uranium would immediately withdraw<br />
their services.<br />
The Government had put it to the unions that a contract<br />
commitment for a July 1976 shipment of 45.4 tonnes of uranium<br />
oxide from MKU to a U. S. power utility should be shipped.<br />
The. Government indicated its view that an earlier ACTU<br />
resolution which would cause unions to disallow shipments until<br />
the report of the Fox Committee of Inquiry was considered should<br />
not apply to this shipment.<br />
An interim report of the Fox Inquiry is expected by the end<br />
of August, and no further shipments of uranium oxide from MKU are<br />
required to be made before October.<br />
The unions have now reaffirmed their earlier decision, but<br />
have urged that the Government should enable the 45.4 tonnes<br />
commitment to be made by, in fact, underwriting the ability of<br />
MKU to borrow from an overseas stockpile.<br />
Successive Governments have reaffirmed that existing<br />
contracts will be honoured. It is natural therefore for the<br />
company, the purchaser and the Government to look to this amount<br />
to be supplied from production at MKU in the normal way.<br />
I repeat what I have said before: existing contracts will<br />
be honoured by Australia. The Government will, after urgent<br />
discussions with the company, re-consider options in the light<br />
of the unions' request.<br />
The threat of cutting off production at MKU will not weigh<br />
in the Government's consideration. That would result in the<br />
unemployment in an isolated area of some 300 people, but would<br />
be solely as a result of the unions' own actions. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
