<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5377</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF ROCKHAMPTON SHOW</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/06/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005377.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR K THURSDAY, 12 JU TE, 1980<br />
OPENING OF , O,,' H' 2' TON" SHOW<br />
Tamie and I are both delighted to be asked to be here today.<br />
Rockhampton is the centre of a wonderful part of Australia.<br />
I can remember when it was possible for me to just call in<br />
unofficially and very briefly a year ago and I was asked<br />
if I could come back next year arid open the Show. It was<br />
something that I was very, very happy to accept.<br />
This is, as you well know, the capital of one of the<br />
largest and one of the best beef growing areas not only in<br />
Australia, but also in the world. 50% of all Australia's<br />
beef cattle are in Queensland. A very large proportion of<br />
those are in the area of which Rockhampton is the legitimate<br />
centre and headquarters.<br />
one of the very pleasing things in going around rural<br />
Australia and country towns and cities at the present moment<br />
is the sense of confidence and opntimism that I think is now<br />
present in every part of Australia. A few years ago, with<br />
disastrous prices and difficult times not only in the beef<br />
industry but also in other rural industries<br />
people just did not know what future there might be.<br />
Now, -for the beef industry, for the sheep and wool industry,<br />
for wheat and for sugar, where prices have increased remarkably<br />
over the last 12 months, the outlook for Australia's major<br />
primary products is reasonable. That means not only a great<br />
deal to the farmers and pastoralists involved, but also<br />
it means an enormous amount to the towns and cities that<br />
service those industries.<br />
It means a great deal to the factories and people in<br />
the capital cities who produce many of the things that we on<br />
the land need to carry on our daily activities.<br />
One or two years ago some people might have doubted the<br />
capacity and the speed with which Australia's rural industries<br />
would be able to recover. It's fair enough to ask why and how<br />
this has happened. I would* place pre-eminently, the skill and<br />
t. e capacity, the adaptability of Australian farmers and<br />
pastoralists. It's something they have proved down through<br />
the decades the capacity to get through difficult times no<br />
matter how difficult Eind black it might seem at the moment;<br />
the capacity to get through, the capacity to survive and take<br />
advantage when markets improve. The ski]. of people on the<br />
land. Also I think it's fair enouc. h to staLe that. oeoole on<br />
th-land that have to sell thc: ir products largely o,; e-vseas ce<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
Governments that are sensitive to their needs. Go-e. ents<br />
that pursue policies that will assist, create the . t<br />
climate, keep inflation down, keep costs under control and<br />
make sure that f: amos can be profita. ble.<br />
There needs to be a partnership n-et: een people in &gt; he rural<br />
communities and Governments, whether that Governr-..: is State<br />
or Federal, because it is so often there are diffi.: iies<br />
and natural disasters, and drought, and some other in: s, where<br />
you need special policies to get through the difficu: l times.<br />
The example is wh'nat can happen in drought, which has recently<br />
bedevilled very large parts of Australia, but which has<br />
been broken in many areas, but which is still beirn--e; perienced<br />
in significant parts of this State, and also in N. S..<br />
Over quite a while, the Federal Government and the State<br />
Governments have co-operated together to try and alleviate<br />
some of the problems caused by drought, and to assess which<br />
special measures are needed. About two months ago, when<br />
it looked as though Australia, very large parts of Australia,<br />
were going to go into a drought, I was speaking with Peter Nixon<br />
and we both thought that we ought to implement ir.-ediately<br />
something which had been on our minds for a while. And that was<br />
to enable the people on the land to write off the total cost<br />
for the constructions of dams and wells anything to do with<br />
water supply in the year in which the expenditure was incurred.<br />
And also to write off the cost of the capital and the equipment<br />
involved in that so that people could get the im. ediate benefit<br />
from it.<br />
While that measure was introduced against the background of<br />
drought, it is of course a long-term measure of a continuing<br />
nature, designed to enable people to improve water supply,<br />
irrigation projects, and to build some greater scre greater<br />
insurance against drought which is probably the greatest<br />
recurri. g disaster that Australia's farmers and pastoralists<br />
have to.. face from time to time.<br />
During the last week, at a meeting in Surfer's Paradise, I<br />
announced that we had agreed with some State Governm. ents to<br />
extend the provision of drought relief, especially to increase<br />
the proportion of transport costs that would be paid and<br />
subsidised by Government for those areas where droucht continues,<br />
especially in this State.<br />
I mention that because I think it is just one of the ways in<br />
which Governments can demonstrate that there needs to be<br />
a partnership in the capacity to respond to circumstances as<br />
they arise. But there are many areas, of course, ::-re<br />
incentives are needed and desirable. Many areas . re soecial<br />
provisions should and are made in relation to tax<br />
and the rest, the abolition of death duties, and in addition<br />
to that, special policies which are needed to support : p. rticular<br />
industries. There were no such policies for the bee industry<br />
through its time of tragic difficulty a few years ago. / 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
Quite apart from that, Governments have to maintain<br />
general economic policies which are going to enable<br />
Australian industries to get out and sell and compete in.<br />
export markets, competitively and properly. That r'eans<br />
that economic policies have to bear down on inflation, to<br />
keep that as small as possible.<br />
It also means that we need to have trade policies that * ill<br />
make sure that markets won't be closed to us as they were<br />
in 1973 and 1974 for example where we lost our entire markt<br />
in Japan, and when nothing much was done about it. And now,<br />
through trade negotiations the Japanese market looks li: k<br />
building up to 140,000 tonnes of beef a year or better. The<br />
American beef levy has been reduced with a guaranteed fall;<br />
something achieved for the first time. While it does not<br />
affect this area so much, for 30 years, Australian Governments<br />
have spoken about getting rid of the American wool tariff.<br />
They are the only country in the world that had such a tariff<br />
on raw wool. Well, we have achieved a 60% reduction in that<br />
American raw wool tariff,<br />
In spite of those who said weshould not, or would not succeed,<br />
we have started to re-open doors to trade with Europe again.<br />
So all of these things are examples of Government working in<br />
partnership with Australia's great rural industries. to<br />
complement the skills and management capacity of Australia's<br />
farmers and pastoralists in moving forward into the 1980s and<br />
beyond. I just wanted to say one word about a policy I do not think<br />
anyone likes very much, and Governments often have to<br />
do things which they do not like doing, but just because they<br />
happen to know they are the only policies that make economic<br />
sense,' or sense for Australia that policy I am referring to,<br />
and some--of you might have already guessed it, is oil parity<br />
pricing which means that each time we fill up our<br />
petrol tanks it costs more, and significantly more, than it<br />
did a year ago.<br />
Our. own reserves of fuel oil are certainly not limitless.<br />
After another few years, what we get from Bass Strait will<br />
start to run down quite sharply. And any Government looking<br />
ahead, any Government planning not just for you and me, but<br />
for our kids and there are a lot of children at this Show<br />
today any Government with those things in mind, has got to<br />
plan for the future. And how are they going to be secure,<br />
and how are our successors going to be secure if supplies of<br />
liquid fuel run out. It's a responsibility for you and. for<br />
me today. Therefore, we have to have policies accordingly.<br />
We have to conserve what fuel we have and make sure it ;. ill<br />
last as long as it can. But more importantly than that, if we<br />
are to avoid being held to ransom at some future time by other<br />
oil-producing and exporting nations, then we have to develop<br />
alternative supplies of that kind of energy. / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
Those alternative supplies '.. ill only come if the people who<br />
invest the money are going to get a profit on it.<br />
The best example of that is that great Rundle shale oil project,<br />
which on present plans, ought to start to cor. e into production<br />
about the-ti e oil from Bass Strait runs dry, or starts to<br />
run do.; wn significantly.<br />
Rundle is just the first of many great shale oil developments<br />
that could and should occur in Queensland. But they will not<br />
take place unless the people who have to raise the billions<br />
of dollars to get those projects off the ground are going to<br />
be able to r. ake it profitable. Therefore, they have to know<br />
they are going to get a price that will make it profitable.<br />
And so the Rundle shale oil project which has been<br />
announced is going ahead, is the classic example of the<br />
benefits of oil parity pricing policies.<br />
The only other point I would like to make is that even<br />
though we have that policy, along with the United States<br />
where the prices are about the same as in Australia, we are<br />
still amongst the cheapest in the Western world, because we<br />
take in fact the lowest world price, not spot prices and<br />
all the higher prices which many others who have got no<br />
reserves of their own have to pay.<br />
You will find in New Zealand they pay about 45½ a litre as<br />
against our price of 32½. In many of the countries of Europe<br />
they are paying 60½, 70½ and upwards of 80½ a litre. Even the<br />
United Kingdom, which is now a significant oil producer from<br />
the North Sea, pays prices-of that kind. Compared with that<br />
of course, therefore, Australia is really better off than many.<br />
But the policy is essentially a policy for the future. It is<br />
essentially a policy for our children, for yours and mine, to<br />
make sure that they are going to be secure, to make sure that<br />
they can carry on our farms and properties in a way which<br />
makes sense, and a way which will give them the energy reserves<br />
they need. I think that is an obligation that we would want<br />
S to meet and we would not want to put aside.<br />
Many people have great and enormots confidence in the future<br />
of Australia's rural industries at the present time. I believe<br />
that confidence is well-based. It really is a joy to go around<br />
the Australian countryside and see people planning for the<br />
future, knowing that they are going to do it to improve their<br />
properties and to improve the breeding of their livestock.<br />
Perhaps for no other reason than that, it is a great pleasure<br />
for Tamcie and myself to be with you today.<br />
The Mayor has asked that I do a couple of things before<br />
officially declaring this Show open. He has delegated to me<br />
some particular powers of the Premier for today, and as a result<br />
of that I have great pleasure in declaring a full school holiday<br />
for all the schoolchildren for Rockhampton and the Rockhampton<br />
District. There can be some discretion for schools as to the<br />
day they take for that holiday, but if the kids find the holiday<br />
not coming up, I suggest'they should get onto the Mayor, whom<br />
I delegate to make sure that all schools provide th holiday. </p>
<p>Now, I have vej r, very great ple , su-lre indeed in Oeoclaring<br />
this 107th ! Rckhampton Show open. 000<br />
S7~ </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
