<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8870</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING, MP ADDRESS AT FORMAL MAORI WELCOMING CEREMONY, HOANI WAITITI MARAE, AUCKLAND, SATURDAY, 22 MAY 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/05/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008870.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PlNKM Mi NMsr], TIM ReON P. J. XNATING, Np<br />
A) DIUSS AI ORILT K&amp; ORI VKUOIXG CERWIDN, OAIi WATI T<br />
AA, AhCvAID, 8ATUtDAY, 22 MAY 1993<br />
2603 PROOF OPY<br />
Can I thank you for the warvith of your welcome, for the<br />
welcome of your warriors, for the singing, of the women which<br />
vas both moving, touching and most appreciated by me.<br />
You welcome me as the Prime Kinister of Australia, you pay in<br />
that case all Australians a tribute and let me return the<br />
tribute by saying that all Australians recognise the spirit of<br />
the maori. I have always been impressed by the resilience<br />
and the strength of the Naori and the culture of the aori.<br />
It is these things we feel that do give, as your Xinister has<br />
said, a distinguishing character to the country of New Zealand<br />
and I am particularly pleased to be here In this year the<br />
Year of Indigenous People when in this year these countries<br />
and those peoples which came to the new world disturbed of<br />
course the old world, the world of the people who were here<br />
first. And those things which Europeans and Buropean settlers<br />
celebrate are often the tragic things, the periods of tragedy<br />
for the indigenous peoples of various countries no less true<br />
of New Zealand and Australia.<br />
But the Neori have in such strength of ' Culture had such a<br />
dominating influence over the culture of New Zealand. And I<br />
am delighted that the education which you have here at this<br />
Harae is one where you have maintained your traditional<br />
cultures, you learn your traditional cultures, you take pride<br />
in your traditional cultures and you also teach your children<br />
about the society in which they live. This is Ism sure the<br />
most effective way of keeping those two cultures in the first<br />
sense alive and flourishing and beyond that weaving their<br />
pattern together.<br />
in Australia, in this Year of rndigenous People, we too are I<br />
think finally coming to a ba-sof reconciliation with our<br />
indigenous people. And unlike the Naori there was no treaty,<br />
there was no equivalent to the Treaty of Weitangi. So the<br />
nation of Australia has sought to come to terms with our<br />
indigenous people and this year our High Court, the Supreme<br />
Court of our country has in fact last year made a very<br />
fundamental and historic decision to give recognition for the<br />
TEL: 22. May. 93 19: 58 No.( I ) 02 P. 09/ 11 </p>
<p>T2E2L:. May. 93 19: 58 No. 002 P. 10/ 11<br />
2<br />
first time that there wasn a native title in the common law of<br />
Australia Wefor* the settlement of Europeans.<br />
This is a very significant decision and now the government of<br />
Australia and the governments of the States of Australia are<br />
now seeking to put Into the body of law a native title for the<br />
indigenous people of Australia. This can and must be the<br />
first effective basis of reconciliation in our country between<br />
indigenous, the Aboriginal people and non-. Aboriginal<br />
Australians. This process of x~ cQn= i1iStian as a nation ve<br />
have dedicated ourself to and lot me say it tills me with a<br />
certain sense of pride to see In this country such an outward<br />
and obvious pride in your culture -the culture of the Maori<br />
and the willing~ ness of the New Zealand community to see this<br />
culture dominate in many respects its own national culture.<br />
one thing that I think indigenous people understand that<br />
European people have never quite understood and that Is the<br />
relationship between the people and the land. And your Mayor<br />
very eloquently said today that this is an environmental<br />
place, a place where the environment has a premium and we have<br />
much to learn trom the indigenous peoples of our countries<br />
abouit the land. We are only now comning to understand what<br />
they know about the land and hov they have preserved the land.<br />
Whereas as a culture we have been often the destroyer. of the<br />
land. We now understand that is a mistake. We nov understand<br />
the land needs respect and we understand that without the land<br />
having the respect it canvt give to us the kind of life that<br />
could only come by a gentle, melding of the Interests of the<br />
people and the land.<br />
it may be that the environment is an issue amongst countries<br />
and peoples around the world, but it has always been an Issue<br />
with indigenous people. This is another thing you have taught<br />
Us. So it we can learn this valuable lesson the futures of Nev<br />
Zealand and Australia two great lands will be different in<br />
the future than they have been in the Immediate past because<br />
we have the opportunity to preserve our land anid to rebuild<br />
the nature of our lands as many countries have now lost that<br />
opportunity and if we can learn that from the indigenous<br />
people of this country, you the Maori and from the Aboriginal<br />
people of Australia, our indigenous people, we will learn<br />
much. The culture of our indigenous people, Ab~ oriqinal Australians<br />
is nov substantially permeating the culture of Australia in<br />
its art, in its dance, in its music and we are in a sense in<br />
this last decade celebrating the renaissance of that culture<br />
within our own. And I'm sure as time goes on it to will start<br />
to play a such larger role in our general national culture as<br />
the Maori have played in New Zealand culture.<br />
with all that said, Indigenous people have since the time of<br />
European settlement rarely had justice and we know that we<br />
will never entirely live in peace or peace of heart without a<br />
true basis of reconciliation with indigenous people and that<br />
TEL: </p>
<p>22. May. 93 19: 58 No. 002 P. 11/ 11<br />
3<br />
is why we must be one people. One people with an ephasis on<br />
different values, with loyalties perhaps to different<br />
cultures, but one people in Now ealand, one people in<br />
Australia and of course between us all Australasians. It we<br />
do that we would do well.<br />
Could I thank you again for the warmth of your welcome to me<br />
and my party, to my wife. I think I have visited New Zealand<br />
properly too and I don't think I would have visited New<br />
Zealand without visiting the Marae and receiving its gracious<br />
and traditional welcome.<br />
ends TEL: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
