<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7074</transcript-id>
    <title>TASMANIAN FORESTRY DISPUTE</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/01/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007074.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 19 JANUARY 1987<br />
TASMANIAN-FORESTRY DISPUTE<br />
The Prime Minister, the Minister for Primary Industry, Mr<br />
John Kerin and the Minister for Arts, Heritage and<br />
Environment, Mr Barry Cohen, today reaffirmed the<br />
Commonwealth's determination both to protect those National<br />
Estate areas in Tasmania that may be of world Heritage<br />
value, and to resolve once and for all the issue of whether<br />
there are viable alternatives to forestry opearations in the<br />
contentious National Estate areas.<br />
The Commonwealth continues to believe that it is necessary<br />
for a full and careful review to take place as to whether<br />
there are environmentally and economically prudent and<br />
feasible logging alternatives within Tasmania to existing<br />
logging plans for the contentious National Estate areas.<br />
The Government has not yet concluded its consideration as to<br />
the most appropriate machinery for such a review, the best<br />
way to ensure that possible World Heritage values are fully<br />
protected during the course of it, and appropriate<br />
compensation arrangements where legitimate commercial<br />
interests are affected by the review process.<br />
Further consultations will be held over the next two weeks<br />
with all relevant interests. The forest industries have<br />
indicated a desire to have consultations, following the<br />
provision of detailed information by the Commonwealth. The<br />
Government also will be consulting with the ACTU. The<br />
Government wishes to allow every opportunity for these<br />
consultations to lead to the co-operation of industry in<br />
undertaking the review.<br />
The Government will also take advantage of the advice of a<br />
senior expert of the International Union for the<br />
Conservaticn of Nature and Natural Resources CTUCN), which<br />
advises the World Heritage Committee on natural heritage<br />
values. The expert, Mr Jim Thorsell, will visit Australia<br />
this week.<br />
The Commonwealth is hopeful of industry and State Government<br />
co-operation, but will consider appropriate legislation if<br />
it becomes apparent that this is the only way that the<br />
necessary review and associated environment protection<br />
arrangements can be put in place. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
