<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9737</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P.J. KEATING MP DOORSTOP. THE VALLEY RESTAURANT, FAULCONBRIDGE, 30 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009737.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, THE VALLEY RESTAURANT, FAULCONIBRIDGE,<br />
AUGUST 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: ( growth figures?)<br />
PM: Well, they are exceptionally encouraging. It has now given Australia<br />
16 consecutive quarters of growth. Four straight years of growth with<br />
low inflation and as a consequence of that growth we have seen<br />
680,000 jobs in the last two and a half years. I think what is<br />
particularly pleasing about the accounts is it shows the economy<br />
growing at 3.7 per cent a strong but sustainable rate with low<br />
inflation. So, if you had to sit down and fill the numbers in the boxes, if<br />
we'd have had that privilege, they couldn't have been any better.<br />
J: Foreign debt hit $ 180 billion, that is a record high.<br />
PM: But, what came down is the debt service capacity. That is, the debt<br />
service ratio, the capacity to service the debt is improving all the time.<br />
It is half of what it was 10 years ago. Only 11 per cent of our exports<br />
now service the debts. Ten years ago it was 22 per cent.<br />
J: Are you happy with just 1 per cent for the June quarter, would you like<br />
to see it a little higher?<br />
PM: It is the year to number that matters and the year at 3.7 per cent is just<br />
about where the Government would like it.<br />
J: So, you don't think it is slowing down too much?<br />
PM: I don't think it is slowing down too much. I think it is just at a nice clip.<br />
J: On another matter, Indonesia, you are going there next month, will you<br />
be raising the report that has come out on the death of these 11<br />
people. N, N </p>
<p>PM: I have heard the Indonesian Human Rights Commission will be<br />
investigating those and we will look to that investigation. They are in a<br />
position, I think, to follow these sorts of issues up and no doubt they<br />
will.<br />
J: What about Richard Court's memory, surely John Howard is<br />
forgettable anyway?<br />
PM: The whole basis of the Court royal commission is now unravelling<br />
before his eyes. Richard Court says he might have said something,<br />
may have, but can't remember and yet he has Carmen Lawrence<br />
before this commission, he has set up an elaborate $ 5 million<br />
commission against one woman who has said pretty much as he has<br />
said. That is, remembering things from years ago, but even the<br />
statements she has made are fairly clear to the Parliament of Western<br />
Australia. And, of course, we have got Mr Wooldridge, the Liberal<br />
Party spokesperson who was conniving with the West Australian<br />
Government and with Mr Court in establishing terms of reference and<br />
a commission against an opponent. Now, of course, he won't come<br />
clean. Mr Howard is all about political honesty and we had all that<br />
cant and incantations from him about the importance of political<br />
honesty, but he won't say whether he and Mr Wooldridge were<br />
conniving with Richard Court to disadvantage Carmen Lawrence.<br />
J: Do you support Gareth Evans' mentioning of Anne Vanstone in the<br />
Parliament yesterday?<br />
PM: I think what Gareth was saying was that justice should appear to be<br />
done. That you have seen, do you remember in NSW here, Mr Temby<br />
was on some matter representing the police as a QC, he declined the<br />
position because at the time he accepted the need that justice should<br />
appear to be done. Here you have got a Council associated with the<br />
Liberal Party in a commission set up against a Labor Party Minister.<br />
J: But, is it appropriate that he is attacking the validity of the Council?<br />
PM: Well, was it appropriate for John Howard to have his communications<br />
spokesman attack my wife for going on a tour with the Sydney<br />
Symphony Orchestra. I mean, in the annals of political cowardice, that<br />
wasn't a bad one.<br />
J: Mr Keating, when you visit President Soeharto this month, isn't it, what<br />
are you going to say to him about the breach of human rights that were<br />
documented today?<br />
PM: Well, I don't know whether it was documented today, that is the thing.<br />
J: Well, it is in the papers. </p>
<p>PM: But, I don't go there with a travelling slate of what I think are human<br />
rights breaches in his country. I mean, he could point to problems we<br />
have prejudicial views about the Aboriginal community, denying them<br />
equal opportunity and access what would you say about that?<br />
J: Yes, but we haven't got reports saying that 19 people were killed while<br />
they were praying in a church.<br />
PM: No, well, that will be investigated, I'm sure, by the Indonesian Human<br />
Rights Commission.<br />
J: Given the worsening drought in NSW, should there be an increase in<br />
federal assistance?<br />
PM: At the moment, there are 10,000 farm families 10,000, I think now it is<br />
over 10,000 on income support in those quite radical changes I made<br />
with Bob Collins last November. And, I think, the response you can<br />
see that from the Graingrowers in Queensland recently acknowledging<br />
that point. I notice Mr Howard this week saying me ' too, me too',<br />
again, ' we'll do the same as the Government'. It is the Government<br />
that has broken all the policy moulds here to try to help the farm<br />
community and the family farm in particular hold through this drought<br />
and all of those arrangements are in place. All those drought<br />
exceptional circumstance arrangements are in place now.<br />
J: So, there will be no increased funding?<br />
PM: The formulas are there. If there is more drought, there will be more<br />
support and there will be more funding.<br />
J: Dame Pattie Menzies died this morning<br />
PM: I hadn't heard that and if that is the case I am very sorry to hear it.<br />
She was a very great Australian.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
