<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3631</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT OF SOVIET TEXTILE TECHNOLOGY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003631.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
26 February 1975<br />
VISIT OF SOVIET TEXTILE TECHNOLOGY<br />
DELEGATION<br />
The Prime Minister and Acting Foreign Minister,<br />
Mr E. G. Whitlam, and the Minister for Science, Mr Bill<br />
Moriison, announced today that a party of five Soviet<br />
textile technologists vill arrive in Melbourne tomorrow.<br />
The group is visiting Australia for twc weeks under the<br />
auspices of the Australian/ Soviet Science Agreement, but<br />
will also undertake somz activities arranged by the<br />
International Wool SecretPariat.<br />
Whilst in Australia the Soviet textile technologists<br />
will have discussions with Australian scientists on possible<br />
areas in textile technology where Australian/ Soviet<br />
collaboration can be developed. Textile technology is one<br />
of the five fields beina given particular emphasis for cooperation<br />
under the Australian/ Soviet Science Agreement.<br />
The Soviet textile technologists will visit the<br />
CSIRO Division of Textile Industry and the Gordon Institute'<br />
of Technology in Geelong, and the CSIRO Division of Protein<br />
Che. istry and the Australian Wool Corporation in Melbourne.<br />
They will inspect textile mills at Albury, Orange, Lithgow<br />
and Melbourne. In Sydney tours to be undertaken by the<br />
Soviet delegation will include visits to the University<br />
of New South Wales, the CSIRO Division of Textile Physics,<br />
and the Australian Wool Testing Authority.<br />
Mr Whitlam and Mr Morrison said that it was likely<br />
that a group of Australian textile technologists, led by<br />
Dr M. Lipson, Chi-ef of the CSIRO Division of Textile Industry,<br />
would pay a return visit to the Soviet Union in April to<br />
finalise the program of co-operaticn in textile technology<br />
tha would be recommended to the Australian and Soviet<br />
Governments. The members of the visiting Soviet textile<br />
technology group are: / 2 </p>
<p>-2-7 t<br />
Mr R. A. Tshaianov;<br />
Head of the Department of Light Industries<br />
Mr B. E. Golovastikov;<br />
Director of the Central Research Institute<br />
of the Soviet Wool Textile Industry<br />
Mr B. G. Eliseev;<br />
Deputy to the Technical Director of the Soviet<br />
Wool Textile Industry in the Ministry of Light<br />
Industries<br />
Mrs R. S. Kusminskaia;<br />
Foreign Department of the State Committee for<br />
Science and Technology<br />
Mr A. I. Kniazev;<br />
Chief of Laboratory of the Central Wool Textile<br />
A_ Research Institute<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
