<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>543</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 44/1962 - CONFERENCES WITH INDUSTRY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/06/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000543.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PoM. NO. 4J'/ 062<br />
CONFER JITH INDUTRY<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister t Rt.. heH on. R. G. Menzies<br />
In announcing on February 6, 1962, a series<br />
of measures affecting the national economy, I stated that<br />
it was the intention of the Government to engage in periodical<br />
consultation with those engaged in practical production and<br />
business. Accordingly, on two days next week, a committee<br />
of senior Ministers of the Cabinet will meet in Canberra with<br />
representatives of primary and secondary industries to hear<br />
their views on the current state of the economy.<br />
The first conference at 10.30 a. m. on Monday,<br />
2nd July, will be with the following organisations<br />
Australian Woolgrowers' Graziers Council Mr. T. L. Bull<br />
Australian Primary Producers' Union<br />
Australian Bankers' Association<br />
Master Builders' Federation of Australia<br />
National Farmers' Union<br />
Federal Chamber of Automotive Industries<br />
Associated Chambers of Manufactures of<br />
Australia<br />
Australian Council of Retailers<br />
Associated Chambers of Commerce of<br />
Australia<br />
Australian Wool and Meat iroducors' Federation Mr. IT. Serjean'<br />
Mr. C. R. Darvall<br />
Mr. W. J. Bryant<br />
Mr. Havard<br />
Mr. B. L. Burton<br />
Mr. J. W. Walker<br />
Mr. T. A. Pettigrc<br />
Mr. J. C. Willic. a<br />
Mr. LH,. Keaslip<br />
The second conference at 10.30 aom. on Tuesday<br />
will be with the Manufacturing Industries Advisory Council,<br />
represented by Messrs. R. J. JWebster, RoA. Irish, J. Burnett,<br />
G. More, Dr. J. Vernon and Sir James Kirby.<br />
The third conference at 11.30 a. m. on Tuesday<br />
will be with Sir John Allison and his colleagues on the Export<br />
Development Council The which was invited to send a representative<br />
to the meeting on Monday, was unable to accept, but will<br />
forward a written submission.<br />
CANBERRA, 29th Juno, 1962. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
