<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9870</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP THE NATIONAL TRADE AND INVESTMENT OUTLOOK CONFERENCE MELBOURNE, 6 DECEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009870.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
6 Dec .95 ' I<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
THE NATIONAL TRADE AND INVESTMENT OUTLOOK CONFERENCE<br />
MELBOURNE, 6 DECEMBER 1995<br />
I am very pleased tu be here to address this National Trade and Investment Outlook<br />
Conference for the third successive year.<br />
The innovative Minister for Industry Science and Technology, Peter Cook, was<br />
instrumental In establishing the conference and the Australian Government is pleased to<br />
sponsor It. NTIOC has become one of the more important conferences on the business<br />
calendar. I thank you all for coming, arid In particular let me welcomne to Australia our visitors from<br />
overseas. This conference is at once a manifestation of the change taking place in Australia and<br />
throughout the world, and an agent of that change.<br />
And that is what, primarily, I want to talk about today the change we are seeing, the<br />
changes we can arid should make.<br />
It is often said these days that we live In an era of unprecedented change.<br />
In fact, I suspect politicians have been saying we are living In an era of unprecedented<br />
change since politics was born. I'm sure I remember a former Prime Minister of ours,<br />
Bob Monzies, saying we were living in an era of unprecedented change and Bob was<br />
reluctant to change a light globe.<br />
I'm equally sure that if anyone had kept an ear to the ground In the 1950s they would<br />
have heard what we sormetimes hear now which is people saying they are tired of<br />
change. These days the sociologists arid psychologists are warning us that people are<br />
fed up with It, exh~ austed by it.<br />
Yet we also see evidence of their willingness to embtrace change. The last decade bears<br />
witness to that. In their workplaces and communities, on their farms and in their<br />
businesses, In schools and universities, in their minds In the way they think about the<br />
world and their country's relationship to It the Australian people have made changes.<br />
They have made Australia a much more competitive country 40 per cent more<br />
competitive than a decade ago. They have seen exports rise by one third in the last five<br />
years. They have seen ETM exports grow by 17.5 per cent per annumn over the past<br />
decade, so that they now make Up airTost 2~ 3 per cent of our total merchandise exports.<br />
Put anotlii way. 17 out of the top 50 Australian export commodities last year were<br />
ETM's In 1983 only 3 of them were.<br />
All this is reason for optimism. So is the growth in Australian services exports 10 per<br />
cent per annimun since 1988/ 89 w~ th the likelihood on current trends of a net surplus this<br />
year. We have recorded national economic growth in every one of the last seventeen quarters.<br />
TEL TEL No 6.. e0c 2925 4: P4?. 0 1 / C </p>
<p>TE: 4L7:. 65. N Do. c0 22 P. 02/ 0<br />
2<br />
And we are looking to positive growth in the eighteenth quarter.<br />
And of course we are becoming more closely integrated with the fastest growing region in<br />
the world. By as early as next year, when our exports to Irdonesia and Malaysia will<br />
each exceed our exports to the United Kingdom, all our top ten markets will be In the<br />
Asia Pacific.<br />
If all these developments give us cause for confidence, so does APEC. In fact few<br />
developments in our recent history are such~ a cause for confidence and optimism as<br />
APEC. The meeting In Osaka recently was an outstanding success. it cemented APEC as the<br />
key regional body for coordinating the development and growth of the Asia-Pacific over<br />
the next century. All APEC members will benefit fromn the liberalisation and facilitation<br />
agenda. Once all the effects have flowed through, the Income of APEC members will<br />
Increase by awound $ 1 trillion.<br />
Australia's real income Is expected to rise by $ 40 billion, and growth of this order can be<br />
expected to generate around half a million new jobs.<br />
For Individual businesses the benefits will be substantial. For instance, differing<br />
standards can add between S and 10 per cent to a new exporters costs. In OsakaIt was<br />
agreed to harnionise and simplify customs procedures on an APEC-wide basis by 2000.<br />
And within the next 10 years the requirement for paper work for key trade and transport<br />
documentation will be entirely eliminated.<br />
In a remarkable step, at Osaka the leaders demonstrated their seriousness of purpose<br />
with down payments on their Uruguay Round commitments.<br />
F or example, Japan accelerated its tariff reductions to the tune of $ 135 million; and<br />
China brought forward to 1998 its WTO accession bid of reducing tariffs on more than<br />
4000 items by an average of 30 per cent,<br />
These were just two of many steps at Osaka which were unthinkable four or five years<br />
ago. When some of them were mooted even 18 months ago, the cynics came out In<br />
force. Seattle, Bogor and Osaka have proved the cynics wrong.<br />
The APEC process has proved a triumph. The Leaders meetings have established a<br />
unique degree of trust and good will and authority. And the decision to establish end<br />
polits, and then move towards them with the weight of that authority arid the force of that<br />
cooperation, gives the process much more momentum than the Uruguay Round and the<br />
WTO could ever achieve.<br />
That is why APEC should give us confidence: it has established enormous momentum in<br />
a very short period of time, shorter than even its most passionate advocates anticipated.<br />
Great as the economic benefits will be, there will hardly be a greater one than the lesson<br />
about the potential for cooperation between countries. As I said after the Bogor<br />
declaration this was not something which necessity demanded we do. It did not have to<br />
be done, Instead, between us we Imagined what we might be capable of doing, and we<br />
are doing It.<br />
And, as I said before, once you create an environment for change and a framework for It,<br />
change begins to grow of itself. Suddenly needs are recognised. Suddenly the solutions<br />
are at hand. The advance on GATT commitments is one example. Another Is the<br />
proposal we put to develop a working group on food security, which Is bound to become a<br />
major Issue as the Asia Pacific grows. Another is our announcement of the APEC<br />
business travel cardl to facilitate regional travel by accredited business people. Another is<br />
the decision of the Leaders meeting to establish a permanent APEC Business Advisory<br />
Council. TEL 6 Dec 95 </p>
<p>TEL: 6. Dec. 95 4: 47 No. 022 P. 03/ OS<br />
3<br />
One important way of Interpreting the policies and initiatives I am announcing today is<br />
that I want Australia to be APECready: ready to respond to the challenges and to realise<br />
the commercial opportunities of the free trade and investment environment we have In<br />
the making.<br />
The Initiatives In many ways reflect the new phase in our industry policy.<br />
Our reforms In the early and mid 80s concentrated on opening the Australian economy to<br />
the world and to global competition. Subsequent reform concentrated on building a<br />
competitive domestic environment through microeconomic change. Neither process has<br />
ended. They are ongoing.<br />
But now we address the question of what it takes for the individual firm to maximise its<br />
competitiveness, meet the challenges of open markets and take advantage of the<br />
opportunities they present. And a key Is a commitment to innovation.<br />
I can, perhaps, best Illustrate this by two very different industry examples. The first is<br />
BHP, Australia's largest company. A little over a decade ago, BHP Steel was a<br />
predominantly domestic producer threatened to the point of extinction by import<br />
competition. In 1983, BHP, the Government and the unions agreed to a Steel Industry<br />
Plan which saw BHP revolutionise its work practices and undertake almost $ 2 billion<br />
worth of Investments, Including investment in new technology.<br />
In a second phase of reform, since the late 1980s BHP has focussed on securing<br />
productivity gains by improving skills, restructuring awards, total quality management and<br />
encouraging a more customer oriented culture.<br />
The effects have been dramatic and are perhaps best expressed this way: production of<br />
tonnes of steel per person in 1982-83 was 175; in 1987-88 it was 257; last year it was<br />
618. It now has one of the highest export/ production shares of any major steel maker in<br />
the world.<br />
In a sense, BHP Steel's story mirrors the story of Australia's reforms since 1983. And it is<br />
not merely among big companies that versions of the tale are told.<br />
Bllcon Engineering is a Victorian based manufacturer of quality precision metal<br />
componenthy. After operating for 50 years, In 1990 it faced closure, but It re-made itself<br />
through innovation and quality. Bilcon has achieved a 220 per cent turnaround in<br />
profitability and more than 100 per cent employment growth and Bilcon components can<br />
now be found in Europe, Asia and South America.<br />
Good policy like good company management Is a process of continuous improvement.<br />
Australia already has the Ingredients of a dynamic and effective innovation system,<br />
ranging from the tremendous national asset of our excellence In science, to our very<br />
strong propensity to take up new technology, to the surge of our companies including<br />
the crop of export-oriented small and medium enterprises towards best practice and<br />
commitment to quality.<br />
So the policies we announce today are not the first word; and, certainly, nor will they be<br />
the last. They represent steps along the road of continuous improvement.<br />
In fact, today's statement provides for measures that will raise $ 353 million more in<br />
revenue over the next four years than will actually be spent.<br />
In this way, the Government Is making room for a range of other initiatives which also<br />
build on success In other areas.<br />
What we are about today Is good public policy and good government.<br />
The Government has already done much to foster innovation by creating a more open<br />
economy and a better macroeconomic environment where competition is more vibrant<br />
and the rewards of Innovation easier to capture. There have also been significant<br />
Investments In education and training and in our basic research effort. </p>
<p>TEL: 6. Dec. 95 4: 47 No. 022 P. 04/ 08<br />
4<br />
Today we take the next steps to strengthen Australia's capacity for innovation by which<br />
we mean: generating ideas<br />
a commercialisIng and using new ideas<br />
linking Australia even more closely into ideas elsewhere In the world<br />
0 encouraging new ideas in business and the work place<br />
accelerating the application of ideas by using the Information super highway, and<br />
promoting access to information technology for all Australians, Including people<br />
with disabilities, those in remote areas, people on low incomes and women.<br />
Put simply, Innovation Is about new products and services and new and better ways of<br />
producing them.<br />
For a company, innovation provides a key to Increased competitiveness.<br />
In today's world, tastes and technology change rapidly information moves fast. And<br />
good ideas are quickly copied or superseded. There is constant pressure to come up with<br />
something new and better.<br />
Success depends on being able to meet the needs of more discerning customers.<br />
The firms that will prosper will be those committed to continuous renewal through<br />
innovation the ones which are enterprising and skilled enough to differentiate their<br />
product and create a distinctive competitive edge.<br />
For the economy as a whole, Innovation lies at the heart of productivity growth. And at<br />
the heart of Innovation lie Ideas. Innovation in putting Ideas to work.<br />
It Is not just the skills of the workforce or management, or the capital they have to use,<br />
but how these are used In ever more productive combinations, which Is the central driver<br />
of economic growth and rising living standards. Fostering an environment which rewards<br />
Innovation Is therefore a powerful lever In raising productivity and growth.<br />
But Imperatives of innovation go beyond the economic. A sophisticated and just society<br />
will be Information rich. It will be enterprising In Its response to new ideas and challenges<br />
and It will utilise technology to its full capabilities. This will ensure the highest quality of<br />
life for all Australians.<br />
There Is no simple model of innovation. It can come from different sources, It can come<br />
from basic scientific research which produces a result capable of commercial<br />
exploitation. It can come from changing the way a workplace is organiised to improve<br />
flexibility and responsiveness to customer needs. It can come from utilising existing<br />
equipment In a novel way, not envisaged by the original manufacturer.<br />
Innovation is a complex process of Interaction and Information transmission which is<br />
strongly Influenced by a nation's culture, particularly Its willingness to rewarr enterprise<br />
and risk taking.<br />
Ideas can emerge from anywhere within such a system. Turning Ideas Into maximum<br />
economic benefit depends primarily on a competitive and responsive private sector and<br />
strong lines of communication between all parts of the system.<br />
These outcomes will only materlalise where Information flows freely within the system.<br />
The most successful firms are those that are highly attuned to the needs of the market,<br />
have access to leading edge technology to convert market needs Into commercial<br />
products or services, and the management and the financial resources to facilitate this<br />
process. </p>
<p>6. Dec. 95 4: 47 No. 022 P. 05/ 0:<br />
Australia already has the basis for building an Innovative and enterprising society. For<br />
many reasons among them the quality of our education, our Investment in world class<br />
science and research, our cultural diversity, our capabilities In technology and<br />
engineering, our first class communications we can build an Information rich society<br />
which complements the advantages which our natural resources and environment<br />
provide. I do not say we have reached optimal levels In these. Indeed, I am very much aware that<br />
we need to work on all of them. They are relative strengths, but collectively they provide<br />
a very strong foundation.<br />
So let me summarise the measures we are announcing today.<br />
First, we need to keep generating new ideas.<br />
The Government has chosen seven visionary science projects which will boost our<br />
science infrastructure and link Industry with large scale collaborative research to keep<br />
Australia abreast of the world's most advanced technologies.<br />
The Government will continue its support for industry research and development<br />
through the 160 per cent R&amp; D tax concession, which will be fine tuned to improve<br />
accessibility, management and cost effectiveness. Change will reduce uncertainties<br />
for companies, while closing all opportunities for abuse.<br />
The Government will renew the $ 40 million a year competitive grants scheme for<br />
Industry research and development. The grants target high quality projects by well<br />
managed companies, recognising that high-technology start-ups are the nurseries for<br />
new Industries.<br />
The Government will fund five new Cooperative Research Centres ( CRCs),<br />
bringing the total to 67, and has decided to establish the CRCs as a permanent<br />
program with new CRCs approved on a rolling two year basis. New CRCs are to be<br />
supported in the areas of advanced engineering, sports science and medicine,<br />
intelligent transport systems, textile technology and building and construction<br />
technology. Next year the Government will contribute around $ 140 million to the CRC<br />
program.<br />
The second category of Initiatives will Improve the flow of finance into business<br />
Innovation and our capacity to commerciallse our scientific research.<br />
A new package of measures designed to help finance the Innovation process will be<br />
implemented. An important source of ' patient' or ' growth' capital will be opened up<br />
with the new ability of the banks to provide equity capital to their clients needing to<br />
fund business expansions. Initially the Investments are likely to be directed to firms<br />
with strong growth potential and tumovers between $ 1 million and $ 50 million. New<br />
programs will upgrade the financial management skills of SMEs to prepare them<br />
better for raising debt or equity finance to make them ' investment ready'. Through<br />
an education campaign, the Govemment will also help Increase the understanding of<br />
the Investment community, particularly superannuation trustees, of the<br />
opportunities for profitable Investment In Australian companies.<br />
Three new Innovation Flagship Projects will bring science, Industry and user groups<br />
together to speed the development of new products, processes and services. The<br />
new projects, costing $ 23m, will comprise a mineral technologies pilot plant, a<br />
hydrodynamic testing facility, and a facility for the development of magnetic<br />
resonance in the advanced diagnosis of cancer.<br />
An additional $ 20 million will be spent over four years to encourage greater access<br />
to, and uptake of, new technology by Australian firms. More Technology Support<br />
Centres, which were established to help SMEs with technical advice and access to<br />
R&amp; D facilities and skills training, will be established. Experience with institutions like<br />
Germany's Fraunhoffer, and the Queensland Manufacturing Institute clearly<br />
demuiinotiate the advantage of these centres to Innovative firms.<br />
TEL: </p>
<p>TEL: 6. Dec. 95 4: 47 No. 022 P. 06/ 08<br />
6<br />
A new Research Commercialisation Program will help get the high quality work<br />
which is done in our public sector science agencies into the market. Tile<br />
Government will also encourage the establishment of new companies as business<br />
spin-offs from the research sector.<br />
0 The Government will strengthen Australia's Intellectual property system to better<br />
protect ideas developed in Australia.<br />
A broad-ranging Innovation Culture Program will raise comnmunity awareness of the<br />
Importance of science, engineering, technology and enterprise to Australia's future<br />
economic and social well-being.<br />
Third, the Government will spend $ 17 million over four years to expand International<br />
science and technology links and cooperation and establish an International panel for<br />
CSIRO to help promote Australian science to the world.<br />
* Subject to private sector participation, the Government will provide funding for an<br />
Australian Trading Company In Osaka, Japan, to help firms, particularly In the food<br />
sector, sell to Japanese retail outlets: and, In addition, support stronger collaboration<br />
between Australian companies and R&amp; D agencies and partners overseas through<br />
strategic alliances, joint ventures and consortia.<br />
Fourth, we will stimulate Innovation In business and the work place.<br />
9 Demand for new and better products Is a potent force for Innovation along the supply<br />
chain. The Government will devote $ 6 million to a pilot Leading Edge Customers<br />
program. Major commercial and Government customers, Including BHP, will<br />
participate. The best Australian managers are equal to the best in the world, but there are nlot<br />
enough of the best. Better management will help generate both employment and<br />
productivity. The Government will support a range of management Initiatives In<br />
response to the recent report of David Karpin's Committee on leadership and<br />
management skills.<br />
We will establish a National Centre for the Workplaces of the 21st Century, and a<br />
Benchmarking Information Service to conduct and sponsor research projects and<br />
spread best practice.<br />
The fifth set of measures relates to information technology, probably the dominant force<br />
Already in Australia the national digital broadband network Is being roiled out. By 1999<br />
Teistra will be servicing 4 million homnes and Optus 3 million.<br />
We are seeing Australians embrace the new on-line services In their schools, their work<br />
places and their homes.<br />
The number of Internet users is currently doubling every three months.<br />
And only the United States has more Internet users per capita than Australia.<br />
Of course, this Is not really surprising because Australians have always shown an<br />
enthusiasm to adopt new technologies.<br />
For example, we have the third highest number of personal computers per head in the<br />
world, </p>
<p>EL: 6. Dec. 95 4: 47 No. 022 P. 07/ 08<br />
7<br />
Australia, as a sparsely populated Island continent, has everything to gain from<br />
Instantaneous flows or Information and the capacity to do business anywhere In the world<br />
at our finger tips. The comnmunications revolution also suits our social ambitions our<br />
egalitarian and Inclusive ambitions.<br />
The Government has created a national strategy for Information and communications<br />
services and technologies.<br />
Today's statement takes the strategy a step further, ensuring wide access throughout the<br />
community to information services, developing content for the Information networks and<br />
providing the support ot information technology to Australian Industry.<br />
The starting point for access must be to ensure that all our school children have the<br />
opportunity to benefit from the new Information services and the confidence to use them,<br />
This will be vital to their future. That is why we have been working with the States and<br />
Territories to establish the Education Network Australia ( Ed NA) to deliver a wide range of<br />
services to every school, technical college and university.<br />
It Is also why Teistra and Optus are spending $ 185 mnillon to provide the Infrastructure to<br />
link our schools to Information services. By 1999, 97 per cent of schools will have ISDN<br />
digital links and half of them Broadband links.<br />
The Government appreciates the Importance of assisting the wider community to be part<br />
of this revolution as well. Homes and businesses are the key platform, but community<br />
facilities must be Included, not least as a safety net. Accordingly, we will:<br />
0 Ensure that every public library Is linked to on-line services.<br />
Extend the comnmunity Information network, which provides a network of computers<br />
In public locations, to all States and Territories by the end of 1998.<br />
And provide a national Indigenous radio and news service and extend the Tanami<br />
network.<br />
The greatest benefits to flow from the new technologies will accrue to those countries<br />
which create the content.<br />
In the Government's cultural policy, Creative Nation, we Identified three waves of content<br />
production, namely material for CD-ROMs, on-line services and broadband Interactive<br />
services. The measures Introduced today will help see this momentum carry on to the second<br />
phase, namely on-line services.<br />
Ten million doiiars will be committed to a new program called " Australia's Story" to<br />
digitise culturai material from our national collections and make them availabie on-line.<br />
The ABC wiil be funded to digitIse Its radio and TV science archives to establish an online<br />
science service for schools. Support wiil be provided for curriculum materials<br />
showcasing Australian science, and for career education materials covering science,<br />
engineering and technology-based employment.<br />
As a result, all Australian schools and libraries will have access to a very rich array of<br />
cultural and scientific material.<br />
School chiildren wili be able to read the journals of Captain Cook, or explore Australian<br />
flora or fauna, or view an Arthur Boyd painting by clicking on a few ( cons.<br />
Information technology has Itseif become an Important Australian Industry. The<br />
Government's decision to extend the computer bounty will secure Australian manufacture<br />
of the computer and communications hardware to underpin development of new products<br />
and services, Including software.<br />
TEL </p>
<p>TEL: 6 b. Lie 9 t 4 4 No. 22 F U U.<br />
But more broadly, Information technology Is vital to our Industry performance as a<br />
pervasive enabling technology. It is, Itself, a key to Innovation across the range of<br />
Industry sectors. Accordingly, we have decided to;<br />
establish a $ 3.8 million Superhighway Ready Scheme to show how businesses,<br />
Including SMEs, can use network information services.<br />
support the new information system, Tradeblazer, to help Australian firms Identify<br />
opportunities and do business by accessing information through the Internet.<br />
accelerate Australia's effective use of High Performance Computing and<br />
Communications through $ 24 million for broadband communications between<br />
existing supercomputers, including between Australia and Japan. Centres of<br />
excellence In supercomputing applications for example, in environmental modeliing<br />
will be established.<br />
I appreciate that many of these announcements today are of domestic Australian<br />
government policy. However, to those of you visiting us from overseas, I say this all<br />
these measures which encourage the Innovative thrust evident in Australian industry will<br />
make us an even more attractive business partner In the years to came.<br />
Innovation whether at the national level, the Industry level or the level of the firm Is a<br />
matter of continuous creativity, adaptation and change. So Is good policy.<br />
Which Is why over the past three and half years we have kept up the momentum. Not<br />
because we think we wiil ever complete the task: we know you never get to the last<br />
chapter in the story of change.<br />
Not that we should find this too odious a fact of modern life I can't think of anything<br />
more pointless than governing without a mandate for reform.<br />
Our objective has always been not only to institute change, but to create an environment<br />
In which change will breed change, and Indeed a greater capacity for change.<br />
The same goes for our efforts Australia's and those of other nations In the GATT<br />
Round and with APEC. The aim Is to create a world and regional environment in which<br />
the great economic forces we are seeing unleashed, and the great revoiution in<br />
technology and global communications, become waves we can all ride in the 21st<br />
century. The emphasis must be on " all". We will meet less resistance, we will grow less tired of<br />
change If we make it with the collective interest at heart. We will generate more<br />
momentum and we will get more far-reaching reform, If we take up the challenge as a<br />
cooperative enterprise one in which all may engage and from which all can benefit.<br />
What is remarkabie about these times is their potential for cooperation. And what is<br />
remarkable about cooperation is its potential to create more general prosperity, more<br />
opportunities and better lives for more people.<br />
Sceptical as Australians by nature are, I think the last few years have deepened our belief<br />
in the potential of the times in which we live.<br />
We recognise a much greater capacity to trade and constructively engage with our region<br />
and the world, a much greater capacity to grow and manufacture products and services,<br />
to work In more productive, creative and satisfying ways, to use technology in ways which<br />
bring to our lives more knowledge, more security, more satisfaction to innovate in ways<br />
which will bring us closer to realising our personal and collective ambitions.<br />
This statement we have released today will help increase the potential of our times and<br />
deepen our faith in it.<br />
So will this Conference and I thank you for inviting me today. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
