<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2765</transcript-id>
    <title>GATT ANTI-DUMPING CODE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/01/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002765.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AAL t!! r HAA IA,~<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 168<br />
9 JANUARY 1973<br />
GATT ANTI-DUMPING CODE<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, released today a report<br />
by Sir John Crawford and by Mr G. A. Rattigan ( Chairman of the<br />
Industries Assistance Commission) on arrangements for imposing<br />
dumping duties in accordance with the anti-dumping code laid<br />
down by the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.<br />
The report recommended that legislation to implement<br />
Australia's accession to the anti-dumping code should ' provide<br />
for the Minister for Customs and Excise to -take anti-dumping<br />
action in respect of any goods which he is satisfied are being<br />
dumped in Australia and are causing or threatening material<br />
injury to established domestic industry or are materially<br />
retarding the establishment of a domestic industry. If the<br />
Minister requires independent advice it was recommended that<br />
the legislation provide for the matter to be referred to the<br />
Industries Assistance Commission and that provision also be<br />
made for appeals to the Commission against the minister's<br />
decision on a dumping complaint.<br />
As announced by Mr Whitlam at his press conference on<br />
11 December 1973, Cabinet has accepted the recommendations of<br />
the report. Copies of the report are available from the Prime Minister's<br />
Press Office or the Protection Policy Division of the Department<br />
of the Prime Minister and Cabinet.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
