<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9486</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP, VIETNAMESE BUDDHIST TEMPLE, LANSDALE, WA 17 FEBRUARY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/02/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009486.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
KXPRIME<br />
MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, VIETNAMESE BUDDHIST TEMPLE, LANSDALE, WA<br />
17 FEBRUARY 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: While I have been in Western Australia, we have had some political<br />
reshaping going on in the east, with Mr Howard trying to do the political<br />
chameleon number and almost vanish against any background the<br />
budget paper, society, his history, his past, his old policies and I now<br />
notice with a round of print interviews yesterday, they again reek of<br />
the opportunism which he displayed all last week in trying to say; " isn't<br />
it a dreadful thing that the Government has got spending cuts", yet he<br />
in fact favoured them. You will have noticed that with the slightest bit<br />
of pressure, which I applied to him last week a little bit of the<br />
blowtorch on the belly and straight away he is now saying that he<br />
only tried the spending cuts racket on the Government as a way of<br />
putting pressure on the Government, and today he is backing off he<br />
says: " he's got to be realistic, and revise his position about big<br />
spending cuts". So he's out there last week saying " isn't it shocking<br />
all these spending cuts", and I say to him " there he is being the same<br />
opportunist about this that he was about all of those things in the<br />
1980s his views on migration, his stand on various other policies",<br />
and straight away he is out there dropping it. But, in these interviews<br />
today, what we can't find if you dredge through the tonnes of wasted<br />
newsprint just from the Howard interviews there is not one single<br />
idea. What I think we can only deduce from all this all of these interviews<br />
is the only plan is to hide his policies. His interviews are dominated by<br />
backflips, indecision, policy weakness and a lack of vision, and as<br />
Geoff Kitney in the Sydney Morning Herald said, " John Howard<br />
remade may be unrecognisable", and then we actually have the<br />
Courier Mail saying " vague is best" " vague is best". So John Howard<br />
thinks he can win a national election by standing for nothing, and by<br />
being as vague as he possibly can. As I said, he keeps trying to<br />
remake himself I described him last week as the Ronald Biggs of the </p>
<p>Liberal Party, that he didn't have a past and now he is trying to<br />
remake himself again this week. He says he is now going after the<br />
blue-collar vote, but who can forget the contempt in which workers<br />
were held with his " JobsBack Policy"? Or who can forget the recent<br />
trouncina of his candidate which w as suffered in the Communication<br />
Workers Union election? I mean, this was only a few months ago. So,<br />
he expects I don't know whether he thinks working Australians are<br />
silly, or gullible but this guy is out to rip their wages to pieces he has<br />
opposed every wage increase since 1983, yet he says he is going for<br />
the blue-collar vote.<br />
He said he would support sensible spending cuts, but then refuses to<br />
nominate which ones he would support, even though he has a primary<br />
list of proposed spending cuts by Departments. He says he denies in<br />
the Telegraph, in Sydney, that he has an inability to make tough<br />
decisions he denies he has the ability to make tough decisions and<br />
then he appoints both Crichton-Browne and Prosser as his delegates<br />
in Western Australia because he won't make the tough decisions about<br />
which one it should be. He says history is important to him when it<br />
comes to the monarchy, but he tells the Telegraph that when it is his<br />
own history, history is not important. When we talk about his history<br />
it's not important, but history is important to him. He tells journalists he<br />
may change his mind on the republic, but he's against it now. In other<br />
words, if the Prime Minister Mr Keating will actually lead Australia<br />
towards a republic, he might make his mind up and he might follow.<br />
Some leader! He indicated he may change his mind about the republic<br />
while he was still opposed to it now he could not say what his view<br />
might be in 5 years. In other words, " if Mr Keating will show<br />
leadership" as usual " I might consider my position, and I might<br />
fol low',.<br />
But as we go through these amazing acrobatics, he says that there<br />
was a reform fatigue in Australia, and in the Australian electorate that<br />
he believed there was a desire for gentler policies. In other words, no<br />
more reform. So if you look at the headlines ' Vague is best", Mr<br />
Kitney's view that he may become unrecognisable, that he is walking<br />
away from all these policies you wonder what he actually stands for.<br />
Some of my critics and his supporters like Mr Alan Woods from The<br />
Australian, or Mr Steve Burrell from the Financial Review, of Mr Des<br />
Moore what do they think of their great dry hero now? When he is<br />
opposed to revenue raising, he's opposed to interest rate rises, and<br />
he's opposed to large spending cuts in other words, he is opposed to<br />
all the variables of an Australian Budget. So where does he stand? I<br />
mean, where is the hairy-chested Budget keeper of old? Where is the<br />
dry Mr Howard? Well, he has dried up. He has almost dried away.<br />
So, it was very revealing... . there is Mr Howard backing off budget cuts,<br />
but then he said Mr Howard said that he would oppose in the<br />
Senate any tax increases in the Budget as an exercise in political<br />
accountability. In other words, he will try and wreck the Government's </p>
<p>budget, but is opposed to tax increases himself, he's opposed to large<br />
spending cuts he says and he is also opposed to using monetary<br />
policy or interest rates to slow the economy.<br />
He says the countrp, has ot reffrrrn fatique. and he mtpnts be a<br />
political chameleon. The question has to be then asked why do we<br />
need him? If we think Australia should become a republic, he says<br />
he's not sure he will see where Mr Keating leads us, and if he leads,<br />
he may follow. Well, I don't mind leading. I don't mind leading and I<br />
am after followers, even if it's him. But he goes on to say that he has<br />
expressed serious reservations about the Racial Vilification<br />
Legislation, casting doubt on the Coalition's promise to produce it's<br />
own Bill, where they would not support the Liberal and National Party<br />
would not support the Government's Racial Vilification Legislation,<br />
but introduce their own, he is now saying they may not even introduce<br />
their own. They may not even introduce their own. So, on that he has<br />
sort of moved backwards. So, I think, I can only, I mean, I'm not a<br />
great admirer of sub editors in this country, but The Courier Mail did<br />
pretty well today and ' Vague is Best' from Mr Howard. I mean here he<br />
is with a round of interviews ' Vague is Best' is about all that people<br />
could drag from Mr Howard's chameleon like stunts over the last<br />
couple of days. So, as long as we now know that the sort of<br />
government which Mr Howard is proposing to Australia is one which<br />
has no policy specificity, no strength in any of the fiscal or budgetary<br />
instruments, no clarity in where he stands ideologically and only an<br />
opportunist view that he is goina to support, look after, the blue collar<br />
people who he spent half of working life trying to down in every<br />
wage round and every tax Lnd every benefit that ever came their<br />
way. I don't know whether he thinks they are silly or gullible or both.<br />
At any rate, at least I now know what I am dealing with a political<br />
blanc mange and one thing about him, I'd probably be able to stretch<br />
him around a bit. If he is pliable and rubbery, that will do me fine.<br />
J: Maybe he thinks all he has to do is tread water.<br />
PM: Or melt. Tread water or melt. Change shape again.<br />
J: You don't seem to be very impressed with him, but Mr Packer does.<br />
PM: Well, that's all right. I mean, he and Mr Packer have obviously had<br />
conversations.<br />
J: Do you think Mr Howard has promised something to him?<br />
PM: Well, I think, there is no doubt that Mr Howard has given him the nod<br />
that he would remove the cross media rules.<br />
J: Are you going to have to make some decisions about that in the near<br />
future? </p>
<p>PMV: Well, I may well do, may well have to.<br />
J: There are reports that Mr Murdoch has bought more Fairfax shares.<br />
PMV: Well, who knows, who knows.<br />
J: Are you going to be intimidated by Mr Packers remarks last night?<br />
PM: No, I told him yesterday, I am in the conflict business. I don't take the<br />
troubles I give them to people like that.<br />
J: Are you going to have to enforce the 15 per cent law though?<br />
PM: I'm sorry, you look taller than yesterday.<br />
J: With people buying shares, Mr Packer and Mr Murdoch, the<br />
Government is surely going to have to step in.<br />
PM: Well, the Government will make policy wherever it needs to be made,<br />
wherever we come to a policy fork in the road, we will go one way or<br />
another.<br />
J: Are you at one at the moment?<br />
PM: Not necessarily, no.<br />
J: There are elements in Caucus that want to tighten the cross, media<br />
ownership laws.<br />
PM: We have got elements in Caucus that want to do most everything, but<br />
anyway.<br />
J: Is that just an anti-Packer thing?<br />
PM: I think there is a genuine desire in this country for plurality in the media<br />
and ownership and it is a good thing. Look here in Western Australia,<br />
you have got one newspaper and one newspaper only, you know the<br />
Pravda of the West. You can have a day out here and not even be<br />
recognised, just obliterated, just like a Pravda sub editor. That is why<br />
we need plurality. That's why I'm glad to see you all here.<br />
J: Is this a nationalistic argument? Is this an argument about Australians<br />
owning Australian newspapers?<br />
PM: Australians obviously should have, at least, as many rights as<br />
foreigners, but again, there is another overlaying thing with that and<br />
that is the concentration of ownership and plurality. </p>
<p>J: Is he just flouting the laws?<br />
PM: I don't know. I'll have to take advice about that. Ok, well let's leave<br />
that bit there. What else have you got?<br />
J: Can I just ask you one more on that.<br />
PM: Well, maybe, just one. Promise, cross your heart and hope to die.<br />
J: Is Mr Packer thumbing his nose at the Government?<br />
PM: I don't know. Did it take you long to think that question up.<br />
J: Have you enjoyed your stay here?<br />
PM: I have actually, but Richard got very snaky yesterday, didn't he? Not<br />
making a pun I mean, snaky and he came and said, he come out very<br />
ashen saying, what was the word he used, he said ' no, I'm not thin<br />
skinned' or words to that effect.<br />
J The Premier has come out this morning and accused you of using tax<br />
payers money to campaign in marginal Labor seats.<br />
PM: Oh shucks, did he? Shucks.<br />
J: What do you mean by that?<br />
PM: Shucks.<br />
J: Have you seen reports this morning that the Ford Motor Company is<br />
considering closing its operations in Victoria?<br />
PM: I haven't seen it.<br />
J: Last time you were here Mr Keating, I suspect you may have been a bit<br />
more reserved about the Premier. You didn't try and upset him.<br />
You're comments were a bit less provocative. Have you changed your<br />
attitude?<br />
PM: I think Western Australians should note that when the Prime Minister<br />
of Australia comes to Western Australia, the West Australian Premier<br />
should try and do business on the things between us. But, you have<br />
got a Western Australian Premier who is so arrogant and puffed up<br />
with his own importance that he thinks he doesn't need to do any real<br />
business with the Commonwealth Government. Well, that's fine with<br />
me, I mean, I think that is a mistake, but that's the way he has chosen<br />
to make it.<br />
J: Is it just words or is it affecting the relationship? </p>
<p>PM: Let the people of Western Australia make a judgement about these<br />
sort of antics that he puts on. I mean, I come over here it is a planned<br />
visit, the itinerary is well known, he was invited to at least one of the<br />
fuJnctions and I do see . jeff Kennett. I do see John Fqhey, I do see<br />
Wayne Goss and half the time the media don't know I'm seeing them.<br />
We go in, just have a talk about various things, try to get things<br />
resolved. But here it is grand standing and little boy games and that is<br />
why I said, if he wants to play games, well we can give him a game.<br />
J: How successful do you think your message was? That is, that the<br />
Federal government is responsible for Western Australia's growth?<br />
PM: Well, that is, I think, the central message that West Australians should<br />
understand. That is, the growth in Western Australia is coming from<br />
the Federal government's policies, but these State Ministers wonder<br />
around cutting ribbons on projects and they say where did these come<br />
from. You know, they are cutting ribbons saying where do these come<br />
from? Well, they came from the Federal government, that's where they<br />
came from. I think it is important that Western Australians know that<br />
the central plank of the last election campaign wherein I committed<br />
myself to growth and employment growth has been faithfully honoured<br />
by me and the Federal Labor party. Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
