<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11163</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH          SENATOR ADEN RIDGEWAY          PHILLIP STREET, SYDNEY                                     SUBJECTS: Constitutional Preamble, Referendum, interest rates, preamble           question, Rupert Murdoch, Reserve Bank, economic reform, Productivity Commission           report</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/11/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE............</p>
<p>  Ladies and gentlemen, Senator Ridgeway and I have decided to call this joint</p>
<p>   press conference to make a joint appeal to the Australian people to vote</p>
<p>   yes to the preamble on Saturday. And the fact that the two of us have come</p>
<p>   together at this news conference symbolises the value of the preamble as</p>
<p>   a uniting element in constitutional debate in Australia.</p>
<p>  Because Senator Ridgeway is a self-declared yes voter on the republic and</p>
<p>   I am a self-declared no voter on the republic. But on the issue of the preamble</p>
<p>   both of us together are asking the Australian people to vote yes because</p>
<p>   we see the preamble as a way as we go into the next century of expressing</p>
<p>   what unites us rather than continuing a debate about what doesn't unite</p>
<p>   us.</p>
<p>  And the values continued in the preamble are values that I believe the overwhelming</p>
<p>   majority of Australians support. For the first time in 100 years there will</p>
<p>   be a positive gracious, decent statement going into our document, our Constitutional</p>
<p>   document, regarding the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people of</p>
<p>   this country.</p>
<p>  The other statements contained in the preamble are all statements that encapsulate</p>
<p>   fundamental Australian values. I believe that if the preamble is carried</p>
<p>   it will make a very positive contribution to the reconciliation process</p>
<p>   in this country. And in practical terms that remains an important goal of</p>
<p>   the Government. I have appreciated very much the practical contribution</p>
<p>   that Senator Ridgeway and many of his other colleagues within the indigenous</p>
<p>   leadership have made towards the process of reconciliation.</p>
<p>  Inevitably, the republican debate was going to dominate the airwaves and</p>
<p>   the newspapers and public comment over the past few weeks and we would like</p>
<p>   to bring a greater public focus in the remaining days of this referendum</p>
<p>   campaign on the preamble. We want Australians to understand that it is a</p>
<p>   uniting statement. It is a statement that carries all upside and no downside.</p>
<p>   It is a statement that the most conservative Australian who has the most</p>
<p>   hostile views towards the republic imaginable can vote yes to. It is equally</p>
<p>   a statement that a person who is an enthusiastic republican can also say</p>
<p>   yes to. And that, in a sense, it is symbolised in that unity and that coming</p>
<p>   together.</p>
<p>  And I am delighted that Aden and I have had the opportunity this morning</p>
<p>   to hold this news conference and to, from our different perspectives on</p>
<p>   the republic, he a republican, I an anti-republican, nonetheless joining</p>
<p>   together inviting the Australian people to cast a yes vote in favour of</p>
<p>   the preamble.</p>
<p>  I'll now invite Senator Ridgeway to address the news conference.</p>
<p>  SENATOR RIDGEWAY:</p>
<p>  Well, I guess the first thing I should say is that it probably comes to</p>
<p>   no surprise that I will be voting yes for the preamble and yes for the republic</p>
<p>   on Saturday. It's also of no surprise that there are diverse views amongst</p>
<p>   indigenous people about whether the preamble and whether the question of</p>
<p>   the republic ought to be supported in any fashion. And it's clear that we</p>
<p>   start from the no/no, to a yes/no, to a no/yes and a yes/yes.</p>
<p>  So I am quite delighted to be here today to, in partnership with the Prime</p>
<p>   Minister, advocate a yes vote and to call on Australians to vote overwhelmingly</p>
<p>   yes in favour of the preamble. I think that it provides a very significant</p>
<p>   opportunity, a moment in history that ought not escape the Australian public</p>
<p>   in terms of the significance of what the preamble says about Australia and</p>
<p>   about Australians.</p>
<p>  For too long we have existed as a country that is nothing more than an annex</p>
<p>   to a British act of parliament. And it's high time that through the preamble</p>
<p>   and perhaps through the question of the republic that we deal with some</p>
<p>   of the unfinished colonial business of our past. The preamble in many respects</p>
<p>   is an opportunity to chart a forward moving path. And the only way to move</p>
<p>   forward is by moving forward. I accept that there is criticism from some</p>
<p>   people about perhaps semantics in terms of what it is the preamble captures</p>
<p>   and what it doesn't. And I remind people again that it highlights and it</p>
<p>   captures, I think, many of the values and principles that are important</p>
<p>   to all Australians in terms of equality, in terms of respect, decency, in</p>
<p>   terms of diversity. These are things, I think, that Australians can vote</p>
<p>   for.</p>
<p>  But I think significantly the preamble also identifies, recognises and captures</p>
<p>   the faces of all Australians - Aborigines and Torres Strait Islanders, immigrants</p>
<p>   and other Australians. But more importantly, it also in the broader sense</p>
<p>   throws a very wide net to capturing younger and older Australians. It gives</p>
<p>   people an opportunity to affirm themselves by voting yes.</p>
<p>  And so on Saturday it will be an opportunity of Australians, irrespective</p>
<p>   of whether they are of the persuasion of being monarchist or a republican,</p>
<p>   to affirm something in themselves. And I call on the Australian people so</p>
<p>   many days out from the time that they cast their crucial vote that they</p>
<p>   vote unequivocally and overwhelmingly yes for a preamble that is a recognition</p>
<p>   of Australian people and a recognition of themselves. Thank you.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Do you have any questions for either of us?</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  The polling shows that the support for the preamble has eroded quite seriously.</p>
<p>   Do you both regret that you didn't get going earlier on this given that</p>
<p>   we are only three days out?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I have tried to avoid in relation to both the republic and the preamble</p>
<p>   to give a running commentary on the polling and I am not really going to</p>
<p>   break that habit this morning. But clearly, we want there to be more focus</p>
<p>   by the public on the preamble in the last days of the campaign. It was inevitable</p>
<p>   that most of the airwaves were going to be dominated by the republic irrespective</p>
<p>   of efforts that were made in relation to the preamble. It should be borne</p>
<p>   in mind that there is no significant campaign against the preamble and to</p>
<p>   my knowledge there will be no organised activity on the polling booths on</p>
<p>   Saturday advocating a "no" vote for the preamble. So it comes</p>
<p>   from the point of view of campaigning you are operating from a different</p>
<p>   vantage point. The important thing about the preamble is for people to know</p>
<p>   what the words are. In the nature of things, the Electoral Commission found</p>
<p>   itself unable to put all of the words of the preamble on the ballot paper</p>
<p>   because of size considerations. It's therefore important and a number of</p>
<p>   steps are being taken including in the remaining days of the campaign to</p>
<p>   bring to the attention of the Australian people the wording of the preamble.</p>
<p>   Our experience has been that once people know what is in the preamble that</p>
<p>   they give very ready assent to the aspirations of the document because they</p>
<p>   are aspirations that most Australians feel extremely supportive of.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Senator Ridgeway is a yes vote more important to you than a yes vote on</p>
<p>   the republic?</p>
<p>  SENATOR RIDGEWAY:</p>
<p>  Well, I have always considered that the pre-eminent question has been the</p>
<p>   issue of the preamble because that's what it does in terms of giving a reason</p>
<p>   for Australians to want to vote for a republic. I think that it's one thing</p>
<p>   to talk about Australia maturing and coming of age and perhaps shoving off</p>
<p>   from mother England, but it's also another question to fill the vacuum by</p>
<p>   affirming something in Australians themselves. And the preamble to a great</p>
<p>   extent does that. But irrespective of the outcome on Saturday, even if it's</p>
<p>   a no vote on the question of the republic, the issue of the preamble is</p>
<p>   one that must be resuscitated and it must be revived in order to ensure</p>
<p>   that Australians vote for themselves. That's what the preamble seeks to</p>
<p>   do. I don't believe that the campaigning for this issue is too little too</p>
<p>   late. The pre-eminent question for other Australians has primarily been</p>
<p>   the issue of the republic and I respect the fact that both camps have had</p>
<p>   an opportunity and a large amount of time in terms of airing the issues</p>
<p>   to deal with those concerns. People I think have gotten to the point of</p>
<p>   having nearly made up their minds about which way they're going to vote.</p>
<p>   There is an opportunity now to draw attention to the issue of the preamble</p>
<p>   for both camps in order to ensure that there is an overwhelming vote of</p>
<p>   yes support for the preamble.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Senator Ridgeway, if the preamble is lost, what moral message does that</p>
<p>   send to the rest of the world that Australians rejected including Aborigines</p>
<p>   or recognition of Aborigines in their constitution?</p>
<p>  SENATOR RIDGEWAY:</p>
<p>  Well I think that it's a significant moment in history and that the eyes</p>
<p>   of the world are watching Australia in terms a range of issues including</p>
<p>   race relations, one of the things that we have to be mindful of is that</p>
<p>   if there is an overwhelming vote of yes then that will come about by the</p>
<p>   tenacity, the moral tenacity of Australians who understand how significant</p>
<p>   this moment is. And I place my faith in Australians because I believe that</p>
<p>   by and large people express a goodwill in resolving a lot of the unfinished</p>
<p>   business, that this can be a yes vote and people can vote according to the</p>
<p>   moral issues that the question of the preamble raises. I would hope that</p>
<p>   perhaps on Sunday or earlier next week we will have a very clear result</p>
<p>   that says the preamble has been successful.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Senator Ridgeway, a lot of Aboriginal leaders have expressed their disappointment</p>
<p>   that there's not actually. that this isn't in the body of the Constitution.</p>
<p>   means that there is no real change in law. So what real advantage is there</p>
<p>   in the reconciliation process to having the preamble to the Constitution?</p>
<p>  SENATOR RIDGEWAY:</p>
<p>  I think you have to understand the constitutional reform has been part of</p>
<p>   a phase in and incremental process. There's no way of removing that. There</p>
<p>   are other issues in the constitution that ought to be dealt with this time</p>
<p>   around as well including some of the racially discriminatory provisions,</p>
<p>   but they're not being dealt with. Having said that people ought to understand</p>
<p>   that the preamble is not the place for setting standards or rights. It is</p>
<p>   the place that recognises the human dimensions of Australian society. And</p>
<p>   the preamble that's currently on offer does all of those things. But in</p>
<p>   addition to that I think that it lends itself to if there is an overwhelming</p>
<p>   yes vote, to revisiting the issue in terms of the main body of the constitution</p>
<p>   and dealing with the question of perhaps other rights based issues. These</p>
<p>   are things I think that are going to have to be worked out over a longer</p>
<p>   period of time. Perhaps the reconciliation process will chart the course</p>
<p>   in terms of dealing with the harder and more difficult issues. But I think</p>
<p>   that somehow you have to rally Australians around a significant focal point.</p>
<p>   The preamble provides the opportunity for that occur and to ensure that</p>
<p>   as we move down the path of dealing with unfinished business we are able</p>
<p>   to take all Australians with us, not just a select few who can rally up</p>
<p>   support and rally in support of a particular issue. It must capture the</p>
<p>   rest of the nation.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  How much do you feel that "it ain't broke don't fix it" is resonating</p>
<p>   with the Australian people in the final few days before the vote and do</p>
<p>   you think that is going to be the decisive issue when they actually go to</p>
<p>   vote?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I think it's something that's resonating significantly. Yes I do. I think</p>
<p>   it is one of the things that people have got to take into account. In fairness</p>
<p>   to the bipartisan way in which this press conference was called, I don't</p>
<p>   intend to use it as a major forum to put my point of view on the republic.</p>
<p>   It's well known. Obviously that's important, but I'd like to endorse what</p>
<p>   Aden has said about the preamble and that is that it's a statement of how</p>
<p>   we see the human attitude and the human condition. And it's an attempt to</p>
<p>   say something simple and noble about what we believe in as Australians and</p>
<p>   it will be a great shame if that opportunity is lost. And if it is lost</p>
<p>   it will be through perhaps people not being aware of the words, not so much</p>
<p>   of them being opposed to the concept or what those words stand for.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Are you worried about whether it sends out the wrong message to the outside</p>
<p>   world?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well I don't any of these things in the end send out as many messages as</p>
<p>   some people like to think they do. I don't know that Australians hang on</p>
<p>   every decision taken by the British Parliament or the American Congress</p>
<p>   or indeed any other legislature. Everybody has their own way of handling</p>
<p>   these things. I mean I am concerned about these issues in so far as they</p>
<p>   affect Australia and in so far they affect how Australians relate to each</p>
<p>   other. I think it would be enormously beneficial if we could go into the</p>
<p>   next century with a united affirmation of some of the fundamental values</p>
<p>   of the Australian community including in particular the recognition in a</p>
<p>   positive, noble, gracious way for the first time of the role of the Aboriginal</p>
<p>   and Torres Strait Islander people. But not only that. Also the contribution</p>
<p>   made by our diggers, the contribution made by immigrants, the importance</p>
<p>   of the environment, the value of the rule of law, the equality of men and</p>
<p>   women, and the common spirit that binds us together in times of adversity,</p>
<p>   called by another name in other contexts.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Isn't the wording of the question though unfortunate though Mr Howard, because</p>
<p>   people are faced with just "do you support the constitution being amended</p>
<p>   to include a preamble?" Given that it has received virtually no publicity</p>
<p>   during the campaign, lots of voters are going to say, well..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well it's not right to say it's had no publicity. Well it's actually had</p>
<p>   quite a lot. I mean it's had quite a lot of electorate wide publicity. Many</p>
<p>   of the newsletters that have been sent out certainly by many of the Coalition</p>
<p>   members that I'm aware of on a householder basis having included a full</p>
<p>   statement of what is in the preamble. So there would be for those who've</p>
<p>   sought to find out in any way there has been quite a lot dissemination of</p>
<p>   the words in the preamble. As you know from your own political experience</p>
<p>   you have to disseminate again and again and again over a long period of</p>
<p>   time for the message to get through to some people. Now that's just the</p>
<p>   nature of the democratic and communication process. But I certainly share</p>
<p>   Aden's view that now is an opportunity, as so many people I suspect have</p>
<p>   formed a view about the other issue. Now here's an opportunity in the last</p>
<p>   three days of the referendum to elevate really a knowledge of the fact that</p>
<p>   there is another vote and in that way people will seek out and have the</p>
<p>   opportunity of reading the words in the document.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  You couldn't have done better with the wording on the ballot paper?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  We looked at all sorts of ways and so did the Electoral Commission and it</p>
<p>   became quite difficult. I mean remember all the debate about the wording</p>
<p>   of the republican question? Michelle, you imagine the arguments we'd have</p>
<p>   had with some people over the summation of the preamble.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  You couldn't have just put it there?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, you could have. You could have put it on the back. But all the advice</p>
<p>   we had from the Electoral Commission was against that.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Senator Ridgeway, you spoke of "reviving the preamble". Are you</p>
<p>   saying that if Australians vote 'no' - that you won't let this matter rest?</p>
<p>  SENATOR RIDGEWAY:</p>
<p>  I think that this is part of an historical process in terms of the development</p>
<p>   of national political history. If there is a no vote it's not a question</p>
<p>   of not advocating for further constitutional change in the future. I think</p>
<p>   that that's going to arise in any event. As to whether we get an opportunity</p>
<p>   to revisit the question of constitutional reform even in the context of</p>
<p>   another preamble, I don't believe that if there is a no vote this time around</p>
<p>   that an opportunity will make itself available in the foreseeable future.</p>
<p>   And I would say that on all counts that even on the question of a republic</p>
<p>   that if there is an overwhelming no vote I don't believe that Australians</p>
<p>   will want to revisit the issue for at least another 100 years.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Do you agree with Senator Ridgeway that a strong vote for the preamble could</p>
<p>   open the way for further constitutional reform and that even the suggestion</p>
<p>   that some of these rights issues might ultimately be incorporated into the</p>
<p>   body of the Constitution?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well our position as a government is that we would like the preamble supported.</p>
<p>   We are not saying to the Australian people that has an automatic consequence.</p>
<p>   Indeed we don't believe it has any consequence in relation to the formal</p>
<p>   wording of the constitution. I respect the fact that Senator Ridgeway might</p>
<p>   have another view on that and it is properly open to him and his party to</p>
<p>   argue that point of view but the Coalition is for the preamble, that's it,</p>
<p>   as to other matters, well, they have to be dealt with on their merits. We</p>
<p>   do believe that the preamble will make a very valuable contribution to the</p>
<p>   reconciliation process and that's why I'm very keen to see it supported.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, are interest rates going to rise further?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I don't comment on the future of interest rates, you know that, in</p>
<p>   either direction. Now, let me say in relation to the increase that was announced</p>
<p>   this morning by the Reserve Bank - the Governor has pointed out that the</p>
<p>   many reductions in interest rates which have given us our lowest level of</p>
<p>   interest rates for 30 years occurred in a climate of a recessed, indeed,</p>
<p>   declining world economy. The very small adjustment that's been made this</p>
<p>   morning reflects the fact that the world economy is growing now quite strongly,</p>
<p>   that the outlook for growth is better than what it was a year ago. There</p>
<p>   have been in countries like Korea very significant improvements in our region</p>
<p>   in the level of economic growth and that of necessity the stance of monetary</p>
<p>   policy ought to change somewhat. As to the future, I don't speculate in</p>
<p>   any way or either way about what's going to happen.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, do you think the Queen or Royal family will be distressed</p>
<p>   if Australia votes to be a republic on Saturday?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I think it's been made abundantly clear and I'm sure it is the view of the</p>
<p>   Queen that this is entirely a matter for the Australian people.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Do you think she'll be upset?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  She has made it perfectly clear all along it's entirely a matter for the</p>
<p>   Australian people. I am certain that whatever decision is taken by the Australian</p>
<p>   people she will accept and respect.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  [Inaudible] I'm about to report back to Aboriginal radio. Given the conflicting</p>
<p>   reasons Aboriginal leaders have given to Aborigines have been given about</p>
<p>   whether to vote yes or no to the preamble, do you have a message to them?</p>
<p>  SENATOR RIDGEWAY:</p>
<p>  Well, I think the message to indigenous Australia is that there needs to</p>
<p>   be an understanding that there has been an absence of recognition of indigenous</p>
<p>   people in Australian society for almost 100 years. This provides an opportunity</p>
<p>   for indigenous people to finally gain some recognition in the Constitution.</p>
<p>   It's not the end game. I think it's the beginning of an ongoing process.</p>
<p>   But I think that people need to understand that in a broader context of</p>
<p>   it is an opportunity to vote yes and affirm something that unifies the nation</p>
<p>   rather than divides the nation. So in talking in the context of unfinished</p>
<p>   colonial business we have to create a starting point for being able to bring</p>
<p>   about the substantive issues of what unification of Australia means in terms</p>
<p>   of all of those that make up all walks of Australian life. So, a call to</p>
<p>   indigenous Australia is to understand that this is clearly a need to understand</p>
<p>   that for the first time they will get recognition and that they can feel</p>
<p>   comfortable about voting yes irrespective of the semantics because it plays</p>
<p>   a vital role in terms of their recognition in national life.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Peak interest groups are saying that the interest rates have risen too early.</p>
<p>   Do you share their view?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  These matters are decided by the Reserve Bank. The Reserve Bank has decided</p>
<p>   to lift the official interest rate by 25 basis points. They've given certain</p>
<p>   reasons which I fully understand and I think they are intelligent reasons</p>
<p>   but I'm not going to get into a debate about whether it should or shouldn't</p>
<p>   have happened. It was a decision of the Reserve Bank. We've held very strongly</p>
<p>   to the view since becoming the Government that monetary policy should be</p>
<p>   set and administered independently by the central bank, therefore, I'm not</p>
<p>   going to get into a debate either way accept to observe that the reasons</p>
<p>   advanced by the bank make a great deal of sense to me.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, Rupert Murdoch today seems to be likening your government to</p>
<p>   the Suharto regime for not embracing the Productivity Commission's suggestions</p>
<p>   on media ownership, draft suggestions..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I didn't see that. I didn't see that.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  [Inaudible] .. in the business section of The Australian.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I haven't got to that, Michelle. I'm still wading through the Sydney</p>
<p>   Morning Herald.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Well, can I just quote: (inaudible)"..sounds like Indonesia under Suharto"..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I'm sure citizen Murdoch was being, you know, particularly - how shall</p>
<p>   I put it - particularly expansionary and colourful in his political comparisons</p>
<p>   when he was making that. Of course any comparison between us and the Suharto</p>
<p>   government is quite absurd and I'm sure he's had his tongue well and truly</p>
<p>   planted in his cheek.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  He had a few side-swipes on the front page.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Yes, I read those.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  What did you think of those?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I think we've got the pace of reform in this country right. This has</p>
<p>   been a very reformist government. I don't think we've been timid at all.</p>
<p>   I think we've been balanced. I think we've been courageous but we haven't</p>
<p>   been foolhardy. And economic reform is just not something which is handled</p>
<p>   for the benefit of the boardrooms of the nation. It is also something that</p>
<p>   has got to carry the people with it. And unless you carry people with economic</p>
<p>   reform you will lose your authority both political and moral to undertake</p>
<p>   reform. And I understand the mood and temper of the Australian people and</p>
<p>   that is that they will accept reform if you satisfy two conditions. If you</p>
<p>   persuade them that it's in the interests of Australia and also if you persuade</p>
<p>   them that it is fair. And it can't be handed down to them in some doctrinaire</p>
<p>   fashion. You have to </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
