<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4081</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORAL TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/03/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004081.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
BROADCAST: -3HA 3XY 14 March 17(<br />
3YB 18 March 17(<br />
EMBARGO: CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 14 March 1976<br />
ELECTORAL TALK<br />
Next Saturday, Victorians cast votes to decide what kind<br />
of Government they want over the next three years.<br />
This year the choice will be perhaps more crucial<br />
than it has ever been.<br />
Australia is once again poised to take advantage of our great<br />
natural wealth. We are poised on the threshold of an<br />
era where every Australian has a decent chance to get down<br />
to the business of living a better standard of life.<br />
But this will not happen if our national household budget is<br />
out of order. It will not happen if our economy is weak,<br />
listless and without real chance of growth.<br />
At the moment, most of our efforts are aimed at reviving<br />
the economic corpse we inherited.<br />
on this point let there be no doubt that for our economic<br />
management to work as effectively as it should, the national<br />
Government needs the support of all State Governments.<br />
We are not just looking for token assistance but for real<br />
interaction and encouragement at both ministerial and<br />
departmental level.<br />
I know we will get just that support from Dick Hamer. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
We also believe that State Governments have a crucial<br />
role to play if Australians are to be allowed to shape the<br />
course.. of their own lives, without interference from<br />
' big brother'.<br />
Todayi Australians have a genuine choice in the kind of<br />
Government they want. They have genuine alternatilres.<br />
The choice is guite simple. It rests between the centralist<br />
socialist policy of Mr Whitlam's and Mr Holding's Party<br />
and the Federalist policy of the Liberal Party. In other<br />
words, it is a choice between more and more government control<br />
and dominance and less central Government control.<br />
Labor beli. eves that all Government power should be placed in<br />
the hands of a few men. They believe Government should have<br />
greater control over individuals lives. Labor has tried to<br />
destroy the role of the States and has even attempted to<br />
exercise central control over local governments.<br />
Labor also tried to destroy the Senate the very instrument<br />
the Constitution established to protect -the States.<br />
on December 13 last, Australians categorically told Labor<br />
what they thought of these and other philosophies.<br />
Next Saturday, Victorians have the same opportunity.<br />
During the recent campaign opening for Dick Hamer in<br />
Melbourne I said that the Liberal Party's Federalismn Policy<br />
will be the strongest guarantee that irresponsible attempts<br />
to centralise all power in the hands of a few men will never<br />
happen again.<br />
Let me stress that point tonight. My Government is deeply<br />
committed to the principle that decisions affectIng local towns,<br />
suburbs and cities must be made by the Government on the spot.<br />
Canberra should not meddle with power hungry hands where local<br />
knowledge and talents can do the job so much better. </p>
<p>Of course, what is needed here is not just a patch-up of<br />
the currently degenerated Federal system. We must create<br />
a political and social climate where the growing demands<br />
of groups and individuals can be heard. People must be able<br />
to participate in a meaningful way in the democratic process.<br />
For these reasons, your vote next Saturday will count, it<br />
will have meaning.<br />
Through the ballot box you can express your opinion as to<br />
the type of State Government you want. You can make a<br />
choice between two opposing philosophies. You can decide<br />
between more Government control or less Government control.<br />
You can opt for socialism. Or you can opt for a Party whose<br />
view of Government is that it should create a society and an<br />
environment where individuals may best fulfill themselves. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
