<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>79</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  P.M.NO. 22/1959  PREMIERS CONFERENCE AND LOAN COUNCIL STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER RT HON .J MCEWEN M.P </title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/06/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000079.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. -No.-22/ I951) 1IXPREMIER-<br />
S CONFERENCE AND LOAN CO-NCIL<br />
Statement by__ the A~ cti~ png Prime minister, Rt. Hon. J. McEwen M. P.<br />
This conference comes about in two ways. First of all,<br />
at this time or about this time in every year the matter of the<br />
State Tax Reimbursements Grants and Loan allocations is decided.<br />
But9 in addition, the Commonwealth has said that it has undertaken<br />
to make some general re-examination of Commonwealth-State<br />
financial relations. This was said in the policy speechgand the<br />
Conference on 4th and 5th March was the first step towards it.<br />
This Conference will resume the discussion on that issue.<br />
It has been apparent for some years that the present<br />
tax reimbursement formula has not satisfied all the States and has<br />
been a source of disagreement both as to the quantum of the annual<br />
grant and its distribution. Every year for many years the<br />
Commonwealth has found it necessary to add an amount, arbitrarily<br />
arrived at, to the tax reimbursement formula grants. F-ru-ther.....,<br />
some States have said that the present distribution arrangements<br />
are unsatisfactory. Over and above that, within the present financial year<br />
two States Victoria and Queensland have raised the question of<br />
applying for special assistance under section 969 i. e. 9 Grants<br />
Commission assistance. If this were to come about, five States<br />
out of six would come within the Grants Comirission arrangements<br />
and this would make the system unworkable. So it was clear that<br />
a study of a possible revision was needed.<br />
At the March Conference the Prime Minister, speaking<br />
for the Commonwealth, said that we would put to study the question<br />
of something new which might rectify any position of disadvantage<br />
in one or two States while ensuring that the needs of other States<br />
were given due recognition,,<br />
So we have made this study. We have looked at the<br />
matter under several headings, -, ihich include the quantum of the<br />
grant9 the distribution arrangements and Grants Commission<br />
arrangements, and we will be putting soe proposals to the States<br />
as we undertook to do. This whole problem does not reduce itself<br />
to simple arithmetic and does not lend itself to any precise<br />
scientific solution, But we have plans to put forward which we<br />
believe to be practical and cormmonsense. It will, of course, be<br />
open for discussion around the table. We have already had from<br />
the States in ansr-j' to our invitation soire helpful views and we<br />
have made use of thcsec<br />
I am hopeful that in a spirit of partnership and cooperation<br />
the seven Governments in conference will work towards<br />
better arrangements for future provision of grants to the States<br />
and their equitable distribution."<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T.<br />
22nd June, 1959, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
