<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12417</transcript-id>
    <title>Launch of the Australia Academy of Science&#039;s Shine Dome, Canberra</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/05/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Science and innovation.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much Professor Anderson, Professor John Shine, Ladies and Gentlemen. It's a special pleasure in a symbolic way as well as in the practical sense of it to be associated with the formal launch or opening of the refurbished Shine Dome here in Canberra this morning.</p>
<p>It's a very symbolic and appropriate way in the presence of so many eminent Australian scientists for me to on behalf of the government honour the contribution of the science community to modern Australian life. It's an opportunity to recall in a slightly nostalgic way the involvement of my predecessor - Sir Robert Menzies - 33 years ago in laying the foundation stone. It's also an opportunity for me to honour on your behalf the extraordinary personal generosity of Professor John Shine who contributed so much of himself to the cost of refurbishing the dome. And to make the observation that it is but the latest example of the willingness of so many Australians who find themselves in a position to do so to contribute in a philanthropic way to the nurturing of the talents that we have, not only scientific talent but also talents in so many other walks of life.</p>
<p>And what has happened over the last few years in relation to the science community in Australia, and I'm very proud of the government's involvement in a number of those things. The contribution to medical science which came out of the Wills recommendations and involved the doubling of research funding for medical science represented an important expression of long term confidence and faith in the capacity of our scientific and medical community. And the role played by so many people here today in helping the government put together its statement Backing Australia's Ability which provided a long term blueprint for investment in science and innovation in the years ahead.</p>
<p>Now I would be the last to assert that that has completed the job so far as the government is concerned. But I think we have seen over the last few years a new assertion of the faith in all sections of the Australian community in the contribution being made by our scientists. I think there is a greater respect and a greater understanding and a greater appreciation of the value that science adds to Australian life. There is a growing awareness amongst the young of the importance of it, but we still have particularly through the education process a very long way to go.</p>
<p>This building I'm told is something of an icon for the scientific community of Australia. And refurbishing icons is always important both in a physical sense and also in an intellectual sense. And what today's opening does is to allow me on behalf of the government to express my gratitude and that of the government for the contribution that all of you make to Australian life, for me to emphasise the ongoing commitment the government has not only to the full and speedy and complete recommendations and announcements of the January statement, but also in a broad sense the ongoing priority that the government attaches to the role of science and innovation within our community.</p>
<p>In the end we as a nation will succeed, or perform in a fairly mediocre fashion, according to the capacity we have over the years ahead to effectively utilise our intellectual and inventive capital. We have great natural resources, we have an enviable lifestyle, but those things alone will not guarantee Australia's security and a high standard of living. Unless we effectively utilise and put to good positive use our intellectual capital, our capacity for inventiveness, and very importantly our capacity to convert good ideas and knowledge to effective practical use, unless we can do that more effectively as a community we're going to fall behind. And that's why you as a community are so very important to us. The opportunities in biotechnology and information communications technology are almost limitless and Australia has some great advantages of the natural and intellectual kind, we have great advantages that will allow us to punch above our weight if we are skilful in putting the resources in the right areas and giving the area the right priority. And that is why today's opening in a symbolic way is so very important.</p>
<p>I want to again on your behalf thank Professor Shine for his extraordinary personal generosity, others who've contributed. I do want to join Professor Anderson in acknowledging the contribution that Margaret Reid and John Ralph and Kate Carnell made to the campaign, to ensure that the government gave the right priority to this particular project. I know how tireless all of them were in those efforts. And can I say that this is a magnificently refurbished facility and I know that all of you will see it as a fitting physical reminder of the centrality of science and all that goes with it in the national life of our country. Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
