<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9185</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP DOORSTOP, HELLFIRE PASS, SATURDAY, 9 APRIL 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/04/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009185.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FROM t267796S4 MEDIR RDVISER TO : 06 273 2923 1940-9 400 N?. 1<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, HELLIFIRE PASS, SATURDAY, 9 APRIL 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Prime Minister, you are drawing parallels from our past to our future,<br />
how do you see this visit here to Hellfire Pass In those terms?<br />
PM: Our first engagement with -Asia. was in war, our first engagement of<br />
substance with this country was In war. It is now an engagement not<br />
only in peace, but in partnership. What happened here was slavery<br />
during the war. The Japanese strategic objectives, many thousands<br />
died using primitive devices to cut a pass like this and other passes to<br />
build a railway which was of strategic value in the conquest of Burma.<br />
We should not simply remember the thousands who died here<br />
including Australians, but the many hundreds of thousands of local<br />
people who had no medical support what so ever as Indeed we had,<br />
but thousands of Australians, British, Dutch, some Americans, Malays,<br />
Thais died here. And for us this has become a symbol of endurance;<br />
of tenacity; of ingenuity; of compassion and part of the Anzac legend<br />
which was born in Gal lipoli and in Flanders and in Western Europe<br />
has been added to during the Second World War in places like this.<br />
So, I think we should have these things in our mind when we think<br />
about that part of Asia closest to Australia, in thinking about the<br />
relationships we now have to draw on this experience and to value it<br />
and learn from it.<br />
J: Prime Minister, should young Australians focus on the atrocities of an<br />
old enemy or the sacrifice of fathers and grandfathers?<br />
PM; We focus on the faith these people had in Australia in what we built<br />
there; in the values we had established there and that which kept them<br />
going through this terrible period of tribulation for them. That is the<br />
spirit we wish to remember and we have seen it embodied in many<br />
Australians. Unfortunately, too many are here still, buried here. </p>
<p>FROM 12677964 MEDIA ADVISER O 30623921994, e4-09 14101 # 87 P. 02<br />
2<br />
J: Prime Minister, you have chosen to go to a war site here, but not in<br />
Vietnam. Can you explain why?<br />
PM: We don't have any cemeteries in Vietnam. We brought all of the<br />
Australian dead home. So, there -isn't the' Australian war cemeteries In<br />
Vietnam that there Is in Thailand or indeed In other parts of South-East<br />
Asia.<br />
J: It Is a more complex equation though isn't It, we are talking here about<br />
a country where Australia was always allies with Thailand, In Vietnam<br />
it Is a more complex situation to deal with though isn't it?<br />
PM: Well, continental Australia was under threat in the Second World War<br />
and I think that it was a battle for our nation and this was of that battle.<br />
J, The resignation of the Japanese Prime Minister, would you care to<br />
comment on that?<br />
PM: No, well, I don't know any more than I think you've already reported.<br />
J: Mr Prime Minister, do you think Japan has adequately apologised for<br />
the war?<br />
PM: I think It has sought to do that. I think we would like the Japanese<br />
people particularly younger Japanese people to understand fully the<br />
ramifications of the war and it Is in the telling of the history that Japan<br />
has to be more fulsome and complete in articulating its role In this<br />
period.<br />
ends. TO I OS 273 2923 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
