<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12816</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL BIOTECHNOLOGY CENTRE OF EXCELLENCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/12/2002</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I have received an independent report from Mr Geoff Allen, Chairman of</p>
<p> The Allen Consulting Group, on the process for selecting the Biotechnology</p>
<p> Centre of Excellence.</p>
<p>The report was commissioned in response to concerns raised about the</p>
<p> integrity of the process which resulted in the National Stem Cell Centre</p>
<p> (NSCC) being selected as the Biotechnology Centre of Excellence.</p>
<p>Mr Allen concluded that the process used in selecting the NSCC "represents</p>
<p> the high end, or even marks new standards, of best practice in the integrity</p>
<p> of such processes".</p>
<p>Mr Allen found no significant deficiencies in the process and has recommended</p>
<p> that the grant to the NSCC proceed. I have accepted that recommendation.</p>
<p>I will table the report in</p>
<p> Parliament during the first sitting of 2003.</p>
<p>A grant of $43.55 million has been allocated, over five years, to establish</p>
<p> Australia';s first Biotechnology Centre of Excellence, with the criteria</p>
<p> for the preferred operator covering quality of research, governance, management</p>
<p> and business and international linkages.</p>
<p>The Centre for Stem Cells and Tissue Repair (now the National Stem Cell</p>
<p> Centre) was selected from 11 applicants to be the operator of the National</p>
<p> Biotechnology Centre of Excellence following a lengthy selection process.</p>
<p>Links:</p>
<p> * Review</p>
<p>   of the National Biotechnology Centre of Excellence Selection Process</p>
<p>   - Biotechnology of Australia website</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
