<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7203</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/07/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007203.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 29 JULY 1987<br />
The Primo 1inister today chaired a meeting of representatives<br />
of the coal industry workforce, coal mining companies, the<br />
Queensland and NSW State Governments and the Commonwealth<br />
Government. Following a constructive discussion, during which there was<br />
a positive contribution from all parties, it was agreed that<br />
there would be an acceleration of negotiations at the<br />
enterprise level about changes to improve mine viability and<br />
secure the future of Australia's largest export industry.<br />
To give effect to this shared commitment it was agreed that<br />
for a period of at least one month:<br />
employers will seek to achieve a moratorium on<br />
retrenchments where there is discretion to avoid<br />
retrenchments ( and whore there is disagreement between<br />
the oaaties in NSW about the scope for discretion in<br />
particular cases, the Joint Coal Board shall be the<br />
point of reference fo determining the facts); and<br />
the unions will cease industrial action, including<br />
overtine bans.<br />
This agroment will be reviewed by the two parties within<br />
the one month period, to assess progress achieved.<br />
o<br />
An extraczdinary meeting of the Australian Coal Consultative<br />
Council wIll be convened by the Minister for Primary<br />
Industriesc and Energy, Mr John Kerin, at the earliest<br />
opportunity. This meeting will supplement the negotiations<br />
which will be occurring at the enterprise level. In<br />
particular, the neeting will consider elements of the<br />
overall strategy which are nore effectively dealt with at<br />
the aggregate level rather than at the enterprise level.<br />
In this regard the Commonwealth will consider enlarging<br />
forms o assistance currently available under the Relocaticn<br />
Assistanice Scheme and the Labour Adjustment Training<br />
Arrangercnt to facilitate relocation and retraining of coal<br />
industry craploycee.<br />
For their part, the NSW and Queensland Governments, further<br />
to the ccncessions they have already given, will examine how<br />
they might assist the coal industry by way of reductions in<br />
State cha:: ges affecting the coal mining industry. This<br />
examination will depend on progress achieved by the<br />
employees and the mining unions in their negotiations. 00 : 4 </p>
<p>t 2.<br />
It was further agreed that if the parties considered it<br />
desirable, the Prime Minister would convene a further<br />
meeting of the various parties at a later date.<br />
The Prime Minister indicated that, in regard to marketing,<br />
while the Commonwealth adhered to its view that there would<br />
be no centralised authority, the Government was open to<br />
represontations from unions and employers on how the<br />
existing reserve power in the export control arrangements<br />
should be utilised. Howevor, the exercise of the reserve<br />
power ultimately will remain the responsibility of the<br />
ministor for Primary Industries and Energy.<br />
Finally, the Commonwealth Government is available at the<br />
request c9 the unions or the employers to facilitate<br />
progreno in negotiations. 00034136 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
