<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10195</transcript-id>
    <title>REBUILDING REGIONAL AUSTRALIA THE CASE OF THE CAPITAL REGION STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE MINISTER FOR SPORT, TERRITORIES &amp; LOCAL GOVERNMENT CANBERRA, 13 DECEMBER 1996</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010195.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
REBUILDING REGIONAL AUSTRALIA<br />
The Case of the Capital Region<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
AND THE MINISTER FOR SPORT,<br />
TERRITORIES LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
Canberra, 13 December 1996 </p>
<p>REBUILDING REGIONAL AUSTRALIA<br />
The Case of the Capital Region<br />
The Liberal-National Government is committed to rebuilding regional Australia. The<br />
Government's priorities of responsible economic management, microeconomic reform,<br />
small business and families will assist regions to maximise their potential and to<br />
contribute to a prosperous Australia.<br />
The Coalition is committed to promoting growth, supporting small and medium sized<br />
enterprises and assisting families in the Australian Capital Region, which comprises<br />
south east New South Wales and the Australian Capital Territory.<br />
The Coalition has identified three broad aspects of the region where it can, and will,<br />
provide strong and active support.<br />
First, Canberra, as Australia's national capital, is the home of many of the institutions.<br />
that define our national identity.<br />
Second, it is the seat of government and centre of national administration which<br />
provides opportunities for business in the region to provide goods and services to<br />
departments and agencies.<br />
Third, the Australian Capital Region is a centre of primary and tertiary production and<br />
it contains a major transport node which links the region with many other parts of<br />
Australia. The region's competitive strengths include its active business community, its centres of<br />
-higher learning and research, its well educated workforce, its proximity to the nation's<br />
centre of administration, its clean environment, its culturally diverse population and the<br />
quality of its rural production.<br />
A Region in Transition<br />
When the Coalition came to power in March this year our first task was to redress the<br />
spending and debt excesses of the former Labor government. We inherited a legacy of<br />
continuing high unemployment and low national savings. We have had to turn around<br />
the 1995-96 underlying deficit of $ 10.3 billion.<br />
We had to stop the rising tide of government debt. Commonwealth debt on issue has<br />
risen, in the last five years alone, from $ 43 billion in June 1991 to a massive $ 1<br />
billion in June 1996. Stopping the debt spiral and restoring sound economic<br />
management has required some hard decisions, but decisions that could no longer be<br />
avoided. Our strong and fair budget aimed to reduce the underlying budget deficit by<br />
around $ 7.2 billion over the next two years.<br />
Fiscal consolidation is essential to increase national savings and thereby our growth<br />
potential and employment. The Australian Capital Region will maximise the benefits of<br />
fiscal consolidation if it develops a strong and vibrant mixed economy of private and<br />
public sector employment through enterprise, self-reliance and diversity. </p>
<p>The Coalition Government acknowledges that its ambitious economic reform agenda<br />
has implications for economic growth and development in the Australian Capital<br />
Region. Although the region is home to nearly half a million Australians, its growth<br />
rate has decreased significantly this decade, and now stands at around one percent per<br />
annum. Although some local government areas such as Queanbeyan and Eurobodalla<br />
are growing more strongly, we recognise that the generally low rate of growth is<br />
having an adverse effect on many businesses in the region.<br />
The rate of unemployment is particularly high in Eurobodalla but it is also a major<br />
concern in Bega Valley, Snowy River, Young and elsewhere in the region. Timber<br />
mills have closed in Eden and Moruya, as have bank branches in many of the region's<br />
towns. Unless corrective measures are taken, this is likely to continue into the medium<br />
term. The public sector will remain a substantial employer in the region as well as a<br />
purchaser of goods and services from the local private sector. The focus of regional<br />
activity and growth must, however, progressively shift to the private sector. The<br />
Australian Capital Region must be repositioned to take advantage of the opportunities<br />
which are emerging within new sectors of the Australian economy and the Asia-Pacific<br />
region. The region already has a strong and active business sector. Canberra's private sector<br />
exceeded that of the public sector in 1989 and now accounts for 52 of total<br />
employment. The expansion of the private sector in the region provides a sound base<br />
for future growth in servicing the needs of government. It is also a solid platform for<br />
exporting goods and services and rural produce to the rest of Australia and to the Asia<br />
Pacific Region.<br />
The Government will play its part in encouraging growth and the recent budget will<br />
contribute towards this end. Many of our policies will directly benefit the region. For<br />
example, the high proportion of young families in the Region will benefit from the<br />
Government's budget initiative which provides a $ 1 billion tax break for families.<br />
Approximately ninety percent of the region's businesses employ less than twenty<br />
people. Small businesses will benefit from the $ 180 million per annum reduction in<br />
provisional tax, the provision of capital gains tax rollover relief for small business with<br />
assets up to $ 5 million and from our commitment to do away with unnecessary<br />
regulation and other bureaucratic imposts.<br />
The report of the Small Business Deregulation Task Force, which was chaired by<br />
Charlie Bell of McDonald's, recently reported on ways to reduce the burden of red<br />
tape on small business. It has made 62 recommendations covering tax, regulatory<br />
compliance and related issues. We will be responding positively to the report by mid<br />
February of next year.<br />
Reduced interest rates benefit families and small businesses alike, and provide powerful<br />
incentives to invest and to create more employment. Since March, official interest<br />
rates have been reduced three times, reflecting progress in locking in low inflation and<br />
the fiscal consolidation strategy. </p>
<p>The Government also expects the ACT and NSW Governments and regional local<br />
governments to be competitive, to minimise their taxes on industry and the community,<br />
to ensure that their services are efficient and keenly priced and that they impose the<br />
minimum of regulation and red tape on businesses.<br />
The Nation's Capital<br />
At the heart of the region is the nation's capital. Canberra has achieved its national and<br />
international standing as Australia's capital largely through the foresight and<br />
commitment of Prime Minister Sir Robert Menzies. His government established the<br />
National Capital Development Commission and transferred many departments from<br />
Melbourne to Canberra. The Menzies Government was instrumental in establishing<br />
such national institutions as the Australian War Memorial and the Defence<br />
headquarters at Russell. Lake Burley Griffin was developed during his time and the<br />
Australian National University was a major beneficiary of his government.<br />
More recently, Malcolm Fraser's government added to the cultural and heritage<br />
infrastructure of the nation by commencing the New Parliament House competition,<br />
the Australian Institute of Sport, the Australian Defence Force Academy, the High<br />
Court of Australia and the National Gallery of Australia.<br />
There is now a substantial investment in national institutions of culture, heritage and<br />
learning in Canberra. Already, over 1.3 million visitors come to Parliament House<br />
each year, over 800,000 visit the Australian War Memorial and nearly half a million<br />
come to each of the National Gallery of Australia and Telstra Tower on Black<br />
Mountain.<br />
The Commonwealth Government, through the National Capital Authority ( NCA), has<br />
an integral role in the planning and development of Canberra as Australia's National<br />
Capital. In addition to its significant responsibilities in the preparation and administration of the<br />
National Capital Plan, the NCA has important capital works and asset management<br />
responsibilities for areas of national significance principally the Central National Area<br />
which includes Lake Burley Griffin, national parklands and the Parliamentary Triangle.<br />
Only this week, Territories Minister Warwick Smith announced the appointment of Air<br />
Marshal David Evans as the new chairman of the NCA. Air Marshal Evans is a long<br />
term resident of Canberra, whose leadership qualities will be of great assistance to the<br />
NCA in its future activities.<br />
A recent study of Australian's views about their National Capital delivered a very<br />
strong message that people are willing to attend events and activities that reflect our<br />
national identity. They also value the ideals of the National Capital, quality national<br />
precincts and national institutions. </p>
<p>In response we have broadened the responsibilities of the former National Capital<br />
Planning Authority which we have renamed the NCA to provide for a greater focus on<br />
strategic development and raising the awareness of the nation's capital. A priority of<br />
the Government is to ensure that the marketing and promotion of the national<br />
institutions, culture and heritage are properly co-ordinated<br />
Equally, the Government is committed to ensuring that the newly structured NCA and<br />
other Commonwealth authorities work closely with the ACT and regional local<br />
governments and the tourist industry to develop an annual calendar of events that has a<br />
broad-based appeal to the Australian community and to international tourists. The<br />
Federal Government stands behind a focussed and practical tourist development<br />
strategy.<br />
In the financial circumstances which the Government inherited from Labor, there is<br />
limited capacity to undertake new building programs. However, within the resources<br />
available, the refurbishment of Old Parliament House is continuing and there is funding<br />
for refurbishment of the Australian War Memorial and an extension for the National<br />
Gallery of Australia.<br />
Consideration will be given to ways in which the parliamentary zone foreshore area can<br />
be enlived and enriched to reinforce the national institutions already present and to<br />
provide a community focal point for national innovation and enterprise events.<br />
Funding has been provided for site and scoping studies for the National Museum of<br />
Australia including the Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander<br />
Studies ( AIATSIS) and the Government appointed leading Canberra businessman, Mr<br />
Jim Service, as the new Chairman. The Board has now completed its studies. I am<br />
delighted to announce that the Commonwealth accepts the committee's<br />
recommendation that the Museum will be located on the Acton Peninsula. Funding<br />
details will be announced in the 1997-98 budget context. As a downpayment on<br />
further work, the Commonwealth will allocate $ 750,000 for a development brief to<br />
commence in January 1997.<br />
We are also continuing the refurbishment of the Old Parliament House and the<br />
Australian War Memorial as well as an extension for the National Gallery.<br />
We must maintain our efforts to make Canberra and the region even more attractive<br />
for Australian families to visit. The museum will add an important new element to<br />
their appreciation of their country's culture and heritage.<br />
These initiatives will increase economic activity during their construction and operating<br />
phases and will also have a wider multiplier effect through the increase in interstate and<br />
international tourism. </p>
<p>The Seat of Government and National Administration<br />
Canberra plays a significant role in Australian life as the seat of government and the<br />
centre of national administration. It Is an important meeting place for Parliamentarians,<br />
public servants, and the many national associations that represent the interests of<br />
businesses, and community groups.<br />
The Government is committed to reducing the cost of administration and to purchasing<br />
from the most efficient providers of effective goods and services. These policies<br />
improve the effectiveness of service delivery and will provide strong incentives for<br />
employment growth in the private sector.<br />
The region's business community has the capacity and drive to undertake the necessary<br />
transition from a public service centre to a broad based region of growth. The<br />
Coalition will be providing many of the opportunities. The Minister for Administrative<br />
Services estimates that in his portfolio alone, there will be up to 2,500 jobs created in<br />
the private sector to largely offset any job losses stemming from the 1996 Budget.<br />
Reforms within the Department of Administrative Services, particularly the<br />
outsourcing of commercial activities, will greatly expand opportunities for the private<br />
sector to compete for Government business.<br />
I understand that the Canberra business community has expressed some concern that<br />
the packaging of these outsourcing tenders will effectively freeze out small business.<br />
This Government is strongly committed to increasing opportunities for the private<br />
sector and our outsourcing programme reflects our commitment to both large and<br />
small to medium enterprises.<br />
When we examine how best to manage our outsourcing programme, it is clear that our<br />
highest priority will be to maximise both efficiency and savings for the Commonwealth.<br />
On occasion, this may lead to the packaging of tenders in large bundles more suited to<br />
the capacity of large business. The small business sector should not, however, feel<br />
overlooked, for such contracts include a wealth of subcontracting opportunities ideally<br />
tailored to that sector.<br />
Nevertheless, the Government has heard your concerns and I will ensure that all<br />
outsourcing proposals are closely examined with a view to maximising opportunities<br />
for small to medium enterprises.<br />
As a first step, just yesterday, a roundtable discussion took place between the Canberra<br />
business community and government officials in relation to outsourcing. It was agreed<br />
that the business community would be consulted in the preparation and development of<br />
outsourcing guidelines.<br />
The Government has also reaffirmed its commitment to Canberra's role as the centre of<br />
national administration through the continuation of the major Defence and Australian<br />
Geological Survey Organisation projects and through the development of a new<br />
headquarters for the Patents Office. Other national administration projects will be<br />
considered in future budgets according to their relative priority and the prevailing fiscal<br />
outlook. </p>
<p>The Capital Region a Centre of Economic Growth<br />
The Commonwealth's economic reform agenda will assist regions to maximise their<br />
potential. Equally, renewed growth in regional Australia will contribute significantly to<br />
national micro-economic reform and will reduce pressure on infrastructure in Sydney<br />
and Melbourne. The Government recognises the role that the Australian Capital<br />
Region can play in this regard.<br />
The region is already undertaking the transition from a heavy reliance on the public<br />
service to becoming an important economic and transport centre. Canberra provides<br />
high order commerce and other services for the entire south east of NSW, but further<br />
reductions in transport costs will directly benefit primary producers and other<br />
businesses in the region. The region is also well placed to take some of the pressure<br />
off Sydney's airport and arterial roads through improved rail services and providing<br />
direct air access to the Asia Pacific Region.<br />
Vei-y East Traiui<br />
The initiative of the private sector to propose the funding and operation of a high<br />
speed rail service between Sydney and Canberra is a major demonstration of<br />
confidence in this region and in the nation. The Coalition believes that a viable very<br />
fast train project, with its potential to extend to Melbourne, Brisbane and Adelaide,<br />
could potentially have a major Impact on the nation as a whole.<br />
If the project's viability is established, it will result in a substantial investment of private<br />
sector funds. It would generate major new construction and operational employment<br />
and markedly reduce travel times and costs for both the business sector and the<br />
community in the Australian Capital Region. It could potentially remove more than<br />
five percent of the current load on Sydney Airport and reduce vehicle traffic on<br />
Sydney's arterial road system. The environmental benefits are of a similar scale.<br />
As I announced on 4 December 1996 the Commonwealth Government has decided to<br />
proceed with a joint Commonwealth/ New South Wales/ ACT approach to the<br />
investigation of options to provide a commercially viable high speed train service.<br />
We will establish a competitive tender process and seek expressions of interest from<br />
interested parties. The Commonwealth will participate in a joint project control group<br />
with New South Wales and the ACT to oversight the tender process.<br />
For twenty years, governments have been closing outdated railways. The Coalition<br />
welcomes private sector interest in the construction of new, efficient and competitive<br />
rail systems that can make a significant contribution to competition in the transport<br />
sector and to national economic reform. </p>
<p>Canberria A irport<br />
Through Canberra's airport, the region now has direct access to many cities in<br />
Australia, with benefits for regional economic efficiency and reduced congestion at<br />
Sydney Airport.<br />
The ACT and regional local governments and industries have the challenge to generate<br />
a demand for charter and scheduled international air services that will, by their very<br />
nature, establish the viability of a Canberra International Airport. The Commonwealth<br />
will actively play its part through marketing the region's attractions to the Asia Pacific<br />
Region and New Zealand. This includes the many world class exhibitions at the<br />
National Gallery of Australia and events at the Australian War Memorial, the National<br />
Science and Technology Centre, the National Library of Australia and elsewhere.<br />
Direct overseas exports of rural produce from the Australian Capital Region will also<br />
generate additional local employment growth. The region is an extremely efficient<br />
centre of agriculture and has an extremely clean environment. Such initiatives are<br />
integral to the Supermarket to Asia Strategy which I announced recently.<br />
The demand for international travel by the growing service sector and higher education<br />
and research institutions in the region will also contribute passenger and freight loads<br />
to a Canberra International Airport and would reduce the number of movements<br />
through Sydney Airport. Indeed, if the Canberra-Sydney high speed train eventuates,<br />
Canberra Airport could occasionally take pressure off Sydney Airport.<br />
For our part, the Government undertakes that services such as customs will be<br />
available as and when required to support international services.<br />
As a tangible demonstration of our commitment, the Minister for Transport and<br />
Regional Development recently announced that the Federal Airports Corporation will<br />
undertake a feasibility study on the upgrade of the airport to handle international<br />
flights. This study is now underway.<br />
The Feder-al anid Barltn Highways<br />
Improvements to the Australian Capital Region's road infrastructure will enhance the<br />
growth of local industry and improve road safety. Increased accessibility within the<br />
region will build on the benefits of improved rail and airport facilities. It will<br />
encourage the establishment of important economic activity such as wholesale markets<br />
for the region's produce and major freight distribution complexes, adding to those<br />
already at Goulburn.<br />
The Commonwealth is already investing heavily in the completion of the dual<br />
carriageway for the Federal Highway. The project is targetted for completion in<br />
1998/ 9. </p>
<p>The Government recognises that an upgrading of the Barton Highway to a dual<br />
carriageway will greatly increase access to the major producer areas that form part of a<br />
wide sweep to the north of Yass. Planning studies for some sections are already<br />
underway as part of that upgrade.<br />
Liaisonuwifh the Comm uni'<br />
The Coalition has a policy of actively liaising with local communities. In a positive<br />
demonstration of this commitment, I have established a forum in which the<br />
Commonwealth Government is liaising regularly with the Canberra business<br />
community and the ACT Government. The Forum is chaired by the Minister for<br />
Territories, the Hon Warwick Smith and the Forum has met twice. The Forum has<br />
been briefed by representatives from the offices of the Minister for Transport, the<br />
Minister for Communication and the Arts and the Minister for Administrative Services.<br />
The prime objective of this very high level group is the promotion of private sector job<br />
growth in the region.<br />
At the local level, bodies such as the Australian Capital Region Development Council,<br />
the Canberra Business Council and the Regional Leaders Forum are also actively<br />
promoting regional growth.<br />
Pu/ p anid Payer Mi/ I<br />
One major opportunity for the region is the development of a pulp and paper mill,<br />
drawing on the considerable and underutilised softwood pulp resources of Bombala,<br />
Tumut and the ACT. The Government stands ready to give its approval when the<br />
project meets the necessary requirements. An upgrade of the Tumut to Canberra road<br />
link would not only enhance the economics of this project but would improve regional<br />
access to the west and increase tourism potential. The new category of road funding<br />
introduced in the last budget " Roads of National Importance" enables the Federal<br />
Government to fund such projects.<br />
Bornyba/ a Bidges<br />
The Forum is also being briefed on the benefits of upgrading the bridges near Bombala.<br />
This would allow B_-Double heavy transport vehicles to operate between Gippsland<br />
and the Australian Capital Region and beyond. A further important initiative is the<br />
three stage feasibility study into a multi-purpose export wharf in the Eden area. Such a<br />
facility would considerably enhance the opportunity to process and export the region's<br />
softwood timber and other resources. </p>
<p>Other Regional Opportunities<br />
In another regional initiative near Goulburn, the Bredalbane Industry Park feasibility<br />
study is examining the potential for increasing the value of regional primary production<br />
by co-locating industries with specific environmental management needs on the one<br />
site. Canberra, as the region's commercial and administrative centre, is the natural location<br />
for a number of government regional offices. However, there has been a trend in<br />
recent years for some of these offices to be closed down or scaled back and relocated<br />
to other centres outside of the region. I have asked my Ministers to ensure that any<br />
such future rationalisation of central or regional offices is properly assessed in the light<br />
of administrative efficiency and the Government's regional policies. Discussions will be<br />
held with relevant groups as each proposal is considered.<br />
I would also like to extend an invitation to the Canberra Business Council to coordinate<br />
a submission, on behalf of the Australian Capital Region business community,<br />
to the Government on its budgetary policies and priorities as part of the annual Budget<br />
process. The region has already developed a recognised reputation for its research and higher<br />
learning. It is home to four significant Universities, many Divisions of the CSIRO, and<br />
the Canberra Institute of Technology. A number of private companies are also heavily<br />
involved in research and development. The region stands to benefit further from the<br />
Government's increased investment in higher education research infrastructure, joint<br />
industry-university research and increased post-graduate scholarships, as well as from<br />
the major increase in base funding for the CSIRO.<br />
Canberra is also a centre for sporting excellence through the Australian Institute of<br />
Sport which attracts top overseas athletes and provides world-class competition and<br />
facilities for local athletes.<br />
Conclusion The Australian Capital Region is a region in transition. The region's business<br />
community is well placed to take on many of the roles previously performed by<br />
government. The Liberal-National Government is committed to enhancing the promotion of<br />
Canberra as the nation's capital. The Government will also encourage the many<br />
exciting opportunities that will markedly upgrade the region's transport and<br />
communication infrastructure and development projects. The region can expand its<br />
growing transport hub in Canberra to provide a first class link between the region and<br />
the rest of Australia and Asia Pacific. It will also have a significant benefit on Sydney<br />
infrastructure. The Government is committed to rebuilding Australia, to pursuing economic reform<br />
and to assisting families. The Australian Capital Region is an important part of the<br />
Government's vision for a prosperous nation. I believe that our policies will see<br />
Canberra and the region emerge as a more vibrant and diverse reflection of Australia<br />
while remaining a focus of national pride and achievement. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
