<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17778</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of Joint Press Conference, Brisbane</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/04/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PM: </strong>It's a great pleasure to be here today. I'm joined by the Premier of Queensland, Anna Bligh, by our local member Graham Perrett, and I thank him for being here. We've got Mick Slater here, Milton Dick from the local council and we're joined by a representative of the mental health community for what is a very important announcement.</p>
<p>I've been here in Queensland over the last few days, talking to people about their journey of recovery as Queensland recovers and rebuild from the floods and from the cyclone. We've in fact been here talking today about the recovery of this lawn bowls club and I've had the opportunity to meet with a range of people, in Toowoomba, in Dalby, here in Oxley, around Goodna, a number of places, talking about the recovery journey. It's still tough for people out there, I certainly understand that but Queensland is being rebuilt.</p>
<p>Already we've got a vibrant game happening behind us, so that's that noise. As people would know, I committed $5.6 billion on the 27th January to recovering from the natural disasters that our country faced.</p>
<p>Already here in Queensland we have provided funding for 44 disaster affected councils, working of course with Premier Bligh's government. We've got reconstruction work well underway with almost 6,000km of roads being reconstructed, almost 4,000km of rail, 55 bridges and culverts repaired to date and ten of the eleven damaged sea ports in Queensland have now been reopened.</p>
<p>And we are, through a tourism push, getting the message through, that there's never been a better time to come and visit here in Queensland - Queensland is open for business and anxious to see people from around Australian and around the world coming and saying hello.</p>
<p>We are of course also investing to bring skilled workers in to assist with the recovery and we've made almost a billion dollars of payments directly to the people of Queensland to assist them with their personal recovery. So far we've helped over 928,000 Queenslanders, that's one in five of the total population.</p>
<p>Today we are here to announce a new package of assistance which helps people recover some of those things of the spirit. There is a lot of fighting will in Queensland but when you look in people's eyes you also see a lot of hurt. And it's community members and community groups that are helping keep people together as they recover from the disasters of the last summer.</p>
<p>So today, with the Premier, I'm here to announce a $39 million package of further support. $20 million of that will be directed to helping communities recover. We want communities to have the resources they need to pull people together. That money will go to assist the employment of community development officers, and also assist not-for-profit organisations that do so much to hold communities together as they rebuild.</p>
<p>Some of that money will also help people develop the kind of memorials they want to have in their community to mark what their community has gone through, what they've lost and what they've rebuilt together. $10 million will be made available to support mental health for disaster affected communities.</p>
<p>We all know that these kinds of natural disasters and the journey of recovery place a lot of pressure on people. Today I met a man who sat in his car for a large number of days after his home was flooded. He could be enticed out of his car periodically, but then went back to sit in his car again because he was so shocked and devastated by what had happened to his home.</p>
<p>I met a woman yesterday who told me that she runs to the local pub when she hears droplets of rain because she wants to be with other people if it's raining. This is the kind of pressure that people are continuing to carry with them. We want them to be able to get help and assistance and that $10 million will go to organisations that can provide a helping hand to people in need.</p>
<p>$5.8 million of the package will go to assist people with financial planning, as people are making the decisions that they need to to rebuild their lives, they need good advice and we want to help people get that good advice. The package will be targeted to those areas of Queensland where there is the most need and I hope, as Prime Minister, that it will make a real difference to those affected communities. I turn now to Premier Bligh for some comments.</p>
<p><strong>PREMIER BLIGH: </strong>Well thank you very much Prime Minister and I welcome the support from the Federal Government as we take the next step in our journey of recovery here in Queensland.</p>
<p>This is $39 million worth of care for our community. This is a direct, hands-on, one on one support for people when they really need it. We know from international research and the experience after the Victorian bushfires, that research tells us that people often really start to hit to emotional wall around three months after a disaster of this size. The three month period after a disaster is when many people start to feel the full impact of the reality and their emotional and psychological wellbeing can be put at risk.</p>
<p>What this package of support will do is allow us to employ more councillors, more people to help, more people to be sitting down and being a listening ear, one on one. We've also got a $2 million component of the package that will provide extra respite for families who are caring for someone with a disability at the same time as they're trying to recover their homes and get themselves back on track.</p>
<p>For people who need just a little bit of extra support managing their responsibilities as a carer, while they also have to go and do all the other things, like get a builder, go to the insurance company, get an appointment with the bank -</p>
<p>[BREAK]</p>
<p>As we're rebuilding Queensland we are going to keep always in our minds that it's about people first. Bricks and mortar and railroads and roads and school buildings are all important, but making sure we look after people will be an essential part of ensuring that we get back on our feet in a genuine way. I'd like to invite Jeff Cheverton, who's known to a number of you. Jeff is the CEO of the Queensland Alliance for medical health to talk about some of these issues.</p>
<p><strong>JEFF CHEVERTON</strong>: Thank you Premier. Good afternoon everyone. Thank you very much Premier. The Queensland Alliance for Mental Health is peak body for mental health in Queensland.</p>
<p>We represent more than 200 community organisations around the state that work in mental health. We advocate for services that support people's recovery in their own homes and communities. We advance the human rights for people with mental illness, and we promote mental health and wellbeing in the community.</p>
<p>We would like to welcome this announcement by the Premier and Prime Minister this afternoon. This is a very welcome investment is sustaining the resilience of Queensland communities. We heard when the floods first started, and then of course we've also had the cyclones up north, we heard about the amazing offerings and volunteers that came out of the woodwork to provide support to their neighbours, their friends and even to people they didn't know. We heard about community groups and community services that went above and beyond their ordinary work duties to meet the needs of people.</p>
<p>This is the great Queensland spirit that we saw at that time and that spirit has continued over the last few months but it is starting to flag and that's why this announcement is such a welcome boost and such a, such a good, a well-timed investment in sustaining that community effort.</p>
<p>It's not a heavy-handed bureaucratic approach. What we're actually seeing in the detail of this announcement is investment in those volunteers and in those community services that have been doing the hard work for the last several months. This is enabling them to keep going and this will enable them to in fact improve their services. We know that in a lot of the communities that have been affected, we're talking about people who take great pride in their independence and their resilience and their ability to meet the challenges that face them.</p>
<p>These are not people who want outsiders to come into their communities to offer them support, they want to support each other. And again, this announcement is investing in self-help, it's investing in providing those people at a local level, who have taken a leadership role, to be informed and to be equipped to promote people with mental health and wellbeing.</p>
<p>So we will see local people helping other local people. We will see Queenslanders doing it for themselves with the support of this investment, and we're very happy to welcome it today.</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> We're happy to take questions and we'll stand back and hope we don't rattle that at all.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Who's paying for this?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Overwhelmingly the package is being funded under the normal formula for our natural disaster relief and recovery arrangements, which is a 75 per cent contribution from the Commonwealth and 25 per cent from the state. But there are some elements of this that are directly state government funded and I will have Premier Bligh identify them.</p>
<p><strong>PREMIER BLIGH:</strong> The $2 million component for extra disability respite services is a fully state funded component, and $1.2 million of the mental health package is state funds have already started to roll out. So overwhelmingly it's a partnership between the state and federal government under the federal and state guidelines but there are a couple of extra components to it.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> And this is all on top of already announced assistance, is that right?</p>
<p><strong>PREMIER BLIGH: </strong>Yes. This is all new investment and new funds to community services and agencies, particularly as we come up to Easter. The three month mark after a disaster is recognised as a very vulnerable time and this year that's going to start that period around Easter, a time when people would otherwise normally be out celebrating with friends and family and so we know that we're moving now to a time when people are more vulnerable and that's why we've put these extra resources in.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Prime Minister, your assistant treasurer released the standard definition for floods yesterday, or a draft discussion paper for it. Do you think that one of the unintended consequences of that is actually insurance premiums will rise?</p>
<p><strong>PM</strong>: I think it's very important that people are able to look at their insurance document, their insurance policy and understand what it means, that people, you know, aren't confronted with tens of thousands of words but they can understand what they're being insured for and what they should, can expect to receive if a natural disaster does strike and hit their home or hit their business.</p>
<p>So I do very much support Bill Shorten, the Assistant Treasurer's reform directions, looking for a standard definition of what it is to endure a flood and also having a key statements, key facts document, which will enable people to understand what their policy covers. Now I just think this is practical (inaudible) for people, so that in the future people, when they get to their insurance policies, will know what is being covered.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Is it too late for the victims of these floods?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Well unfortunately we can't go back in time and rewrite people's insurance policies and I understand that there are many Queenslanders who are feeling ripped off by insurance companies - I've met some today and yesterday.</p>
<p>And to those Queenslanders, what I've been saying is I think it's important that the insurance companies come and talk to people face to face, which is why I'm so disappointed (inaudible) Bill Shorten, the Assistant Treasurer, yesterday, to go with him and to meet the people of Ipswich, hear what they've got to say, hear what they've got to say that's gone well for them with their insurance, but also hear the many stories where people are feeling ripped off and deal with it direct. So we'll be keeping the pressure on insurance companies to do just that.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> So you would be angry about them increasing premiums after the floods and the cyclones?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> I think the insurance industry works on a calculation of risk and that's how premiums are struck but the equation has to work for both sides. The insurance companies know what they're liable for when they're issuing these very (inaudible) policy documents. Unfortunately, too many Australians don't know what they're paying for because they really don't understand the detail of what's in and what's out of their insurance policy. This is a simple consumer protection idea that people would be able to get a key facts statement that explains to them, ‘what are you insured for' so you can make the best possible decision you can about which insurance policy to select.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> After speaking to the victims, do you wish you had the power to say to the insurance companies ‘pay up' (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Look, we don't live in a world where a government can come in a retrospectively rewrite contracts...</p>
<p><strong>PERRETT:</strong> Wish you could.</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> I can understand the frustrations of local members like Graham Perrett and I understand the frustrations of the Queensland community. I understand people are really feeling like they're being ripped off by insurance companies. I get that. We don't live in an economy though where government can come in and retrospectively rewrite contracts that people have entered into but we can have a name and shame policy of the people doing well and people doing badly, and we will in respect of insurance companies. We can put the pressure on insurance companies to look people in the eye and hear their complaints and we can (inaudible) for the future so people can get (inaudible) information they need (inaudible). Should I actually go and get a different policy, go to a different company. People deserve to have that information.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Prime Minister, do you feel, as leader of the government, ripped off by insurance companies because you've had to make up the shortfall of what otherwise might have assisted a lot of people, particularly in this area and in Ipswich.</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Tony, the sense of rip off that I'm referring to is the individual Queenslanders that I've met and that Premier Anna Bligh would meet every day and Graham Perrett as he goes about his work in this local community, and I'm sure Mick Slater and others meet people every day too who have got a personal story about their insurance policy.</p>
<p>So it's that sense of being ripped off for those Queenslanders that I'm referring to. On behalf of the government, we want to do the right thing to rebuild Queensland. That's why we are working so strongly with the state government, with the Queensland Recovery agency to get resources out there to rebuild. We've, you know, provided almost a million Queenslanders with direct cash support, we are working with the state government to rebuild roads and rail to get things moving again.</p>
<p>But I understand for individuals there's still a big difficult journey ahead for many, which is why I think the Premier is absolutely right in saying it's at this time after a natural disaster, when maybe the adrenaline has gone out of the individuals involved and the reality of how big a journey they've got in front of them is settling on them, that we want to be there to help with some things of the spirit and that's what this package is about.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> You say you're willing to name and shame the insurance companies. It's three months now (inaudible) isn't it time to start actually naming them?</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>Well look we will, as we deal with individual matters, using insurance company names and I think you would find...</p>
<p><strong>PERRETT:</strong> I did two weeks ago I think.</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Local members like Graham have been doing it very consistently.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST: </strong>Insurance companies say they can't turn up to a public forum and start addressing individual concerns because of privacy restrictions?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Well look I can't, I can't agree with that one. I mean I am not expecting that people at a public meeting like the one that was conducted in Ipswich yesterday would be there, giving their full name, address and policy number. What they would be there doing is saying look, you know, this is my experience and if people want to volunteer their experience in front of their fellow Australians, then I think they should be able to make that decision and to get an answer. Now it may be that there are some things that would then need to break up into face to face discussions. But we are not without experience on this. I mean we all have Community Cabinet.</p>
<p>I had a Community Cabinet in Perth very recently. People do come to Community Cabinet's and say ‘this is my problem with the social security payment I'm getting'. They're happy to say it in front of their fellow Australians. If they're happy to say it, I'm happy to answer it in front of their fellow Australians, and then if you need really in detail follow-up, or you need to know things about peoples income levels and bank accounts, then you can break into a one to one meeting. We do that all the time. I don't think we're asking insurance companies to do anything more than the sorts of things the Premier and I and our local members, local councillors, local state members would do every day of the week.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Well we might just finish with any of the flood questions because we might then have some of the others step out of shot. Are there any more questions on floods, flood recovery, today's package? No? Okay. Thank you. So yes?</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> The latest sex scandal (inaudible) is there a culture (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> I don't want to comment on a matter that is going to be subject of investigation by the Australian Defence Force and by the Australian Federal Police. But I am prepared to say, as Prime Minister, very, very clearly, I've got a lot of respect for Australians who decide to dedicate their lives to the Australian Defence Force and there should be no one who makes that decision and then has their trust (inaudible) and their dignity subject to assault. That is absolutely not what want happening in our defence forces. I meet terrific young men and women dedicating their lives to the protection of this country and I want them respected in every sense of that word.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Are you worried there is a culture?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> I certainly think that the Australian Defence Force leadership (inaudible) that in a modern defence force they want to see everybody treated with a culture of respect and they've got no tolerance for misconduct in the way that I've got no tolerance for misconduct. We've seen some incidents in the past that were unacceptable. I don't want to say anything directly about the matter in the media now because it will be the subject of investigation but I do want to make my attitude very clear.</p>
<p>You join the defence force whether you're a young woman or a young man because you want to dedicate yourself to protecting this country and we are (inaudible) of our defence force to do remarkable things for this nation. They join because they've got that (inaudible) and they shouldn't have their trust abused or their dignity stripped away from them.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST</strong>: (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM</strong>: Look I can say at a leadership level of the defence force there is a (inaudible) that they want women (inaudible) enjoying work environment that values their contribution in the same way that the contribution of men in valued.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Do you think the Singapore takeover of the (inaudible) against the national interest?</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>I suspect I'm going to disappoint you but I'm not going to be drawn on this matter. As has been (inaudible) reported, this matter is in a process that the deputy Prime Minister and Treasurer is responsible for and under the legislation we work under with foreign investment, it is he who's got the discretion in this area and I'm not, as Prime Minister, going to comment on it while the matter is still being worked through to finality by the Deputy Prime Minister.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>I think the Deputy Prime Minister does a remarkable job in all aspects of his responsibilities</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Do you think it's inevitable that het Australian Stock Exchange is going to have to merge with another body because there's been like 13 consolidations across the world (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Nice try. But I'm afraid while this matter is still being dealt with by the Deputy Prime Minister, under the relevant legislation; I'm not going to be drawn on commentary on it.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST: </strong>The Premier of NSW is saying he wants to build a new rail between Sydney's North West rail link and (inaudible) federal funding?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Well the new Premier of New South Wales, I see a wry smile on Premier Anna Bligh's face. I will at the appropriate time be meeting with Barry O'Farrell. I am more than happy to discuss with him his policies and plans for New South Wales. But when we work with state governments, as Premier Bligh Would now, we work through our infrastructure Australian process.</p>
<p>We work with hard costings and volumes of detail. So I will talk to Mr O'Farrell and look forward to that, but we don't deal with these questions in running commentary in the media. We're talking about, any big infrastructure in this country is billions of dollars of taxpayers' funds and we're very careful with it, as Premier Bligh would attest, having been through some of these processes.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST: </strong>Prime Minister, this morning Kevin Rudd, asked about his comments on Q&amp;A that of course (inaudible) said that they were appropriate and that he would, when he felt necessary, continue to correct the record from the period that he was in government. Does that concern you at all about discipline in your government and the sort of things that should be said about what might or might not have occurred during cabinet meetings?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Look I've said earlier today that inevitably Kevin Rudd will get questions about his time-period as Prime Minister. He got asked such questions on Q and A on Monday night and that's been remarked upon in the media. What's been less remarked upon, I'd have to say, is his very clear statement on Q and A on Monday night, that his shoulder is to the wheel delivering this government's policy agenda.</p>
<p>Here we are, a big part of what the government's doing, working with the state government, with the Premier and rebuilding Queensland and of course, every day we pursue the policies necessary to make sure that this country is a land of opportunity for the future that every child, every Australian gets an opportunity for the great chance in life and tackling the challenges of the future, like climate change and like the National Broadband Network</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> (inaudible) solidarity though?</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>Sorry?</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Hasn't he broken the rules of cabinet solidarity, though?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> I've said, I've said earlier today and I'm happy to say again, it's inevitable that Kevin Rudd will get questions from time to time about his period as Prime Minister and he's dealt with that.</p>
<p>Under my government we have a clear cabinet process and we have a clear policy of cabinet solidarity. But Kevin will be asked questions about the past and from time to time he'll answer those questions.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> On the subject of the NBN do you think it's slipping on its timeframe with the latest resignation and the tender process (inaudible)?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Well of course it has been reported today that a senior figure in the National Broadband Network has resigned and as he's gone to look for other opportunities, he said this is a courageous and visionary project.</p>
<p>It is both of those things. It is a project that will give us the technology we need for this nation to be a prosperous nation in the future, rather than export jobs to countries with better technology and particularly, in a highly regionalised and big state like Queensland, it will make a difference to service delivery in health and education. So we'll continue to rollout the National Broadband Network.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST: </strong>Time Magazine, (inaudible) poll on influential people has rated Ms Bligh above Justin Bieber.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> And Oprah.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> (inaudible)</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>Okay, I've got to get this absolutely right. Above Justin?</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> But not quite Oprah.</p>
<p><strong>PM: </strong>Well I think I haven't heard Premier Bligh sing but however good her singing voice is, I am happy to day that's an appropriate ranking above Justin. To be ranked above Oprah I suspect we'd have to find a way of making Premier Bligh truly global and she and I might go and have a little chat about that.</p>
<p><strong>JOURNALIST:</strong> Ms Bligh?</p>
<p><strong>PREMIER BLIGH: </strong>Well 2011 started as a very strange year, sorry, I'm determined to break of everything on there. 2011 started as a very strange and in my experience every week it just gets a bit stranger.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
