<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10191</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH ELIZABETH JACKSON - 2CN</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/12/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010191.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME INISTE<br />I1I December 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />THE HON. JOHN HOWARD, MP<br />INTERVIEW WITH ELIZABETH JACKSON 2CN<br />E&amp; OE<br />JACKSON: John Howard was elected Prime Minister last March. We haven't had much of a<br />chance to catch up with him since then. But this morning we're happy to remedy that.<br />Prime Minister, welcome.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well it's very nice to be here Elizabeth.<br />JACKSON: Nine months down the track are you still relaxed and comfortable?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Yes I am. I feel as we come to the end of the parliamentary year that we can look<br />back on the last nine months and feel that as a Government we have made a good start.<br />I don't say that in any sense of complacency. We've worked very hard to keep in<br />touch with people. We've always taken the view that being the Government of<br />Australia is an immense privilege and that when governments lose a sense of humility<br />and acquire a sense of pride or hubris then that's when they start to go wrong. I've<br />endeavoured myself and I've tried to encourage all of my colleagues to remember that<br />we are there as the gift of the Australian people, as a gift from the Australian people,<br />and we certainly don't take that support for granted. We have to work hard to both<br />earn and retain the respect of the Australian people. And I feel after nine months, and<br />it's nine months to the day that we were sworn in on the I11th of March 1996, I do<br />think the building blocks have been put down. We have brought about some changes.<br />I know some of our decisions have been unpopular. I freely acknowledge that because<br />of some of the changes in the size of government they've had a differential impact on<br />the Canberra community, I regret that I'm sorry about that. I have to point out that<br />it's not as a result of us singling out public servants or the Canberra community. It just</p>
<p>happens that there is a proportionately larger number of Australians employed in the<br />public service in the Canberra community, some 48 per cent, than in any other part of<br />Australia. But I can assure you that there's been no hidden agenda. We're not an anti-<br />Canberra Government, we're a pro-Australian Government and Canberra is the proud<br />national capital of Australia and it will always be that way.<br />JACKSON: I do want to talk to you about those perceptions of you being an anti-Canberra<br />Government because I'm sure you've heard those suggested...<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Oh they have and there's no point in my pretending that there aren't some of those<br />perceptions around and I want to acknowledge that in a forthright manner that there<br />are those perceptions around. I want to say that they are wrong and I want to try in<br />this interview and in other ways to reassure the people of Canberra that we care as<br />much for their future as we do for all Australians and that the decisions that we have<br />taken in no way exhibit a bias against public servants as such. I'm very proud of the<br />fact that we won the support of a lot of public servants in the last election. They are as<br />entitled to justice and fair treatment from my Government as any other section of the<br />Australian community.<br />JACKSON: I think the question that they're asking today is how much worse is it going to get?<br />Many of them have been, well, many of them have taken redundancy packages, a lot of<br />them are working in very insecure environments at the moment. They want to know is<br />it going to get worse?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />I suppose I should start to answer that question by saying that working in an insecure<br />envirornent is no new thing for many other Australians. One of the differences<br />between the recession of the early 1 980s and the recession of the late 1 980s was that<br />the first recession largely left people in the public sector untouched. And the<br />downsizing in government began at a State level years ago and in a sense what had<br />happened in Canberra in recent months is no different from what has happened in other<br />parts of Australia so far as the public sector is concerned over a number of years. I<br />also have to say in defence of my Government that a lot of downsizing of the Federal<br />Public Service commenced under the former Labor Government. I mean, the figures,<br />there were thousands and thousands of redundancies under the former Labor<br />Government. Now I'm not seeking to say whether that was good or bad. I'm trying<br />to put it into perspective and once again this idea that Canberra is being singled out for<br />some kind of discriminatory treatment is just not correct.<br />JACKSON: But what about the future, Prime Minister, what's going to happen?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well, we made certain announcements in the last Budget. We achieved savings of<br />some $ 7.2 billion over a period of two years. Now we are very keen to implement and<br />achieve those savings. We do want to put the Budget into underlying balance in year<br />three if we can. I mean, this things inevitably get affected by economic activity and<br />revenue flows and some of which are very hard to predict. But whilst I can't bind the<br />hands of the government in future budgets I can say that we saw the target of those<br />cuts in the first Budget, brought down in August, we saw that as the kind of target we<br />wanted to achieve. In other words, I don't have in mind another five or six billion<br />dollars of cuts on top or even another two or three billion dollars of cuts on top of the<br />7.2. So that is about the best way in which I can answer...<br />JACKSON: The worst is behind us in other words?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well I believe that if we can consolidate what we announced in that Budget, if we can<br />achieve what is needed to be done to realise those savings of $ 7.2 billion over a period<br />of two years then we will have achieved our medium term fiscal consolidation goal. I<br />choose my words carefully because I don't want, later on, somebody to say well you<br />promised this and you haven't delivered that. I don't want to be in that situation. If<br />we can achieve those savings then I think it is possible for me to say to the Australian<br />public ' we have made a very solid fist of fixing up the Budget problem because we<br />have achieved the savings that will put the Budget on target for an underlying balance<br />in year three of our first term in office'.<br />JACKSON:<br />Prime Minister, there's a perception in this city that when we hurt here the rest of<br />Australia doesn't care very much. In fact, there's a perception that they actually clap<br />their hands and smile and think it's a good thing. There's also a perception that you<br />don't care much either for a range of reasons. I think you've already acknowledged<br />that perception does that concern you?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well it does because it's wrong. I mean, I don't clap my hands about anybody having<br />a redundancy. I don't clap my hands about any decision that governments take that<br />have adverse effects on individuals. I don't like it at all, I don't enjoy it for one<br />second. Anybody who thinks that I get some kind of pleasure, or my Government gets<br />some kind of pleasure out of reducing the size of the public service for the sake of<br />reducing the size of the public service is wrong. And any other Australian who does<br />get that kind of pleasure won't get any comfort out of me. I do believe in the private<br />sector very strongly. I am a great exponent and proponent of the cause of small<br />business and that's very important to Canberra's future and I'd like to say something</p>
<p>about that later on. But my passion for the private sector Is not borne out of hostility<br />to the public sector. It is a belief that it is through private sector investment,<br />particularly in small business, that you have the greatest possibility throughout the<br />whole country of generating jobs. But there is nothing punitive, malicious or<br />prejudiced in the attitude of my Government in the decisions that it takes towards the<br />public sector. We value the contribution of a professional public service. I reiterated<br />that when I opened the new Foreign Affairs and Trade building a couple of weeks ago<br />I do so again. It's an integral part of the fabric of our community and the<br />professionalism of public servants in Canberra is something which we should be rightly<br />proud. JACKSON: Okay, I'm just aware that there are a couple of issues I do want to move through.<br />There's even been a suggestion that you've advised the local Liberal branch not to run<br />a candidate in the by election for the seat of Fraser because you're worried you're<br />going to take a bath in Canberra.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well the question of what happens with that is something that will be decided by the<br />Party organisation. I've obviously had discussions with them about it and political<br />organisations take decisions on whether they run candidates or don't run candidates in<br />by elections in relatively safe seats held by their political opponents for a whole variety<br />of reasons and...<br />JACKSON: Would you like to see them run a candidate?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well that's a matter for them to decide and I believe very strongly in the relationship<br />between the organisation and the Parliamentary Party where the organisation decides<br />where the candidates are run. Obviously the organisation talks to the relevant<br />parliamentary leader and that's me because it's a federal by election and then takes a<br />decision but I would point out to you that if the organisation were to decide not to run<br />a candidate, it wouldn't be the first time that a party has done so in a by election. I<br />mean, the Labor Party didn't run any candidate when Mrs Bishop came from the<br />Senate into the seat of Warringah or when Michael Mackellar retired and Tony Abbott,<br />I'm sorry, Mrs Bishop went into Mackellar and Tony Abbott into Wamrngah. The<br />Liberal Party didn't run a candidate in Blaxland earlier this year when Paul Keating<br />retired so there's a bit of a pattern to that and I don't think you should draw any<br />particular inferences but that is a matter for the organisation to decide. Obviously my<br />view has been sought and I've expressed it.<br />JACKSON: What was your view?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well that's a matter for the organisation, my view it was privately expressed to people<br />in the organisation and it's a matter for the organisation to take the decision and I'm<br />not going to publicly canvass something that rightly ought to remain between myself<br />and the Party organisation. The Party organisation has an important role. I respect<br />that role. I've always accepted the understanding that the Parliamentary Party is<br />supreme in policy matters but in organisational matters, whilst they should listen to the<br />views of the Parliamentary Party, it's their prerogative to take the final decision.<br />JACKSON: The Prime Minister, John Howard, is my guest this morning. We're talking at the<br />moment about issues affecting Canberra specifically. In a moment we will move on<br />and talk about some other matters. Prime Minister, everyone that I have spoken to<br />including our Chief Minister, Kate Carnell, believes that your decision not to live<br />permanently in the Lodge sends out all the wrong messages, messages that you don't<br />care about Canberra. I know we've already addressed this question. Will you<br />reconsider your decision not to live permanently in the ACT?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />No I won't. I'm aware that it is an unpopular decision in Canberra. I must say to you<br />that it has not been criticised in other parts of the country and I obviously am the Prime<br />Minister of the whole of Australia. I'm not just Prime Minister of Sydney or Prime<br />Minister of Canberra or Prime Minister of Melbourne. I'm Prime Minister of the<br />whole of Australia.<br />JACKSON: Even Malcolm Fraser went fishing here.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well can I tell you that the perception that I don't spend any time here is completely<br />wrong and that comment about Malcolm sort of implies that I don't even do that. I<br />haven't got the final figures because they change every day obviously but my<br />perception is apart from the time that I've spent travelling to other parts of Australia or<br />overseas since I became Prime Minister, I've spent about 60% of my nights in Sydney<br />and about 40% in Canberra. Now that can hardly be categorised as the behaviour of<br />somebody who doesn't even go fishing in the ACT. The reality is that my family is<br />based in Sydney. When Parliament is sitting of course I am always here. I am always<br />here for extensive periods when Parliament is not sitting. We spend as I say roughly<br />about 40%, the only measure is where you spend your night, in Canberra. Now the<br />suggestion from that that I am unfamiliar with the Canberra community, the suggestion<br />from that that I am in some way retaining nothing more than a nominal association<br />with Canberra is wrong. Now I know it is not popular here. I accept that. The best I</p>
<p>can do is to explain the facts which I have just done which rather refuites the idea that I<br />just sort of blow in occasionally. I mean, that is ridiculous. I plainly don't.<br />JACKSON: And you've spoken about your children's education too and the importance of<br />maintaining the family home in Sydney but what about, I mean, they're not at primary<br />school any more. The children are getting older. Once they've completed their<br />education, would you then consider moving to the ACT permanently?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well I am not going to, I am not going to commit myself to what might happen in<br />years three, four, five or six. Our own circumstances may change, our own views may<br />change. I took a decision and I believe it's not only, it's not only a decision based on<br />famidly consideration because I acknowledge that a lot of people don't have that luxury<br />and I know a lot of people in Canberra their families are separated because if they are<br />in the diplomatic service, they may have to go overseas but equally, if they have the<br />opportunity for their family to stay together. well they would take that opportunity and<br />I don't think anybody would suggest otherwise but I also took it for reasons of<br />wanting to maintain as well as my contact with the Canberra community, which I<br />believe I do retain because I spend a lot of my time in Canberra as the figures I've just<br />spelt out demonstrate but it's also by spending some time in Sydney as well I am able<br />to maintain very direct contact with the business community in that city. It's not the be<br />all and end all of the business community in Australia but it's a fairly sizeable chunk of<br />it and I think there is value in spreading oneself around.<br />I think there is value in recognising that whilst Canberra is the national capital and<br />Canberra is the political, admidnistrative and legal capital of Australia, it is not the<br />commercial heart of this country and that we do need people in Government who have<br />a broad understanding of the whole country and there is a danger, no matter how well<br />intentioned you are, if you spend all of your time in Canberra mixing with the same<br />group of people, reinforcing one particular view of life, it is possible, however well<br />intentioned you may be and the people with whom you converse may be, it is possible<br />to end up being a little out of touch with views in other parts of Australia. So I put a<br />very positive light on the decision that I have taken. I think you have the advantages<br />of a Prime inister who understands and is in touch with the Canberra community but<br />also understands and is in touch with a very big community in the largest city in<br />Australia and I think that is an advantage and I think it gives me an insight and an<br />understanding that with respect, I think my predecessor lost and perhaps some of his<br />predecessors may have lost.<br />JACKSON: Prime Minister, let's talk about the Kevin Andrews' Bill. How do you answer<br />concerns of Canberrans that we have effectively now got a lame duck Assembly.<br />They're our democratically elected representatives but if they legislate something that<br />you don't like, you overrule it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well can I make two comments about that. The first is that the euthanasia issue was a<br />non-party issue so it wasn't Government policy to support the Andrews' Bill. I voted<br />for it because as John Howard, Federal Member for Bennelong, I generally supported<br />the principles of the Bill. You raised the question of States' rights or territory rights.<br />The ACT is not a State. The Northern Territory is not a State. The law of Australia<br />allows the Federal Parliament to pass a law overriding a territorial law. Now until the<br />ACT, or if and until, and I have to say that, if and until the ACT becomes a State and<br />there is certainly no proposal for that on the horizon, that while ever the ACT remains<br />a territory, then the argument that in some way it's rights are being denied because of<br />the existence of this under the law of Australia is just not correct. I mean, I deal in,<br />and you have to deal in the legal reality. The law of Australia expressly allows the<br />national Parliament to pass the euthanasia law, or the anti-euthanasia law so far as it<br />affects a territory and if the ACT were a State it would be a different situation and<br />there's a good historical legal reason for that because the Commonwealth of Australia,<br />the national Parliament came out of the federation of the States and the understanding<br />at Federation was that there would be States and there would be a Commonwealth<br />Government and they would have certain powers. Now the powers given to the States<br />at Federation were not given to the territories so there's nothing wrong or illicit or<br />unfair or illegal about it. I mean it's just what the law allows and it was always<br />intended by the Australian people that that should be the case.<br />JACKSON: It certainly is the law, no one would dispute that, but I think it would also be fair to say<br />that a lot of Canberrans feel that it is unfair. I mean, we elected these people, we<br />elected them to make...<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />I have had very I have to say I have had very few complaints from people living in<br />Canberra on this issue. I mean, I've had complaints about other things but not on this<br />issue, and after all, something which goes so directly to the kind of society we are,<br />whatever your views are and I voted in favour of the Andrews' bill but I do<br />understand the conscientiously held views of a lot of people who voted against it and I<br />don't try and ram my own view down other people's throats.<br />I've quietly reached a conclusion myself that there are some absolutes in life that ought<br />to be maintained and respect for human life and every effort to maintain it is one of<br />those absolutes, but it is not a view that I seek to ram down anybody's throat from<br />some kind of moral high ground. But after all, that kind of issue does go very directly<br />to the kind of society we are and inevitably if it happens in one part of Australia it will<br />have an influence on what happens in another part, and surely if the national Parliament<br />is worthy of its name it ought to be able to express a view on and pass a law about<br />such an issue.<br />I mean, I just have to say as an Australian, the idea that being a member of the<br />Australian Parliament I am denied the capacity to cast a vote for or against something</p>
<p>as fundamental as this simply because, according to some theory of the division of<br />powers it is something that belongs to the territories and not to the national<br />Parliament, can I say I find that quite unacceptable as an Australian. I mean, I am an<br />Australian before I am anything else, and most Australians feel that way. I'm an<br />Australian before I am I don't feel a New South Welshman I am an Australian first<br />and foremost and that is how a lot of people have reacted to this when I've had<br />discussions with them.<br />They feel very strongly that this is an important issue. People hold strong views on<br />both sides of the argument and what a joke it would be for the national Parliament to<br />be told you can't express a view on this because according to some view of territorial<br />rights you have no business expressing a view. Now, I know that puts me at odds<br />with some of my colleagues at a State and Territorial level but as you can see it is a<br />view I hold quite strongly.<br />JACKSON: There is some concern in Canberra though that this might be the first domino. All<br />right, we've seen Euthanasia, what about the X-rated video industry, are we going to<br />get rid of that?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well, if you are talking about dominoes in respect of things were clearly the power lies<br />with the territorial legislature, well there are no proposals to cause those dominos to<br />fall. As far as particular things are concerned, well obviously in areas where the<br />Federal Government still has a role and still has a legal ight, well the capacity to act<br />must be reserved if the Federal Government in future were to decide to do it.<br />JACKSON: Prime Minister, we could talk about Pauline Hanson. I don't know about you but I<br />suspect a lot of people like me are getting pretty sick of her giving one liners.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />I suggested some weeks ago that sections of the Australian media were becoming<br />obsessed with the issue and as days go by I'm more and more convinced that I was<br />correct. And I was quite interested to read in the Sydniey Morning Herald this<br />morning an extract from an editorial in the Far Easterni Econiomic Review. This is a<br />journal whose writings were used against me several weeks ago by some of my critics.<br />And the editorial actually concludes that my remark that Australia is not made up of a<br />mob of bigots, is absolutely correct; that Australia has a record of racial tolerance and<br />racial understanding, which is an example to the rest of the world, and while we're not<br />perfect and while we have stains on our past, which we plainly have, we are a, in<br />relative terms, a strong achiever, if I can put it that way, in the area of racial tolerance<br />and racial harmony.</p>
<p>JACKSON: I was actually going to suggest that we give Pauline Hanson the flick this morning.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Good. JACKSON: Let's not talk about her, let's move on. The Teistra legislation is expected to go<br />through the Senate this Thursday. I'd like to just try to clear up one specific point.<br />Isn't it simply the truth that under the new legislation people in the bush will pay more<br />for their phone calls than people in the city and with the partial privatisation of Telstra<br />that the Government will have less control over that differential?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Look, the situation is that people, as a result of our measures, will not be worse off<br />and I believe, this is generally speaking, than they are now. They will not pay higher<br />charges. I believe the course of the deregulatory thrust, they more likely than not will<br />have lower charges and greater access. The regime that we are implementing so far as<br />the differentials are concerned is not different than the regime that was operated by the<br />former government. I mean, the people in the bush will be better off. They'll be better<br />off because we're going to invest $ 250 midllion into telecommunications infrastructure<br />in the regions...<br />JACKSON: But Prime Minister, is it not true that they will be paying more for their phone calls<br />than people in the city?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />No, no, no, that look, they will not be paying any more than they're paying at<br />present. The question of..<br />JACKSON: But will they be paying more than people in the city?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well, people in the city will get and people in all parts of Australia stand to benefit<br />from competition. Now, you're asking me to sort of prescribe what may happen in<br />every part of Australia to telecommunications' charges. I can't do that. No sensible<br />person can. What I can say is that we will produce a regime which because of its<br />competitive thrust will deliver greater benefits than now exist. It will hold out the<br />prospect of lower charges around Australia than now exist. And because of our 9</p>
<p>investment in rural and regional telecommunications infrastructure access by country<br />people will be better than it is now and much better than it would have been if the<br />former government had continued in office, because they didn't have this commitment<br />to invest $ 250 million in rural infrastructure. I mean, they essentially voted against it.<br />They don't want us to upgrade the bush telecommunications infrastructure. And we're<br />going to put over five years $ 250 million into that. That's going to generate jobs, it's<br />going to ensure that people in regional and rural Australia have a world class<br />communications future and a communications future that is the equal of people in the<br />cities. JACKSON: Prime Minister we've only got three and a half minutes left unfortunately. I do want to<br />ask you about the future of the ABC. Bob McMullan was outside this building with a<br />petition yesterday, a petition that had been signed by 6,000 Canberrans. He says the<br />funding cuts to the ABC in his opinion will be a big issue in the Fraser by-election.<br />The ABC Board seems to be saying that we have now put our house in order with the<br />restructuring to save something in the vicinity of $ 27 million. Any further cuts they<br />say will certainly affect programming. Will, given that that's their position, will you<br />want insist on the full $ 55 million target for the ABC?<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Well, we've made our position about funding clear. haven't myself been involved in<br />any discussions with the ABC Board. I did hear an interview by Mr McDonald a<br />couple of days ago on AM about the changes that the Board had announced. And I<br />gathered from what he said that he wanted to talk to Senator Alston in the first<br />instance and perhaps to me about the ABC's plans. I believe if that is the case then I<br />will pay him the courtesy of hearing what he has to say because we don't want to be<br />unreasonable with the ABC. Equally we've made commitments and you'll gather<br />from what I said earlier that we're quite resolute in our commitment to maintaining the<br />savings that were put down in the Budget. But if Mr McDonald wants to talk to me or<br />to Richard Alston, we're happy to do so. I know these cuts are unpopular with the<br />ABC but although it may fall on deaf ears for ABC lovers in the ACT, we don't have<br />any secret agenda about the ABC. I think the ABC renders and enormous service to<br />this country and it's a very valuable part of the fabric of national life in Australia. That<br />doesn't mean to say I agree with every news emphasis of the ABC and it doesn't mean<br />that I don't remain of the view that on certain issues the spectrum of opinion in the<br />ABC is far too narrow, and if it had a broader spectrum of views on certain issues then<br />it might have broader community appeal.<br />JACKSON: Prime Minister, we do have to leave it there, we're out of time. Thank you very much.<br />PRIME MINISTER:<br />Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
