<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6704</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/08/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006704.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
lj, 3AUSTKA LItA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 23 August 1985<br />
I am aware that there has recently been public criticism<br />
of the work of the Australian Bicentennial Authority from<br />
a number of sources.<br />
I wish to make it clear that I have complete confidence in<br />
the Authority, and its Chlairman, Mr John Reid and his Board.<br />
They have the full support of the Government in their<br />
important task of giving direction to and managing the<br />
preparations for the Bicentenary. I look forward to<br />
continuing to work with them in the future, and I am<br />
confident that as a result of their efforts the celebrations<br />
in our Bicentennial year 1988 will be a resounding success.<br />
The Board of the Authority of course comprises representatives<br />
of the Commonwealth, the six States and the Northern Territory.<br />
The staff of the Authority has been headed by Mr David Armstrong,<br />
who today resigned from his position of General Manager. The<br />
Government is appreciative of his contribution to the<br />
development of plans by the Authority for the Bicentennial year.<br />
It is important that the Australian community, as well as<br />
governments, give the Authority its full support. I have in<br />
mind here particularly major corporations and businesses, as<br />
well as individuals.<br />
It is important that the Authority be given all possible<br />
financial support and assistance now to help it in its<br />
important task, and I am confident this support will be<br />
forthcoming. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
