<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4076</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S ADDRESS AT THE PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON FOR THE KING OF JORDAN</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/03/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004076.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F76/ 47<br />
1! QA WEA MBARGO: CCHEEKCA GAINST D15I. R<br />
FOR PRESS 3 March 1976<br />
PRIME MINISTER' S ADDRESS AT THE PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON<br />
FOR THE KING OF JORDAN<br />
I have great pleasure in welcoming His Majesty, the<br />
Kin ofJordan, to Australia.<br />
It is also a great honour that His Majesty could be accompanied<br />
by Her Majesty Queen Alia and their. Royal Highnesses Princess<br />
Alia and Princess Basma.<br />
A ustralians, indeed most people have admired King Hussein's<br />
determination and personal courage,, a courage and determination<br />
that he has demonstrated since he came to the throne at the age.<br />
of seventeen.<br />
Few men could have surmounted with such ability and grace the<br />
problems which have faced the King throughout his career.<br />
O Even fewer men could have combined the King's capacity to deal<br />
so effecively with political and military issues while pursuing<br />
a multiplicity of other activities flying, racing Mercedes<br />
O c3o00n suSmL, m atfee ncsiknigl, l . horse riding at all, let alone with the King's<br />
King THussein has ruled Jordan during a time of great turbulence<br />
in the Middle East. A time marked not only by high tension<br />
and open conflict between the Middle East States but also the<br />
superpowers open involvement and competition in the region.<br />
Through these conflicts, the King of Jordan has acted as a<br />
force for responsibility and moderation in the relation~ s<br />
between Middle East States.<br />
His attempts to render Middle Eastern conflicts more amenable to<br />
resolution, give him a great claim to international respect<br />
and understanding.<br />
They also give the world a right to be optimistic about the<br />
future of peace, and mutual accommodation in the area. </p>
<p>As well as his record in international affairs, the King's<br />
astute planning has made a great contribution to Jordan's<br />
economic advancement and its recovery from the damage brought<br />
by war.<br />
Australia is concerned that there should be a just and lasting<br />
settlemrent in the Middle East, a settlement which accords<br />
with the international accepted principles established<br />
by the U. N. Security Council and which takes' account of the.<br />
legitimate interests of all the groups concerned.<br />
The just recognition and realisaticn of the legitimate claims<br />
of all groups in the Middle East constitutes the touchstone of<br />
our fpolicy in the area.<br />
King Hussein is the first Arab Head of State to visit Australia.<br />
The Australian Government look s forward to the opportunity<br />
prbvided by his visit to gain the deeper appreciation of the<br />
Middle East's problems, and the possibilities of their<br />
resolution that personal discussions with a man of his knowledge<br />
and stature can bring.<br />
We hope that the King will not only be able'to have productive<br />
discussions with the Australian Government but also see and<br />
enjoy the continent of Australia and meet the Australian people.<br />
Perhaps he will also have the opportunity to pursue some of<br />
the other activities in which he has gained such a formidable expertise<br />
despite his onerous duties as Head of State.' </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
