<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>148</transcript-id>
    <title>P.M. NO. 2/1960 - ANTI-SEMITISM IN AUSTRALIA - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000148.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. No. 2/ 1960<br />
ANTI-SEMITISM IN AUSTRALIA<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. R. G.<br />
Menzies<br />
I have hitherto made no statement about some recent<br />
manifestations of anti-Semitism in Australia, evidenced by the<br />
painting up of slogans on walls and other malicious or foolish<br />
activities. I have myself had experience of painted slogans directed<br />
against me, but have not treated them seriously. But as<br />
many of our Jewish fellow citizens are genuinely distressed at<br />
these recent events, I think that I should now say that there<br />
is absolutely no room in Australia for anti-Semitism, no<br />
justification for it, and that I believe that there is no real<br />
substance in it.<br />
There is a long history in Australia of distinguished<br />
service to our country by Jewish citizens. The Jews in<br />
Australia are good Australians. Any attempt to create an anti-<br />
Jewish feeling in Australia is doomed to failure. It may be,<br />
of course, that these sporadic actions are those of irresponsible<br />
people on the " lunatic fringe" who hope, by their childish<br />
antics, to secure some form of anonymous notoriety. It may be,<br />
on the other hand, that those who seek to divide our country<br />
are using this as one means of doing so, So far we have no<br />
clear evidence that there is an organised campaign of such a<br />
sinister kind, but we are of course watching the position very<br />
closely. As we found when we attempted to deal legislatively<br />
with Comnmunist activities, the powers of the Commonwealth<br />
Parliament are limited. But I say without any hesitation, first,<br />
that we roundly condemn any attempt to stir up false issues and,<br />
second, that we invite the people of Australia to treat these<br />
outbursts with contempt. I am sure that every Member of the<br />
Federal Parliament of whatever Party shares our feelings on<br />
this matter.<br />
CANBERRA, 26th January, 1960. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
