<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>548</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 48/1962 - ROYAL TOUR - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000548.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. No. )+ 8/ 1962<br />
FOR RELEASE 6.-3o P. M. JULY<br />
ROYAL TOUR<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister the Rton Menzies<br />
The Commonwealth Government has appointed Vice-<br />
Admiral Sir Roy Dowling, C. 3.7 to take<br />
charge of the planning of the visit to Australia next<br />
year of Her Majesty the Queen and His Royal Highness<br />
the Duke of Edinburgh.<br />
Sir Roy Dowling will be Her Majesty's Australian<br />
Secretary for the occasion and will be a member of the<br />
Royal Household throughout the visit.<br />
Arrangements have been made for him to visit<br />
London in about two weeks' time to confer with the Queen<br />
and Prince Philip. His discussions at Buckingham<br />
Palace will take place over a period of about three weeks.<br />
He will be accompanied to London by Lady Dowling.<br />
Before leaving for England, Sir Roy Dowling<br />
will, in accordance with arrangements made between the<br />
Prime Minister and Premiers last week in Canberra, meet<br />
State Directors, and will thus be able to take with him programme<br />
suggestions for discussion with Her Majesty.<br />
The States have been asked to indicate what<br />
events of special significance will be taking place during<br />
the period of Her Majesty's visit and the final arrangement<br />
of the itinerary will depend, in some measure, on the<br />
proposals forthcoming.<br />
CANBERRA, July, 1962. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
