<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3078</transcript-id>
    <title>PRICES AND INCOMES</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/11/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003078.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
, LW51AR(; U: 8.-W P: 4 THURSDAY 122 : 7ov 7 3<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR E. G. WHITLAM, TO THE<br />
LABOR COUNCIL OF N. S. W. TRADES HALL, SYDNEY THURSDAY 22 NOVEMBER 1973.<br />
PRICES AND INCOMES<br />
I welcome this opportunity to address the Labor Council<br />
of N. S. W. on the forthcoming referendums on prices and incomes.<br />
Your council is the largest State trade union organisation in<br />
Australia. Clearly the attitude of the one million members of<br />
the 110 unions affiliated with this council will play an important<br />
part in determining the success of the referendums.<br />
I believe it is undeniably in the interests of these<br />
people and all of the wage and salary earners of N. S. W. that<br />
the referendums do succeed. For what we are seeking the power<br />
for the Australian Parliament to make laws about prices and about<br />
incomes will enhance our abil. ity to try to ensure that the<br />
prosperity of our nation is a reality for all our people, and not<br />
just an illusion. Such a power will not be a cure-all but it will<br />
add significantly to the armoury of economic weapons which we can<br />
deploy) particularly in the fight against inflation.<br />
No section of the community can be more aware of the<br />
effects of inflation than the trade union movement. No section of<br />
the community is more constantly engaged in trying to achieve a<br />
real improvement in living standards in the face of inflation than<br />
the trade unions. With one possible exception, it is their members<br />
who suffer most from rising prices. That exception would probably<br />
be pensioners and other people on low fixed incomes and the<br />
trade union movement has always shown a vigorous concern about any<br />
erosion of the value of their benefits and savings. / 2 </p>
<p>The Government has demonstrated beyond doubt its<br />
determination to deal with the problem of inflation. Not that we<br />
concede for a minute that the overall economic picture should be<br />
regarded gloomily. This year we have lifted our national growth<br />
rate to) a near record of We are enjoyingj conditions of<br />
buoyant business prosperity. We are intent on keeping things<br />
that way. Nevcrtheless we rus~, t recognise, and we have recognised,<br />
that Australia, in common with the rest of the world, is undergoing<br />
a period of hiqh inflation. Rising prices must obviously diminish<br />
to an extent the benefits of any general prosperity, particularly<br />
for wage and salary earners. Already we have acted by introducing<br />
a series of carefully timed and related anti-inflationary measures.<br />
We have established the Prices justification Tribunal. We have<br />
cut tariffs. We have revalued the dollar twice. And other fiscal<br />
and monetary action has been takcn when needed.<br />
I would mention in this context our decision this we]'<br />
to cut tariffs on television sets and other electronic equipment.<br />
Primarily this has been done to ensure that ~ Australians do no-' L<br />
have to pay excessive prices for colour television sets. We are<br />
sure that Australians will be able to benefit from this decision<br />
without any drop in the level of employment in the industry. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
one measure we have not been prepared to take to counter<br />
inflation is to create unemployment. We are not prepared to see<br />
a return to the situation in 1972 when economic action taken by<br />
the previous government resulted in 130,000 people being out of<br />
work. We repudiate firmly and unchangeably such an antiquated<br />
and harmiful approach to dealing with inflation. Indeed, within<br />
months of coming into office, the Labor Government has reduced<br />
unemployment as nearly as possible to acceptable limits.<br />
I have already mentioned however, that, despite the<br />
action we have taken to try to counter rising prices, the Australian<br />
Government is denied a full complement of economic powers to deal<br />
with this problem. The power to make laws about. prices and<br />
incomes resides with the States. They have been unwilling or<br />
unable to use effectively their power to contain prices. This<br />
applies particularly in Victoria and Queensland, all of<br />
which are dominated by non-labor governments. The Australian<br />
Government has asked the States to refer their powers to it so that<br />
national action can be taken but the three largest States have<br />
refused co-operation.<br />
It -is against this background that we are now taking<br />
this question to the people in the referendums to be held on<br />
8 December. This approach is based on the firm conviction that<br />
inflation is a national problem which demands national answers.<br />
All comparable countries have the powers that we are seeking.<br />
We are asking the people to give us nothing more and nothing less<br />
than the economic authority which the governments of these countries<br />
command. / 4 </p>
<p>The trade union movement is, of course, solidly behind<br />
us in seeking the prices power. It knows that this power wijll<br />
provide the chance for hard-won wage and salary gains to catch<br />
tip on price increases. It knows that it will give the elected<br />
government the opportunity to protect the incomes and savings of<br />
pensioners and fixed income earners. It knows that it will give<br />
homebuyers the prospect of stabilised * costs for land and materials.<br />
The Government does not intend to rigidly apply wideranging<br />
price control. It will make flexibl. e and selective use<br />
of the powers which it is seeking. However, it should have the<br />
ability to prevent, where necessary, excessive rises in the price<br />
of essential commodities. I am confident that with the continued<br />
support of the trade unions and other sections of the community,<br />
that we will be given this ability on 8 December.<br />
T'he union movement however, is not solidl. y supporting us<br />
in seeking the power to make laws about incomes. I know that the<br />
fear of a number of officials is that this power might be used to<br />
introduce a freeze on wages. I have said before, and unequivocally<br />
I will say again, that the Australian Government has no intention<br />
of taking such drastic action. You have more than just my pledg~ e<br />
on that; a freeze on wages and salaries would be contrary to<br />
the statement in the A. L. P. Platform that " good industrial relations<br />
will be best achieved by agreement initially arrived at between<br />
trade unions and employers." I also believe that even our opponents,<br />
if ' they were returned to office, would be forced to recoil from such<br />
a free2ze because of its arbitrary and heavy-handed nature. The<br />
disruption and disharmony that this type of action would cause,<br />
would. I believe, deter them. </p>
<p>Despite this, we are all aware that the Australian<br />
Council of Trade Unions has called upon affiliated bodies to<br />
campaign against the incomes power. The ACTU Executive on<br />
October decided that this proposal. is " beyond ACTU policy".<br />
I am not suggesting that too much significance be read into the<br />
use of the world " beyond"; but it is interesting that the<br />
Executive did not say that the proposal is " against ACTU policy".<br />
The substantial ground of objection by the Executive<br />
is that " the A. C. T. U. will under no circumstances accept a wage<br />
freeze and will actively campaign against any proposal to<br />
implement a wage freeze in this country." I have already pointed<br />
out that the incomes power and a wages freeze are definitely not<br />
the same thing. You have the undertaking of the Government and<br />
the Australian Labor Party that there will be no freeze; and you<br />
can make the realistic assessment that any blustering inclination<br />
towards it by our opponents would disappear if they had the chance<br />
to consider such a move.<br />
I do not believe that the incomes power is against the<br />
interests of trade unions. Indeed, I would point out to you that<br />
the ACTU Congress the supreme policy-making body of the<br />
organisation as recently as 4 September carried without dissent<br />
as part of its economic policy for the ensuing two years a demand<br />
that " direct regulation over non-wage forms of incomes as a means<br />
of ureve nting excessive increases in these incomes" be introduced. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
There is no way that any national Government could act<br />
on this demand without the incomes power which we are seeking.<br />
It would be a legislative nightmare although perhaps ultimately<br />
a lawyer's delight in the courts for us to frame and seek a more<br />
restricted power. How would we define non-wage incomes for the<br />
purpose of an amendment to the Constitution? I do not believe<br />
that we could achieve the necessary precision of definition. I<br />
believe that the public would be so confused by any attempt to do<br />
so that, in keeping with the result of so many referendums in the<br />
past, people would play safe and reject a proposal of this kind<br />
in favour of the status-quo.<br />
In making my opening broadcast on the referendums on<br />
national television on Tuesday night, I said that, if powers over<br />
prices and incomes are to be effective, they must be uniform,<br />
immediate and unchallengeable in their application. Even if we<br />
were to attempt to succeed in an attempt to acquire a limited<br />
power over incomes, that power could not be either immediate or<br />
unchallengeable in its application.<br />
So we are left with the proposition that, for the national<br />
government to do anything about non-wage incomes, it must be given<br />
the power that we are seeking now. In keeping with our attitude<br />
towards price control, we would only apply our authority over<br />
incomes flexibly and selectively. Even then, it would be a mistake<br />
to regard this as a purely negative power. It would, for example,<br />
enable us to ensure the eventual attainment of equal pay for all<br />
women in the workforce. It would also permit the Australian<br />
Parliament to make allowances for inflation, if necessary, by making<br />
periodic adjustments to wages and salaries, as it is already making<br />
periodic adjustments to pensions. </p>
<p>-7-<br />
On this last point I was amused recently when my attention<br />
was drawn to a statement made by Mr Snedden, when he was Treasurer,<br />
in an interview published in the " National Times" in February 1972.<br />
He was asked about his attitude towards quarterly costs-of-living<br />
adjustments to wages. And he said: " It's curious if you go back<br />
to I think it was ' 53 when the adjustments were suspended, they<br />
were doning damage at that time in a different environment. The<br />
curious inversion now is that if you had quarterly adjustments you<br />
would reduce the wage increase." The changing attitudes of<br />
Mr Snedden become curiouser and curiouser! The only effective way<br />
that he could pursue such a policy would be for the Australian<br />
Parliament to have the power to make laws about incomes.<br />
Aside fromL Mr Snedden's vagaries, a strong economic<br />
argument can be made for the introduction of regular cost-of-living<br />
adjustments to wages and salaries. The argument rests on the view<br />
that some wage and salary demands are forced very high by the<br />
fear that more moderate pay increases will be rendered inadequate<br />
by rising prices. The Australian Government at present does not have<br />
the power to introduce cost-of-living adjustments to counter this<br />
problem. It is unable to do more than ask the Conciliation and<br />
Arbitration Commission to do Clearl,, it would be a qreat<br />
advaintagje to unionist!: to Le able tr; cnter , waye and salary negotiation<br />
or award hearings with the knowledge that the Government could, if<br />
necessary, subsequently adjust upwards any new wages or salaries<br />
achieved through these processes, if their value was eroded by rising<br />
prices. / 8 </p>
<p>I also ask you to consider the use to which income<br />
powers have been put by the State Government in NJ. S. W. To m~ y knowledge,<br />
no N. S. W. Government of any political complexion has used its<br />
legislative authority to decrease or freeze wages or salaries.<br />
In fact, any legislative action has always resulted in an improvement.<br />
The only action to diminish pay has always been taken by the<br />
Industrial Commission.<br />
The general reduction in wages in N. S. W. during the<br />
Depression was made by the Commission, for example. Then we can<br />
look at what has happened to cost-of-living adjustments in this<br />
State. In 1953 the Commnission followed a Commonwealth court<br />
decision to abolish these adjustments to the bas-ic wage. Otate<br />
legislation in 1955 reouired the restoration of the adjustments.<br />
This legislation was abandoned in 1964 but the State basic wage was<br />
increase sign~ ific antly by the Parliament to equate it with the<br />
Federal basic wage. Finally, we can examine the history of the<br />
movement towards equal pay for women. A State Industrial Corriissicn<br />
decision failed to adopt completely a 1950 Commonwealth court<br />
dlecision to increase the basic wage of one pound a week arid to lift<br />
the female basic wage from 54 per cent t'-o 75 per cent of the vale<br />
rate. Legislative action in the N. S. W. Parliament in 1956 redressed<br />
this decision and introduced a program for the attainment of equal<br />
pay. In short, legislative action based on. the State's incomes<br />
power, even if it has not been used to a great extent, has been in<br />
favour of employees for 40 years. This means that no party in office<br />
has been prepared to use that power to reduce workers' pay. I argue<br />
that this provides a positive indication that no party in control 9 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
of the national Parliament would use an incomes power to reduce<br />
or freeze wages and salaries.<br />
The Australian Labor Party has gone further than giving<br />
an unequivocal commitment on this point. Our Federal Executive<br />
declared in October that the implementation of prices and incomes<br />
powers " can only he successful with the direct involvement of the<br />
trade union ntovemcnt in the formulation and aOnministration of any<br />
policies affecting trade unionists." All overseas experience hWE<br />
proved that policies on incomes cannot work without a broadly-based<br />
community consensus and the co-operation of the bulk of the trade<br />
union movement. Lny failure to achieve this cornsensus anC this<br />
co-operation has inevitably led t~ o a failure of such pol icies<br />
overseas. Thus there can be no question of coercing the bull of<br />
the union movement or of the business world as we would need their<br />
support to make any action on incomes effective. However, the<br />
powers we seek would prevent any small recalcitrant minority from<br />
imposing its will contrary to the consensus of the community.<br />
My final point is that division within the labor movement,<br />
often based on short-term considerations, has usually resulted<br />
in the defeat of constitutional amendments put to the people by<br />
rcferendum. Members of the labor movcment have come to regret<br />
these earlier failures in subsequent generations. On this occasion<br />
I hope that we can learn from our history and minimise any<br />
disputation which might result from doubts or fears. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
