<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8436</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP, MELBOURNE 4 MARH 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008436.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, MELBOURNE<br />
4 MARCH 1992<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: this morning, do you take any heart from the fact<br />
that the majority of Australians polled would seem to<br />
support the concept of a republic?<br />
PM: Well, I think it is a reflection of a growing sense of<br />
independence in Australia, and that independence is<br />
again shown here today. This is a very important<br />
milestone, this plant, in Australia's industrial<br />
history, its development, indeed its independence.<br />
This is a first state of the art, world ranking plant<br />
which will be developed under the Government's car<br />
plans. If you like, part of the renewal of Australian<br />
manufacturing in the 1990s and beyond. A plant that<br />
will service in the 21st century. It is part of the<br />
reason why Australians can make it. We can trade<br />
successfully and of course, into the area of the world<br />
we live in, the Asia-Pacific, where all the growth is.<br />
And it is that, I think, independence and capacity of<br />
independence with Australians are feeling. And you are<br />
seeing that reflected in polls.<br />
J: On another issue, would you like to see an early<br />
election here in Victoria?<br />
PM: Not for me, that's a matter for Premier Kirner.<br />
J: Do you know if members of the ALP are pressuring Mrs<br />
Kirner to go early?<br />
PM: Look, I don't know, I don't know.<br />
J: What advice would you have for her?<br />
PM: Look, I've got no advice for Mrs Kirner, she can look<br />
after herself in these respects. But I am pleased to<br />
see her here today. I am pleased that the Victorian 1 </p>
<p>Government has so supported this project as it has. I<br />
mean thiLs is a real thing. I mean often newspapers are<br />
talking about things that don't matter. This does<br />
matter. This is part'of Melbourne's future into the<br />
next century. That's what this thing stands for today.<br />
This is about, the great change outward to become a<br />
sophisticated industrial society and a great vote of<br />
confidence by a world ranking company, the Toyota Motor<br />
Company, in this country, in Australia, in Australian<br />
workers and in the Australian nation, in our<br />
competitiveness.<br />
J: Mr KeatLng, how do you rate your chance in the Wills?<br />
PM: Well, I think the Liberal Party has got a 15 or<br />
point lead, that ought to be shoe-in for them, but we<br />
will be fighting them all the way.<br />
J: When can those electors expect to go to the polls?<br />
PM: Well, that's got to be decided by the Speaker, amongst<br />
other things.<br />
ENDS<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
