<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1013</transcript-id>
    <title>PARTIALLY BLINDED SOLDIERS ASSOCIATION SILVER JUBILEE DINNER, PADDINGTON TOWN HALL, SYDNEY - 30TH OCTOBER 1964 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/10/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001013.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PARTIALLY BLINDED SOLDIERS ASSOCIATION<br />
SILVER JUBILEE DINNERPADDINGTON<br />
TOZ4 HALL,_-SYDNEY OCTOBER, 1964+<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt.. Hqn._. Slr Robe t Menzies<br />
Sir and Your Excellency the High Commissioner<br />
I am quite accustomed to beaing made a bit of a<br />
chopping block but I have been chopped in three different<br />
directions todUght. I have a sort of raixed assortment of<br />
tasks. One I will conclude with, tb-Pt is the task of handing<br />
over this remarkable historic volume Mr. Maloney for the<br />
Government. I think I should perhaps begin by discharging<br />
the lightest of my duties, I think it is rather sinister to<br />
give a politician the Order of the Double Cross. ( Laughter)<br />
Don't you? I know that it is well meant. but it lends itself<br />
to misunderstanding, if you don't understand these things<br />
quite well. I think I had better take it of" f for a moment<br />
so that I can see this. There is a picture in the middle of<br />
what I will say is a gentleman and I have had a quick glance<br />
at it, and so help me Bob I couldn't make up my mind<br />
whether it was Khrushchev or Nasser or Menzies ( Laughter).<br />
Might be any one of the three.<br />
I must tell you about..... I mustn't dejcr-ibe<br />
him as the late Mr. Khrushchev as far as we know he is<br />
not late. ( Laughter) But something has happened, ut I had<br />
a long discussion with him once in New York in his office there<br />
at his Embassy. . JlI want to tell you that he has a nice<br />
earthy sense of humour. It may not avail him very much now,<br />
but then, humour is wasted when you are out of office.<br />
( Laughter) I went in to see him and his first remark he<br />
doesn't speak English at least he pretends not to but he had<br />
a brilliant interpreter so that the conversation was practically<br />
non-stop. He stood up, shook hands with me and then looked<br />
ct me and said, " For an imperialist you are not a bad specimen."<br />
( Laughter) To which I retorted wiih that courtesy for which<br />
I am famous, " Sir, for a Communist, you are, on the whole,<br />
rather better than I expected." ( Laughter) And after that we<br />
got on fine. He talked about disarmament without achieving<br />
any and he went through all the old usual gambits which occur<br />
in the vicinity of the United Nations in New York. But there<br />
it is. Come to think of it, you know, the top part, the<br />
cap, rather suggests Soekarno, doesn't it? ( Laughter Well,<br />
there you are. Isn't it a brilliant piece of work? It looks<br />
to me so ambiguous as to make it possible for it to be any one<br />
of four men, with a snake down in the corners...... Now,<br />
I would be upset about this to be called a Double Crosser, to<br />
be called a snake in the grass or whatever it is, this would<br />
be very annoying, except that f would have you know that this<br />
is not the first decoration that I have ever received. I am<br />
a physician, did you know that, ( Laughter) I am a Fellow<br />
of the Royal College of Physicians. Doesn't make the faintest<br />
difference to the bill. ( Laughter) So there I am, I have a<br />
certificate to show. And the medical profession have a symbol,<br />
you know, which was vulgarly described by a friend of mine<br />
in law once as a snake crawling up a stick. ( Laughtor) a a. a 0 0/ 2 </p>
<p>2 a<br />
And so I am not unfamiliar with the symbol of the snake<br />
in the grass. The raw prawn is a particularly Sydney expression.<br />
( Laughter) In the genteel quarters of Melbourne in which<br />
I used to live once, nobody ever heard of a raw prawn.<br />
( Laughter) When I came to Canberra and fell. into low<br />
company and had to meet a lot of Sydney fellows, you know,<br />
in Parliament I became accustomed to hearing one of them<br />
say " Oh, dontt come the raw prawn.'" ( Laughter) They had<br />
another expression, " There wore sharks in the bay," ( Laughter)<br />
These, of course, were meaningless to Victorians. There are<br />
no prawns and no sharks, or at an ae oshrsi h<br />
bay. Anyhow, Sir, I thai., k vou very much. This will<br />
be hung in a suitable place of -onr.( Laughter) ( Applause)<br />
I will execute, of course, a deed of trust so that it goes<br />
to my descendants ( Laughter) and If -It is valued by some<br />
curiosity-hunter some day at a sufficiently high figure,<br />
it will attract, so I am told by my colleague the Treaslrer,<br />
a suitable rate of taxation. ( Laughter)<br />
Now, Sir, the next thing I want to say is that<br />
I was delighted to find that your guest last year was the<br />
General General Muttukumaru, the High Commissioner of<br />
Ceylon. He has only been in Australia for what only a<br />
couple of years now just under two years. He Is a familiar<br />
friend of all of us, and I am delighted to think that two<br />
years running, ho has come here. Indeed, if I may betray<br />
a Scottish secret, I may tell you that among the many<br />
occupations I have, I am President of the Melbourne Scots,<br />
and he is coming down as a guest this year. ( Laughter)<br />
That, of course, is bad enough from our point of vie, but<br />
he's going to make a speech. ( Laughter) And so you can see<br />
that Le has established himself.<br />
Well, now, I dontt want to make a long speech<br />
to you and I know that I am not to make a political speech<br />
to you. Indeed, I have never been brave enough to ma~ ke<br />
apolitical speech in Paddington Town Hall. ( 7au K~<br />
You understand that, Jim, don't you? ( Laughter) -Anyhow,<br />
I never have, but I must say that in the same electorate<br />
one year, I made what was regarded as a speech at the<br />
stadium. Now, you take it from me, if you want to' have a<br />
novel experience, make a speech at the stadium,, standing<br />
in the middle of the ring, with an all-direction mic. rophone<br />
and noboay there with you ( Laughter) and 8,000 people, 2,000<br />
of whom hate the sight of you and occupy the first threo or<br />
four rows. A very remarkable experience. Every now and<br />
then, I would look down and I would see my wife. She was<br />
there. She never misses, do you see. My secret weapon.<br />
And she was there and she was in the front row there and she<br />
couldn't hear a word I was saying. I've never seen her look<br />
at me with such mystified respect. ( Laughter) Not a word<br />
could be heard. We finally got away, sound in wind and<br />
limb, and went back to the hotel and they were rebroadcasting<br />
this speech of mine. Honestly with very great respect to<br />
the surroundings I hadn't a clue as to whether I had begun<br />
a sentence or ended one. Because if you can't hear yourself,<br />
it is very difficult to know whether you arc talking.<br />
But that's been my experience. I like to hear myself because<br />
sometimes I have a shrewd idea that nobody else is listening.<br />
( Laughter) When we got back to the hotel, and heard the<br />
radio, I said to my wife, " By Jove, this fellow's doing<br />
well. Who's this?" And sho said, you." ( Laughter)<br />
ee s/ 3 </p>
<p>-3 -A<br />
Well, I don't need to tell you that I went on from then through<br />
the next three weeks, won an election and have been in office<br />
ever since. ( Laughter) So peace to Paddington and good luck<br />
to the stadiuml ( Laughter) Is it still called the stadium?<br />
There is one in Melbourne they now call the Festival Hall.<br />
( Laughter) They have a festival there this afternoon. You'll<br />
read about it in the papers in the morning,,<br />
But, Sir, I didn't mean to be so absurd as all<br />
this. I just want to say this to you, This eye bank scheme,<br />
this, I think is one of the most remarkablo things in<br />
Australia, H~ would bring credit on any organisation that<br />
thought of it and put it into effect. This is a tremendous<br />
thing and it is a tremendous thing done by peoples many<br />
of whom have already done tremendous things for thisocountry.<br />
These are matters that we must never forget. And I was<br />
thinking about tonight and saying t,-o myself, " g4ell, what is<br />
there beyond the usual platitudes that one can say on an<br />
occasion of this kind? WIhat is thore as we look forward to<br />
the future that ought to be in our minds?" And I came to<br />
one conclusion and I venture to state it.<br />
It sounds a truism but it is more thin that.<br />
It is that every year is a new year. Now this of course is<br />
qiiite right, but every year is a new year. You begin a<br />
year, you look back on a year in which the problems have<br />
beenIA and B and C and in the next year you find thnt the<br />
problems are D and E and F, They are changing all the time<br />
because every year is a new year and the world is a new world<br />
every year. The world is a new world for e~ eyperson born<br />
into it. We all, don't we, remember our own childhood and<br />
so on* That's the kind of world we know somethiing about<br />
and we've lived in, but for everybody it's a new world, f~ or<br />
every year it's a new world.<br />
This year is, as usual I think a year full of<br />
most critical events. I read them from left to right, I<br />
wonltcbtain you very long, but it is worth thinking about<br />
them. Next Tuesday there will be an election in the United<br />
States of America, the election of a President. I am<br />
not taking sides, this is not; my business or ycurs in That<br />
sense but the Presidential eieutions may have a prufound<br />
effec' on the relations of the United States witb. the rest<br />
of the world. It may. I don't know. There arc controversies<br />
going on in that country. I don't know one of thj candidates<br />
Senator Goldwater. I do have the honour of knowing t-he<br />
present President. But the important thing is that, whatever<br />
comes or goes in an election of this kind, whatever mud is<br />
thrown or whatever extravaganzas of argument may occur, it<br />
is vital from our point of view, isn't it, that America<br />
should continue to be the greatest stronghold of freedom in<br />
the Western world, of tremendous importance to uls because of<br />
her strength, because of her goodwill, of tremendous<br />
significance to Australia's future security and freedom.<br />
WIhen I say that, let me remind you that nothing<br />
would ever persuade me or you to be anything else but<br />
British. We're proud of it, But the facts in the world today<br />
are the greatest single power) with its resources and good<br />
will is the United States of America. It is from my point<br />
of view, vital that the United States of America and Great<br />
Britain and the whole of the Commonwealth should be as close<br />
together as two groups of nations can be because we have a<br />
common purpose and, I think, a common destiny, I think that's<br />
one rather crucial event that has been played out and we will<br />
all be listening at some time on Wednesday to discover the<br />
result, </p>
<p>Then the next thing is this, in respect of which<br />
this is a new year. We have a new Commonwealth. You<br />
mustn't suppose when you look at the General which is<br />
something to give you pleasure; look at me which is perhaps<br />
in a different c, togory you mustntt suppose that we are<br />
typical of the new Commonwealth. He comes from a country<br />
which has a parliamentary system, which has elections and<br />
parties. We have elections and parties. We live as<br />
Winston once said to me in a fine eighteenth century<br />
fervour of politics. We do. We, on the whole, rather<br />
enjoy them. But here we are, we ae both democracies,<br />
Great Britain of course, the father, the mother, of the<br />
whole democratic system.<br />
The interesting thing rjbcut the new Commonwealth,<br />
and we will know more and more about it over the next two or<br />
three years, is whether the new Comonwealth will be something<br />
that advances democracy or retards it, because don't be under<br />
the misapprehension that some peopile are in other countries<br />
that all the new Commonwealth countries are democracies.<br />
Not at all. I don't think Nkrumah would pretend for a moment<br />
that Ghana was a democracy, because as I have had occasion<br />
to say to him, playfully, more than once, " At any rate, we<br />
don't put the Leader of the Opposition in gaol in Australia"<br />
( Laughter) and therefore, any description of Ghana as a<br />
democracy must be one, I think, rather modified by the facts.<br />
And, of course, a number of the other new countries<br />
have declared themselves for the one-party State, The oneparty<br />
State. Indeed, when Mr. Mboya of Kenya was here during<br />
the year, he spoke to a great number of Members of P'arliament<br />
about the one-party State and the reason for it. 1tbs a<br />
rather simple conception. There is just one party. there is<br />
no-one else to vote for. This is, depending on youx. point<br />
of view, a rather agreeable conception. But, of course, it<br />
would be impossible with us.<br />
One of my Labour friends in the Housp, whenn iMboya<br />
vas getting warmed up on this, tapped me on i: l2d: r and<br />
said, " Don't worry, old boy, yot'e had it fclr :. een years."<br />
( Laughter) But, you see a one-party State in w! iich you have<br />
no choice tends to consolidate a species of dictateship,<br />
Now I believe, myself, implicitly that in all thesoae<br />
countries, these new colleagues of ours the whole process<br />
will tend to break this dowm, to establish from a beginning<br />
of highly-centralised power in government, what re call a<br />
democratic system, so that people are free and free to vote<br />
and to make their choice. I think that's going to be the<br />
process, but don't expect that totnppen overnight,<br />
But whether the new Commonwealth survi.; res in the<br />
form in which we now see it in my opinion largely depends<br />
upon how far over the next live years or ten years its<br />
activities and its attitudes advance democracy or retard it.<br />
Now thatts the second thing that we are looking at a little<br />
distantly at the present time in this year of grace, in your<br />
twenty-fifth year, your jubilee year.<br />
And the third thing is what's going to happen in<br />
this corner of the world? Will South-East Asia continue to be<br />
non-Communist, continue to be free from the Communist drive?<br />
Now, I am not just talking a lot of hot air and politics on<br />
this business, but everybody must realise that our future, the<br />
a </p>
<p>future of neighbouring countries, the future of New Zealand,<br />
these are all wrapped up in whether South-East Asia this area<br />
of the world manages to remain outside the Communist orbit,<br />
whether the Communist orbit is Russian Communism or Chinese<br />
Communism and this is something on which really we must begin<br />
in Australia to rise superior to detal. ed party differences.<br />
There can't be any difference-on this matter, surely-that our<br />
freedom, the future of this country, the future of free people<br />
like the Malaysians who have a democratic system of government,<br />
people in New Zealand, our close kinsraen, we must all be in a<br />
position to feel that we are the mast-3rs of oir own future and<br />
that the peace that we enjoy is the peiacc of freedom and not the<br />
peace of submission, This is the great issue this part of the world.<br />
I won't elaborate it, but you see I mean when I say each<br />
year is a new year in the United 3, tes, in the New Commonwealth<br />
in South East Asia, we hav,; seen problems emerga,<br />
crystailise, become known, sometimes become critical sometimes<br />
become easier, all in the space of one year, and next year will<br />
bring its new problems, problems to which we will all have to<br />
devote whatever talents and courage we may possess.<br />
Now everything that I have said is really an expansion<br />
of what I said to you at the beginning because I am here in the<br />
presence of men who have done groat service to freedom in this<br />
country great service. And they have themselves, w. th this<br />
splendil effort of imagination, established this bank in order<br />
that lots of people may have the opportunity future of. having<br />
their sight improved or saved. This is an iraginative bold<br />
thing and I am delighted to discover how magnificently it has<br />
succeeded. And therefore I take the most sincere pleasure in<br />
handing over the Volume Three of the eye bank to Mr. Malcney<br />
who will receive it on behalf of the Government of New : 3outh<br />
Wales. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
