<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6183</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER - IMPACT OF SEX DISCRIMINATION BILL</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/08/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006183.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Icr use of assistid<br />
enhance proto<br />
U. S. and EEC<br />
ng a substantial<br />
of agricultural<br />
irotracted negoic<br />
level of Aus-<br />
Sagreed figure of<br />
matisfactory than<br />
as a strong comse<br />
that the rural<br />
jtion to our sura<br />
vital role in the<br />
nt recession. All<br />
ig called upon to<br />
very. I can assure<br />
to bear a disproow<br />
has brought<br />
Smost States of<br />
drought and, in<br />
onstrate the very<br />
lethods of assess-<br />
I wish you every<br />
: claring the third<br />
imary Industry,<br />
more aggressive<br />
rimary produce<br />
ew and expandincreasing barcrnment<br />
would<br />
, Itain access to<br />
ie Middle East<br />
entitled ' The<br />
Id Trade and<br />
cheon held by<br />
' elopment of<br />
in, China and<br />
of Australia's<br />
Ir Kerin said<br />
have become<br />
iral products<br />
n the future.<br />
tic. re flecting<br />
in domestic<br />
lent between<br />
. ide primar)<br />
panded mar-<br />
' the drought<br />
growth. Bupoint out<br />
&gt; r to its long The Minister added that restoring balance and<br />
growth to the Australian economy would also depend<br />
on a sustained recovery in the world economy.<br />
While he welcomed signs of progress in the U. S.<br />
economy, Mr Kerin warned that pressure on the U. S.<br />
dollar, and fears of it fuelling inflationary pressures<br />
and rising interest rates meant the ' recovery' had to be<br />
viewed with caution.<br />
The Minister also warned of the dangers of a trade<br />
war between the U. S. and the EEC and said that of<br />
J particular concern to Australia is the potential for<br />
enormous damage to our rural industries from subsidised<br />
competition in our export markets especially<br />
from the EEC.<br />
Mr Kerin said that in formulating its economic strategy<br />
the Government had been mindful of the impact of<br />
its policies on primary producers.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Message to Robert de Castella<br />
15 August 1983 The following message was today<br />
sent to Robert de Castella by the Prime Minister, the<br />
Hon. R. J. L. Hawke:<br />
Your great victory in Helsinki, establishing you unquestionably<br />
as the world's top marathon runner, is one that has<br />
delighted all of Australia. Your dedication and commitment<br />
are an example to all of us. We all extend to you our<br />
warmest congratulations.<br />
Impact of Sex Discrimination Bill<br />
18 August 1983 The Minister Assisting the Prime<br />
Minister for the Status of Women. Senator the Hon.<br />
Susan Ryan, said today:<br />
Under the Sex Discrimination Bill 1983, discrimination in<br />
employment on the ground of sex is unlawful and the Bill<br />
contains machinery to deal with complaints from people<br />
who believe they have been discriminated against.<br />
However the bill exempts certain conduct so that it is not<br />
unlawful to discriminate against a woman on the ground of<br />
sex in relation to her employment, engagement or appointment<br />
in a Defence Force position involving combat or<br />
combat-related duties. The meaning of ' combat-related<br />
duties' is to be prescribed by regulations.<br />
That means if the position of pilot in the RAA. F is classilied<br />
as combat-related a woman who is discriminated<br />
against when pilots are employed will have no case to bring<br />
under the legislation.<br />
It does not mean that if the RA,\ F decided to hire a<br />
woman pilot that Sex Dicrimination Bill would provide<br />
anN legislative obstacle. It is therefore incorrect to state that<br />
when the Bill comes into effect. women will be barred by<br />
law from combat and combat-related duties in the Defence<br />
Force. The Government has initiated and inter-depart niental<br />
review of Defence Force employment of women. The review<br />
in which the Department of the Prime Minister and<br />
Cabinet and the Attorney-General's Department will take<br />
part. is to commence shortly.<br />
The aim of the rcvics is to identify those duties in the<br />
Defence Force which are combat and combat-related and 1.<br />
the positions to which they relate. It is intended that the review<br />
will result in furthering the Government's objective of<br />
broadening of opportunities for women in the Defence<br />
Force. Passage of the Sex Discrimination Bill will in no way<br />
limit opportunities for women in the Defence Force.<br />
Resources and Energy<br />
Catalogue on water research<br />
16 August 1983 The Minister for Resources and Energy,<br />
Senator the Hon. Peter Walsh, today announced<br />
the publication by his Department of the first issue of<br />
Water Research in Australia. Current Projects. This<br />
catalogue contains summaries of all water research<br />
projects being undertaken in Australia during 1982,<br />
and includes details of nearly 850 projects.<br />
Contributions were received for the catalogue from<br />
a large number of organisations, and their co-operation<br />
will ensure that this publication becomes a key reference<br />
document on the national water research effort. It<br />
will be particularly useful in identifying gaps and<br />
eliminating duplication in water research in Australia.<br />
It represents the first tangible result from the recently<br />
established national water information data base<br />
STREAMLINE. The document is being widely distributed in<br />
Australia and to a range of key institutions in other<br />
countries. The research in progress information on the<br />
data base will be updated annually to provide a current<br />
record of water research throughout Australia.<br />
Copies of Water Research in Australia" Current<br />
Projects 1982 are available from the Department of<br />
Resources and Energy and the Australian Government<br />
Publishing Service bookshops.<br />
Speech to World Solar Congress<br />
18 August 1983 The following is the text of a speech<br />
by the Minister for Energy and Resources. Senator the<br />
Hon. Peter Walsh, at the World Solar Congress in<br />
Perth: For some years the highest profile energy policy issue<br />
debated in Australia has been that of nuclear power. There<br />
is negligible dissent from the view that Australia itself has<br />
no need for nuclear power---at least for some time. The debate<br />
has focused on whether Australia should facilitate, as a<br />
major supplier of uranium. the nuclear power plans of<br />
other countries.<br />
Opposition to Australian involvement is dericed principally<br />
from fears about the immediate and long term cnvironmentnal<br />
dangers of nuclear power including, at the extreme.<br />
the possibility of unrestrained nuclear war. the<br />
environmental consequences of which, for the humian<br />
species ai least, would probably be terminal.<br />
Use of fossil fuels, the major present source of primary<br />
energy. does not entail that spectacular threat to human<br />
existence. It does however, in common with nuclear power.<br />
liberate additional heat which may have signilicant effects<br />
on the world's climate. More importantly, it dumps in the<br />
atmosphere obnoxious gases like sulphur dioxide and carbon<br />
dioxide the gas which, though inert, is widely believed<br />
to have the potential to significantly increase temperature<br />
and drastically change rainfall distribution.<br />
ugust 198315-21 August 1983 Commonwealth Record </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
