<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4982</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT BY HRH THE PRINCE OF WALES</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004982.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J STRALIL UI<br />
PR, IME PAiJNSTZ1<br />
FOR PRESS 8 MARCH 1979<br />
VISIT BY HRH THE PRINCE OF WALES<br />
Details of the program for the visit to the Australian Capital<br />
Territory this month by His Royal Highness the Prince of<br />
Wales were released today.<br />
The Prince of Wales is scheduled to arrive at RAAF Base Fairbairn<br />
on the afternoon of Saturday 24 March. He will be received<br />
by the Governor--General and Mr. Hunt, representing the Prime Minister.<br />
While in Canberra His Royal Highness will stay with the<br />
Governor-General and Lady Cowen at Government House.<br />
On Sunday the Prince of Wales will attend Divine Service at<br />
St. John's Church, Reid, and that evening will attend a<br />
Reception for young people arranged by the Prime Minister<br />
and Mrs. Fraser at the Lodge.<br />
On Monday morning His Royal Highness will be inducted as a<br />
Ro-yal Fellow at the Silver Jubilee anniversary celebrations<br />
of the Australian Academy of Science.<br />
Following the Academy's Silver Jubilee lunch at University House,<br />
Prince Charles will unveil a plaque commemorating the Silver<br />
Jubilee of the opening of University House by his father<br />
the Duke of Edinburgh.<br />
During the afternoon His Royal Highness will receive at Government<br />
House representatives from the Royal Australian Armoured Corps,<br />
me.. zers and ex-students of the United World Colleges and<br />
participants in " Operation Drake".<br />
On :. onday evening His Royal Highness will be guest of honour<br />
at a dinner given by the Governor-General and Lady Cowen<br />
at , Government House.<br />
Hi-s Royal Highness will lay a wreath on the Commemorative Stone<br />
when he visits the Australian War Memorial on Tuesday morning.<br />
He will then visit the Queanbeyan City Council Chambers before<br />
going on to inaugurate the Googong Water Supply Project. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
The Prince of Wales will be guest of honour at a<br />
Parliamentary Lunch which the Prime Minister will<br />
host at Parliament House that day.<br />
Later that afternoon His Royal Highness will attend a<br />
Reception at Government House for members of The Queen Elizabeth<br />
The Second Silver Jubilee Trust for Young Australians.<br />
On Tuesday evening His Royal Highness will dine at The Lodge<br />
as the guest of the Prime Minister and Mrs. Fraser.<br />
The Prince of Wales will inspect a Guard of Honour at RAAF<br />
Base Fairbairn and a twenty-one gun salute will be fired<br />
before he leaves Canberra on Wednesday morning 28 March.<br />
He will be farewelled by the Governor-General and the<br />
Prime Minister.<br />
Following his official visit to Canberra The Prince of Wales<br />
will spend three days privately on Lizard Island before<br />
leaving Australia on Sunday 1 April by RAF<br />
from Townsville. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
