<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8448</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP OPENING OF CAMPAIGN OFFICE FOR BILL KARDAMITSIS, WILLS ELECTORATE, MARCH 10 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008448.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTERI<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
OPENING OF CAMPAIGN OFFICE FOR BILL KARDAMITSIS, WILLS<br />
ELECTORATE, MARCH 10 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Bill, Haroula, ladies and gentlemen, we know this will be a<br />
difficult el. ection for Labor but we believe we can win it.<br />
We believe we can win it because it will be a test, in many,<br />
respects, about the way Australia runs whether or not the<br />
Government should be involved in a recovery, the Government<br />
should be inLvolved in the economy, or whether it should be a<br />
policy of Government withdrawal as our friends in the<br />
Opposition wish. That is, that the Government sits on the<br />
side lines and lets the economy just simply move at its own<br />
pace, to not accelerate a recovery, to not try to make<br />
things better for Australia, and then to not try to make the<br />
economy more efficient and society better.<br />
So this contest is going to be one where the style and<br />
policies of the Labor Party, the policies about partnership,<br />
about people working together, about co-operation, are in<br />
the vogue or whether it is policies which are about<br />
confrontation, about survival of the fittest and loser take<br />
the hindmost.<br />
And it is about those issues that I think we will be<br />
campaigning. And Dr Hewson should tell us, as he called our<br />
One Nation Statemnent irresponsible, he should tell us why he<br />
is opposed to the Western Ring Road around Melbourne, why he<br />
wants traffic running through these suburbs, why he is<br />
opposed to the expansion of Tullamarine Airport, why he is<br />
opposed to the building of a standard gauge railway line<br />
between Melbourne and Adelaide to lift the commerce of this<br />
city, why he is opposed to putting our young childre~ n into<br />
technical and further education so that they have the<br />
opportunities in TAFE that others have had in universities<br />
why he is opposed to these things. Why he is he opposed to<br />
one-off payment to families, why he is opposed to on-going<br />
payments to ' the low paid and the families of the low paid.<br />
These are the things that he should tell us. And he. should </p>
<p>-2<br />
tell us how Australian women are going to wear the burden of<br />
the goods and services tax. He should tell us how they are<br />
going to carry that 15 per cent impost in their grocery<br />
bills, in their dry cleaning, in their clothing, in all of<br />
these other things. He should tell us about transfers<br />
within famil'. ies and how women who run households will get<br />
that 15 per cent transfer in their household budget to make<br />
the system work. He should tell us those things as well.<br />
And he shoul. d tell us particularly about why he believes a<br />
tax on our Kelloggs and our clothes and our shoes and our<br />
newspapers and our dry-cleaning and everything else is going<br />
to really make a dif ference to the way we live how it'Is<br />
going to fix: the railways, how it's going to fix the ports,<br />
how it's going to make the factories more efficient, how<br />
it's going to change the enterprises. These are the things<br />
which, of course, he hasn't been able to say because he<br />
knows that a goods and services tax won't fix these things.<br />
So, Labor will stand again for the sort of society it has<br />
always stood for progress, bringing the nation together,<br />
co-operation, looking after the disadvantaged, looking after<br />
low paid families, looking after families in general,<br />
looking after children and giving them their chance in<br />
secondary school, and beyond. These are the things we have<br />
always stood for and the things we will continue to stand<br />
for. And particularly now, inducing the recovery, having<br />
the Government get off the sidelines and into the action to<br />
promote a recovery in Australia, to bring employment and<br />
jobs to Australians, rather than sit on the sidelines<br />
offering tax cuts to the wealthiest people in society.<br />
That's what this battle is about and that's why I'm glad<br />
Bill is at my side in this by-election, as a person of<br />
substance in the electorate of Wills, a person of the<br />
community of the electorate of Wills, that people will<br />
relate to himi, people will relate to him as someone who has<br />
taken an active role in this community and as somebody who<br />
stands for al~ l of those ideals of Labor which we think are<br />
going to be important to Australians, now and always.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
