<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9941</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP 1996 PRIME MINISTERIAL WOMEN AND SPORT AWARDS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/02/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009941.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
r<br />
~ 4u<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
1996 PRIME MINISTERIAL WOMEN AND SPORT AWARDS<br />
There has been a suggestion that Samantha Riley has been exciuded from<br />
the Prime Ministeriai Women and Sport Awards.<br />
Winners of these awards are selected by a committee under the auspices of<br />
the Australian Sports Commission and are not decided by the Prime Minister<br />
or the Office of the Prime Minister.<br />
Reports of intervention by my Office following publicity surrounding the<br />
unfortunate incident involving Samantha Riley are completely without<br />
foundation, as confirmed by the Australian Sports Commission.<br />
As in previous years, the committee will decide the winners of this year's<br />
awards and I will be delighted to honour the achievements of those selected.<br />
All Australians feel great sympathy for the predicament Samantha Riley has<br />
found herself in as a result of the inadvertent use of a banned substance.<br />
She remains one of a number of outstanding Australian sportswomen and<br />
teams in contention for the Prime Ministerial Women and Sport Awards and<br />
for my own part I would be more than happy to present her with this award<br />
should she be the committee's choice.<br />
I confess to being a great fan of hers and I wish her well.<br />
MELBOURNE 14 FEBRUARY 1996<br />
41822 L S1 S/ St Pt As<br />
ch Sa<br />
Th th. th,<br />
Jo us to CA 14 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
