<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>55</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES, C.H., Q.C., M.P., AT CANBERRA ON THURSDAY, 12TH MARCH, 1959, AT 3.30 P.M.</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/03/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000055_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BZ THE PRIMI: 4 MINISTER, RiT. HON. R. G. MENZIES.<br />
C. HQ.. TCNER ON THURSDAY. 12TH MARCH. l9) 5. AT<br />
Up. m.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: Under-Secretaries, sir, have you made a decision<br />
on their future? You said in the Cabinet statement<br />
you would be considering this.<br />
No, not yet. I have been having some discussions<br />
on it in the last two days.<br />
There is a suggestion, sir, that you might have<br />
been considering them going on to the Executive<br />
Council. Would that be possible, sir?<br />
I have no idea. No, I have nothing to say about<br />
that yet.<br />
Can you te2.1 us, sir, if there is any legislation<br />
pending we haven't heard about. I mean in this<br />
session, not these sittings?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know what ones have been announced,<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: Sir, what has happened about the proposal to bring<br />
in legislation on union fees, or rather union<br />
charges for the political parties. I think<br />
before the elections there was some discussion that<br />
you may bring a Bill to prevent the victimnisation<br />
of people who refused to pay.<br />
Yes, I remember there was some discussion about that<br />
at the tail end of the last session the last<br />
Parliament but I have not seen anything on it of<br />
late. That is not to say that the Minister for<br />
Labour is not going into it.<br />
Has the Government made a final decision not to<br />
proceed with the F104+ in any form for the R. A. A. F.?<br />
That's the star fighter. We rejected that one a<br />
long time ago.<br />
That's finally rejected?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER: What about the 105 millimetre Lowitzer?<br />
Not that I know of. I think you had better ask the<br />
Minister for Defence that.<br />
Sir, at the opening of Parliament, Sir William Slim<br />
made some reference to Australia wanting to have<br />
closer trade links with Asia. Much the same thing<br />
has been said by Mr. Casey at the E. C. A. F. E.<br />
Conference. Do we take that as being a deliberate<br />
policy by Australia to try and strengthen her<br />
ties with Asia?<br />
Look, I'm not up with the discussions at E. C. A. F. E.<br />
I don't know about them yet and I would want to<br />
have a talk with Mr. Casey about that before I said<br />
anything on that point.<br />
His thinking was along the same lines as Sir<br />
Williama Slim in his policy speech by saying that<br />
we wanted closer trade links.<br />
Yes; but if you want some particulars on that, I<br />
am not able to give them to you. a<br />
11 0 1 </p>
<p>QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
COMMENT: It wasn't so much particulars, sir as to whether<br />
it was a sort of a general policy that we are now<br />
trying to establish ourselves as leaders or<br />
Western leaders in Asia tbarough trade and various<br />
other things.<br />
I think that's a very large inference. I think<br />
you ought to talk to the Minister for Trade as to<br />
vrhat the possibilities are, because I sometimes<br />
hear rather exaggerated estimates of them; but<br />
he's the expert on that. You ask him.<br />
Sir, in view of Mr. Casey's talks today with<br />
Mr. Firubin, can you tell us what advantages there<br />
will be for Australia in a physical resumption of<br />
diplomatic relations with Russia?<br />
No is Mr. Casey having talks with Mr. Firubin<br />
today? It has been reported so.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I didn't even know that.<br />
COMMENT I think Mr. Firubin announced it, sir.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Did he?<br />
COMMENT: Ye s.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh well, no doubt it's true.<br />
COMMENT: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: And reporting to Cabinet.<br />
Well, we've heard nothing about that. I ari not<br />
going to engage in a discussion of the pluses or<br />
minuses of something until it is something which<br />
calls for decision.<br />
Is it true that the International Bank has rejected<br />
the idea of a dollar loan for the Mt. Isa-Townsville<br />
railway be. cause Mt. Isa Mines wouldn't guarantee<br />
sufficient tonnage on the line?<br />
The whole nub of the argument there has been<br />
whether an effective freight contract can be made<br />
between the Queensland Government and the coinpany.<br />
So far, the result hasn't been entirely satisfactory;<br />
but I know that discussions are still going on, but<br />
they primarily concern the Queensland Government<br />
and the company, and it is not for mie to say what<br />
the point of view of the International Bank is.<br />
But I know that on its past practice, it would want<br />
to see an effective freight contract, so that the<br />
amount of any loan could be armortised within the<br />
appropriate time.<br />
Does the Commonwealth come into it at all, sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We come in as the borrower.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER-.<br />
QUESTION: Has the Bank rejected the request?<br />
Don't ask me to make announcements on behalf of<br />
the Bank; I'm one of their customers.<br />
Has the Commonwealth Treasircx, sir, had discussions<br />
with the company on any tax concessions that m~ ight<br />
help to get that kind of a contract you are<br />
speaking about?<br />
91. 1 0 1 </p>
<p>PRIM'-E MINISTER: Look, I know that the company has from time to<br />
time raised tax problems, but really, you ought to<br />
ask the Treasurer about that, I think. I mean I<br />
do' know what developments there are in that<br />
field.<br />
QUESTION: Does the Commonwealth have to give any guarantee,<br />
sir, along these lines?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: If the Conmmonwealth borrows money from the<br />
International Bank, it is the borrower and it is<br />
completely responsible. The Commonwealth then<br />
proceeds to lend the rioncy, and in that case, suppose<br />
and it's only a suppose suppose there<br />
were an International Bank loan for the Mt. Isa<br />
railway project, then we would be the borrowers<br />
and we would advance the money to the Queensland<br />
Government; and in order to enable us to pay off<br />
our debt and interest to the World Bank, the<br />
Queensland Government would enter into corresponding<br />
arrangements with us, and their capacity for doing<br />
that is quite plainly affected by the nature of<br />
, ihatever freight contract they make with the<br />
company. So it is a three-cornered affair. But the<br />
prime matter for discussion is one between the<br />
Queensland Government and the company. We have<br />
exhibited great willingness to do our part with the<br />
WJorld Bank and we hava had, of course, a number of<br />
discussions withi them. But whether there is a<br />
World Bank loan or not depends on many things:<br />
first and foremost, it depends on the decision taken<br />
some day by the board of the World Bank; nobody<br />
can anticipate that. But the basic material that<br />
would be needed before you made a formal applicatia<br />
for the loan would be some arrangement on freig ; hts<br />
between the Queensland Government and the company,<br />
of a kind which we thought, at any rate, fitted<br />
into the pattern of the lending policies of the World<br />
Bank,<br />
QUESTION: Sir, on the question of overseas investment, I<br />
think Mr. Foley of the British Tobacco Company<br />
made a statement recently saying that he was<br />
becoming rather worried about the overseas companies<br />
gradually taking over a vast number of Australian<br />
companies. Mr. McEwen has made a suggestion that<br />
it might be a good idea for every overseas investor<br />
to enter into partnership with Australian investors,<br />
Is that something that you<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think that it is first of all, we welcome<br />
overseas investment. The general Australian<br />
opinion does, because we can't generate inside<br />
Australia from our own resources P11 the capital<br />
that is needed for these developmental projects,<br />
~ hether they are public or private. think<br />
th4at it is eminently desirable that wher-ever it is<br />
po6ssible overseas investors should establish some<br />
kind of partnership with Australian citizens<br />
which means that wherever possible, they should<br />
admait Australian investors to the equity capital<br />
of the enterprise. We haven't laid down any rule<br />
about that. First of all, probably because we<br />
couldn't and secondly because circumastances differ<br />
in every case. But whenever overseas people see<br />
me or see my colleagues on this matter of investment<br />
we never fail to draw their attention to the<br />
fact that we think it desirable that they should<br />
have some Australian proprietary interest in<br />
whatever it is. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Sir, do you see any indication of thoso overseas<br />
investors coming more and imore to that point of<br />
view?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I th-ink I have of late yes.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: General Motors Holden, sir?<br />
I can't say that, because we know what their share<br />
structure is. But I think the last half dozen<br />
people of consequence in this matter who have come<br />
to see me just to have a general talk about policy<br />
have fully understood that point I'll say it<br />
that way.<br />
Sir, will there be a Commonwealth Prime Ministers'<br />
Conference in London this year, and if there is--<br />
Well, I think not; but that will be for Mr.<br />
MacMillan to decide. Frankly, I don't expect that<br />
there will be one. They've got all these<br />
preoccupations at the present time, and the Queen<br />
goes to Canada in June for a couple of months over<br />
the St. Lawrence waterway. Later on in the year<br />
wetve got a visit by Princess Alexandra. No; it's<br />
only my guess, but I think it's about right.<br />
Do you propose making an overseas trip yourself?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'm hoping to yes.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: Can you tell when you propose to make the visit?<br />
No I haven't arranged it yet, but I'm hoping to.<br />
I Lhink I should this year.<br />
It is tho first time since 1957, isn't it?<br />
Yas. Pay a brief visit at any rate, to America<br />
and Great Britain in particular, probably going<br />
through the one to the other.<br />
Corning back through the Far East, sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know yet.<br />
QUESTION: What time of the year?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'n11 hoping to do this in May-June.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, in relation to your recent invitation from<br />
Dr. Subandrio has that been confirmed at all by<br />
an official invitation froma President Soekarno.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. I've heard no more.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER: You wouldn't contemplate going under the present<br />
conditions? No, I would expect an invitation from the head of<br />
the Government, yes. I've heard nothing more<br />
about that.<br />
Can you give us any idea of the reasons why you<br />
want to go to America and Great Britain? Is there<br />
any particular subject you want to discuss?<br />
No. I think that the Prime Minister of Australia<br />
ought to be in direct personal touch with these<br />
people at reasonable intervals of time. It is<br />
very important. </p>
<p>QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: On the general subject matter foreign affairs,<br />
economics I want to if I go I want to have some direct<br />
intimate informal discussions about, no doubt, all<br />
the current matters as little program as possible.<br />
East Berlin in particular?<br />
Dontt ask me to say what the subjects are. Our<br />
experience of life is that all the subjocts that<br />
are current today are non-current in two months'<br />
time who knows. Whatever is a lively issue,<br />
I would hope to discuss.<br />
How long will you be away for?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, I don't ! now yet.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: Sir, would the rocent successes that the Government<br />
has been having with its internal loans lead you to<br />
expect that the overall cash deficit would be abou'k<br />
less than half what you anticipated last budget<br />
t i02<br />
I think it is very early to say that, but it will<br />
be substantially less, because the cash<br />
responsibilities on the loan program will quite<br />
plainly be lower and so there will be a reduced<br />
deficit. As a matter of fact, I noticed that when<br />
the Treasurer said the other day that he anticipateC<br />
there would be another deficit next year that's<br />
quite right; there must be somebody read into<br />
that an inference about taxes, but it has got<br />
nothing to do with that. I mean all other things<br />
being equal, I would anticipate that there would be~<br />
a cash deficit next year, for reasons sim11ilar to<br />
the ones that produced it this year.<br />
To a large extent, that would rule out any major<br />
tax concessions?<br />
Don't ask me that. W~ e won't begin to consider that<br />
until we are alpproaching the budget. And when we<br />
begin to approach the budget, you boys will all<br />
publish the mñ ost authoritative stories as to what<br />
is going to be in it, won't you? ( Laughter).<br />
Is there anything you can say, sir, about the<br />
Governor-Generalship on the departure of Sir<br />
William Slim and the appointment of a new one?<br />
No. We have a rather loose arrangement on that.<br />
I would think well, he won't go before Princess<br />
Alexandra has gone. I suppose that rmeans somewVhere<br />
about the end of the year. But we have got no<br />
hard and fast date in our rainds.<br />
Can we assumae that this will be one of the subject!,<br />
you will discuss when you are in Britain?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You could, yes.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER: Sir as you will be away in May and June, does<br />
thai maean we will havc a late budget, or what, or<br />
will you discuss the budget before you go?<br />
No; we never begin to discuss the budget until<br />
July. </p>
<p>COMENT: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: I thought there was always a preliminary discussion<br />
before the Premiers' Conference and Loan Council.<br />
The general state of affairs well, we've had that<br />
and therc will probably be another one before the<br />
next Premiers' Conference. We have to consider the<br />
problem of tax reimbursement, for example, and the<br />
overall state of the loan program. Yes, we discuss<br />
those things, and they have an effect on the<br />
budget. But we don't actually get to the problem<br />
of budgetting until after we have got rid of those<br />
things.<br />
Sir, have you made any definite arrangements as yet<br />
about the appointment of an independent committee<br />
to review the tax laws?<br />
Yes; it has been under discussion between Ministers<br />
and the Treasury. We have been working out the<br />
terms of reference. It is quite alive. I would<br />
hope to have something announced on that any moment<br />
in the next week or two; certainly quite soon.<br />
Mr. Menzies, is there any indication of when Sir<br />
Garfeild Barwick will be in a position to put<br />
submissions on constitutional changes to the<br />
Cabinet? Is it likely this year or early next year?<br />
I don't know. The first thing is to re-establish<br />
the committee. I think that will probably be done<br />
in the next week.<br />
Under his chairmanship?<br />
Well, that is one of the problems we have to<br />
consider, as to whether he can put in time on it.<br />
When we clear that up, we will * et the committee<br />
re-established, and they will go on with their<br />
-vork. They have made an interim report. We<br />
haven't considered the interim report. I don't<br />
know whether he has or whether he thinks that<br />
within some limited time he can make suggestions<br />
to us. But I haven't discussed that.<br />
I understand, sir, that Sir Frank Richardson has<br />
either delivered his report to you or is about to<br />
do so.<br />
They tell me that he is delivering it quite soon.<br />
It hasn't yet been delivered.<br />
Sir there is no hard and fast view as to whether<br />
youll wait until the new coimAittee has completed<br />
a further report before Cabinet considers the<br />
interim reDort of the coimittee?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, there's no hard and fast rule.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER: Sir, on that report, do any recormmendations apply<br />
from July 1, or will they<br />
My dear boy, I haven't a clue as to what the<br />
re commendations are.<br />
Any of them?<br />
I haven't a clue what they are. How can I start<br />
discussing problems of retrospectivity. For all<br />
I know, the reco-+ nendations are all negative. </p>
<p>COMMENT: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION:<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: I meant July 1 this year.<br />
I an not going to anticipate any of those things.<br />
I will read this report first when I get it.<br />
Did you read, sir, that the Scotch were burning<br />
your immigration literature?<br />
I saw that. I concluded it must have been a cold<br />
winter. ( Laughter).<br />
Mr. Menzies, there was an earlier question on<br />
possible legislation arising from the union<br />
political levies. Isn't the position that the<br />
Government is waiting for a High Court decision<br />
for the Burbury decision?<br />
I think you are right. I think that does have a<br />
bearing on it. But really I haven't given any<br />
thought to that matter myself lately, but now you<br />
mention it, the decision of the Court probably will<br />
throw a good deal of light on this thing. That is<br />
quite right. I don't know whether the Attorner<br />
has been looking at this.<br />
Sir, have you been asked to represent Australia at<br />
the Ii7, perial Cricket Conference at Lords in June?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, sir. Oh no, there's some limit. ( Laughter).<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: Sir is it proposed to introduce in the current<br />
sittings a Bill to authorise the secondf2 million<br />
grant for development of the north-west?<br />
Well, I hope so. There are always a few technical<br />
matters that have to be thrashed out on that and<br />
that may affect the dat_ of introduction. It won't<br />
affect the date of operation of the second<br />
million, because you remember that I said that<br />
we had agreed to find over a certain period of five<br />
years œ 29 million and that we would double that.<br />
Well, the œ 5 million covers the same period.<br />
So that unless the State gets on with the job in<br />
a hurry, they run the risk of losing portion of<br />
the œ 5 million?<br />
I don't know, but the original million was<br />
offered in relation to projects which were put<br />
forward by the States by Western Australia I<br />
mean and in a general way approved by us.<br />
Certain ones were put forward and approved and they<br />
are understood to be in hand. Subsequently to<br />
that, the Premier has put up a proposal in relatior<br />
to the Ord River, and it is not quite clear yet as<br />
to whether this is designed to be part of the<br />
million, or whether it is a separate project<br />
which he is asking for to be additional. The last<br />
I heard of that was that we had asked him for<br />
further information.<br />
I understood, sir, that in the House the other day<br />
you gave the impression that the Premier had<br />
now told you that most, if not all, of the<br />
million would be spend on the projects already<br />
approved by the Cormm1onwealth. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUJESTION: I don't think I said that. But having regard to<br />
the nature of' the projects, I wouldn't be surprised<br />
if they needed all the money, because they are<br />
quite substantial. I mean, our U23-million was<br />
really designed to help on that matter and I would<br />
think that these projects might easily absorb the<br />
whole sum; in which case, this Ord River proposal<br />
would be something additional; but at present I<br />
have asked to have that cleared up and until it is<br />
cleared up, it may be a little difficult to<br />
appropriate the œ C5 million for certain purposes<br />
with that matter still vague. And that may give<br />
rise to a little delay in introducing the<br />
legislation, but it won't give rise to any delay<br />
in our acceptance of our own responsibility from<br />
July, 1958, for five years, or the increased stun.<br />
Would it be a reasonable assumption, sir, that the<br />
second additional grant from the Commonwealth might<br />
only result in a saving for the State Treasury,<br />
the way the State intends to handle the scheme?<br />
Well, I suppose that's up to the State. We intended<br />
it to be of assistance in the development of' the<br />
north-west. But in all -these matters, one is very<br />
much in the hands of a State Government within<br />
whose area the particular things come.<br />
Mr. Menzies, are you going to appear on the platform<br />
with Mr. Morton for the elections in New South<br />
Wales? I don't Imow who's going to be there. I axi making<br />
a speech they tell me tomorrow night in North<br />
Sydney. I will go down and I will make a short<br />
speech and come home.<br />
Are you going to underwrite his promises?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'm not an underwriter. ( Laughter).<br />
QUESTION: Will this be your only appearance in the campaign?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
QUESTION: Are you also going to the iiest, sir?<br />
PRIMVE MINISTER: No.<br />
QUESTION:<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
COMMENT: PRIME MINISTER: Mr. Menzies, is it true that the Snowy Mountains<br />
Authority is spending ahead of its 1958/ 59<br />
allocation, and that -the Government has agreed to<br />
give it a supplementary grant until the and of the<br />
year to enable it to keep its work ahead of<br />
schedule. I roally think you ought to got that frorm Senator<br />
Spooner. Don't you think so? He's been handling<br />
that. I know about it mayself, but I'd very much<br />
prefer--Ijust thought you r. night be able to give us some<br />
details. I'd much prefer him to deal with it. I'll just<br />
say one thing about it: Yes, they have been ahead<br />
of their scheduled expenditure and at least one<br />
reason is a very satisfactory one and that is that<br />
the contractors have got on with the job so fast<br />
that really they have almost begun. to run out of<br />
" chips" </p>
<p>QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: It involves bonus payments to a great extent,<br />
doesn't it?<br />
Well I don't know how it's been done, but I know<br />
the Lthority is delighted with the efficiency,<br />
not only of the American contractors but of the<br />
Australian contractor, and of course I've got a<br />
rather favourable eye on expedition of this matter,<br />
because the sooner any stage is finished, the<br />
sooner it becor,-, cs revenue-producing. There has been<br />
a financial problem about it, but we thrashed that<br />
one out and I think I wouldn't trespass on the<br />
jurisdiction of m-] y colleague, but if you ask him,<br />
he could probably tell you about it.<br />
There is no suggestion that this extra grant will<br />
cone out of the 1959/ 60 allocation, which could<br />
force them to cut that work?<br />
No, whatever is done won't interfere with the flow<br />
of the job no. But ask him about that, because<br />
I don't like making statements on matters that one<br />
of my colleagues has been handling in Cabinet and<br />
on which he has secured agreement. But he's got<br />
an interesting story to tell, I should think, which<br />
you might ask him about.<br />
Were you pleased, sir, to have Sir Thomas Playford<br />
back . gain at your conference table this time?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: W-ell, it wouldn't be the same without him.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER: Sir, during the Preim. iers' Conference, Mr. Cahill<br />
m.. ade some reference: s to the future of the federal<br />
system. Do you believe that current Commonwealth-<br />
State financial relations and the temiper of the<br />
recent Pramiers' Conference have been jeopardised<br />
or could jeopardise the future of the federal<br />
system?<br />
As a matter of fact, I thought this last Promiers'<br />
Conference was the best tempered conference we have<br />
ever had. I did indeed. Of course, there is no<br />
question about it that uniform tax brings about a<br />
de facto result in constitutional balance that's<br />
quite true. But practically all the States have<br />
accepted that feature of life. As you have<br />
noticed, five out of six in the case of Victoria,<br />
of course, some of their troubles arise from the<br />
formula, and their disabilities on that matter are<br />
quite perceptible, because they arise from the<br />
fact that Victoria was a very low taxed State<br />
before uniform tax, you see. It was almost the<br />
lowest taxed State. State taxes in Queensland were<br />
probably three times as great as those in Victoria,<br />
It was the policy in Victoria to keep State income<br />
tax down, and if you establish a formula on the<br />
average of tax collections over a period of years<br />
then they are bound to suffer and they have. 0<br />
course the form~ ula has had its internal adjustment<br />
over ten years, so that it is now on adjusted<br />
population, which means population adjusted for the<br />
density and the number of school children between<br />
and 15. And Victoria says that is not quite a<br />
fair thing because there are other factors that<br />
ought to be taken into account. For example, they<br />
say: " I'le may have fewer school children per<br />
thousand than some other States, but we have had<br />
more migrants. Ile have had a considerable increase<br />
in our adult population. While that modifies </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER( continuing): relatively the demand on us for<br />
schools, it increases the demand on us for housing<br />
and services and other things." And then they<br />
also say: " We've had a very acute industrial<br />
development and all these developments in areas<br />
like Dandenong and Thomastown and out towards the<br />
hills and around Geelong by concentrating<br />
population in certain places sets up demands for<br />
now schools, whereas if your increase is more<br />
spread, existing schools with a little extension<br />
could cope with it." In other words, they say<br />
two factors have been selected: density of<br />
population, on which they are bound to lose as a<br />
small State, and school children population, and<br />
there are other factors. I stated quite plainly<br />
that I am not appy about this formula. I think<br />
that it is really the root of the Victorian<br />
trouble about uniform tax, and the day after the<br />
conference the Treasurer and I had a long<br />
discussion with Mr. Bolte and Mr. Rylah about the<br />
formula and invited then to make suggestions that<br />
we should be able to consider. At the same time,<br />
we are going into it, to do a little analysis<br />
ourselves with the idea of meeting the Premiers<br />
the next lime with some constructive proposals<br />
about how the formula ought to be stated. Then,<br />
of course, entirely apart from that, which is the<br />
formula of distribution, the formula amount itself<br />
has chronically proved inadequate and it may be<br />
that we ought to write a new formula, but sta: rt<br />
a new base year as wIl. The formula of increase<br />
will still go on; it works tolerably well, but<br />
it started too low.<br />
( TAPI:] TCAH IANGILD AT TTF] IS STi-IGE)<br />
, QUESTION: By the time you meet them, sir, do you expect to<br />
have a Cabinet decision on the payment of social<br />
services to aborigines?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh yes.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER: Mr. Menzies, some time ago Professor Bland<br />
criticised some unnamed civil servants for speaking<br />
in public on matters of policy and last night in<br />
the House, Dr. Coombs was also criticised for<br />
having made some statements in the Mills Memorial<br />
Lecture about the administration of monetary<br />
policy. I wonder if you could tell us what your<br />
own feeling is about the extent to which civil<br />
servants should be allowed to speak and the<br />
latitude they ought normally to be granted when<br />
speaking on matters of policy in public?<br />
sell, I always think it undesirable for any civil<br />
servant to speak publicly on matters of policy<br />
which civil servants have to administer, because<br />
that involves entering into the political field<br />
which I think is very undesirable, and I'm now<br />
talking about senior civil servants. Dr. Coombs,<br />
you know, is in rather a different position. He<br />
is Governor of the Bank, and the Bank is set up<br />
it is not a branch of the civil service like any<br />
of the departments and he, of course, with his<br />
board, makes an annual report in which many<br />
coamients and observations are made relevant to the<br />
operations of the central bank, and if a man of<br />
that distinction is invited to do the Roy Milne<br />
Lecture they even got me to do it once many<br />
years ago on some aspect of central banking, or<br />
.1 </p>
<p>11.<br />
PRIME MINISTE~ R<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: ( continuing) discussing the problems of' central<br />
banking, I think it would be depriving people of'<br />
valuable expert Imowledge if there were sonie rule<br />
that he couldn't do it. But ho would use his<br />
discretion; ha always does in my experience. I've<br />
never knowrn him to exceed the bounds of proper<br />
discretion on those things. I very groatly admire<br />
his discretion and judgment.<br />
In his speech on banking the other night, Dr.<br />
Evatt suggested that the establishment of' the new<br />
money market had been organised in the arbitrary<br />
grant of access to the market to a chosen number of'<br />
stockbrokers, in order to make it possible for them<br />
to in sonmway skim the creara on Government bond<br />
dealings in the various m-. arkets<br />
Yes, I heard that said. As a miatter of fact, the<br />
possibility of having a short-term money market has<br />
been under discussion for many many years. An<br />
abortive atte,:. ipt was made to do it in a small way<br />
about 20 years ago more than 20 years ago. A<br />
short-term money market has great advantages as<br />
the experience in bigger countries shows; but, as<br />
it happens on this occasion, the idea of this kind<br />
of entry into a short-term money market was<br />
promoted by the Commronwealth Bank, very powerfullynot<br />
by somebody else. And after a long examination<br />
proved by us, and in order to miake it operate<br />
certain people enter into relations with the<br />
Commonwealth Bank and with their own banks all<br />
that is quite normal. A's it happens, the creative<br />
idea on this matter cana from the Bank.<br />
That doesn't rule out the possibility of others<br />
entering into the same relationship?<br />
Oh no there's no monopoly rights here. They'll<br />
have lo comply with certain conditions which relate<br />
to their stability and so on, but the bank will see<br />
to that.<br />
A ny views, sir, on the Berlin question?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No; there is nothing at this stage.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER: W~ ill Sir Arthur Fadden be going into the bank job,<br />
sir? I haven't a cluo. Legislation is not through yet.<br />
I might apply for it myself. ( Laughter). Well,<br />
it would be the fifteenth job I've been nominated<br />
for. ( Laughter).<br />
In the last few days in the House at least three<br />
Government backbenchers, while praising certain<br />
points of the legislation, have said more should<br />
be done to protect various aspects would it be<br />
true to say that the Government has completely<br />
closed the door to further amiendmients, or not?<br />
Is the way still open at a later stage?<br />
Look, the Government has had an examination of all<br />
the points that have been raised both ways this<br />
year. The Treasurer has had long discussions with<br />
a few mornbers who had particular ideas. We~ then<br />
examinod the whole of those; we made two<br />
amendments; and so far as I arm concerned, that<br />
is it. There has been no suggostion mnade to me<br />
that Cabinet should re-consider any of these<br />
decisions. They were discussed for a very very<br />
long time. </p>
<p>12.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER:<br />
QUESTION: Do you expect to be going overseas before the next<br />
Premiers'I Conference?<br />
I don't know the date of the Premiers' Conference<br />
yet, so I don't know. I was saying something<br />
earlier that I think it desirable to go overseas<br />
this year some time May-June, somewhere round<br />
that period.<br />
Will you be away for long, sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know yet.<br />
QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER: Will you fly all the way, sir, or go by sea part<br />
of the way?<br />
( lell, I had a good look at my wife the other day<br />
and I decided that if anybody ever wanted a<br />
fortnight's holiday, it was may wife. She is<br />
greatly overuorked. I think I might get her on<br />
to the water for a little while.<br />
With the complim~ ents of:<br />
Hugh Dash,<br />
Press Secretary to the Prime Minister,<br />
CiINBERRA, A. C. T.<br />
0-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
