<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3695</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S SPEECH AT THE COMMEMORATION DINNER, PORT AUGUSTA, SOUTH AUSTRALIA, 11 APRIL 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/04/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003695.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH AT THE COMMEMORATION DINNER, 2y<br />
PORT AUGUSTA, SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
11.4.<br />
M4r. Wallis, Mr. Smith, Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
We are meeting tonight at the road and rail crossroads<br />
of Australia and we are meeting on a very great occasionan<br />
important place, an important landmark in our history.<br />
It was from this place in 1912 that the East-West Railway<br />
commencod construction and tomorrow at Tarcoola we will<br />
see the commencement of construction of the biggest railway<br />
project since then.<br />
This has been a remarkable week in the history of railways<br />
in Australia. On Wednesday we tabled in the Federal<br />
Parliament the terms of agreement by which the Commonwealth<br />
Railways acquired' the South Australian Railways with the<br />
consent of South Australia. Yesterday we passed through<br />
both Houses of the Federal Parliament the Australian National<br />
Railways Commission Bill, and, once the Governor-General has<br />
signed that Bill, the Commonwealth Railways will become the<br />
Australian National Railways; the A. N. R. And yesterday, too,<br />
we introduced in the Federal Parliament the Inter-State<br />
Commission Bill to establish that great instrument of national<br />
co-ordination and unityywhich the Constitution ordains.<br />
Before I come to describe some of these things, may I pay<br />
a tribute to the manner in whi~ h the Commonwealth Railways<br />
has just met a great test. For the first time since 19* 12,<br />
the creek at Zanthus flowed and broke through the railway.<br />
Within a fortnight the breach has been restored. The<br />
Commonwealth Railways proved well able to cope with sudden<br />
emergencies, unprecedented emergencies and ruptures.<br />
What I want to speak about tonight is the great constructive,<br />
creative role which is being played by the A. N. R. and, by<br />
railways in general in our nation. In no area of Government<br />
respoonsibility is there a greater need for modernisation and<br />
reform than the railways. In no area have there been greater'<br />
Constitutional and administrative obstacles to reform. The<br />
railways are usually historically regarded as the great<br />
instrument for unifyihng a continent. It was Transcontinentals<br />
that united the United States, united the Canadian provinces<br />
and united the Soviet Union from the Baltic to the Pacific.<br />
One would have thought that railways would be the great<br />
instrument for uniting Australia. It has not turned out that<br />
way, because our railways were started in the middle of last<br />
century by the States and they are still run, with the exception<br />
of the by the States. This occurs in the Australian<br />
Federal system only. In West Germany the railways are run by </p>
<p>the Federal Government. In Canada there are two great<br />
railway systems, one run by the Canadian Government and<br />
the other by a nationwide, an international company. In<br />
the United States all the railway systems are co-ordinated<br />
by the Interstate Commerce Commission. In Australia, far<br />
from uniting our country, the railway systems have been<br />
organised so as to disrupt the unification of the nation.<br />
They have been used to centralise our settlement, our<br />
commerce, in State capitals. There is, fortunately, a<br />
provision in the Constitution which enables the Commonwealth<br />
with the consent of the States to build or to acquire railways.<br />
It was because the States of South Australia and Western<br />
Australia permitted the Commonwealth to build a railway, that<br />
w.. e got the East-West railway. It was for that reason that<br />
we got the old railway, which is always prone to floods from<br />
Qodnadatta up to the Northern Territory border. It is because<br />
of that provision that the Commonwealth, with the consent of<br />
the State of South Australia, is now acquiring the nonmetropolitan<br />
railways in South Australia. And this will<br />
transform the railway scene in Australia, east and west and<br />
north and south. It will be a very significant system and<br />
it will be an immense re-inforcement and multiplication<br />
of the things that can be done.<br />
I look back to the first year or so I was in Federal<br />
Parliament. The Chifley Government, under a Prime<br />
Minister who was a dedicated railway man, had placed the<br />
orders to modernise the Commonwealth Railways which had<br />
always been the most losing railway proposition in Australia.<br />
I came into Parliament just when the orders were being<br />
fulfilled. The Commonwealth Railways became the first in<br />
Australia to have every locomotive a diesel, to have every<br />
carriage air-conditioned, to have every wagon with bolies.<br />
Within the course of a year they became the most profitable<br />
railway system in Australia. That illustrated to me that,<br />
with proper equipment and proper capitalisation, railways<br />
could be profitable.<br />
But the railway system still ran from nowhere to nowhere<br />
in national-commercial terms. It ran from Port Pinie'to<br />
Kalgoorlie, which meant that every load, every passenger,<br />
every piece of freight had to come over another system.<br />
In 1972 one of the first Acts of my Government was to make<br />
an offer to each of the States to accept responsibility for<br />
the railways of that State. You see the first acceptance<br />
of that offer, by South Australia. We will now have a<br />
system where there will be a merger of the South Australian<br />
Railways and the Commonwealth Railways. It will be possible<br />
to cross the whole continent, east . or west, with the same<br />
carriages, wagons and diesel locomotives. It will put an<br />
end, I hope, to this absurd situation that, even after we<br />
had the same gauge right across the continent,' the locomotives<br />
had to be changed at Broken Hill and at Pinie and </p>
<p>at Kalgoorlie. It has been a farce up till now. The<br />
Commonwealth Railways, the Australian National Railways,<br />
the are now the key to rail transport, the basic<br />
form of transport in this nation. They will soon join with<br />
the Victorian Railways in operating between Adelaide and<br />
Melbourne. We shall soon see how unified a force, how<br />
excel-lent an investment it is to have railways of a national<br />
character. Railways can more safely, more quickly, more<br />
economically, transport goods long distance than any other<br />
transport mode that man has devised.<br />
I now come to another achievement of this week the Bill to<br />
establish the Inter-State Commission. In my 1972 policy<br />
speech, I said " The Inter-State Commission was intended<br />
to end the centralisation fostered by all the State governments<br />
through their railway systems. It-should now provide not<br />
only for the co-ordination of our six mainland railway systems<br />
and our major ports in the period before the Commonwealth,<br />
like other federal governments, inevitably takes responsibility'<br />
for railways and ports; it is also the ideal instrument for<br />
co-ordinating our major roads and airlines and pipelines."<br />
" A Federal Labor Government-will promptly restore the<br />
machinery the Constitution intended and vest it with the<br />
Commonwealth's full constitutional powers to plan and<br />
provide modern means of communications between the States."<br />
One of the pieces of legislation we were able to put through<br />
last year was the agreement between the Australian and South<br />
Australian Governments for the Australian Government to build<br />
the standard gauge railway between Adelaide and Cryst'al Brook.<br />
When that is finished, it will be possible to go by train from<br />
any State capital to the next State capital and, except for4<br />
Melbourne, from any State capital to any other State capital<br />
without a break of gauge.<br />
One of the great handicaps to profitable railway operation<br />
in this country has been the lack of adequate rolling'stock.<br />
At present railways need over 3,000 extra wagons for intersystem<br />
travel alone. It has been estimated that the Victorian,<br />
South Australian, New South Wales and Commonwealth Railways<br />
lost over $ 65 million in 1972-73 because they were not able<br />
to meet the demands-of inter-system travel. Therefore, in<br />
this year's budget, last September, we embarked upon a<br />
continuing rolling stock purchasing program which, over<br />
the next two years, will provide some 1300 modern bogey<br />
wagons for inter-system use. These wagons will be available<br />
for lease to the States. </p>
<p>4.<br />
Tomorrow we embark upon the construction of the railway<br />
from Tarcoola to Alice Springs, the largest railway project<br />
which Australia has undertaken since before the First World<br />
War and one which will make an immense difference to the<br />
people in The Centre. It will make a great difference to<br />
the tourist industry, the cattle industry, the mining<br />
industry. I have always found romance in the construction of railways.<br />
Railways were a distinguishing feature of those industrial<br />
countries which were settling vast new areas. The United<br />
States, the old Tsarist Empire, Canada, all did it. Australia<br />
had to wait to do it this century. A new railway has always<br />
carried with it an aura of romance, a spirit of pioneering.<br />
Nothing suggests more vividly the determination of a vigorous<br />
society to develop its resources and improve its communications.<br />
Something was missing from our national life during the long<br />
years when the r4ilways were allowed to decline. Men and<br />
families who have given a lifetime of service to the railways<br />
were encouraged to lose faith in the importance and future of<br />
a great industry. I hope and believe that we are seeing tonight<br />
the rebirth of the railways in this continent, the beginning<br />
of a new era of growth and development. You can be sure that<br />
my Government will do its utmost to see the railways prosper<br />
and resume their rightful, their historic role as the basis<br />
of an efficient, modern and economical transport system.<br />
A remarkable week it has been. A great disaster strikes<br />
the Transcontinental railway; * it is overcome within a fortnight.<br />
We set out to re-establish the Inter-State Commission ordained<br />
in the Constitution. With the consent of South Australia, we<br />
acquire the South Australian Railways. We create the Australian<br />
National Railways. 1<br />
It is appropriate to have this commemoration in Port Augusta<br />
where it all began, where it all passes. Prosperous and<br />
efficient railways are an efficient and essential condition<br />
of a prosperous and efficient nation.<br />
I give you the toast The Railways of Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
