<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6821</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, BALLARAT, 25 JANUARY 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/01/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006821.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I# TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE BALLARAT<br />
January 25 1986<br />
0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, I was wondering COcl I ask<br />
you yesterday the ALP decided to put off the whole Hartley<br />
saga for another ten days. Does that damage the ALP in<br />
the interim?<br />
PM: No, not at all. YOu have got to realise that that<br />
Executive is composed of very busy people with important<br />
commitments. For instance, the President, Neville Wran,<br />
the Premier of New South Wales. And he just can't day<br />
after day, and they have got to ensure that the situation<br />
is handled fairly. And that adjournment is quite appropriate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Ten days. that is a lot of time?<br />
PM: Let me assure you, in moving around Australia, I know<br />
what the feeling is on this matter. It is not doing the<br />
ALP any harm at all. If you are worrying about factionalism<br />
don't look at the ALP. Look at the other mob.<br />
JOURNALIST: Sir, that is the point. there is factionalism<br />
in the Liberal Party. But it would appear that you could<br />
make a great deal of mileage out of this one if you wanted<br />
to be a critic of the ALP.<br />
PM: I wouldn't have thought so. What we are about is dealing<br />
with a situation of a person who has made statements which<br />
are seen not to be in the interests of the Party And so<br />
regarded. Now a judgement is in the process of being made<br />
as to whether continued membership of the Party is<br />
appropriate. It is reasonable in those circumstances that<br />
the Party not rush the judgement, that they should treat<br />
it fairly. And far from this being a negative course for<br />
the Party and for the Government the opposite is true.<br />
It is seen to be dealing with-this issue seriously and<br />
fairly and giving all opportunities that need to be given<br />
to the person concerned. That is the way it should be done.<br />
JOURNALIST: It is a case of copping the damage in the short<br />
term<br />
PM: NO damage. The contrary is the case -that an important<br />
issue should be dealt with fairly. All opportunity should<br />
be given. That is being done. NOw, this is not stopping </p>
<p>us from getting on with the business of not just policy<br />
formulation, but Policy implementation. We are governing<br />
the country, we know what we are about. We know our purposes,<br />
we know our policies. If you look at the Liberals, well<br />
of course, I suppose from mirth really, they haven't got<br />
a policy about anything on which they are not wracked with<br />
division. Doesn't matter whether you look at tax or wages<br />
or privatisation, if I can mention that dreadful word.<br />
They don't know where they are.<br />
JOURNALIST: But the Liberals would have chopped Hartley qA(&amp; ktq.<br />
PM: NO. The Liberals are different the way they handle<br />
things. Of course they do expel people. YOu ask Mr Francis<br />
in Victoria. They get rid of people. But there they isolate<br />
them. Mr Howard doesn't like a particular group. Well<br />
then he dumps them from the front bench. And now in that<br />
si'tuation they go off and form their little groups to undermine<br />
Mr Howard. It is a very interesting little kettle of fish<br />
the Liberal Party in Australia at the moment. No wonder<br />
they haven't won an election in mainland Australia since<br />
1980.<br />
PM: Why wouldn't the Labor Party chop a person like Hartley<br />
as quickly?<br />
PM: When you are going to say we are considering whether<br />
a person is not going to be any longer a member of a party,<br />
a person who has been there for a period of time. It is<br />
fair and it is proper that the processes are taken through<br />
so that the person in question can have all the opportunity.<br />
If he has got witnesses he says he wants to present, okay,<br />
they should be presented, should be listened to. And that<br />
is what is happening.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime MInister, on another important issue<br />
cricket. Greg Chappell has criticised the planned appointment<br />
of Olive Lloyd he says it is a political stunt.<br />
PM: Of course, Mr Chappell is known to have no involvement<br />
or interest in politics. Like hell. You talk about politics<br />
he is a political figure. And that is good, I am glad<br />
ex-cricketers get involved in politics. But don't let Mr<br />
Chappell stand up and let it be said that he is a non-political<br />
person making a simply sporting statement. That is not<br />
true. And I say to Greg, good on you, get into politics.<br />
But don't try and delude people that you are not in politics<br />
as well. Now on the issue itself. This is a matter for<br />
decision by the Institute of Sport. We fund the Institute.<br />
We have an interest in promoting sport in Australia. But<br />
I am not going to be saying what their decision is if<br />
their decision is to appoint Clive Lloyd, and I make it<br />
quite clear that there have be~ n discussions in which my<br />
opinion has been sought. Not in terms of saying that this<br />
is what happens. But I have respect for Olive Lloyd<br />
as do 99.999 per cent of Australians. If it is the case<br />
that they appoint Mr Lloyd, then I am sure he will do a<br />
brilliant job. And certainly the cricketers and the young<br />
cricketers of Australia would be very well served. But<br />
I repeat the main point is the decision on this matter is<br />
not mine, it is not the Government's, it is the Institute's. </p>
<p>3.<br />
JOURNALIST: But wouldn't you personally prefer a great<br />
Australian cricketer to take up the post?<br />
PM: I am a person who, I guess there is no-one in Australia<br />
who has greater pride in his country than I have. I talk<br />
consistently and with conviction about Australia's achievements<br />
and I do that in this country and outside. But I am not<br />
only an Australian. I am a person who, I hope, has a capacity<br />
to look beyond our own borders and I am not punning there<br />
when I am talking about cricket but we must do as Australians,<br />
whether it is in sport or in other fields of endeavour,<br />
is to draw upon the best resources that are available.<br />
This is not an isolated world in which you put a barrier<br />
up around you. And say here we are, we have got the best<br />
of everything. If there are others who can help us whether<br />
it is in cricket or in art, industry, commerce, if we can<br />
draw on other resources we should do it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you made any personal representatiora<br />
in favour of Lloyd.<br />
PM: I have been engaged in some discussions not really<br />
in a sense as Prime Minister, although that is part of it,<br />
but as a passionate cricket follower. I have had the opportunity<br />
of talking with Mr Bennett. And this issue has been canvassed.<br />
NOt just the name of Olive Lloyd, others. But what I believe<br />
is that Australia needs to develop its resources in cricket<br />
perhaps in a more criticism of what has happened to<br />
them. But I think we can do more. And so you draw upon<br />
wh ' atever resources are available to do that great deal<br />
of confidence in the future of Australian cricket. We went<br />
through a trough. I think we have hit the bottom and we<br />
are very much on the way up. We have got some very, very<br />
talented young Australians emerging now that are in the<br />
team or on the edge of the team. And I think what we have<br />
got to do now is plan for the future to make'sure that we<br />
keep those young people coming up.<br />
JOURNALIST: won't win the current one day series?<br />
PM: Well, there is always a chance in sport that you won't<br />
win but you have got to be confident and you have also got<br />
to study form. And on disclosed form we deserve to be,<br />
as we are, favourites. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
