<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8610</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, AND THE MINISTER FOR LAND TRANSPORT, THE HON BOB BROWN MP. FEDERAL GOVERNEMENT APPROVES $4704 MILLION FOR SOUTH AUSTRALIA RAIL PROJECTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/08/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008610.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINJISTER<br />
joint statement by the Prime Minister, the<br />
HoD P J Keating, and the Minister for Land<br />
Transport, the Hon Bob Brown MIP.<br />
FEDERAL GOVERNMIENT APPROVES $ 47.4 MILLION<br />
FOR SOUTH AUSTRALI[ AN RAIL PROJECTS<br />
The Federal Governument today approved the $ 47.4 million first instalment in its One<br />
Nation upgrading program for South Australian railways. The funding will create about<br />
1200 new jobs.<br />
The largest single expenditure item is a $ 45 million contribution towards converting the<br />
Adelaide-Melbourne railway line to standard gauge. A further $ 2 million will be used to<br />
increase the height of eight bridges on the Adelaide-Kalgoorlie route to facilitate, in the<br />
long term, trains carrying double-stacked containers to operate with safe clearances.<br />
Design work for the rail loop to be built adjacent to the Adelaide Outer Harbour No 6<br />
container terminal will proceed following the release of S400 000 of One Nation funding.<br />
Eventually, the $ 8 million facility will help create an integrated ship, road and rail freight<br />
transfer facility.<br />
The Prime Minister, Paul Keating, and the Minister for Land Transport, Bob Brown, said<br />
today that the combined effect of the Federal Government investment would be to<br />
enhance Adelaide's reputation as a transport hub serving much of Southern Australia.<br />
' It is estimated that the Outer Harbour improvements alone will mean that 50 000<br />
additional containers could be shipped through the Port-of Adelaide, which will become<br />
an international terminal specialising in high priority containers under the One Nation<br />
strategy', Mr Keating and Mr Brown said in a joint statement.<br />
All three projects announced today support the interstate freight operations of National<br />
Rail, the organisation which the Federal Government and the governments of New South<br />
Wales, Victoriai, Queensland and Western Australia agreed to establish last year.<br />
National Rail will take over and manage all interstate rail freight services throughout<br />
Australia. 2<br />
1101 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Mr Keating and Mr Brown said the effects of this decision on the residual r., leinents of<br />
Australian National would be announced within the context of the Federal Budget.<br />
They said the $ 45 million to be spent on converting the line between Adelaide and<br />
Melbourne would meet the cost of supplying and installing concrete sleepers on the<br />
section from Adelaide to Kiki, track and crossing loop conversion and some work in<br />
connection with acquiring STA track.<br />
' From Kiki to the border, existing timber sleepers will be replaced with gauge-convertible<br />
concrete sleepers under an existing Federal Government project. Concrete sleepers have<br />
the advantages of reduced maintenance costs and fewer speed restrictions'.<br />
Mr Keating and Mr Brown said that following installation of gauge convertible sleepers,<br />
one rail on the line would be moved inwards to conform with the standard gauge<br />
measurement of 1435 mm. T7his would take place over a two and a half week period<br />
early in 1994.<br />
' Rail clearances will be increased between Adelaide and Kalgoorlie by raising the height<br />
of bridges or lowering the track at eight locations in the long term. Ibis will facilitate<br />
trains carrying double-stacked containers in well wagons while maintaining safety<br />
clearances'. Mr Keating and Mr Brown said the revitalisation of rail transport under One Nation were<br />
supported by other government initiatives, such as waterfront reform and more<br />
streamlined administration of the road transport industry.<br />
' All these measures will have far-reaching effects on transport efficiency and Australia's<br />
ability to compete effectively in world markets, particularly in those commodities with a<br />
high transport cost component', they said.<br />
Sydney 6 August 1992<br />
For more information, contact Richard Desmond ( 06) 274 7306<br />
1102 </p>
<p>ONE NATION EARLY START PROJECTS<br />
PERTH TO ADELAIDE ADELAIDE<br />
FREMANTLE ISLINGTON UPGRADING<br />
To faclltate clarances for continer stacking $ 2.0m PURCHASE OF MATERIALS FOR<br />
USE ON THE NATIONAL SYSTEM<br />
Manufacture of concrete leepers<br />
Purchase of rail $ 2.7m </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
