<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1676</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: MEETING BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTERS OF NEW ZEALAND AND AUSTRALIA JOINT COMMUNIQUE</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/10/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001676.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS MEETING BETWEEN THE FRIME MINISTERS<br />
CF NEV' ZEALAND AND AUSTRALIA.<br />
JOINT CCMMUNICUE<br />
Mr Holyoake and Mr Holt have had several discussions<br />
in Canberra during the past two days on matters of common interect.<br />
The New Zealand Minister for Defence ( Mr Thomsort and Australian<br />
Ministers participated. New Zealand and Australian officials were also<br />
present. These talks were supplemented by separate discussions among<br />
the officials. Both Mr Holyoake and Mr Holt had indicated ' n statements<br />
before the meeting that they did not see the'r discussions as leading up to<br />
any immediate decisions. The talks form part of the process of regular<br />
and continuous consultations between the New Zealand and Australian<br />
Governments. The talks ranged over a wide field. The major questions<br />
discussed were in the areas of defence and foreign policy. The two<br />
Governments are pursuing common obj ectives and the problems they face<br />
are similar. Consequent on the Brtish Government's announcement<br />
of a progressive reduction in forces in South East Asia, both the New<br />
Zealand and Australian Governments are in process of reviewing their<br />
respective defence arrangements. The discussions have been most useful.<br />
As both Mr Holyoake and Mr Holt have previously stated, it will be<br />
necessary to consult other interested governments.<br />
Both countries have forces engaged and operating together<br />
in Viet Nam. Both countries are also giving economic and other civil<br />
assistance ' n Viet Nam. The Viet Nam situation and the prospects for<br />
peaceful settlement there are major preoccupations of both Governments<br />
and the opportunity to consult has been valuable.<br />
Mr Holyoake and the Australian Deputy Frime IV nister,<br />
Mr McEwen, discussed trade relations between Australia and New Zealand,<br />
including the New Zealand/ A ustral'a Free Trade Agreement.<br />
All the talks were held in a most friendly and co-operative<br />
atmosphere. Mr Holyoake's visit to Canberra was welcomed by the<br />
Australian Prime Minister as an opportunity for the Australian Government<br />
to ascertain at first hand the views of the New Zealand Government on<br />
matters which concern both countries. Mr Holyoake also saw the talks<br />
as reflecting the close relations between the two Governments which are<br />
resolved to continue to work closely together.<br />
FRIME MINISTER'S CFFICE,<br />
CANBERRA. 4TH OCTOBER, 1 ' 7.<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
