<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7681</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPENING OF THE FIRST NATIONAL CONFERENCE OF OFFICIALS OF THE AUSTRALIAN WORKERS&#039; UNION SURFERS PARADISE - 14 JULY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/07/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007681.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING OF THE FIRST NATIONAL CONFERENCE OF<br />
OFFICIALS OF TEE AUSTRALIAN WORKERS' UNION<br />
SURFERS PARADISE 14 JULY 1989<br />
Errol Hodder,<br />
Friends. The Australian Workers' Union holds a very special place -in<br />
the history of trade unionism and the history of the<br />
Australian Labor Party.<br />
More than a century ago, forty shearers joined together in<br />
the pursuit of better wages and working conditions and<br />
formed the Amalgamated Shearers' Union, the forerunner of<br />
the AWU. For more than a century your union has played a<br />
vital role in improving, through the processes of<br />
consultation and conciliation, the wages and working<br />
conditions of your members.<br />
In 1891, when members of the shearers, unions were faced<br />
with the imminent collapse of their great strike, the<br />
historic decision was made to pursue their just cause<br />
through the ballot box.<br />
And so, with the active support of working men and women<br />
throughout Australia, was founded one of the world's first<br />
labour parties the Australian Labor Party.<br />
It is as leader of that Party, as leader of a proudly Labor<br />
Government, and as a committed trade unionist, that I feel<br />
honoured to open the first national conference of officials<br />
of the Australian Workers' Union.<br />
What the Amalgamated Shearers, Union set out to achieve in<br />
1886 was the goal, through effective organisation, of better<br />
and more secure living standards and working conditions for<br />
members. That remains the primary challenge of the modern<br />
trade union movement.<br />
But it is a proof of the complexity of the modern economy,<br />
of the magnitude of the challenges facing Australia and, not<br />
least, of the maturity and capacity of the Australian trade<br />
union movement, that we meet today to discuss issues of<br />
broader, of national, significance. </p>
<p>My friends,<br />
we meet at a time when union/ government co-operation is at a<br />
level unsurpassed in Australian history.<br />
Over the last six years, the Accord years, the Australian<br />
labour movement has shown what can be achieved when<br />
governments and trade unions work together. It is with a<br />
sense of pride that I assert that together, we have produced<br />
economic achievements of fundamental and lasting importance,<br />
not only to trade union members, but to all Australians.<br />
Nowhere is this better illustrated than in our record of job<br />
creation. New figures yesterday from the Bureau of<br />
Statistics confirmed the massive growth in jobs in the<br />
Australian economy. Nearly 1.5 million jobs have been<br />
created in the Australian economy since we took office a<br />
rate of employment growth over twice the OECD average and<br />
over four times that of the previous Government.<br />
This unprecedented employment growth has slashed the<br />
unemployment rate from double digit levels down to<br />
6 per cent the lowest it has been for seven and a half<br />
years. Inflation has fallen from 11 per cent to around 7 per cent.<br />
Economic growth has averaged around 4 1/ 4 per cent a year<br />
over the past six years.<br />
These achievements have been the direct result of the trade<br />
union movement's willingness to accept real wage restraint.<br />
It was a watershed decision taken by unionists in 1983.<br />
They could legitimately have pursued a strategy of increased<br />
wages for themselves but chose instead, through wage<br />
restraint, to expand dramatically the number of jobs in<br />
Australia and the overall competitiveness of the economy.<br />
At the same time, as an integral part of the Accord, real<br />
wage restraint was accompanied by Government commitment to<br />
lifting the social wage.<br />
As a result of that commitment, this Government has a social<br />
justice record second to none.<br />
There have been major increases in Government assistance for<br />
low income families, real increases in pensions and<br />
benefits, reforms to the education system and the<br />
restoration and improvement of universal health coverage.<br />
Through all these means we have significantly eased the<br />
burden of restraint on those who are most in need in our<br />
community. </p>
<p>I recall the words of Bill Kelty at the 1987 ACTU Congress<br />
when he said that the benefits offered the less well off<br />
through the Government's Family Assistance Package<br />
represented gains in living standards that would have taken<br />
years to achieve by traditional industrial means.<br />
Underpinning all this, we have reformed the taxation system.<br />
We have progressively cut the levels of-income tax, and we<br />
have ended the capital gains and fringe benefits rorts<br />
whereby the ordinary taxpayer assumed an unnecessarily large<br />
burden of the tax bill and whereby tax payment by the well<br />
off was more a matter of choice than obligation.<br />
Not least of the achievements of the Accord was the wage/ tax<br />
negotiations in the lead up to the April Statement which<br />
delivered a $ 5.7 billion package of tax cuts and family<br />
assistance, while achieving continued restraint in the<br />
growth of labour costs for Australian industry.<br />
As Paul Keating said at the time, that was a result that<br />
only a Labor Government could have delivered, working<br />
through the processes of the Accord.<br />
Last week the first of these tax cuts flowed into the pay<br />
packets of Australian workers.<br />
Even before these tax cuts, previous tax reforms, increased<br />
family assistance and our massive increase in jobs had<br />
lifted per capita real disposable income by more than<br />
since 1982-83.<br />
My friends,<br />
We stand today on the threshold of further improvements in<br />
the remuneration and job satisfaction of Australian workers<br />
improvements being progressively negotiated through the<br />
historic processes of award restructuring.<br />
Through award restructuring, we are achieving productivity<br />
improvements that go to the essential question of<br />
Australia's economic competitiveness and, therefore, of our<br />
future prosperity. And we are doing so with consensus and<br />
cooperation across the parties, ensuring that decisions made<br />
are the right ones and the gains made are permanent ones.<br />
Through the Accord, wage fixing in Australia has progressed<br />
from a rigid system that merely followed price movements, to<br />
a system that is a catalyst to labour market reform and<br />
productivity improvement.<br />
What is significant and what is completely different from<br />
the Liberals' proposals to abandon the system of centralised<br />
wage fixing is that the flexibility of this process is<br />
going hand in hand with an institutional structure that<br />
protects the industrially weak while still producing a<br />
responsible aggregate wages outcome. </p>
<p>Award restructuring provides an unprecedented opportunity<br />
for workplace reform reform which is essential if<br />
Australia is to enter the 21st century with an<br />
internationally competitive economy and if we are to protect<br />
our living standards for future generations.<br />
At its simplest, award restructuring leads to two main<br />
gains: the first is the removal of obsolete job<br />
classifications and the broadbanding of-jobs under an<br />
appropriate single classification; the second is the<br />
establishment of skill-based career paths.<br />
Already in some key industries, the parties have reached<br />
agreement on award restructuring proposals. The Industrial<br />
Relations Commission has approved new work structures for<br />
Telecom and the domestic airlines, and is considering a new<br />
structure for Qantas engineers. Negotiations are well<br />
advanced in the metal and steel industries.<br />
The increases in productivity flowing from award<br />
restructuring will in some cases be immediate, and in other<br />
cases take longer. But in all cases they will be enduring.<br />
And in all cases they are being achieved, not through<br />
confrontationist tactics in which everyone is the loser, but<br />
through sensible and constructive negotiations in which<br />
everyone, in the industry and in the economy more generally,<br />
is the winner.<br />
My friends,<br />
When the founders of your union resolved to advance their<br />
goals through political as well as industrial means, one of<br />
their main aims was to secure legislative reform.<br />
Soon after coming to office, my Government established the<br />
Hancock Review into Australia's Industrial Relations Law and<br />
Systems. Keith Hancock's brief was a wide one: to advise<br />
us on how to modernise the law governing industrial<br />
relations.<br />
The outcome of that Review and of the extensive<br />
consultations that followed, was the Industrial Relations<br />
Act 1988 the most far reaching revision of Australia's<br />
federal industrial relations system ever undertaken.<br />
The Industrial Relations Act has provided a more effective<br />
framework for preventing and settling industrial disputes.<br />
It places special emphasis on settling disputes at the<br />
workplace level, and provides scope for greater flexibility<br />
in working arrangements and remuneration.<br />
Of particular importance for you, the Act substantially<br />
clears the way towards union amalgamations. </p>
<p>Indeed an amalgamation between two big unions, such as the<br />
AWU and the Federated Ironworkers', with all the benefits<br />
that entails, would have been almost impossible before this<br />
Act. Under the new Act, as long as the Industrial Relations<br />
Commission rules that a " community of interest" exists, a<br />
simple majority of votes cast in favour will approve the<br />
amalgamation. Let me take this opportunity to commend you for your<br />
initiative and vision in working towards this amalgamation<br />
and to offer you my best wishes for its success. It is a<br />
move which is clearly in the interests of all relevant<br />
unionists and is therefore firmly in the mainstream of your<br />
long tradition of service to Australian working men and<br />
women. My friends,<br />
I have spoken today about some of the new challenges facing<br />
the AWU and the trade union movement generally.<br />
The basic challenge of course has not changed since your<br />
union was founded. It remains the challenge of effective<br />
organisation so as to secure better living standards for<br />
your members. But the way that challenge is now pursued has<br />
been revolutionised.<br />
From sectional organisations concerned solely with the<br />
interests of union members, trade unions now have<br />
responsibilities extending to the well being of all<br />
Australians. Trade unionists once sought political representation,<br />
through the political wing of the labour movement; now they<br />
are vital partners with the Labor Party in government.<br />
From once seeking an equitable sharing of prosperity, trade<br />
unionists are now also intimately involved in, and committed<br />
to, creating the framework within which further prosperity<br />
is generated.<br />
Only the ideologically obsessed fanatics of the Right see<br />
this as a threat to good economic management.<br />
Regrettably, such fanatics hold increasing sway within the<br />
mainstream conservative parties.<br />
Their blinkered dogma, their overwhelming preference for<br />
confrontation over consultation, their refusal to accept the<br />
legitimate and constructive role of the trade union movement<br />
in resolving issues across the spectrum of theAustralian<br />
economy indeed their determination to break up the system<br />
of centralised wage fixing, to weaken union structures and<br />
to banish trade unions from effective participation in<br />
decision making all these pose grave threats to the<br />
achievements I have outlined today. </p>
<p>And what an irony it is that one of the first struggles this<br />
union fought in the 1880s and 1890s is still, in modern<br />
clothes, very much on the agenda today.<br />
The conservatives then talked about " freedom of contract"<br />
a pretty phrase that concealed an ugly intention to give an<br />
employer the right to exclude the union from wage<br />
negotiations with their employees.<br />
Things haven't changed much. There are still those who wish<br />
very earnestly to push unionism aside, and so to exploit<br />
those individual employees too weak to defend themselves.<br />
So I wish you well in this Conference, secure in the<br />
knowledge that your discussions today, covering issues such<br />
as amalgamation and award restructuring, will be in the best<br />
traditions of Australian unionism by which I mean that<br />
they will benefit not only your immediate members but,<br />
ultimately, all Australians. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
