<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6382</transcript-id>
    <title>PARTIAL TRANSCRIPT - PRESS CONFERENCE, CAIRNS, 24 APRIL 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/04/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006382.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MSTER<br />
8. -Proof On"' y<br />
P~ lTAL TRANSCRIPT PRESS CONFERENCE, CAI. RNS, 24 April 1984<br />
QUESTIOT4: Mr Hawke, Crallam Lo. ver, North Queenal~ nd Televi Sion.<br />
Sit, a couple of national quostions.<br />
Yes<br />
QESTION: First and foremost harkinq back to the Chinese<br />
ateel talks, just. how are they ib. f~ ict progren3Sing?<br />
Yes, they are going even better than we enapcted when I<br />
was there in February. I would like to say that some indication<br />
of the accurac of the Judgemant beifng made by the Australian<br />
people about the patheLiC nature of the Opposition in this<br />
country and its leader.-It is to be taken from their pe~ rformance<br />
dn this issue. One wouldbh haz t tthat,-any politblcñ niin this country<br />
concerned with the future of Australia wouldc welcome positivu<br />
achievementsa by Government which are nacessarily going to mean<br />
an Improvement In the economic status of Australia. What we<br />
arrived at in China,. between Premier zhao and myself woro that<br />
there should be the investigation of developricnt 6 in five areas<br />
that is the supply of further raw materials to China, mutuial<br />
interchange of technology, possible investment by China in<br />
Australian iron-ore mining, Australian investmient In the Chinec-tu<br />
steol industry and the supply of Australian pig-iron or processed<br />
raw steel to China. Now in respect of thoqu five things there has<br />
been a remarkable degree of progress. WiLhil a very short tine-of m~ y<br />
return to Australia officials went from Australia to China, and<br />
~ t worked very closely there already the joint working pafty<br />
in China. The Minis-er, the Chinese. M~ inis~ er for Metallurg~ y,<br />
Mr Lee will bo coming herc within a matter of two or thren weeks<br />
now, for a couple of weeks Work here in Australia. Now, iL is<br />
quite clear that the develor-n. et-z that I have talkedi About will be<br />
shaped up and according to tho sort of timetable I tailked abouit.<br />
This nonsense that Mr Peacock has alluded to, of trying to say<br />
that I talked about some doubling of Australian steel production<br />
another 6 million tonnes. To say that this was some short-tern<br />
thing is a deliberate grotesque MISrepresentat-ion and distortion<br />
of what was clearly said by myReif. And if you look at the<br />
record I talked about the possible doubling by the ond of this<br />
century, and that's in tile written record.<br />
Now, this G'overnment has donc more by this initiative than was<br />
dlone in seven years by the consorvative Covernmant to geL hold<br />
of the possibility of a distinct improvement-in thc e~ conomic<br />
performance of our stciel industry. And, it sticks in my gullet:<br />
that these poople, our prodecessors had run down the Austral1ian<br />
steel industry to the point when we took office that wo wore. </p>
<p>P. M. cont<br />
looking at the disappearance of the Australian steel industry<br />
-that was the reality. Now, I promised that I would save it,<br />
aad we did. We novi have riot a disappearing steel industry, but.<br />
a viable, efficient cost-competitive, very profitable industry.<br />
no, e ' ve brought that about by bringing the industry, the unions<br />
and tho Government tcgeilher, and as part of this commitment that<br />
we have to the development of the Australian steel industryue<br />
have taken this initiative with China, which is recognised by<br />
everyone in the industry here as proceeding now beyond the<br />
eurpectations that tie could have had in February. Now, I find<br />
it difficult to think that Mr Peacock and the opposition could<br />
be going dowrn the political gurgler any faster than they were<br />
two or three weeks ago. But, if he goes on like this there<br />
disappearance id going to be even more rapid tha6i even their<br />
few remaining supporters could have conceived.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, are you disappointed in some of the comments<br />
that have been attributad to BHP senior management about the<br />
issuc?<br />
P. M Well, let me read what Mr Lotion has said. I am told<br />
that his statement which has excited the poor Mr Peacock so much,<br />
,, as not in a prepared statement that he made, but in an answer<br />
to a question he made some off-the-cuff observations, which this<br />
ao I say -poor opposition has sought to grab hold of and distor7t.<br />
Now, what Mr Loton has said in a prepared statement is thisthe<br />
understandings reached by the Prime Minister have been very<br />
helpful in that they have meant a significantly increased interest<br />
by the Chinese in co-operating with the Australian industry.<br />
N~ ow that's clear, he goes on to point out that obviously as we!' ve<br />
Gaid right from the beginning finally there will have to be<br />
commercial decisions made. We facilitated those commercial<br />
discussions. CRA has gone to China, BHP has gone there. And as<br />
a result of what we've done, as Mr Loton indicates, it'-s been<br />
very helpful in improving the context-within which they are<br />
operating. Now, the commercial enterprises will have to-in<br />
co-operation with the Governments make those decisions which are<br />
going to lead to an improvement in the industry. Those will happenand<br />
that's what Mr Loton has said about the contribution of the<br />
Australian Government.<br />
QUESTION: So, you are saying that Opposition are really distorting<br />
the issue. Well, not only am I saying it, but everyone who knows<br />
anything else about is. I am looking forward to Parliament so<br />
that we can deal with these things in the way that they ought<br />
to be dealt with.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Hawke, Wayne Wallace 4CN News, jvst harking back<br />
to Premier Joh's comments about foiling any proposed early federail<br />
election When is he going to stop attacking the Liberals. I mean<br />
really what he is doing to them i~ s terrible.<br />
QUJESTION: Do you think his comments are a mere sabor-rattiing<br />
or is there any basis of truth behind them? / 3 </p>
<p>Oh I would say sabor-rattling, but again as I point out the<br />
sabor, I think it is pointed at the throat of the Liberals his<br />
dear friends!<br />
QUESTION: So, you think out of any confrontation with<br />
the Liberals. Well, they have been lean so far. Do they still exist<br />
in Queensland, the Liberals. I mean if they do, I mean I think<br />
what he is doing is trying to boot them out entirely very<br />
naughty of him.<br />
QUESTION; Sir, harking back to the April the first comments in<br />
relationship to Waltzing Matilda. What is the state of play with<br />
Waltzing Matilda now?<br />
Well, when I had this brought to my attention a short<br />
while ago, I instructed the Attorney-General's Department to<br />
examine the issue very closely. They were doing that at the<br />
time when I left for the Easter break. I will have a report<br />
when I get back, and if it does seem that the unthinkable<br />
is the case that the Americans do have some copyright on this<br />
most sacred of our possessions, then I will be making an<br />
approach to the United States authorities to see that this great<br />
wrong is remedied.<br />
QUESTION: Well, quoting you on 60 Minutes, will you in fact<br />
be picking up the phone and talking to Ron?<br />
be<br />
I will certainly talking to Ron if it is the case that<br />
we don't have the copyright, as I say of this, one of the most<br />
sacred of our possessions. And I Would think I would receive<br />
a very sympathic hearing from Ron.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, again a fairly local issue, the Democrats are<br />
making great play over the fact that Senator Margaret Reynolds<br />
may find herself facing a more difficult task on the Senate<br />
Committee. They claim that your Government could face a<br />
political backlash in the North if that was to be the case.<br />
When I get to the stage when I need the Democrats of<br />
Australia to look after the fortune of my Party, the Australian<br />
Labor Party then I'll let them know. I would think that they<br />
would be well served, like the Liberals in Queensland in lookiog<br />
after their own meagre chances. And I would have thought that<br />
given their demonstrated limitations of capacity by their<br />
performance in the Senate where the Democrats and the Liberals,<br />
together with the National Party have shown themselves as the<br />
friends of the tax avoiders of this country, andl know that they<br />
are going to have to face up to the judgement of the Australian<br />
people and it is going to be a very harsh judgement. And you<br />
know I am a charitable person, I would just kindly say to them<br />
in a kindly fashion, look don't dissipate your very limited and<br />
not too adequate resources by trying to tell us how to look after<br />
our affairs. We will go into the half Senate election whenever<br />
it is held and I haven't been told yet when it's going to be,<br />
but when we go into the half Senate election, and whatever form of<br />
election it is we'll be in the very best of shape, and I believe<br />
that that shape will include the representation of Senator Margaret<br />
Reynolds in a prominent and winnable position on the Senate ticket.<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>4.<br />
But we will sought that out, and as X say they've got<br />
loads of problems themoelvos. They really ohould concentrate<br />
on their own problems. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
