<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4638</transcript-id>
    <title>PARLIAMENTARY STATEMENT, 2 MARCH 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004638.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-AmP 3<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARLIAMENTARY STATEMENT 2 MARCH 1978<br />
On 14th July, 1977, Sir John Kerr announced his intention to<br />
relinciuish the office of Governor-General. lie made his decision<br />
because he believed that the events of 1975 and<br />
the position into which he had been forced while serving as<br />
Governor-General of Australia had left some scars on the<br />
Australian body politic, which would be more quickly healed if<br />
he stepped down. Sir John protected the Australian people and<br />
Parliament according to the law, according to the Constitution<br />
and according to his duty as Governor-General.<br />
The attempt of the Labor Government to stay in power in defiance<br />
of Parliament compelled his proper and inevitable dismissal of<br />
that Government. An executive governing without the sanction of<br />
the Parliament is the hallmark, not of a democracy, but of a<br />
dictatorship. His difficult decision gave the people the opportunity<br />
to vote and upheld the Parliamentary system. The people of<br />
Australia passed their clear judgement on these events and<br />
Sir John's actions in the election of 1975. History will judge<br />
them just as clearly. It will support the actions Sir John Kerr<br />
was compelled to take in the extraordinary circumstances in which<br />
the Government of the day so reprehensibly placed him.<br />
Australia, as a nation of free people, owes as much to the courage<br />
of Sir John Kerr as to any man in our history. Had he not acted<br />
as he did, had he not prevented the unconstitutional designs of<br />
the last Government being consummated the shape of Australian<br />
democracy would have been twisted and distorted. Sir John's<br />
action was opposed by a hostile and bitter minority. Division<br />
was caused by the statements of the then Leader of the Opposition,<br />
by Senator James McClelland and other members of the Labor Party<br />
who sought to make the Governor-General a scapegoat for their own<br />
actions. Because of this unjustified bitterness, the office of<br />
the Governor-General became a matter of national controversy.<br />
Sir John recognised this we all did.<br />
He believed he could best serve Australia by standing aside, by<br />
allowing another to serve as Governor-General. This he did.<br />
His action was applauded. I believe his action was right, that<br />
it contributed to our nation's healing process to a return to<br />
normalcy. In this Parliament two days ago, I drew attention to Sir John's<br />
long and notable career of public service, and to the fact that<br />
both as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of N~ ew South Wales<br />
and as Governor-General, he would have been able to devote more<br />
of his life to serving Australia had not most unusual events<br />
intervened. / 2 </p>
<p>At the time of Sir John's resignation, he said he looked towards<br />
new fields of constructive actitity. It was clear that he still<br />
wished to serve this country in some other capacity where he<br />
could serve energetically but out of the public gaze. Recognizing<br />
Sir John's desire to continue serving Australia, I after<br />
consultation with my senior colleagues, offered him on behalf of<br />
the Government the opportunity to do so. This became possible<br />
after the Minister for Foreign Affairs wrote to me on 1 February,<br />
advising that in his judgement the Australian diplomatic posts<br />
at Los ngeles, Bombay and UNESCO should be re-opened. As a<br />
result of that advice from the Minister for Foreign Affairs and<br />
after consultation with my colleagues, the Government decided to<br />
offer Sir John Kerr the post of Ambassador to UNESCO.<br />
The Government took this step in the firm belief that Sir John Kerr<br />
would fill the post with honour and as ably as any man available<br />
from within or without the public service. The Government<br />
believed that having served this nation honourably, Sir John<br />
should not be cast aside, relegated to the shadows, simply because<br />
he was forced by the Government of the day to make a difficult<br />
decision. The Government believed that he had earned the right<br />
to serve the nation quitely, at peace with himself, at peace with<br />
the nation at peace with his family.<br />
There were people in this community who were determined that<br />
this should not be so. Since his appointment as Ambassador to<br />
UNESCO, the attacks on him in the Parliament and attacks outside<br />
it have been renewed. Sir John Kerr, once having discharged his<br />
duty to the nation under the most difficult circumstances, has<br />
no wish to continue as the centre of public dispute, making it<br />
impossible for him and his family to live the normal life to<br />
which we are all entitled.<br />
An Ambassador at UNESCO trying to carry out his functions under<br />
these conditions would find it impossible to discharge the<br />
responsibilities of his office.<br />
Mr. Speaker, I inform the House that I have today re ceived a<br />
message from His Excellency Sir. John Kerr who was today to have<br />
commenced duty as Australian Ambassador to UNESCO. Sir John has<br />
informed me that with great regret he feels he cannot take up<br />
this post. I read to the House the message that I have received:-<br />
" My dear Prime Minister,<br />
I have become aware since arriving in Paris of<br />
the attacks that have been made upon me and upon<br />
the Government as a result of my appointment as<br />
Australian Ambassador to UNESCO. These attacks<br />
have been made in the Parliament, under Parliamentary<br />
privilege, by members of the Opposition Parties.' and<br />
they have also been made in various branches of the<br />
media. I am bound to say that the virulence of these<br />
attacks and their unfairness has shocked me. I<br />
have to contemplate serving in this appointment<br />
in the face of them, and possibly perhaps likelytheir<br />
continuation. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
" There is no doubt that in these circumstances,<br />
my ability successfully to undertake the work of<br />
Ambassador to UNESCO would be severely impaired.<br />
For most of the time I should be absent from'<br />
Australia and, holding an Ambassadorial appointment,<br />
be unable to reply in the way that I would wish and<br />
to overcome them as I believe I did during my term<br />
as Governor-General. Beyond this, I have had to<br />
consider whether the purpose that led me to leave<br />
the Governor-Generalship earlier than the normal<br />
term will be defeated if controversy over this new<br />
appointment continues.<br />
As you know I felt that by leaving the office of<br />
Governor-General when I did there would be an<br />
opportunity for remaining wounds to heal and<br />
controversy to die down. The importance of the<br />
Gov ernor-Generalship and its protection stand high<br />
in my objectives. My consideration of all these<br />
matters has led me to the conclusion that I should<br />
ask to be relieved from taking the post of<br />
Australian Ambassador to UNESCO in which I would<br />
have begun duty today.<br />
I believe there is too much at risk, greatly as<br />
the position would have attracted me personally<br />
and much as I feel I would hay e been able to<br />
contribute to Australia's interests with UNESCO.<br />
There is a further reason which concerns me in the<br />
decision I now make. That is the feelings of my<br />
wife and family, who with me have had to withstand<br />
the vilification and attack for part of my term as<br />
Governor-General, and now in prospect through a<br />
term as Ambassador to UNESCO. They with many others<br />
have stood by me without question through all that<br />
has happened. I am not prepared to demand more of<br />
them. I am not prepared to subject them to this<br />
further trial by innuendo and falsehood, even though<br />
my personal instinct is to stand firm and make<br />
certain once again that this tactic of persecution<br />
fails. Prime Minister, I trust that you will understand the<br />
considerations that have led me to this decision.<br />
I appreciate the support I have had from the Government<br />
and your desire to allow me to continue to serve<br />
Australia in public office.<br />
My decision, however, is made. It is with sadness<br />
and regret that I inform you of it.<br />
Yours sincerely,<br />
John Kerr." </p>
<p>-4-<br />
I can only deplore the actions that led to this decision.<br />
The bitterness of the attack, especially in another chamber,<br />
since Sir John left the protection of the office of Governor-<br />
General, has shown that the Labor Party still blame him, when<br />
in logic and in justice, they should be blaming themselves.<br />
They are still seeking to find a scapegoat for their own<br />
misdeeds. The A. L. P.' s refusal to allow Sir John to serve<br />
his country in peace has been despicable; their actions and<br />
statements on this mat-ter have served only to descredit<br />
themselves. There have been some who have sought to confuse the high<br />
purpose of this man with the remuneration he would have<br />
received in his new post. If this is to be a point of<br />
principle, then it should equally have been applied to<br />
appointments such as that of Senator Murphy to the High Court,<br />
Mr. Barnard to an ambassadorship.<br />
The principle of taking a full salary while retaining their pension<br />
was established by the previous Labor Government. It is plain<br />
that this itself is not the major matter of dispute.<br />
If there are others who believe Sir John's actions in 1975 to<br />
have been proper and necessary, but who now want to pass him<br />
by, who want to forget he ever existed and deny him the possibility<br />
of service; I only ask them to ask themselves how much justice,<br />
how much fairness there is in that view.<br />
By his decision, Sir John Kerr leaves public life. A long and<br />
distinguished public career is thus ended. I respect his decision.<br />
I cannot argue with it.<br />
To be an ambassador, constantly pilloried, constantly in the<br />
public glare, who had his family placed under intolerable stress,<br />
was something he did not want; he deserved better.<br />
I feel shame for those events which led to this decision. I<br />
expected less meanness, more generosity and more understanding of<br />
a person who only wanted to serve his nation. I can only hope<br />
that all Australians will now show Sir John the decency and respect<br />
in his retirement that his great integrity and courage in public<br />
office have earned him.<br />
Sir John Kerr ' can hold his head high as he leaves the public<br />
arena he has served so faithfully and well.<br />
.0000.... </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
