<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3553</transcript-id>
    <title>SYDNEY HARBOUR NATIONAL PARK</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003553.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 418<br />
17. December 1974<br />
SYDNEY HARBOUR NATIONAL PARK<br />
The Australian Government has agreed to release to<br />
the New South Wales Government on 1 January l97fapproximately<br />
312 hectares of land including 250 hectares of sydney Harbour<br />
foreshore holdings for the creation of a Sydney Harbour National<br />
Park and 60 hectares for other recreational purposes.<br />
This was announced in a joint statement by the<br />
Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, and the New South Wales Premier,<br />
Sir Robert Askin, today.<br />
The joint statement followed today's State Cabinet<br />
meeting. The 312 hectares of land will be purchased by the<br />
New South Wales Government oni the understanding that it will<br />
be dedicated permanently either for national park or for public<br />
recreation purposes. The Australian Government has aiso agreed to vaeate<br />
at a later date a further 126 hectares of foreshore land for use<br />
for similar purposes. In discussion last week the New South Wales Govenment<br />
also agreed to sell to the Australian Government 13,600 hectares<br />
of land at Holsworthy, 2850 hectares of land at Beecroft Peninsula.<br />
Both of these areas are used by the Australian Government for<br />
defence purposes. Formal transfer of the land will take place as<br />
soon 49 practicable. Vacant position will be-given to most of the<br />
land on 1 January 1975.<br />
Agreement of this and other points was reached at<br />
a meeting between the New South Wales Minister for Lands and<br />
Tourism( tthe Hon. T. L. Lewis, Minister for Services and Property,<br />
the uQno F. M. Daly, and the Minister for Environment and<br />
Consafvation, the Hon. Dr M. Cass.<br />
The Initial 312 hectares includes holdings at<br />
Dobroyd Head, Middle Head, North Head, and South Head, as well<br />
as similar pracels at Steel Point, Clarke Reserve, Williams Park,<br />
Mqrks Park, Henry Head, Barrenjoey Head, and Georges Heights.<br />
Canberra. ACT. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
