<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4502</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT OPENING OF COMMONWEALTH REHABILITATION CENTRE, TARINGA, 26 SEPTEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004502.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS. MR CARMODY,.+<br />
26 SP'TEIBRR 1977-<br />
ADDRESS AT. Q0PENING OF' COMM4ONWE. ALTH REHABILITATION CEI# TRE, TARINGA:<br />
it is very good to be.-heze today to participate in the official:.<br />
. opening of this centre. . Of course, in the great tradition of<br />
-official openings, the centre is already well and trigy operating.,'<br />
But this is still a good occasion for us to mark the notable<br />
achievements which have been made by all involved in rehabilitatio<br />
of the handicapped, and the challenges which still lie ahead.<br />
This centre is a fine example of what can be. achieved with modern,.-'<br />
planning and technology -and.$ 3.5: million of your funds as taxpayers.<br />
* The -rebuilding programme has-significantly increased the capacity<br />
of the centre. Some eighty people can now reside here,. anl<br />
further eighty can train and be treated here on a day-attendance<br />
basis. This enlarged centre and another like it at present being<br />
structed in Townsville will greatly improve the capacity of the:-.<br />
Commonwealth Rehabilitation service to assist handicapped people-"<br />
in Queensland.<br />
Another centre is being built in Hobart, and when that is complete<br />
the sexvice will be operating at least one major training and trea<br />
ment centre in every state, as well as rehabilitation casework tea<br />
in thirteen provincial centres such as Rockhampton and Town. sville'<br />
in all, the service assists some 3,000 handicapped people every<br />
year.+ But of course it is only part of the overall services an4' d<br />
facilities, subsidies, pensions and benefits which the comwiity.:<br />
provides to those of i-ts members who are handicapped.<br />
The Commonwealthb provides a comprehensive scheme of pensions and<br />
benefits to maintain minimum incomes for handicppped people, and.-*<br />
each of the state governments provides a range of services. An-.<br />
essential link is provided by voluntary agencies.<br />
My Government firmly believes that voluntary social welfare-agenol<br />
have a vital role to play a role complementary to that provided..,<br />
by Government. Frankly, there are many axeas in which Goverxnent,' / can.-</p>
<p>ican never match the service which voluntary agencies can.<br />
provide. Voluntary agencies have an inherent flexibility,<br />
dedication and sense of personal commitment which makes them<br />
Vixigularly well able to provide warm and compassionate help to<br />
those who are in need of help. A.<br />
,::, TheComzivnwealth Government is seeking to give maximum assistance<br />
. to voluntary agencies which provide training,' residential care,<br />
~ g~: activity therapy anid sheltered workshop facilities for handicapped<br />
people.--,. For the three year period 1976-79 we have committed<br />
ourselves to provide subs idies of $ 121 million to such agencies.<br />
. TeCommonwealth, the States and voluntary agencies are not<br />
:-. competitors but partners in the chaliengp-of providing effective<br />
and. prompt help. to all disadvantaged and underprivileged in our<br />
community.<br />
~--What-we must do. is to achieve the most effective co-operation and<br />
-interaiction between us, and to do this, we must all be prepared<br />
constantly to, re-examine, our programmes to see whether we are<br />
.~ doing. enoug h, whether our programmes are really helping those<br />
nmsot, in need, whether long established programmes which we are<br />
used to, require fundamental redirection to meet changing<br />
*-Comunity needs.<br />
The Government In the past two years has been undertaking this<br />
_:.... challenging and difficult task. In many instances, we have made<br />
fundamental changes and extensions ixn our programmes to. ensure<br />
_-. that effqctive assistance actually reaches those who most require<br />
-orhelp. We have done this in the area of children' s services,<br />
in-legal aid, and with such innovations as the Famly Allowance.<br />
In the area of care for the handicapped, when we calne to office<br />
we-found that levels of assistance were quite inadequate, and we<br />
have moved to Increase our assistance sharply. Even though this<br />
has been a period of severe restraint in Governtment. spending, we<br />
w. Service by 24%, raised subsidies to voluntary agencies under the<br />
hanicapedpersons assistance scheme by 301 and allocated a<br />
further l8 million for the handicapped childrens allowance<br />
that is a rise of<br />
First, we have amended the rules to make more parents of handi--<br />
capedchildren eligible to receive the handicapped child's<br />
allowance. Previously it was necessary to show that the childwas<br />
severely handicapped within the meani-ng, of strict criteria<br />
laid down In the Social Services Act. -We have now authorised<br />
the Director-General. of Social Security at his discretion to pay<br />
the $ 15 a week allowance to low income earning parents of less<br />
.7 . handicapped children If the expense of care is causing the family<br />
financial hardship.<br />
Second, we have widened the scope of the Commonwealth Rehabilitation<br />
Centre. F~ or some thirty years, the service has been training<br />
handicapped people to enable them to take on jobs and become<br />
independent merabers of the workforce. ut thia system discriminated<br />
against women who did not want to take-a job but wished to stay at<br />
/ home </p>
<p>home,. to look-after-their family, and needed training to be.<br />
able-. to dothis with greater ability and independence. . We<br />
have D.. OW decided.. that--the service . will be extended toinld.<br />
disabled housewives. and mothers, to increase their capacity to,.<br />
* lead-an. independent or semi-independent life at home.<br />
This. decision' iS-in: line with -recommnendations m~ ade inte<br />
.,-. third _ main report of. the Poverty Xnquiry, and with advice<br />
given. to us-from the. National A~ dvisory Council . on the Eandicapped,-<br />
Ladies and gentlemien,. th is Rehabilitation Centre offers to the.<br />
many:-people-who will pass through it, a renewal, a fresh sense.<br />
of hope and-purpose, of achievez~ ent and independence.-<br />
If that can be achieved, then the community'sa support-in..*.<br />
creating this new larger centre is an excellent investmnt-<br />
Indeed.. it gives me great pleasure to declare open these major<br />
extension~ s to the Cc'nmnwealth Rehabilitation Centre for.<br />
Brisbane.. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
