<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5651</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/09/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005651.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
7-/ 2<br />
/ 3 EMBARGO: 5: 00* pm<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 2 0 SEP-, 1B õ 9 81<br />
ELECTORATE TrALK 22; 3 S<br />
The Commonwealth of Nations is a major international institution<br />
and it has a cai~ acitv to make a constructive contribution in<br />
relation t* Lo issues of" world concern and of concern to Australia.<br />
The Commonwev alth uHeads of Government Meeting in Melbourne wi: ll<br />
be the largest and m. os t sigrifricant international conference ever<br />
held. n ths country. The fact that this meeting is being held in<br />
Australia is a tribute to the contribution which successive<br />
Australian Cove rra. en ts have made both in the Commonwealth and in<br />
other internatiOnal forums. The fact that this meeting is held<br />
in Austr--ali-* a w4i enhance Australia's position in the world.<br />
The . cnweith s aunique international organisation. It"<br />
appra:~ prb~ emsclingthrough consensus and its discuss ions<br />
are characterised b-y. mutual respect, tolerance and inforimaliy..<br />
It tes.! on:-t:. e rnasis that quiet discussion and a genuine<br />
meetin: Ct ns w from the glare of publicity arc or<br />
produ -zie thian pu,, blic disputation.<br />
At the ( nmnelhHeads of Government Meeting, there w. aS<br />
the ofz~ ZZJ9~ babw,, e, which proved to be amenable -to Commnowealth<br />
4initiatjv-es. So -that particular meeting had a quite dram-oatic<br />
outco-n. e and' as a resultqRobe-rt '. 1ugall-) will be coming to Melbrourne<br />
as Prime ster of Zimbabwe.<br />
There will b F no such outstanding single issue dominating the<br />
Melbourne Cating, but there are neverthe less issues of profound<br />
and lasting sianif--icance for Australia which will be at the<br />
forefront In t-he discussions. The meeting will be discussing in<br />
a practi-cal and speci* fic way the problem of food, how to improve<br />
production,-storagre and security of supply to those chronically<br />
in neea. 1.1 will be discussing energy supplies and also how trade<br />
between as~ valorpocd and developing countries can be increas. aid and<br />
made or eqit-able We shall1 be discussing how aid can be<br />
increased~ and. adem effective and how the internation,:: 3. financia<br />
and mone.-tary i n tutions can uce improved to serve the interests<br />
of the countries they serve in a more satisfactory TTwca, y . J r e<br />
many highily tLechnical questions involved in all this, but behind<br />
the technicalitics l-e very basic questions not onl. y oE morality<br />
and hurmanitarian concern, but of stable development of pe aceand<br />
h-irFmony between nations. </p>
<p>2<br />
The issues to be discussed affect not only the world in which<br />
we live, but will also have an incalculable impact on the kind<br />
of world in which our children will live. All these issues<br />
of development are particularly important for Australia, as<br />
nearly all our neighbours are developing countries.<br />
The Melbourne meeting will be the first. Commonwealth Heads of<br />
Government Meeting in the Pacific region. Many of the countries<br />
of the region are s: mll, and suffer from particular hardships,<br />
like remoteness, small size, distance from markets and slender<br />
natural resources. Australia is aware that these countries<br />
should be able to draw value from the Commonwealth as do the<br />
larger countries. These countries will not be forgotten in<br />
Melbourne and I expect special attention to be given them at<br />
the meeting.<br />
The meeting will also examine the important area of Commonwealth<br />
functional co-operation the practical programmes of co-operation<br />
that form much of the substance of the Commonwealth's ongoing<br />
business. At a tir. me when the vast potential of the Pacific<br />
region in trade and economic terms is being increasingly recognised,<br />
Australia can only benefit from the opportunity which this<br />
conference offers for wide-ranging discussions of Pacific issues<br />
and for cerenting further our friendship with so many Pacific<br />
nations. During the conference an international spotlight will be turned<br />
on Australia. Overseas journalists will not just report the<br />
confere-ce, th ey wil also report on Australia, what thE-y see of<br />
it and think of its people, what their feelings are about Melbourne<br />
and Canberra.<br />
The conference is a great opportunity for the city of Melbourne.<br />
The ir. re. sion of Australia that our visitors carry away with themn<br />
will reflect the interaction they have had with Australians<br />
from all walks of life. This conference is not therefore just<br />
a matter for Govern. ment. It is a matter for all of us to put<br />
our best foot forward for Australia. Melbourne will be Aulstralia' s<br />
front window during this meeting. I am sure it is a front window.<br />
of which all Australians will be very proud.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
