<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6198</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO THE HOUSING INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION (MANUFACTURING INDUSTRY COUNCIL) DINNER-DANCE, 12 SEPTEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/09/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006198.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHIECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO THE HOUSING INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION<br />
( MANUFACTURING INDUSTRY COUNCIL) DINNER DANCE<br />
12 SEPTEMBER 1983<br />
YOU HAVE ALL SPENT A LONG DAY TAKING A CLOSE LOOK<br />
AT DEVELOPMENTS IN THE HOUSING INDUSTRY, AND THE. ASSOCIATED<br />
OUTLOOK BOTH FOR THE INDUSTRY AS A WHOLE AND FOR YOUR OWN<br />
OPERATIONS-IT MIGHT NOW BE APPROPRIATE FOR ME TO ATTEMPT<br />
TO PROVIDE A BROADER PERSPECTIVE ON YOUR DELIBERATIONSMORE<br />
SPECIFICALLY, I SHOULD LIKE TO RELATE my GOVERNMENT'S<br />
HOUSING INITIATIVES TO OUR MORE GENERAL ECONOMIC POLICY, AND<br />
TO OUR AIMS AS A GOVERNMENT.<br />
THE BUDGET IS STILL THE MAIN FOCUS OF ATTENTION IN<br />
ECONOMIC POLICY-THERE ARE THREE MAJOR STRANDS TO THE<br />
BUDGET STRATEGY THAT THE TREASURER INTRODUCED IN THE<br />
PARLIAMENT THREE WEEKS AGO. THESE ARE: FIRST, TO SET A<br />
FLOOR OF ACTIVITY IN THE ECONOMY WHILE THE PRIVATE SECTOR<br />
REMAINS DEPRESSED; SECONDLY, TO SPREAD MORE EQUITABLY AMONG<br />
THE COMMUNITY, THE BURDEN OF THE RESTRAINT THAT IS NECESSARY<br />
FOR ECONOMIC RECOVERY, AND THIRDLY, TO IMPLEMENT THOSE<br />
REFORMS AND POLICIES NECESSARY TO ENSURE THAT RECOVERY, ONCE<br />
UNDERWAY, IS SUSTAINED, AND NOT CHOKED OFF BY HIGHER<br />
INFLATION AND INTEREST RATES-</p>
<p>THE INITIATIVES WE HAVE TAKEN TOWARDS THE HOUSING<br />
AND CONSTRUCTION INDUSTRIES ARE NOT ONLY ILLUSTRATIVE OF<br />
THIS APPROACH. THEY ARE CRUCIAL TO ITS SUCCESS.<br />
As YOU ALL KNOW OUR HOUSING POLICY WAS DEVELOPED<br />
THROUGH A PROCESS OF INTENSE CONSULTATION. THE HOUSING<br />
INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION WAS INTIMATELY INVOLVED FROM THE<br />
BEGINNING-BILL KIRKBY-JONES AND FRANK FISHER ATTENDED THE<br />
NATIONAL ECONOMIC SUMMIT AND MADE A MAJOR CONTRIBUTION TO<br />
ITS DELIBERATIONS-IMPORTANTLY THE SUMMIT URGED JOB<br />
CREATION THROUGH AN IMPROVEMENT OF THE ECONOMIC<br />
INFRASTRUCTURE. THE HOUSING SECTOR WAS RECOGNISED AS<br />
OFFERING SPECIAL POTENTIALMY<br />
GOVERNMENT HE. EDED THIS SUGGESTION. FOLLOWING<br />
THE SUMMIT, A MINI HOUSING SUMMIT WAS CONVENED. APPROPRIATE<br />
FORMS OF ASSISTANCE WERE IDENTIFIED AND INTRODUCED WITH THE<br />
REFORMS IN THE MAY STATEMENT AND THROUGH THE PREMIERS'<br />
CONFERENCE. ANXIOUS TO GET THINGS MOVING WE CHOSE NOT TO<br />
WAIT UNTIL THE BUDGET IN AUGUST.<br />
SUBSTANTIAL INCREASES MADE IN OUR FUNDING OF PUBLIC<br />
HOUSING WILL LIFT ACTIVITY IN THE INDUSTRY. DEPENDING ON<br />
THE AMOUNTS STATES NOMINATE FOR PUBLIC HOUSING FROM THEIR<br />
LOAN COUNCIL PROGRAMS, TOTAL PAYM ENTS TO THE STATES AND<br />
TERRITORIES FOR PUBLIC HOUSING ASSISTANCE MAY BE SOME $ 700<br />
MILLION IN 1983/ 84, up 144 PERCENT ON THE HUM/ 8 LEVEL-</p>
<p>WE HAVE ALSO, AS YOU HEARD EARLIER TODAY,<br />
RESTRUCTURED OUR ASSISTANCE TO INDIVIDUAL HOMESEEKCRS, TO<br />
MAKE HOME OWNERSHIP ACCESSIBLE To AUSTRALIANS WHO WOULD<br />
OTHERWISE HAVE BEEN DENIED THE OPPORTUNITY-BY<br />
CONCENTRATING ASSISTANCE ON PEOPLE FOR WHOM IT WILL MAKE THE<br />
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN HOME OWNERSHIP AND EXCLUSION, THE NEW<br />
PACKAGE WILL DO MUCH MORE TO STIMULATE THE HOUSING iNDUSTRY.<br />
THE FIRST HOME OWNERS' SCHEME, TO START NEXT MONTH,<br />
IS CENTRAL TO THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICIES TO STIMULATE THE<br />
PRIVATE HOUSING SECTOR. DEMAND FOR NEW HOUSES IS LARGELY<br />
FROM YOUNG PEOPLE PURCHASING THEIR FIRST HOMES-IN THE PAST<br />
FEW YEARS, RISING INTEREST RATES AND THE WORSENING ECONOMIC<br />
CONDITIONS HAVE DISCOURAGED MANY YOUNG PEOPLE FROM ENTERING<br />
INTO HOUSING MORTGAGES. THE FIRST HOME OWNERS SCHEME SHOULD<br />
REVERSE THIS. CONFIDENCE WHICH HAS BEEN SO LACKING IN<br />
RECENT YEARS SHOULD BE RESTOREDAPART<br />
FROM PROVIDI'NG ALL ASSISTANCE TO PRIVATE HOME<br />
BUYERS THROUGH A SINGLE PROGRAM, THE FLEXIBILITY INHERENT IN<br />
THE FIRST HOME OWNERS SCHEME WILL MAXIMISE THE VALUE TO EACH<br />
INDIVIDUAL, AND HENCE TO THE INDUSTRY. Too MUCH ASSISTANCE<br />
UNDER PREVIOUS SCHEMES WAS DIRECTED TO THOSE IN NO REAL<br />
NEED, AND HENCE HAD NO REAL IMPACT ON THE LEVEL OF ACTIVITY-</p>
<p>ACTIVITY GENERATED BY THIS SCHEME TOGETHER WITH OUR<br />
DIRECT SPENDING ON PUBLIC HOUSING IS EXPECTED TO CREATE AT<br />
LEAST 30,000 ADDITIONAL jOBS. rHE iMPACT WILL BE SEEN BOTH<br />
IN ON-SITE LABOUR, AND THROUGH THE OPERATION OF SUPPLIERS TO<br />
THE INDUSTRY YOURSELVESWHAT<br />
ABOUT THE MEDIUM TERM, AND OF THE NEED TO<br />
ENSURE THAT RECOVERY IS SUSTAINED? WE ARE WORKING TC AVOID<br />
THE CYCLES OF BOOM AND BUST THAT HAVE SO CHARACTERISED THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN HOUSING INDUSTRY IN' THE PAST.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT'S WIDER POLICIES ARE DIRECTED TO<br />
THIS END. TO GET THE ECONOMY MOVING AGAIN, WE HAVE PROVIDED<br />
IN THIS YEAR'IS BUDGET A SUBSTANTIAL BUT RESPONSIBLE FISCAL<br />
STIMULUS. THIS STIMULUS HAS BEEN CAREFULLY CALCULATED TO<br />
AVOID DISRUPTIVE PRESSURES ON FINANCIAL MARKETS, COSTS AND<br />
PRICES AND THE BALANCE OF PAYMENTS.<br />
FOR PRIVATE SECTOR RECOVERY TO BE SUSTAINED, THERE<br />
MUST BE REDUCTIONS IN THE PUBLIC SECTOR DEMANDS IN FINANCIAL<br />
MARKETS AS THE RECOVERY PROCEEDS-WITH THIS YEAR'S FISCAL<br />
POLICY MEASURES, TAKEN IN BOTH THE MAY STATEMENT AND IN THE<br />
BUDGET, WE HAVE LAID THE BASIS FOR A REDUCTION IN THE<br />
STRUCTURAL DEFICIT IN FUTURE YEARS. AN ONGOING PROCESS OF<br />
EXPENDITURE REVIEW WILL BE UNDERTAKEN TO ENSURE THAT THE </p>
<p>BENEFITS OF THIS ARE NOT WASTED, AND THAT THE CURRENT LEVEL<br />
OF FISCAL STIMULUS IS REDUCED AS APPROPRIATE IN RECOVERY,<br />
PRESSURE ON FINANCE AVAILABILITY AND INTERESTr<br />
RATES, WHICH HAVE PROVED SUCH A SCOURGE TO YOUR [ NI) USTRY<br />
IN THE PAST, SHOULD THEREFORE BE ALLEVIATED. IN THIS REGARD<br />
THE DECISION BY WESIPAC AND THE COMMONWEALTH SAVINGS<br />
BANK LAST FRIDAY TO LOWER HOME LOAN INTEREST RATES WAS<br />
W" ELCOME, IT WAS A POSITIVE SIGN THAT THE MARKET HAS<br />
CONFIDENCE IN THE GOVERNMENT'S OVERALL ECONOMIC STRATEGY<br />
AND PARTICULARLY THE 1983-84 BUDGET.<br />
INDUSTRIAL UNREST CAN ALSO THREATEN THE DURABILITY<br />
OF RECOVERY. MY GOVERNMENT ATTACHES SOME IMPORTANCE TO THE<br />
ACHIEVEMENT OF LONG-TERM INDUSTRIAL STABILITY AND PEACE<br />
IN THE BUILDING AND CONSTRUCTION INDUSTRY, OUR PRIORITIES<br />
IN THE HOUSING AREA AND FOR THE ECONOMY MORE GENERALLY<br />
COULD OTHERWISE BE THWARTED.<br />
[ HE MINISTER FOR EMPLOYMENT AND INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS<br />
HAS WORKED HARD IN THIS AREA. HE HAS MET WITH BUILDING<br />
INDUSTRY EMPLOYERS AND UNION REPRESENTATIVES AND HAS CONVENED<br />
THE NATIONAL BUILDING AND CONSTRUCTION INDUSTRY CONFERENCE<br />
UNDER THE CHAIRMANSHIP OF MR ALAN VOSTI, AS A RESULT<br />
THE PARTIES INVOLVED IN THE BLF DEREGISTRATION CASE ARE<br />
NEGOTIATING ON A BASIS FOR WITHDRAWAL FROM THE PROCEEDINGS.<br />
THE CONFERENCE WILL ALSO PROVIDE A FORUM FOR CONTINUING<br />
DISCUSSION BETWEEN EMPLOYERS AND EMPLOYEES ON THE MEANS<br />
TO ACHIEVE STABILITY IN THE INDUSTRY. </p>
<p>THE DIFFICULTIES INVOLVED IN REACHING AGREEMENT ON<br />
SOLUTIONS TO THE COMPLEX AND LONG-S'ANDING PROBLEMS INVOLVED<br />
ARE ENORMOUS. BUT IT IS THROUGH CONSULTATION OF THE K1IND WE<br />
HAVE INITIATED THAT A FIRM BASE FOR FUTURE GROWTH IN THE<br />
BUILDING SECTOR CAN BE ESTABLISHEDBEFORE<br />
CONCLUDING LET ME COMMENT BRIEFLY ON THE NEW<br />
PRESCRIBED PAYMENTS SYSTEM. THIS IS A MATTER UPON WHICH MY<br />
GOVERNMENT RECEIVED STRONG REPRESENTATIONS FROM JOHN GRAHAM<br />
AND BILL KIRKBY-JONES. THESE REPRESENTATIONS, ASSISTED BY<br />
THE FACT THAT THEY WERE MADE REASONABLY, DIRECTLY TO<br />
MINISTERS, RATHER THAN WILDLY IN THE MEDIA, DID INFLUENCE<br />
GOVERNMENT THINKING-IN PARTICULAR THEY ALERTED US TO THE<br />
NEED FOR EASIER TRANSITIONAL ARRANGEMENTS, AND FOR REVIEW OF<br />
THE SYSTEM IN THE FIRST SIX MONTHS OF ITS OPERATIONBUT<br />
DESPITE REPRESENTATIONS BY THE HOUSING INDUSTRY<br />
ASSOCIATION FOR MORE FAR-REACHING MODIFICATIONS, MY<br />
GOVERNMENT EVENTUALLY DECIDED THAT THE NEW SYSTEM OF<br />
COLLECTING INCOME TAX IN THE BUILDING AND SOME OTHER<br />
INDUSTRIES SHOULD PROCEED FROM SEPTEMBER 1.<br />
IT IS UNFORTUNATE THAT THE NEW SYSTEM HAS OFTEN<br />
BEEN REPRESENTED IN THE MEDIA AS A NEW TAX-WHAT WE HAVE<br />
ESTABLISHED IS A METHOD OF SECURING THE PAYMENT OF INCOME<br />
TAX FALLING DUE UNDER PRESENT LAW-OUR AIM IS TO STAMP OUT </p>
<p>7.<br />
EVASION OF TAX. As SUCH, APART FROM EFFECTS ON CASH FLOW<br />
THROUGH THE YEAR, AND A SMALL ADMINISTRATIVE REQUIREMENT, IT<br />
DOES NOT SUBSTANTIALLY ADD TO THE COST OF PRODUCTION.<br />
CERTAINLY IT SHOULD NOT, AS SOME HAVE CLAIMED, ADD 10<br />
PER CENT TO THE COST OF A NEW HOUSE.<br />
THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT ANNOUNCED THE SYSTEM IN ITS<br />
BUDGET LAST YEAR, TO COME INTO EFFECT ON 1 JULY 1983. ON<br />
COMING INTO OFFICE, WE EXAMINED THE SITUATION CLOSELY AND<br />
CONSULTED CLOSELY WITH ALL INTERESTED PARTIES, INCLUDING THE<br />
HOUSING INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION. WE DECIDED THAT A SYSTEM OF<br />
THE KIND NOW INTRODUCED WAS NECESSARY TO STEM THE EXTENSIVE<br />
EVASION OF TAX THROUGH NON-REPORTING OF INCOME IN A NUMBER<br />
OF INDUSTRIES. IN CERTAIN INDUSTRIES LITTLE MORE THAN HALF<br />
OF THE TAX LIABILITY WAS BEING PAID.<br />
THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN. CHEATING ON THEIR TAXES WILL BE<br />
ADVERSELY AFFECTED BY THE NEW SYSTEM. BUT THE REST OF THE<br />
COMMUNITY CAN ONLY BENEFIT IF THOSE NOW GETTING OFF<br />
" SCOT-FREE" ARE FORCED TO PAY THEIR TAXES.<br />
IT IS GROSSLY UNFAIR THAT SOME MEMBERS OF THE<br />
COMMUNITY CAN SHIFT THE BURDEN ONTO OTHERS BY EVASION OF<br />
THEIR TAX LIABILITY. ADDITIONALLY, SUCH EVASION CONFERS AN<br />
UNFAIR COMPETITIVE ADVANTAGE ON EVADERS OVER BUILDERS AND<br />
SUB-CONTRACTORS WHO ABIDE BY THE LAW. EQUITY IN THE<br />
TAXATION SYSTEM IS IN THE INTERESTS OF US ALL-</p>
<p>I APPRECIATE THE ANXiETY WITHIN THE INDUSTRY A<br />
MONTH OR SO AGO ABOUT DIFFICULTIES OF OBTAINING EXEMPTION<br />
AND VARIATION CERTIFICATES-I AM PLEASED THAT THIS HAS NOT<br />
PROVEN TO BE A BIG PROBLEM IN PRACTISE, PARTLY BECAUSE OF<br />
TRANSITIONAL ARRANGEMENTS ANNOUNCED A FEW WEEKS AGO.<br />
ALTHOUGH A LARGE NUMBER OF APPLICATIONS HAVE BEEN RECEIVEDABOUT<br />
60,000 BY 1 SEPTEMBER STEPS WERE TAKEN TO ENSURE<br />
THAT APPLICATIONS WERE PROCESSED EXPEDITIOUSLY. THOSE STEPS<br />
INCLUDED THE REDEPLOYMENT OF SOME STAFF. AS A RESULT THE<br />
GREAT BULK OF APPLICATIONS, MORE THAN 92 PERCENT, WERE<br />
PROCESSED BY 1 SEPTEMBER. LESS THAN 3 PERCENT OF THOSE<br />
APPLICATIONS WERE REFUSED-STEPS WERE ALSO TAKEN TO ENSURE<br />
THAT TAXPAYERS WOULD NOT BE DISADVANTAGED WHERE THE TAX<br />
OFFICE OR TAX AGENTS WERE UNABLE TO FULLY PROCESS<br />
APPLICATIONS BY 1 SEPTEMBER. ALL SUCH TAXPAYERS WERE ISSUED<br />
WITH INTERIM CERTIFICATES FOR PERIODS OF UP TO TWO MONTHSFINAL<br />
CERTIFICATES WILL BE ISSUED WHEN THE COMMISSIONER'S<br />
INVESTIGATIONS HAVE BEEN COMPLETED.<br />
WE RECOGNISE THAT THE SYSTEM IS A MAJOR CHANGE IN<br />
THE METHOD OF APPLYING TAX FOR MANY AND THAT THERE MAY BE A<br />
NEED TO MAKE ADJUSTMENTS IN THE LIGHT OF EXPERIENCE. THIS<br />
IS THE REASON WHY WE DECIDED TO REVIEW THE SYSTEM AFTER SIX<br />
MONTHS. THAT REVIEW WILL BE UNDERTAKEN IN CONSULTATION WITH<br />
YOUR ASSOCIATION-IT WILL EXAMINE, FOR EXAMPLE, HOW THE<br />
SYSTEM WILL AFFECT CONTRACT BUILDERS VIS-A-VIS </p>
<p>9.<br />
OWNER-BUILDERS AND THE ADMINISTRATIVE LOAD ON PAYEES, PAYERS<br />
AND THE TAX OFFICE. ALREADY THE COMMISSIONER FOR TAXATION<br />
HAS SUGGESTED THAT A MINOR ASPECT OF THE SYSTEM MAY NEED TO<br />
BE CHANGED TO CUT DOWN ON THE AMOUNT OF PAPERWORK REQUIRED<br />
TO BE FILED WITH THE TAX RETURNS OF A LIMITED NUMBER OF<br />
LARGE FIRMS WHO HAVE EXEMPTION CERTIFICATES-UNDERSTAND<br />
THAT THE COMMISSIONER IS ALREADY WELL ADVANCED IN LOOKING AT<br />
THAT QUESTION-WE HAVE ALSO SUPPORTED AN INQUIR-Y INTO THE<br />
SYSTEM BY THE SENATE FINANCE AND GOVERNMENT OPERATIONS<br />
COMMITTEE, TO WHICH YOUR ASSOCIATION IS ALSO MAKING<br />
SUBMISSIONSLADIES AND GENTLEMEN, I HAVE TAKEN UP SOME OF YOUR<br />
EVENING DISCUSSING A FEW MATTERS THAT I THINK ARE OF<br />
IMPORTANCE TO THE HOUSING AND RELATED INDUSTRIES.-HOPE<br />
THAT YOU AGREE WITH ME ABOUT THAT IMPORTANCE, AND ABOUT THE<br />
NEED FOR CONTINUED CONSULTATION IF WE ARE TO ENSURE THAT<br />
CORRECT POLICIES ARE ADOPTED-PERSONALLY APPRECIATE VERY<br />
MUCH THE WAY THE HOUSING INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION HAS PUT ITS<br />
VIEWS TO THE GOVERNMENT. YOUR ATTENDANCE AT TODAY'S SEMINAR<br />
HAS DEMONSTRATED YOUR BELIEF THAT AN UNDERSTANDING BY THE<br />
INDUSTRY OF GOVERNMENT ACTION IS NECESSARY. FOR MY PART I<br />
BELIEVE THAT UNDERSTANDING BY THE GOVERNMENT OF THE<br />
INDUSTRY'IS VIEWS IS EQUALLY VITAL. TOGETHER I AM SURE WE<br />
WILL GET IT RIGHT-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
