<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6889</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH MIKE WILLESEE, 17 APRIL 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/04/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006889.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
^ APR. 18 ' 86 17: 42 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC HETWORK P. 08<br />
STRICTLY EMbARGOED UNTIL 6.10 A/ ST<br />
jif-Aj7<br />
4kyA 4 lA~ i<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH MIKE WILLESEE 17 APRIL 1986<br />
E 0 E PRPOOOOFF OONNLLYY<br />
This is an unedited transcript and should be checked against<br />
what goes tp air.<br />
WILLESEE: danger of escalation carrying that burden<br />
* to<br />
PM% He is very conscious of it. One of the things that<br />
he said to e which is sustained in thi time was that he<br />
had spoken Ito the wives of the pilots of the plane that is<br />
missing. And even in their time of personal tragedy that<br />
they have expressed support for him. And he seemed to ake<br />
some measure of comfort from that.<br />
WILLESEE: pid you discuss the possibility of escalation<br />
with the Preasident?<br />
PM: Well, in the discussion that we had on the issue, not<br />
only with him but with others Mike, there was some reference<br />
to the possibility that there would be further attacks, iyes68<br />
that was mentioned further terrorist attacks.<br />
WILLESEE: How do you assess that danger?<br />
PM1 Well, iI can't go to all the evidence available to me,<br />
but I think there is not much grounds for optimism that there<br />
may not be some further attacks. But what I believe needs to<br />
be done, Mike, and this is in a modest way, the contribution<br />
that we try to make in the United Nations, to say look the<br />
Charter of the United Nations, which was invoked by the<br />
United States, Article 51, does provide a range of possible<br />
methods for trying to bring parties together. We have go,<br />
all of us, to try and bring that about.<br />
WILLESEEt I'll come back to that point in a moment Prime<br />
Minister. ' How much have you seen of President Reagan's<br />
irrefutable proof of Libyan involvement, direct involvement<br />
in acts of terrorism.<br />
PM: I havI seen a good deal. I saw some before I left<br />
Australia. And I have been given a further briefing here.<br />
II / 2<br />
I' ' f. </p>
<p>APR. 18 ' 86 17: 43 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK P. 09<br />
WILLEBSEE Enoigh to convinoe you?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
WILLESEE; Rev yOU asked the President why he doesn't reveal<br />
that infprmatitnypublicly?<br />
PM: I have p t to the President and others my view that it<br />
is in the best interests, not merely of the United States, but<br />
I would think f the whole community, that that direct evidence<br />
should be publ c. They say they have given, if you like, a<br />
sort of synthe is, a condensation of it. I take the view, personally,<br />
that it is bes to have the actual material. But let me say this,<br />
while that viel I express is an obviously sensible one, you have<br />
got to take inito account the concerns that they have about<br />
the exposure of their intelligence system. And it would be<br />
presumptuous for any of us to tell, I think, the United states<br />
what it should do in terms of some concern it has about exposing<br />
these capacities. I can only say, in terms of my own experience,<br />
Mike, that I ve seen the evidence, I have had some considerable<br />
briefing. An I am convinced both as to the authenticity and<br />
the oompelling nature of the evidence.<br />
WILLESEE: DiO President Reagan seek public support from Australia?<br />
PM: NO, he ddn't.<br />
WILLESEE: Do you believe he would like it?<br />
PMt I believe that the United States is sensible about this.<br />
I made it clear before I left Australia, we made it clear in<br />
our statement in the United Nations, I made it clear in the<br />
private conversations that I have had here in the United States<br />
which reflect our public position. What we are about is to try<br />
and say how we see it as to what has happened and as to what should<br />
happen in the future. The future is the important thing. Now,<br />
our statements have been interpreted in a number of ways.<br />
Following our statement in the United Nations, Mike, a<br />
representativ of Libya attacked us for supporting the United<br />
States. Befote I left Australia Mr Howard attacked us for not<br />
supporting them. Now, I am not, as I said before I left I<br />
Australia, going to get into some squalid auction about where<br />
you get on some support metre. Our responsibility is to say<br />
it as we see it. We have made it quite clear that the essential<br />
condition for bringing to an end the tensions in the area, is<br />
an undertaking and abiding by a comitment by Libya not to<br />
direct acts ol terrorism.<br />
WILLESEE: Did the President express any attitude about the<br />
reaction to his decision from his European allies?<br />
PM: Well, I hink it is fair to say Mike, and you will appreciate<br />
that when you have discussions with people like the President,<br />
there has to be a degree of confidentiality, but I think I don't<br />
breach that c nfidentiality to say there is some sense of<br />
disappointmenI / 3 </p>
<p>' 7 3.<br />
WILLESEE: Wh4t was the President's reaction to the Australian<br />
proposal for he United Nations' intervention and the mediation?<br />
PM: Re didn't go into that in any detail. I think the fair<br />
statement is ihis, Mike, that the United States like the rest<br />
of us, would like to see a resolution of this matter by one<br />
or the other of the peaceful avenues which as identified in<br />
Article 33 of the Charter of the United Nations. Now there must<br />
I suppose, on the evidence to this point, be some doubt about<br />
the preparedness of Libya to give the undertakings to desist<br />
from terroris activities. But that, as I have said in the<br />
Parliament, a d as Mr Hayden has also said and as we have said<br />
in the United Nations, is the essential condition for bringing<br />
an end to this confrontation.<br />
WILLESEE: There is one newspaper report which said that US<br />
Government so rces disliked the Australian proposal because<br />
" it equated Libyan terrorism with what the US sees as a<br />
legitimate UsIresponse". Now have you come across that sort<br />
of feeling in Washington?<br />
PM: No, there is not an equation. And I have received no<br />
criticism along those lines. And I think indeed, if you look<br />
at the statemqnt I made in the Parliament and the sorts of things<br />
that Mr Hayden has said in response to questions and the statement<br />
made by Mr Woqlcott on Australia's behalf in the United Nations<br />
it is quite clear where the basic emphasis is put. Andl repeat,<br />
there can be no end to this tension, this conflict, until there<br />
is a repudiatiIon Libya of the tactic of terrorism.<br />
WILLESEEt Ho% many other countries supported the Australian<br />
proposal in the Security Council?<br />
PM: What I am given to understand Mike is this, that the Secretary-<br />
General and the President of the Council have expressed interest<br />
in the concept of our approach. And, I understand, without having<br />
had identifie4 to me the particular countries but a number of<br />
countries have expressed some interest in what we have said.<br />
I am told that after the statement was made, there was a more<br />
than usual interest in acquiring copies of the speech by<br />
Mr Woolcott. There does seem to be a considerable amount of<br />
interest. Now, whether that goes to the point that there is<br />
sufficient support for some sort of resolution, I am simply not<br />
in a position to say at this point.<br />
WILLESEE: Di you discuss with President Reagan what sort<br />
of person or Persons might play the role of mediator?<br />
PM: No, I didn't. Indeed, nor did our statement to the United<br />
Nations suggest that there was one nation or one particular group<br />
of nations that should assume the role of mediator. Because after<br />
all, Article 33 of the United Nations Charter only talked about<br />
mediation, Mike, as one possible area. There is mediation, there<br />
is negotiatio there there is a range of things. So Australia<br />
didn't specifically suggest a nation or a group of nations as<br />
mediator. / 4<br />
9, . II.<br />
APR. 18 ' 86 17: 45 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETI-. 1ORKP. </p>
<p>-APR. 18 ' 86 17: 46 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK P. 11 4.<br />
WILLESEE: Pr me Minister, it seems reasonable to presume that<br />
the US has god quality intelligence coming out of Libya. Have<br />
you had accesl to that?<br />
PM: You will appreciate, Mike, that I can't breach confidentiality.<br />
I have, in confidence, been briefed. And all I can say is two<br />
things. Firstly, there is no doubt as to the authenticity of<br />
the material hat I have seen. And in the light of seeing that<br />
material and he briefing I have received, I find the evidence<br />
compelling asjto the fact that Libya has directed, controlled<br />
and exported terrorism against innocent civilians and that it<br />
has prepared 4n the past fairly extensive plans for further<br />
acts of terrorism. And my plea for what declared One Prime<br />
Minister of one concerned nation is worth, is this that Libya<br />
should see that in the interests of its own people and-the<br />
interests of the region and in the interests of the world,<br />
that the pursuit of that course can lead to nothing but disaster.<br />
And I would plead that Colonel Gaddafi should bring an end to that<br />
tactic, I am prepared to sit down and try resolve the areas of<br />
differences that we have. That is the course of action that,<br />
we believe as a government, is a responsible one. And we will<br />
do what we can to try and produce that outcome.<br />
WILLESEE: What is your understanding now of Colonel Gaddafi's<br />
position in Llbya, is he under threat?<br />
PM: I understand that since the attack there has been some<br />
evidence of internal dissension and some fighting. But, I haven't<br />
got up to the iIlatest hour briefing on that, Mike.<br />
WILLESEE: Has this trip to Washington brought youmloser<br />
personally to the American view on this issue?<br />
PM: Well, I hink what you will see, that the statement that<br />
was made in t~ e United Nations since I have been here and which<br />
was made following consultations between Bill Hayden and<br />
myself is, if lyou like, a consolidation of what I have<br />
said in the Parliament before I left. The development that<br />
has taken plaIe since I have been here, is that I have had<br />
the opportunity of further briefings, which further confirm*<br />
the evidence that I had the opportunity to see together with<br />
Mr Hayden in Canberra before I left Australia.<br />
WILLESEE: I gather that security surrounding you personally<br />
is unusually strong.<br />
PM: It seems to be fairly substantial. I can't recall, comparing<br />
security that has been operating when I have been before, whether<br />
it is significantly greater. I am not trying to fudge the issue,<br />
I just really don't know. I don't personally look into these<br />
security questions. I have extreme confidence in the competence<br />
of my own people and their relations with their counterparts in<br />
countries that we visit.<br />
WILLESEE: In view of what you know now about the role of some<br />
of Libyan People's Bureaus around the world, are you now concerned<br />
about the presnce in Canberra of a Libyan bureau? </p>
<p>APR. 18 ' 86 17: 48 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK P. 12<br />
PM: You will appreciate that in January1 Mike, when trouble<br />
arose previou ly, we responded positively to the request of<br />
the United St tea to take some action that reduced the level<br />
of representajion of the Bureau. Obviously, we will be watching<br />
with this sit lation very closely, as indeed I believe other countries<br />
in other part of the world are.<br />
WILLESEES Prime Minister, you went to Washington originally to<br />
talk about tride and especially with regard to agricultural<br />
exports.<br />
PM: Not only originally, but that has remained my central task<br />
and responsibility.<br />
WILLESEE: Briefly, have you had any result with discussiona at<br />
this stage?<br />
PM: I am glad you have come to the central purpose of the mission.<br />
I can say to r y friends in rural Australia that we have received<br />
a very positive response from the President down, all people conceraei<br />
There is a recognition that Australia is an efficient producer of<br />
agricultural, that we are non-subsidising of our exports and that<br />
we donit deserve to be hurt, affected adversely by any action<br />
which the Uni~ ed States undertakes against the impact of the<br />
Europeans. And so what we have confirmed and built upon the<br />
work originaliy done by Mr Dawkins by Mr Dawkins earlier in the<br />
year here, welhave created a clear framework of consultation<br />
and capacity for discussion with the United States so that we<br />
can consistently now put into those who are making decisions<br />
about the imp1 ementation of their own programs, we can put into<br />
them our concjrns. So we have got that. Secondly, we<br />
have the unequivocal agreement of the President and others<br />
here that they will take a lead in trying to ensure that in<br />
the multi-lateral trade negotiations which commence later<br />
this year, that they will make every attempt to have agriculture<br />
right up there on the agenda so that togqther we can try and bring<br />
about a situation where the present corruption of international<br />
trade in agricultural products would gradually be brought to an<br />
end.<br />
WILLESEE: How confident are you that that will happen?<br />
I<br />
PM: I am totally confident, Mike, that the United States will<br />
take the lead in this. That together we will attempt to produce<br />
that result in the rounds. We have to realistically<br />
acknowledge that there will be some opposition to having<br />
agriculture up front like that in some quarters, including at<br />
least some of the Europeans. But we have got to do is to try and<br />
get across an understanding that this corruption of the international<br />
Australian agriculture is not merely against the interests of<br />
efficient pro4ucers like Australia but it is fundamentally against<br />
the interests of the Europeans themselves because the misallocation<br />
of resources which is involved in the vast millions of dollars<br />
into the subs disation of agriculture means that they have got<br />
a misallocati n of resources, which means that there is something / 6 </p>
<p>ø 4V<br />
9PR. 18 ' 86 17: 49 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK<br />
1 4933 / i 6.<br />
PM contt like a million and a half less Europeans in mploy ant<br />
than there othirwise would be. It means their growth rate is<br />
less than it o herwise would be. They are paying, the ordinary<br />
people of Europe, are paying a very high price for this policy<br />
of the CAP. Ad we have got to get that message across.<br />
WILLESEE: Pr . a Minister, thanks very much for your time.<br />
PM1 Thanks Mie.<br />
ends P. 13 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
