<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5562</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005562.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-PRIME MINISTERFOR<br />
MEDIA ~ PR L 1981<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Two weeks ago I spoke to you about the Government's attitude<br />
to the Campaign by militant trade unions to force a 35 hour<br />
week on Australian industry. Since then the M~ inister for<br />
Industrial Relations, Mr Peacock, has made an important<br />
statement to the Parliament, and there has been a lot of<br />
discussion in the community about the 35 hour week.<br />
The view of the Government is that this campaign will have<br />
a serious effect on the Australian economy's capacity to<br />
provide the additional -job opportunities we are all seeking.<br />
It is essential,. that it be resisted in every reasonable way<br />
possible. The question is not whether the forty hour week<br />
is unchangeable for all time. The Government believes that<br />
it is fair that genuine productivity gains in industry be shared<br />
by all, by consumers in the form of lower prices, by<br />
businesses, in the form of profits needed to create jobs,<br />
by employees,,. in the form of improved working conditions.<br />
But the present union campaign is not about distributing<br />
the benefits of productivity to the community in the way that<br />
I have described. It is an attempt by a few powerful and<br />
irresponsible unions to grab all those benefits, and more,<br />
for themselves and their members.<br />
The introduction of shorter working hours is not a matter<br />
to be settled at the expense of the community by deals<br />
between big business and big unions. During this week the<br />
Government was pleased to receive support for this view<br />
from the Chairman of ICI who stated that contrary to press<br />
reports his company did not intend to concede a 35 hour week<br />
to its unions.<br />
It was also pleasing to hear some more responsible statements<br />
by Labor Party spokesman and Premier of New South Wales,<br />
Mr Wran, who stated that he didn't believe that a 35 hour<br />
week was inevitable. Indeed, he said, " We should not think of<br />
a 35 hour week across the board in any circumstances." Less<br />
than a year ago, Mr Hayden was saying much the same thing.<br />
He said, " I have got to say frankly that as an economist,<br />
and a former treasurer I would not support a<br />
hour week at this time. In my view it would have damaging<br />
cnsequences-to many industries and I see a much greater need<br />
at this point to use resources that are available to generate.<br />
more jobs, to get the economy fully employed rather than<br />
moving to a 35 hour week." It is regrettable that instead<br />
of maintaining this responsible attitude, the Federal Labor<br />
Party is now siding with the powerful unions. </p>
<p>-2<br />
During Mr Hawke's Presidency of the ACTU in 1979 the resolution<br />
was adopted that unions in all industries should " immediately<br />
develop and actively pursue programmes for achieving shorter<br />
working hours." Mr Hawke and others continue to support<br />
the view that shorter working hours are inevitable<br />
and there should not be strong resistance to the present<br />
irresponsible campaign. It is time that Mr Hayden, in<br />
his role as leader of the Labor Party, stood up for the principles<br />
he enunciated so clearly a year ago, instead of silently<br />
supporting the confrontationist approach of the militant<br />
unions._ I<br />
The Altona dispute is a good example of the kind of thing<br />
which this 35 hour week campaign involves. The companies<br />
were forced, by a campaign which started with " sit-ins" and<br />
ended with strikes, to make quite unreal concessions. In<br />
return, the unions in some cases agreed to nothing more<br />
than to work in accordance with existing awards. It was<br />
agreed, for example, that correct timekeeping would be<br />
implemented, that work and job cards would be used more<br />
efficently and that tea breaks would be restricted to<br />
the existing allocated time. The agreement was heralded as<br />
based on productivity gains. * In reality, unionists were<br />
rewarded for giving up undesirable work practices that should<br />
never have existed.<br />
The Government cannot stand by and allow the unions to use<br />
improperly imposed restrictive practices as a basis for<br />
so-called productivity bargains. Nor can we remain silent and<br />
inactive when we see the possiblity of big business making<br />
concessions which will eventually lead to unemployment and<br />
unprofitability in less insulated and protected industries.<br />
The dangers of these undesirable results are especially<br />
acute when one set of productivity gains are double-counted,<br />
used once to secure pay increases and again to secure shorter<br />
hours of work. And they are increased even further when the<br />
same gains are then used to justify a general flow-on of<br />
benefits to others. Double-counting of benefits can only<br />
refuel inflation and reduce employment prospects.<br />
The Government is seeking the co-operation of trade unions and<br />
business leaders in ensuring that the benefits of higher<br />
productivity are widely shared by the community as a whole.<br />
The fact is, however, that a major assault has been launched<br />
on industry by the organised union movement' to extract gains<br />
for a relative few without any sense of eortmunity responsibilit~ y.<br />
Those people looking for work, senior citizens and retired<br />
people, small businessmen and others who are, damaged by<br />
the 35 hour week campaign deserve better from powerful<br />
institutions like the trade unions and the Labor Party than<br />
they are gettting at the moment. It is time for responsible leadership </p>
<p>-3-<br />
in the union movement and the Labor Party to recognise this<br />
fact and to acknowledge their responsibilities to other<br />
people in the community. The central issue in this 35 hour<br />
week campaign is really one of the moral responsibility of<br />
a few to the rest of the community. 000--</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
