<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4551</transcript-id>
    <title>POLICY SPEECH, 21 NOVEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/11/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004551_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
* SRC830 PRIME~ MINI&amp; TER<br />
.';:. UNDER STRICT EMBARGO UNTIL g p. m. CAU8ERI^<br />
POLICY SPEECH 21 NOVEMBER 1977<br />
Oar nation is on the move.<br />
We are ready to stride into a new era of prosperity and<br />
development. We have broken through in the fight against<br />
inflation. Under Labor, inflation reached nineteen percent. We have<br />
halved that. Inflation is nine percent and falling.<br />
We have reduced taxes, revived incentive and restored fair<br />
reward for achievement.<br />
Under Labor taxes doubled. We have ended the big tax ripoff.<br />
Now Mr Whitlam wants to start it again.<br />
Business is being revitalised, profits are up, interest rates<br />
have begun to fall and they will k; ecp on falling.. We've<br />
been doing the job we were elected to do.<br />
We have been able to reduce inflation, reform the tax system,<br />
revive business and start interest rates falling because we<br />
have brought Government spending under control; because we<br />
have halved Labor's four and a half billion dollar deficit.<br />
We have given Australia reliable and responsible economic<br />
Government. We have restored integrity in Government and<br />
all praise to ' Phillip Lynch who has upheld the highest<br />
traditions of the Westminster system.<br />
Our policies have given people the confidence and incentive<br />
to invest in Australia's future. Australia is ready to go<br />
with six thousand million dollars of development in coal,<br />
iron ore, bauxite, alumina, petroleum and nickel, in<br />
manufacturing industry, in construction and retai. ling.<br />
And in the coming three years we can look to other vast<br />
developments: the three billion dollar North-West Shelf project,<br />
bigger than the Snowy Mountain Scheme;<br />
the development of our vital oil and gas reserves;<br />
and using ' our immense uranium deposits for peaceful<br />
purposes under the world's strictest safeguards. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
-'. ttee0m:~ rieaetpeo-j jcotb s, StilnUIZhte growth,<br />
and prospCrity. They w* iA3: hring Wealth a91( work<br />
to ( Iii cokntry.<br />
We all J~ rnOw what the real 11nswer to n~ n~ ycti<br />
it's qelieratill, qrowth and development;<br />
it's3 industry providing new j6, bs;<br />
it's trainiAg rpeople to fill new acb~ jJhnede p themt.<br />
1,, e ha ve saved. tens of thousands of Aus; tralian jobs because we gave<br />
Utail iridIStYY the PXotec-' tion we proJnisecl Unlike Mrt Whitj. am<br />
We not enoto xted thousands Oi : jobs t16htough acxoss the hoardl<br />
tarlifi eslasing.<br />
? eusu. of ouar p-. olicies new jobs are being created. our<br />
trainin-and joii assistance sche,. ies are 9cetting9 the unemployed<br />
into real jobs, prodluctive jobs, jobs that they can keep.<br />
lie a?-c spending more than $ 100 m~ illionl on traininq and job<br />
assistarico schoerrse which especially help young people learn<br />
new rsilJs. 7Ktrcady woll over 120,000 people have been or<br />
arc being helped by our schemes and we tire constantly<br />
Imnproving them,.<br />
Sdetermined that our children will have job ' 0zills<br />
slills; that the education system often fails to teach.<br />
xad r. 1 thie ' education programmeo for uonemployed yotith<br />
gTivj; e s youncl people the chance to acq-, ire the basic<br />
1ls1 andI MOtivation -they need to get a job.<br />
Wew~: Lspend afurther $ 50) million over an bove o; tng<br />
cornmtr, ents on replacing the outmodeed technical schools~ in<br />
OIur Lrinex city axeas and country towns.<br />
Ln thie last two yeaxs, the Commonwealth Bployment* Eexv'ice,<br />
hasVcc 900,000 people in jobs. We are upgrading the<br />
c f fcotiVeness of the C. lE. S. to )) elp more people finrd m~ ore<br />
JBecauseC Of our job assistance strategy, because of the<br />
c2Xwt-jand development our~ policies have made possible<br />
611
and Gentlemen, above all. else, this election will<br />
~ iethe we ill ) b) iild oni the achicvc'inents of the<br />
X. t'; O year:;, or whether we will let Labor throw xt aill<br />
e. le Lit j, committed to reversing the policies that have qiven<br />
Austral1ians confiaence. Labor is the Party of extravagance,<br />
of AI. Intion, of * high taxes, of in~ dustrial . lawle:. sne!; s.<br />
I* t is Labor that is the Party of unemployment.<br />
Labor today are still pedaling the same policies which in<br />
one ,' ear increaseo unemplolment. by 157%. / 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
That's 192,000 moxe Australians out of y4ork. Why eloesn't<br />
Mr Whitlam tell us how many Grand Final crowds that would<br />
make. When~ they were in Government, they stopped grovith and<br />
development. The only things that went ahead were ilifintioll,<br />
and uncrmploymcnt. Mr whitlannow wants to do it all over<br />
again.<br />
There has rarely beeni an election giving the Australian<br />
people a clearer choice.<br />
The choice is between this Government, which has restored<br />
sanifty to Government spending, given fthe Australian people<br />
the greatest tax reforms in our history, and the Labor Opposition,<br />
which would unleash Government spending and imm-ediately impose<br />
higher taxes.<br />
. Labor has itself admitted that it would increase spending<br />
by ani extra $ 800 million, anid this is only a sytall part<br />
of their plans.<br />
just six of theik other promises would cost mnore than $ 3,000<br />
million per year-. And on top of all this they<br />
would spend a further $ 1,700 million to abolish payroll tax.<br />
To pay for tU!%.-Lbor %, ould pass a law taking six dollars<br />
a weekc out of the average wage earner's pocket.<br />
At one blow, Labor woald increase Australian's personal tax<br />
burden by $ 1700 million dollars.<br />
Labor wouild end the reward for initiative and achbievement<br />
which is the basis for economic recovery; the basis for<br />
creating new jobs.<br />
I have no doubt at all that the working men and women of<br />
A% 3stralia will reject this recipe for disaster,<br />
Mr'Wran has said he wanted tax cuts.<br />
Mr Dunstan has said he wanted tax cuts.<br />
Mr Hawke has said he wanted t~ x cuts.<br />
These nf--n must now deplore Fir whitlarn's policy of taking mtoney<br />
away fromn Austxalia's workers and putting it in the pockets<br />
of large companies.<br />
We w. ould. all pay * higher taxes for* Labor's extravagance and we<br />
would pay in highier interest rates, higher inflation, higher<br />
unemployment*. Labor'. s policies would stop investment in Australia and stop<br />
growth. They would deny Australians the right to work. They<br />
would dishonour contracts. </p>
<p>1 9 7 5 ) mr WI, i t i r-J onjfeA d'x; rt* his<br />
p~ ys lie mvver sicjneei ariythinyj-now thr-j" Say UranMI\' In Shou11'<br />
T JXca bo~ c Party i~ tryiII9 to Obst-xutt AUStr a 1 i Z.' s dv e.-o pmc -n t<br />
Thy rcs partne-; cs in c'bstjuction id~ h ext~ mmist tinion 1c.-. 1ers.<br />
e: trcm3t Led unionfs are all affi1iated wi-th the Lnb-tro<br />
12! 3r I-Y; they all paty mrincy to thc L~ abor Party; the-1-l he~<br />
Z*!; hoCide off icial Lnbor Policy.<br />
1t. i1i1s-11s policy that b~ d: lyr iiiJ 1~ </p>
<p>explore, and develop.<br />
That's why it is Labor's Official~ policy to put unions above<br />
the law. That's why Labor endlorsed the Victorian power strike.<br />
T~ hey7 endorsod a strike which laid off 450,000 p eople for weeks.<br />
They endorsed a strie which tbrew 36,000 people completely out<br />
of a job.<br />
We have shown that the public can bec protectcd; that a fair<br />
and resolute stand can work.. It worked in the -air controllers Strikil<br />
in the postal workers dispute; it wor); ed against the ACTUIS xuraniun;<br />
moratorium tbey baclked dowvm. And in the Victorian rpower clisplitc,<br />
it was our move to derogister the unions involved -that 2ed to the<br />
strikers returning to work.<br />
we have been the first government to pass laws protecting individual<br />
unlionists and give responsible rank arnd file unlionists the chance<br />
to make their voices heard.<br />
Sec; ret postal ballots for union elections are now compulsory. 14e<br />
have set uip the Xndustrial Relations Bureau to protect the public<br />
interest und also to act as an inelustrial'onibusdman: Unions are now<br />
required to tell. their MeMbers how union Clues are spent. We are<br />
protecting individuals against being forced to join unions against<br />
their will.<br />
Responsible unionizts have welcomed these laws. Only the cxltremist<br />
and the L~ abor Party have follght against thein. These laws will not<br />
change things overnight. ) 3% t ovar time they will have a major<br />
impact. At last, responsible unionists have a chance.<br />
Labor woold tako it from them; Labor would back 6own on all these<br />
laws.<br />
We won't back dlown on any of our responsibilities.<br />
-Let' s look at some of -the reforms we have brought In since coming<br />
to office, and how we wi'll be building on these reforms in the<br />
years ahead.<br />
WIe will be . Zurther developing our existing programmes which are<br />
working well and in some cases initiating new prograntmes,<br />
The total cost of these new programmes is an additional. $ 20 million<br />
this financial year -no more: and $ 250 million in 1978/ 79.<br />
This Govern-ment has brought in the lares rId fairest reforms ever<br />
made to Australia's tax: system. T'ax indexation snves every<br />
Astralian taxpayer more money each year.<br />
From February 1st, further tax~ cuts will come in for every Austral.'<br />
wiage anel salary ear-ner. This year alone, the person on average<br />
ear-ningjs will be saving $ 6 a week from these two xeforms. From<br />
V'ebruary 1st, more than 225,000 low income earners will cease to<br />
pay any tax at all. And becauase we have rcluced the marginal rate<br />
of tax: its now worthi wor1ing overtime again.<br />
1% 1e ) aIovi decl business with essential tax incentives to inve st, </p>
<p>irpar: t from-1 our tax: c~ r ~ m to J~~~ t\ I4nc ' C12 OOr<br />
pc~ n1tax YCAOYnB savc\'" $ i 30 J~ I3 on<br />
Th e AI : tr ! A! i1' I. I -eop I e 11 n ot ncc Ip z3 .1te o : o ha01<br />
ed uty has cakiseel( i. t'L alle ) hPriM to t~ oolliarnI!:<br />
1. i Jh o, all cieceaseei estzites and gifts rxwssi nq botw. eenr ) Ixsali<br />
rt-i6 kiidf, ptarent and ch-ilc, wi&amp;: Li bo exempt xrorn<br />
nxu
Over the 1i4fe of* the next Parl-liarnent estate and q~ ift dluty will11<br />
both be . entirely nboi. hed.<br />
.~ eout: dew'n c-UC5inl yvcuXl rates by giving loccal oenet<br />
Ssharcc al l prsonzil incor ax : cecr-4te. . Thni y-ar it<br />
a Over the nevt three-ycars, we will inc-cfease<br />
thW. c-" share to~ 2%.<br />
e e ~ e -c ci Ee i ithe c mii rf , o f mo s-t r.) 1 A1 s br a~ E<br />
frate to assistbtsirtess so tht, r b<br />
cc. n Y. e created.<br />
T. UZ-w hav a b een d i f1ic~ it f or Aus tr a 1 a Is tbo-or nd SL 1, -rr1l<br />
is:. Ii-je ss le n. We have hel~ ped emall bukiiiness with our tka; cocncessiojim<br />
x~ igStocko with the investMe~ lt allOWRIxcc ; nd 011r pc-8r) inal<br />
t ckL arnr3 we Tm-i:, Le more iinance Livaila'blc to : nmnal. l c<br />
t~: h U IA -C 011, MOrnnw e i t I IDa v e Iop: Ye n t 3 a n hi6e A I. 0. C<br />
' u-. 4~ eLrbox-, thjs G; over nrent has 1-o-ught Atistra i-nn !-1aereAMC possibU<br />
w. 11. L coi-tinue to buy Yvustralian.<br />
. t We wil ,, ct to~ inr-e the proc 35J. L19~ A r, J\ ii-. ~ r~ iz x u<br />
Vc~ have endted Labor's savage bias Cuais Orhrñ c-ara3.<br />
cc~~. nty. Otr miany prcogran1ales are helping thie TuraL Commurnity<br />
~; v
TA~ uhct raianRural Bank will open, in 1978.<br />
Pet-! c'l-P prices in country are-as will be rccduceil to within in ccont<br />
Wc L. tC the )) oxfjr; ( city rc-t., ail price i. t) hout ~ r y 11) cxe0,1 rL<br />
ct ri ce s a S a x esu 1t. </p>
<p>-7-<br />
Ove-r the nc-;
1C1than half a ceQnt pc-r litro.<br />
We will' in consultatiorn with the industries corncernedl act to<br />
imnprove beef and wool mark-etinc. arrangements,<br />
. Phere are other rneaslares zlupportingi rural indistry sct out in the<br />
supplementary statements izsued tonight and the Deputy Prime M~ inistl<br />
will elaborate on these tomorrow evening.<br />
Social Secuxity' and* V-ealt~ h<br />
Our soc~ ial ref orms, have helped families and ifldLviluals and<br />
widened freedoin of choice.<br />
Our Family Allowance is tho most important innovation in vielfare<br />
for decades.<br />
The Nedibank refotrms give Australians choice in health insiuxance.<br />
The old harsh means test haS been replaced by a simple income<br />
test. We have tak~ en politics out of pension increases by linking t-hem<br />
auitomati cally-with-the* Consumer Price Index.<br />
We have brought in a pension for all sole parents another<br />
major reform.<br />
N~ ow, so that mare homes and centres for the aged and handicapped<br />
can be bxiilt, we will extend the present threa ye-ax funding progjzau<br />
for a further year. . We will provide larger grants to hoines for<br />
the age4d in remote areas, and subsidise the added costs people in<br />
remote areas must pay to obtain specialist medical treatment.<br />
We will encoarage families to care for their sick and, aged by<br />
increasing and expanding the domiciliary nursing care benefit.<br />
We have given the handicapped a new deal and we will maintain our<br />
expanded child care programme.<br />
Boducation The Gov'ermient has given education high priority.<br />
We have established the new Tertiary Fducation Commission and<br />
appointed the Williams Comnittee of Inquiry into P-ducation and<br />
Train in(.<br />
Government schools in all States have substantially exceeded<br />
school's comission targets.<br />
We are conscious of the disadvantage of ifany non-government schoolsI<br />
and our policies which place due emphasis on needs, are desig9ned<br />
to provide egiiality of apportbnity for all Australians. </p>
<p>A c'rA ni t. i ati'c e 1. L rLW er' t C) c rn a c*<br />
J i-too . oivj icj'&amp; c Uho ' 3neiC ~ ovr~ b . t<br />
to ree~ a~ c or-n())-ral chiWCD, but. r71,1 y~ ru<br />
of iU,,~ jcnppcC1 chi. 1dre-n pay hiond-eds of their<br />
J1 f' ( M'luc; ticn and -III-s ia ' ust3 cC Ww3i. l cez~.. e. C( Ie r<br />
t'iisGc. w\' rnrvi-t they wdll. no lo qr-hmic G-oc(-3c,) i<br />
-toe thesce chiXC~ rer n c~ jul chanc-,.<br />
Ouc 1hC) flh sav-I Ig S c r P. t f3 c h e h as h e1)( I I hIc; p n5 t. n s<br />
o: o ui ; a n ds o 1 p e 0p c t o buyv teir f ir t ho m<br />
I, I c 0 0 F, te.? 1-U tt e~ a Cl ir n . r ia n c m, s n<br />
p an i n s ur an c I cm e poIteo, 0t i s~ zv i q% c: p o . e~ vs~<br />
bnwi 10C. ing Soo i eties.<br />
19. t7 8/ 73 \ c,?. ill oxpand eis-tinq-progra,. c. es to y': covi( 3c a 4--ttal r'f<br />
; rullyf teh l:. U ex t Y'eac rs to Arprco\ e 11: ban<br />
We wil also vuiCaeitakc a~ five year prograrune to iipyrade cri'tica1<br />
i~ e~ ti 0o1 the national. railway network.<br />
rna~ e StartI-pi-% nin Drisb&amp; ne tba irntennatioa ip<br />
en(-m vealk : a tat is. o </p>
<p>I. 1 cc<br />
~ itoutan icreseinbasic'ratat fo te ast 1two. years.' Now<br />
Ve wil 1 move to cut off-peak telephona charges to about<br />
of the normal rate.<br />
Enrg cy<br />
Under our comprehensive national energy policy we will step<br />
up research and developyaentof new energy resources, especially<br />
coal and solar energy.<br />
Aborigines<br />
We are acting to and the offensive paternalism of past policie,%<br />
towards~ Aborigines. ' We wdll. continue to encouxage self -management<br />
of Aboriginal programmes anid make them masters of their own<br />
affairs. In addition to the many prograrunes we now have, wo wgill start<br />
new prograrmncs designed to improve facilities anid services<br />
for young Aborigines; provide training and management an~ d<br />
other sk; ills; and let Aborigines participate more fully in<br />
preventive health care projects.<br />
Bthnic Affairs<br />
Australia is a multi-cultural society.* The Government is concend<br />
for ou-r 13thnic comminities. in the next three years weshl<br />
concentrate on overcoming the larig; uatle ba. ricrs in our society.<br />
Our measures will include:<br />
ecic ftEhg ih to migrants and in co-oneration<br />
with the States expand thce teaching of ethnic languages<br />
and culture in our schoolu<br />
-the provision of Ethnic liaison officers in Government<br />
Departmnrts<br />
more interprc~ tcers, translators-and migrant welfare<br />
officers<br />
-more migrant resource centres.<br />
Ir'or the first time the age service pension will be paid to non-.<br />
British former members of the allied forces.<br />
We -have put Ethnuic broadcasting on a permanent basis, nnd we<br />
will establish Zthnia television.<br />
iniiul i~ t<br />
We have protected individual rights and reformed outdated laws.<br />
The Ombudsman, and Administrative Appeals Tribunal protect<br />
basic civil liberties.<br />
we WAIll establish a Human Rights Commission to extend that<br />
protection further and we will bring in freedom of informration<br />
laws. </p>
<p>( 11-<br />
' Ihpac -frminent. Worenls P~ yto adtvi r; thc<br />
( c) Vi&amp;-n'irien', t On Womns A f fai r.<br />
We have pyovided increased firlanical a Eistance and tax: incentivCeS<br />
to the sirts, reform~ ed the Australia Council, &amp; nd now we will<br />
help our filr, industry by allow. ing film procflucticn costs to<br />
be wr-itten off over two years iflstea~ l o~ f twenty five.<br />
IelAe vigilantly protected the erivironnment. We are establishingj<br />
I , uladul the world ' s lar( Iest national park., and ani independent,<br />
OCngtuirI t o cXar: lillIC the most c-' fective why! 3 coflsc-rvisg and<br />
projtoctingC. till r~ pCciecr 01 jqhal.-,. We are helpigte~ irc i~ i<br />
fund to set up a bxanch in Australia.<br />
Security and Foe( n11lc<br />
P.',, tralia' a security and forcign policy is always a hi. gh<br />
priority for a.. Libera). Nationial Country Party Gove~ rnm~ ent.<br />
Thc Roval Commission on Security aned Intelli(. ence cc'Tcludc~ d<br />
thit We iace serious threats of espionage and subvewsion,<br />
Va7 re strongthening all areas 01J the Clefencc forces. Pox<br />
orNaple, t-his progatmne includes the construction 0ñ fourten<br />
fa; 7-t vatrol boats built. by a great North Quenslarie shipbhuilder<br />
iat Cairnsi, the const1-riiction ait Newcastl. c of a car:( o Lhip -or the<br />
dufonocc forces~ and the oirderini a thi. re quided Tr~ sol frigate.-<br />
We hanve rostcccd close relations with our frionds and alliesI<br />
an6 extc), ende the vital Pine Gap agreemeo. t with the tlnite( I<br />
Sta-' Ces, for a forther ten years,<br />
W'e have imprcovcd oiar relations with nll ou) r n~ et neiq~ hbouirs.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen, the new initiatives I have outlineed<br />
tO))-Vht and further policies which are set out in the<br />
suJplementary -, tatemenils are, tt creative, xespoiisiIle and<br />
baqinced rproiraine.<br />
S ince coming to of fice, we have f acecl the diñ l 1 u t choices.<br />
Th~ touqgh dc~ sions have been iziae.<br />
W: V been ooiing the Job % qe wc-Incechted to do.<br />
Th the great issue befw~ e every one of us ii, whethxer we will<br />
1) u it'Ci on these hard won foundations, whether we will grasp<br />
Oh'lciportunity to make Australia the great coiuntry we all<br />
can be:<br />
an) Astralia where people have the freedom to achieve<br />
-to biuild the kind of life they want wh) ere there<br />
arc rowards for initiative and incentives for<br />
entetpri" e;<br />
-an hust aliaI which is stronc! and secore, whi~ ch cares<br />
for those in need, whe're all people can live and viork<br />
together in self-respect. </p>
<p>rr iC-lr<br />
ihere are still problems to bc fnced, there is still<br />
work to be done.,<br />
T3ut Aistralia is ready to iake the breakthrough into n<br />
period of real prosperity.<br />
A vote for the Liberal Party is a vote fox an exciting ar:'<br />
rewarding future for Australia.<br />
With your suppot this Goverzment is determined to buil~ d n<br />
what we have already achievP to make Australia a sc-cieiy<br />
wich can set a standard for the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
