<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5616</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH TO UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINA COLUMBIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005616.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
3y 4-~~ fA\ 4~<br />
J!,_ AUSTRAI4<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
WEDNESDAY, JULY 8, 1981<br />
SPEECH TO UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINACOLUMBIA<br />
You have asked me here today as the Prime Minister of Australia.<br />
Had I the time and you the patience, there are many aspects of<br />
my country that I could enlarge upon: Australia's role as a<br />
significant, independent-minded middle power; Australia as a<br />
leading member of what people are starting to think of as the<br />
Pacific coammunity, a region which contains the most rapidly<br />
growing economies in the world; Australia as an ally of the<br />
United States, ( and, incidentally, one of only two countries<br />
which have fought alongside America in four major wars in<br />
this century); Australia as the world's leading exporter,<br />
or very near to it, of a range of important minerals iron ore,<br />
coal, alumina, mineral sands, lead, zinc and several others;<br />
Australia as, along with the United States and Canada, one<br />
of-the--wor'Ld's-maj-or--efficient producers and-exporters of food.<br />
But it is another aspect of Australia that I particularly want<br />
to draw your attention to today, for it is pertinent to my<br />
theme. Along with New Zealand, Australia is the only stable<br />
democratic, liberal, Western society in the Southern hemisphere.<br />
While we are thoroughly Western in our values and institutions,<br />
all our neighbours are Third World countries. They belong<br />
to the " South" in terms of the " North-South" dichotomy that is<br />
now widely used, while by almost every test except geography<br />
we belong to the " North". Li vin9 near to these countries and,<br />
I might add, associated closely with many more of them<br />
through the Commonwealth we are of necessity very much aware<br />
of their perspectives and problems, more so perhaps than other<br />
developed countries of th ' e Northern hemisphere. Our situation<br />
requires us to give serious, constant attention to relations<br />
between the West and the Third World.<br />
It is about this subject that I want to talk today. But before<br />
I do let me make one thing very clear. If I concentrate on<br />
these questions on this occasion, it is not because Australia is<br />
indifferent to or complacent about East-West questions, about the<br />
seriousness of the military threat of the Soviet Union to freedom<br />
and democracy in the world. On the contrary, we are most concerned. </p>
<p>-2<br />
Since assuming office in 1975, 1 and my Government have<br />
constantly emphasised the gravity of this threat and the<br />
need for an effective response by the West. We did so even when<br />
belief in detente was in the ascendancy and the views we<br />
expressed were unfashionable and characterised as<br />
provocative.<br />
Now, and none too soon, things have changed, partly due to<br />
the blatant nature of Soviet behaviour and partly to the<br />
remobilisation of will in the United States which<br />
President Reagan embodies. In my talks with the President<br />
last week, I made it clear that Australia profoundly welcomes'<br />
the re-found resolve and firmness of the United States towards<br />
the Soviet Union. As a middle power, Australia will do all<br />
within its means to encourage and support strong and purposeful<br />
American leadership in this respect.<br />
I say with absolute conviction that such leadership from you<br />
is an essential precondition for the security of peace, freedom<br />
and democracy in the world. I say also, and with equal<br />
conviction, that you are entitled to and must receive support<br />
from other democratic Governments in this task.<br />
The American nation has carried a huge burden in defence of<br />
freedohm over the last four decades. Its shoulders are strong.<br />
But itiorally and materially the burden must be shared, shared<br />
by other democracies which have grown wealthier and more<br />
powerful behind the protection you have provided and, in the<br />
case of Western Europe, as a result of the economic help you<br />
gave -_ in, t he -_ imm , dei a , te-post-war years.-( The Marshall Plan still<br />
stands out as a magnificent example of enlightened<br />
self-interest, a definitive reminder that generosity is often<br />
very sound policy.)<br />
We all know now that there is no such thing as a free lunch;<br />
Western countries should also recognise that in the long run<br />
there is no such thing as a free ally. Australia well<br />
understands this. It is because we do, and also because we<br />
owe it to those Australians who fought and died in earlier<br />
wars, that we have spoken out and will continue to speak out<br />
about the need for a concerted effort on the part of the<br />
West. For such an effort is the surest guarantee of peace.<br />
I stress this not only because it is of vital importance in it~ s<br />
own right, but because it is a necessary background to what I<br />
have to say abodt relations between the West and the Third<br />
World. For my position is somewhat untypical.<br />
In the West, those who are tough-minded and realistic about<br />
East-West relations sometimes tend to be sceptical and<br />
dismissive about the Third world and North-South issues.<br />
They are disinclined to take them very seriously. </p>
<p>-3<br />
Conversely, those who are concerned about North-South<br />
issues, who accept they are important, only-too often dismiss<br />
a serious preoccupation with the Soviet threat as outdated,<br />
exaggerated and a diversion from the crucial problem of<br />
managing global interdependence.<br />
I believe that both groups and the either/ or mentality<br />
they represent are profoundly mistaken. I believe that<br />
East-West issues and North-South issues are of the utmost<br />
importance. I believe moreover that the two sets of issues<br />
are closely interlinked, that what happens 7 or equally<br />
important what does not happen with respect to one will have<br />
crucial implications for what happens to the other.<br />
There is no question of choice involved. As a matter of basic,<br />
rational self-interest they must both be attended to and<br />
attended to urgently. As I judge it, the most immediate danger<br />
to guard against at present with respect to relations between<br />
the West and the Third World is that of scepticism and<br />
indifference.<br />
There are thoughtful, honest and responsible people who<br />
maintain that there is really no such entity as the " South"<br />
or the " Third World", that it is merely the figment of the<br />
imagination of intellectuals, ideologues and journalists.<br />
They Point to the heterogeneity of the Third World, the<br />
great differences which exist among its claimed members, to<br />
their disparate and conflicting interests. And they conclude<br />
that there is no substance behind. the-jabels, . They maintain<br />
_ th erefor etha't Western -dealings with the countries involved<br />
should be bilateral and selective and that we should refuse<br />
to accept the notion of a North-South dialogue.<br />
There are others who say that even if there is some substance<br />
there, it is fast disappearing as memories of colonialism<br />
fade and as a significant number of Third World states become<br />
more developed and wealthy. They anticipate a process of<br />
" graduating out' which will leave the Third World an<br />
increasingly unimportant rump. On this basis, they argue<br />
that what the West should do i~ s to stall and play for timeto<br />
keep issues " on the back-burner" as the saying goes in<br />
anticipation that pressure and demands will diminish with time.<br />
Most important of all, perhaps, there are those who maintain<br />
that even if the'Third World exists and continues to exist, it<br />
need not be taken too seriously. The advantages, they claim,<br />
are all with the developed industrial countries.<br />
You remember that Stalin once contemptously asked the question,<br />
" The Pope? How many divisions has the Pope?" These people<br />
take a similar attitude towards the Third World. -Overall, they<br />
point out, it is poor, it lacks political and military power, it<br />
is dependent on Western capital, know-how, aid and managerial<br />
capacity. It needs us much more than we need it. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Therefore, they complacently conclude, we can afford to<br />
resist its demands, to drive a hard bargain or, indeed, to<br />
refuse to make any bargain at all. I believe all these views<br />
to be profoundly mistaken.<br />
Everything that is said about the diversity and conflicting<br />
interests of Third World countries is true. But as well as this,<br />
and despite it, there is also a real sense of identity, of<br />
unity and solidarity among these countries.<br />
You may recall that it was said of the Holy Roman Empire that it'<br />
was not holy, Roman or an empire; yet it was a potent actor-in<br />
European politics for centuries. In the same way, the Third World<br />
is today a potent reality despite its internal diversity and<br />
divisions. That reality is evident in the voting patterns of<br />
the United Nations. It is evident in the institutions that the<br />
recently independent countries have forged for tlxemselves,<br />
particularly the Group of 77 and the non-aligned movement.<br />
It is evident in the degree of support the now oil-producing<br />
countries have given OPEC despite their interest in low oil<br />
prices; in the willingness of non-African states to support the<br />
Africans in their opposition to South Africa and apartheid; in<br />
the willingness of non-Arab states to support the Arabs over<br />
Palestine; in their ability to agree on the programme for a new<br />
international economic order. It is evident most of all in their<br />
ideology.<br />
-Those-who-dismiss.-this.-ideology-as " merely rhetoric" are, I<br />
suggest, ignoring the overwhelming and cruel evidence which this<br />
century has provided of the decisive importance of ideology in<br />
modern politics. I agree with Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan<br />
that " the beginning of wisdom in dealing with the nations of the<br />
Third World is to recognise their essential ideological coherence"<br />
For in political terms the Third World is essentially a state<br />
of mind: a matter of shared memories, frustrations, aspirations<br />
and sense of what is equitable and just. Like the working classes<br />
in the domestic politics of the 19th century, they want to have<br />
full citizen rights in the world, to be subjects who act rather<br />
than objects who are acted upon: Just as Stalin was foolish in<br />
overlooking the spiritual power of the Papacy, so it would<br />
be foolish to underestimate the binding and motivating force of<br />
this aspiration in the Third World.<br />
As to the claim that the Third World will disintegrate before long,<br />
that there will be a'" graduating out", I simply observe that<br />
twenty years after the main wave of decolonisation there is no<br />
evidence of it. Many Third World countries have made great economic<br />
progress in that time some have transformed themselves but none<br />
has sought, as a result, to disassociate itself fromi the group<br />
or shows any sign of doing so. </p>
<p>Surely, if there were substance in this thesis of a natural<br />
" graduating out" process there would be some evidence to support<br />
it by now. In this respect I am sceptical of the sceptics. The<br />
Third World, or the " South", exists and is likely to continue to do<br />
so for the foreseeable future.<br />
But is it important? Should the West take seriously what it<br />
represents? My answer to that is an emphatic " yes". In economic.<br />
terms, something of the order of 25 per cent of the West's entire<br />
trade is with the Third World. In the case of the United States the<br />
figure is over 40 per cent and in the case of Japan 50 per cent.<br />
This means that hundreds of thousands of jobs in Western countries<br />
depend on this trade and that the serious unemployment we are now<br />
experiencing would reach crisis proportions proportions which<br />
would threaten tL-he existence of democracy itself if it was<br />
disrupted.<br />
There are manv in this audience and there are many In my own country<br />
who can remer~ ber the demoralising effect of the mass unemployment<br />
that occurred in the 1930s. In my own country over 30 per cent of the<br />
workforce was jobless during the worst period. A recurrence of<br />
unemployment on that scale would threaten the existence of<br />
democracy itself. Rising living standards and growing markets in<br />
Third World countries may play a critical role i n ensuring that<br />
we do not.. In addition, of course, the trade we have with the Third<br />
World involves commodities which are vital to Western economies<br />
and societies.<br />
Oil is the clearest and most important example, with 60 per cent of<br />
the world's oil coming from a handful of Third World countries.<br />
Out of conviction or prudence, or a mixture of both, those countries<br />
have shown themselves unwilling to divorce the question of oil from<br />
other matters of concern to their fellow members of the Third World.<br />
Beyond this there is the fundamental point that the West's<br />
commitment to a global market system requires and depends on the<br />
participation of the 120 or so countries of the Third World, over<br />
two thirds of all the countries which exist in the world.<br />
One should not talk of these economic relationships purely in terms<br />
of potential danger. The language of opportunity is equally relevant.<br />
Over the last decade a number of Third World countries the so-called<br />
newly industrialising countries have sustained growth rates well<br />
in excess of those achieved by the rest of the world, including the<br />
West. By doing so they have prevented the world recession from being<br />
much more severe than ~ it would otherwise have been. Insofar as<br />
this vigorous growth is * maintained and extended to other Third World<br />
countries, insofar as countries which are now clients, through rising<br />
living standards, are converted into customers and consumers, the<br />
economies of the West will benefit. And insofar as this does not<br />
happen they will be impoverished. / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
This is why it is essential that, in its dealings with the<br />
Third World, the West should be true to its faith in the market<br />
system, should allow the newly industrialised countries access<br />
to its markets and should reject firmly the temptation to resort<br />
to protectionist measures which deny those countries the rewards<br />
for their own efforts and enterprise. In saying this I am<br />
emphatically rejecting the Marxist notion that the prosperity of<br />
the West depends on the impoverishment of the Third World.<br />
Thomas Jefferson's observation that " it is a kind of law of nature<br />
that every nation prospers by the prosperity of others" seems to<br />
me to be much closer to the mark and a much better guide to policy.<br />
Australia is in as good a position as anyone to appreciate all this.<br />
We happen to live in a part of the world where-many of these newly<br />
industrialised countries are concentrated, countries whose economies<br />
have been growing at twice the world average, or better, over<br />
recent decades. They together with Japan, which iuo many respects<br />
has provided a model for them have proved invaluable to Australia<br />
at a time when structural changes were threatening our traditional<br />
markets in Europe. They have made possible a remarkable change in<br />
our pattern of trade.<br />
Of course, it is true that if the West is dependent on trade wi th<br />
the Third World,-the Third World is even more dependent on trade<br />
with the West. Over 70 per cent of its trade is with the developed<br />
industrialised countries. But it is a serious error to assume, as<br />
some do, that bec-ause of this or for that matter because of the*<br />
substantial OPEC investments in the West the Third World can be<br />
taken for granted, that in the last resort it has no option but toco-<br />
operate with the West on Western terms.<br />
The basic error here is to assume the primacy of economic<br />
rationality over politics, an assumption that runs counter to the<br />
fundamental experience and character of the Third World. We would<br />
do well to remember the advice given by President Nkruxnah of<br />
Ghana to African nationalists: " Seek ye first the political<br />
kingdom". We would do well to remember too Sukarno' s " go to hell<br />
with your aid", uttered when the economy of Indonesia was a shambles<br />
and when it desperately needed all the American aid it could get.<br />
For these words represent widespread and deep-seated attitudes in<br />
the Third World.<br />
More recently, despite its irrationality and intolerance, what<br />
has happened in Iran has pointed to the same lesson: the lesson,<br />
that is, that many cou'ntries in the Third World will not hesitate<br />
to sacrifice their own immediate economic interests for political<br />
reasons of status, independence and what they believe is justice.<br />
./ 7 </p>
<p>7<br />
Those of us who fail to understand the force of this, do so only<br />
because we have forgotten our own history because we have<br />
possessed freedom and independence for so long, have come to<br />
take them so much for granted, that we do not recall the<br />
passionate intensity of feeling they invoke when they are newly<br />
acquired. But the author of the Declaration of Independence<br />
understood that feeling and shared it. " By the God that made me",<br />
he wrote in 1775, " 1 will cease to exist before I yield to a<br />
connection on such terms as the British Parliament proposes".<br />
That, or something very like it, could have been said by many Third<br />
World leaders in our time.<br />
It is also worth contemplating the potential power of the weak, of<br />
those who feel they have little left to lose the power to threaten<br />
collapse, disorder and chaos.-This is a potent power against<br />
those who have a large stake in stability and efficient working of<br />
the existing order. In this respect, the question that should be<br />
asked is not whether the Third World could conceivably reject the<br />
existing system and establish a viable one of its o~ fi, but how<br />
much damage would be done in any attempt to do so.<br />
Edmund Burke said it better when he observed, in the process of<br />
cautioning Britain on its treatment of the American colonies,<br />
critical moments in the fortunes of all states, when they who<br />
are unable to contribute to your prosperity may be strong enough<br />
to complete your ruin." Today, all the Western countries need<br />
to heed that advice.<br />
Apart from all this, there are compelling strategic and geopolitical<br />
reasons for taking the Third World seriously. Some of the most<br />
sensitive areas in the world the Middle East, the Caribbean and<br />
Central America, Southern Africa, the Korean peninsula are<br />
Third World areas. Most of the key " choke points" in the world<br />
the Straits of Hormuz, the Panama Canal, the entrances to the<br />
Red Sea, the passages from the Indian Ocean to East Asia lie<br />
within the Third World. Over and above this, East-West rivalry<br />
has been and is largely fought out in the Third World and the West<br />
is extremely sensitive, rightly so, concerning any significant<br />
gains made by the Soviet Union in the Third World.<br />
Moreover, despite its poor overall record in providing aid to<br />
developing countries, the Soviet Union can exploit tensions in<br />
relations between the West and the Third World. Given the<br />
unprecedented military strength it has at present, the Soviet<br />
Union is likely to make' a particular effort in this respect<br />
during the next few years.<br />
If the West is concerned to prevent these efforts from succeeding<br />
there are several things it should do. First, it should act to<br />
ensure that Third World perceptions of the East-West conflict<br />
are not of a declining West and an ascendant Soviet Union. For,<br />
as a political leader of a country allied to the United States once<br />
succinctly put it on returning from a visit to Moscow, " no-one<br />
wants to be caught on the wrong side". / 8 </p>
<p>-8<br />
Secondly, the West should act in ways which minimise the<br />
need for Third World countries to contemplate turning to the<br />
Soviet Union in order to get the aid and assistance they<br />
desperately need. That in turn means maintaining a constructive<br />
and forthcoming relationship which does not systematically<br />
frustrate Third World hopes.<br />
Thirdly, the West should do what it can to emphasise and show<br />
understanding of the economic dimensions of Third world affairs<br />
and the development aspirations of the Third World; for as long<br />
as the principal issues are economic the Soviet Union is not in the.<br />
race as a competitor to the West.<br />
What is needed, in other words, is an integrated policy which<br />
combines a stress on restoring, and then maintaining a military<br />
balance which can preserve world peace and a positive attitude<br />
towards economic relations with the South.<br />
I repeat, there is no real choice involved between these two<br />
components of policy. Both are essential. So far, I have<br />
deliberately concentrated on making the case, for a serious<br />
Western concern with the Third World in terms of direct political<br />
and economic self-interest, for that case has to be established<br />
if Wlestern Governments are to respond. But that does not mean<br />
that I do not recognise other aspects and arguments. I should<br />
like to mention two of these.<br />
First, there are the altruistic, humanitarian dimensions of the<br />
problem. We shculd never forget the extent of the stark human<br />
suffering that is involved in the Third World, never allowannoyance<br />
at ithe posturing and hypocrisy which sometimes<br />
characterises North-South relations to obscure it.<br />
According to the World Bank, not a body given to emotional<br />
exaggeration, 800 million people are living in conditions of<br />
" absolute poverty" in the Third World. The infant mortality rate<br />
in low income Third World countries is twelve times as high as<br />
it is in Western countries. Life expectancy in them is still<br />
under 50 years. Thousands are dying every week from malnutrition<br />
and outright starvation.<br />
As a society which holds Christian and humanitarian values, we must<br />
be diminished and damaged as long as we continue to live in a world<br />
where such conditions are commonplace. It is not a question of our<br />
masochistically accepting guilt for creating these conditions; that<br />
is an absurd oversimplification of the historical record. It is a<br />
question of our responsibility, in terms of our own professed values<br />
rather than of the demands of others, to work for the abolition of<br />
these intolerable conditions. And, again, of our interest in seeing<br />
them abolished.<br />
My second observation is that, even apart from the claims of the<br />
Third World, there is another dimension of international relations<br />
which points to a clear and urgent need for action. This is the one<br />
covered by the now familiar phrase " the management of interdependence" / 9 </p>
<p>9-<br />
It is true that in recent years the case for this has sometimes<br />
been overdrawn and it is foolish to maintain, as some have done,<br />
that this task somehow renders obsolete the traditional concerns<br />
of power and national interest. But even after this exaggeration<br />
has been discounted, the basic case is sound enough.<br />
The trebling of the number of states in the world; the very rapidO<br />
increase in the volume of transactions among these states;<br />
revolutionary changes in communications, transport and other<br />
technologies; much greater demands and pressures on man's physicaL<br />
environment; the emergence of trans-or multi-national corporations<br />
as a major force in international economic relations: all of these<br />
point to the necessity for developing multilateral negotiating<br />
processes to deal with the new and unprecedented complexity and<br />
to respond to the new awareness of global environmental problems.<br />
The quality of the world in which our-children will live will<br />
depend crucially on whether we succeed or fail in-this respect.<br />
But improving the management of interdependence and the North-South<br />
dialogue are intimately linked and progress in one depends on<br />
progress in the other. They must be approached as parallel<br />
enterprises. If the second is stalemated so will the first. At<br />
present the North-South dialogue is stalemated. The global<br />
negotiations which were to be held have been postponed and<br />
postponed again. There is little evidence at present of the<br />
political will necessary to break that stalemate and to initiate<br />
progress. As I have indicated I believe that there are compelling reasons why<br />
the effort to marshal that will must be made. There will be<br />
opportunities to make that effort in the near future: in the<br />
Ottawa Sunmmit this month; at the Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
Meeting which I shall chair in Melbourne in October; and at the<br />
summit meeting in Mexico on North-South issues shortly afterwards.<br />
If these oppor-tunities are not seized, if by the end of the year<br />
no progress has been made, the outlook will be very bleak indeed<br />
and the last decades of this century will promise tension, frustraltion<br />
and instability rather than hope. The Western nations should seize<br />
these opportunities.<br />
In doing so I suggest that there are a number of guidelines we<br />
should follow if we are to succeed:<br />
First, and fundamentally, we should accept and take seriously<br />
the reality of the outh or the Third World as . a political presence<br />
on the world stage.<br />
Second, we should accept that, given the great transformation that<br />
has occurred in the world in the past 40 years, significant changE! s<br />
in international institutions and processes are inevitable. The<br />
question is whether these changes are to be orderly, negotiated<br />
ones or imposed by disruption and breakdown. </p>
<p>10<br />
Third, substantively we should adopt an innovative, constructive<br />
attitude towards the North-South dialogue,. rather than be reactive<br />
or passive, leaving all the initiative to the Third World. For<br />
we have very important interests of our own in seeing progress<br />
made. Fourth, procedurally the efforts of the West should be directed-'<br />
to forging more effective and efficient forms of multilateral<br />
negotiations, rather than to avoiding, delaying or frustrating<br />
them.<br />
Fifth, if we want to retain credibility we should not play fast<br />
and loose with our commitment to the market economy. We should<br />
not preach it in order to dismiss Third World claims while<br />
simultaneously pleading special circumstances to justify exceptions<br />
in our own case. If exceptions can be made for our needs, why notfor<br />
those of the Third World? Conversely, if it is an overriding<br />
commitment, why not apply it in dealing with the ' Third World's<br />
claims for access to markets?<br />
Sixth, we should always bear in mind the interrelationship betweeL<br />
North-South and East-West issues and not treat them as two separate<br />
categories. Success in dealing with the Soviet Union will always<br />
require the -maintenance of a military balance. But in the middle to<br />
long term-. it will also depend significantly on the resolution of<br />
North-South differences. If Third World leaders come to us for the<br />
teachers, the advisers, the technologies, the capital, and in some.<br />
cases the political support they desperately need; if they make it<br />
evident that, given a choice, they do not want to deal with the.<br />
monolithic bureaucracy of the Soviet Union, that they are suspicious<br />
of its demands for political association as the price for aid; and<br />
if we still refuse to respond to them then we do so at our own<br />
peril and the consequences should come as no surprise. The needs<br />
of the Third World are such that, in the last resort, it will turn<br />
for assistance to wherever it is available, rather than go without.<br />
The West must ensure that that last resort is not the Soviet Union.<br />
Seventh, we should act in such ways as to support and strengthen<br />
the moderate elements in the Third World. Those elements which<br />
seek co-operation and want to achieve accommodation with us. Too<br />
often in the past we have behavea in ways which weaken the moderates<br />
and strengthen extreme forces hostile to us.<br />
Eighth, as well as working to reinvigorate the North-South dialogue,<br />
each of us should do'what is within our means, bilaterally and<br />
regionally, to contribute independently towards improving the<br />
prospects of the developing countries and relations between them<br />
and the West. Important as the North-South dialogue is, everything<br />
should not be made to wait on it.<br />
Ninth and last, we should work on the assumption that time is a<br />
wasting asset, that the longer the delay in addressing them the more<br />
intractable will the problems become. / il </p>
<p>11<br />
I should make it clear that in advancing these principles, I<br />
am not suggesting that it only the West which must revise its<br />
attitudes and behaviour if progress is to be made. The same is<br />
true of the Third World and I hope that there will be voices<br />
in it which will urge a moderate and constructive approach.<br />
Neither am I suggesting that the developed countries should<br />
simply accept the package of demands made by the Third World.<br />
Rather that the approach should be a positive one which seeks<br />
to identify what is justified and sound in the Third World case<br />
and respond to it. In that process wider criteria than economic<br />
rationality should be employed because more than economic interests<br />
are involved.<br />
In conclusion let me say that to respond to the North-South<br />
dialogue adequately we must be prepared to see it in broad<br />
historical perspective. In little over a generat-ion, over a<br />
hundred new countries have come into existence. Nearly all of<br />
them have a colonial past. Nearly all of them are very poor compared<br />
with Western countries how poor it is difficult for us in our<br />
prosperity to conceive. Think of how long it takes you to spend $ 200;<br />
then contemnlate that there are over one billion people in the world<br />
whose average annual income is less than that amount.<br />
Again, and equally important in political terms, all these<br />
countries are deeply concerned about their place in the world,<br />
their dicani-tv, status and influence. These countries and their<br />
needs have to-be accommodated, and accommodated in a world which<br />
is simultaneously becoming smaller, more crowded and more complex.<br />
The conditions must be created which give them opportunities to<br />
break the grinding circle of poverty in which they are caught.<br />
There is much they can and must do for themselves. But simply tc<br />
tell an under-nourished man who is working hard, arid, poor soil<br />
with a wooden plough, in the certain knowledge that his crop will<br />
be at best meagre and there are millions of such men simply<br />
to tell him that he must work harder and show more enterprise<br />
is insulting and dangerous nonsense. We cannot solve the Third<br />
World's problems; but we can help to create the conditions under<br />
which they can be tackled with some hope of success; and perhaps<br />
only we can.<br />
This is essentially what the North-South dialogue is about and<br />
the atmospherics and frictions of day to day events should not<br />
be allowed to obscure it. Developing the statecraft and the wil.<br />
to achieve this accommodation is one of the decisive challenges<br />
of our time. It is not an easy challenge to meet. It lacks the<br />
drama and crisis of war and political confrontations. It invites<br />
the resigned answer that " the poor are always with us". if<br />
we fail, the effects are unlikely to be immediately catastrophic,<br />
they may not be felt this week or this year. But, make no mistake,<br />
they will be felt and felt with cumulative force over the next<br />
decades, and we will be cursed by our children for our shortsightedness,<br />
our selfishness, our failure to seize opportunities<br />
in good time. / 12 </p>
<p>4 4 12-<br />
Mr President, before I came to the United States on this visit I<br />
had been told that the current mood of the. American people was<br />
not receptive to accommodating the Third World. Given the burden<br />
that you have carried in world affairs and given also the need for<br />
that renewal at home which President Reagan called for in his<br />
inaugural address, I could understand that some might feel like<br />
that. I will not presume to assess the American mood on the basis':<br />
of a brief visit, though I can say that I did not find indifference<br />
or lack of understanding in Washington last week. In any case, I<br />
believe that there are certain periods in history when timely and<br />
bold adjustments to new forces are necessary to forestall convulsion,<br />
disarm revolution and preserve peace. I believe also that<br />
conciliation and magnanimity are usually sound policy.<br />
At the tir~ e of the dispute between England and the American people<br />
in the 18th century, a dispute not without relevance to the<br />
contemporary situation, one of the wisest and most penetrating<br />
of political observers said: " It is not whether -you have the<br />
right to render your people miserable, but whether it is in your<br />
interest to m~ ake them happy. It is not * what a lawyer tells me I<br />
may do; but what humanity, reason and justice tell me I should do.<br />
Is a political act the worse for being a generous one?"<br />
In the 19th century, the countries which enjoyed domestic peace<br />
were thcse who responded in good time to the aspirations of the<br />
new working classes and adopted democratic political institutions.<br />
In our lif etine we have the evidence of the magnificently generous<br />
A-merican response represented by the Marshall Plan to novel and<br />
dangerous circumstances. It is worth recalling, too, the enlightened<br />
recognition of and response to the " wind of change" in Africa which<br />
in a matter of three or four years transformed a continent of<br />
colonies into a continent of independent states with minimum<br />
bloodshed. I believe profoundly that we are now at a turning point in<br />
global history which is at least as critical and important as<br />
these great episodes I have referred to. The magnitude of the<br />
problems, the scale of the adjustments necessary, the vision<br />
required should be conceived in these terms. Mr President, ladies<br />
and gentlemen, for the sake of this and succeeding generations, I<br />
trust that they will be. o000000000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
