<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6454</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT, PRESS CONFERENCE WITH PRIME MINISTER, SUVA, 4PM, 29 AUGUST 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/08/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006454.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRTASCRIPT PRESS CONFERE: iCE WITH PR. IME[ M, I NISTER SUVA,<br />
.1.00 P. 14M., 29 st 1984,<br />
E E PROOF C: LY<br />
Well ladies and gentlemen I've just had talks with<br />
Prime Minister of Fiji, Ratu Mara, and members of the<br />
Cabinet and I'm pleased to say that in the view. of both<br />
the Prime Minister of Fiji and myself that the bilateral<br />
relations between our two countries are in excellent shape<br />
and I believe-that they , ill become even stronger. Not<br />
only are our bilateral relations in good shape but we share<br />
perceptions in regard to matters effecting the region, both in<br />
economic co-operation and regional security terms. So this<br />
has been a very cordial, productive meeting.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Prime Minister could you refer to some<br />
specific issues that you may have taken up with the Prime<br />
Minister, our Prime Minister or some issues that our Prime<br />
Minister may have raised with you.<br />
The only matter that the Prime Minister alluded to and<br />
which he indicated didn't need any spelling out between us<br />
was the area of trade under the SPARTECA arrangements, and they<br />
have some concerns in regard to apparel and the content and<br />
origin. But that matter has already been discussed in a recent<br />
meeting with our officials and we have an understanding that<br />
we'll continue those discussions and I believe those matters<br />
will be sorted out. It's not a matter of problem between us.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister you said you discussed regional<br />
security with matters. Did the Prime Minister express any<br />
concern thatNew Zealand's decision not to allow U. S. nuclear<br />
ships into its ports might weaken ANZUS and therefore weaken<br />
the position of Fiji.<br />
I think the question of discussions between leaders<br />
of two Governments involving other Governments, it's notappropriate<br />
to go into those matters. But I can make the general comment<br />
that the strength and viability of ANZUS is a matter of<br />
interest to the Government of Fiji and so they are interested<br />
in current developments, but I don't go to the question of<br />
discussions between us involving other countries.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did he ask for more aid from Australia?<br />
No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the Australian High Commissioner<br />
in Suva is to have an Australian Defence official attached to<br />
it. Does that mean that Australia is going to somehow increase<br />
its very sniall military invovlement in Fiji. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
P. M. No, I believe that there is satisfaction here and in<br />
Au trat ] a k., tthce of t2 cfn; c c o--opcr tic t st.<br />
T--ere has nIo; incic. tionC o : ivss ". out It<br />
sCems to be work in: well, not only directly in . he co-oer: Ction<br />
which includes technical assistance, it includes training in<br />
Australia. I think as of the last year there are : 49 members of the<br />
Fijian defence forces who have been undergoing some form of<br />
training courses in Australia. So in the direct force to force<br />
co-operation and the training co--operation, a:' d also in particular<br />
the co-operation which historically and currently taking place<br />
in t he Middle . East I think in all aspects of the relationship<br />
it is satisfactory.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister has the decision by New Zealand<br />
to ban nuclear ships lead to a need to reassure this region<br />
that the security arrangements under ANZUS are still in place.<br />
I don't think it's the right way to put that there's been<br />
a need to reassure. The only partners of the relationship,<br />
as you know, are the three countries Australia, New Zealand<br />
and the United States. But nevertheless you're right in<br />
the assumption that other countries, including Fiji, do have<br />
an interest in the effective operation of that Treaty. I think<br />
that they have been reassured by the strength of the Australian<br />
recommitment to the relationship. And I think they, like<br />
Australia, are taking the sensible view that the issues that<br />
currently exist between the new New Zealand Government and<br />
the United States are in the process of being talked about<br />
at a number of levels to look through. And that's the way<br />
it's got to be and I remain optimistic, I am optimistic that<br />
those processes of discussion will work through in a satisfactory<br />
way. But to go into and try and analyse the stage that those<br />
discussions have reached could be counterproductive, so I'm<br />
not going to enter into it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Prime Minister the unemployment is a major<br />
problem in this part of the world and in your ( country) too.<br />
Do you think your Government will consider bringing in some<br />
schemes to take workers from this part of the world, from the<br />
island states of the Pacific, for short periods.<br />
The concept of guest workers has not been accepted by<br />
any Australian Government. It is not a concept which is<br />
accepted currently across the political spectrum in Australia.<br />
So my Government continues what has been a traditional view.<br />
We have opened up Australia in the post war period in an<br />
historically unprecedented way to people from overseas. That<br />
has not on a guest worker basis or temporary basis, but on the<br />
basis of permanent citizenship. The contribution that we are<br />
making in current terms and into the future consists of these<br />
elements. We still have an immigration component in the order<br />
of 70,000. We make contributions to the capacity of other<br />
countries, not merely in general aicd programs which are<br />
calculated to try and assist economic growth in those countries<br />
and therefore to create more employment opportunites but also<br />
in terms of spccific education.: l. op: ortunities. These are the<br />
ways in which meaningfully, Australia tries to do something for<br />
those countries around us which don't have the same economic<br />
advantages that we do. We will continue to do that as I said<br />
/ 3. </p>
<p>P. M. cont.: today we have a program of $ 300 million aid in<br />
the period up to 1987/ 88, . that five year period. And that<br />
aid is not aid which we'determine ourselves and say this<br />
is what should happen, but we have sought to get the vie-.' s<br />
0œ rec: c:; t : rtries a s L ?-tc aid are<br />
likelv to strengthen the i: frastruct.. re of tine recic. ient<br />
countries so that there will be, as a result of the use of<br />
that aid, the creation of miore employment opportunities<br />
within the countries. These are the ways, the specific<br />
concrete ways, in which we think we can be of most assistance.<br />
JOURNALIST: One criticism has been that Australia and other<br />
countries which take people from this part of the world take<br />
skilled workers, professional people, which may be scarce in<br />
this island country. Has this concern been expressed to you<br />
by any of the island people?<br />
No it hasn't been put to me. Obviously, if you are<br />
talking about real assistance both ways there is no point,<br />
from Australia's point of view, in taking components of<br />
immigration for which there is already a surplus of that sort<br />
of labour in Australia. That doesn't do anyone any good.<br />
As far as the areas of skilled shortage, the facts are that<br />
there has been a drastic reduction in Australia in those<br />
components. We had a category of immigration which was called<br />
the skilled shortage component now, that had a very very large<br />
number of components, that has been drastically reduced in<br />
recent times so that the number of people who would be eligible<br />
to come into Australia on the basis of a shortage of that skill<br />
in Australia is now very restricted. So I don't believe that<br />
either from our point of view what makes sense to us internally<br />
or what maybe seen as some sort of potential problem surrounding<br />
countries is an issue at the moment, ir. certainly hasn't been<br />
put to me by anyone.<br />
JOURNALIST: That leads us Prime Minister to the Jackson Report<br />
which recommends that the Tuvalu and Kiribati islanders have<br />
no economic future, virtually no economic future and they should<br />
be resettled in Australia and New Zealand. What are your views<br />
on that report and the reconmmendations?<br />
Well there are two things I would say about that.<br />
Firstly, that the Government has received the Jackson Report<br />
and there is one area of the Jackson Report concerning stucents,<br />
overseas students, which has also been covered by another report<br />
received at the same time, the Goldring Report. Those two reports<br />
are with the Government and particularly in the hands of the<br />
relevant Ministers and we will be receiving submissions on those<br />
reports and coming to conclusions about them in the future, in<br />
the relatively near future. But we haven't as a Government<br />
officially considered our position on the reports. The first<br />
thing I would say, I can't therefore add any second point I<br />
would make in regard to your reference to Tuvalu is that having<br />
just had the pleasure of being there, I am not sure that if I<br />
were a Tuvaluan that I would see a net balance of advantage in<br />
leaving that idealic situation and coming to Australia. </p>
<p>JOUR! NALIST: Prime Minister, you arc f -:; iliar with<br />
Papua New Guinea and I think to the residents of this<br />
country. las your perception of the Pacific been changed<br />
b' wha-t you s'. w l a; 0-Q : Cur tc<br />
t: e :-orum c. s ins i: bt in: u?<br />
Well, let me say again, two things about that.<br />
I believe that it was an e:: tremely useful exercise to have<br />
the Forum meeting in Tuvalu. I think it is right to say<br />
that there was perhaps some not apprehension is not the right<br />
word, some sort of sceptisim about having it there, but I<br />
believe that anyone who went there would not have remained<br />
with that feeling. It was the most direct way in which otlers<br />
of us who are more fortunate by traditional economic criteria<br />
if you say fortune, can see the problems confronting the smnaller<br />
Pacific island states. And I certainly, speaking for myself,<br />
have a much clearer perception now of the issues confrontirg<br />
those states than I did before I went there, so that's useful.<br />
Secondly, I would say in regard to that part of your question<br />
about the Forum, it confirm. ed my view that the Forum is a<br />
useful mechanism, it's, I guess if you look at the whole range<br />
of international institutions and gatherings, it's not one<br />
which ranks high in terms of international recognition, but<br />
I believe that it operates sensibly, its not a high budget<br />
organisation, a million dollars in respect of the actual<br />
organisation, of course there are other economic cooperaticn<br />
elements which occur within that structure. Now it seems to<br />
me to operate in a non-formalised way. The discussions that<br />
are held are not bogged " down by the where-as's and recognising's<br />
and all that perambular nonsense of United Nations Agencies.<br />
It tends to get down to issues and fairly practical issues.<br />
It certainly gives Australia, as the richest, most developed<br />
nation within the Forum, a direct. opportunity to talk with the<br />
leaders of these countries to get a direct understanding of the<br />
sorts of problems they have got and to see for ouselves, as<br />
political leaders, what are the sorts of ways in which our<br />
aid is most likely to be useful. Now I regard the Forum as<br />
very useful practical institution and I am very glad that this<br />
meeting was held in Tuvalu.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what value do you think the<br />
Ministerial grouping that the Forum decided upon to approach<br />
the Independence Front and the French authorities would have<br />
on New Caledonia on the issue of independence in New Caledonia.<br />
And is Australia going to be a member of that group and if not,<br />
why not. We're not going to be a member of it. Again basically<br />
because it's more appropriate that the countries immediately<br />
involved or directly involved should be part of it. We have<br />
our capacity to talk with France. What will come of it I don't<br />
know. You would have to say that on the experience of last.<br />
year, France wasn't particularly forthcoming when we sought to<br />
get acreement to a delegation from Forum countries to go to<br />
New Caledonia. So I just don't know what their reaction wil].<br />
be. Let how: ever, make this point in regard to their<br />
conzact of z.: is group w. ith the independence front. I hope<br />
that the e:.: istenc: of this cru: of five to have contiruinc<br />
contct . iCth the I. ndeendence Front m-ay be useful in dive: ing<br />
the Front from those developments that I alluded to in Tuv. lu. </p>
<p>P. M. cont That the influence of these five countries of the<br />
Pacific will be such as to persuade the Independence Front not<br />
to co outside the r. eion and seek resort to the p: or-oes; scs of<br />
cL~^ canc: terrmo0r. : T So i hawe t&gt; it1L sC e (: oiiC 7<br />
c:. t of that croup.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think once a year is enough for Forum<br />
meetings, is it sufficient or should the Forum leaders should<br />
meet more regularly.<br />
No, once a year is enough. We've all got a range of<br />
responsibilities but what is clear is that there should continue<br />
to be w: hat is-already happened and will happen more I think<br />
a meeting of officials. The role of political leaders is<br />
to review events of the past year, see how they've been operating,<br />
see whether there are some new mechanisms that need to be put<br />
in place and to maintain an interest, to have reports coming<br />
through to you on what's happening. And then meeting once a year<br />
is adequate in those circumstances provided you have the<br />
commitment through at your official level, which we do have.<br />
JOURNALIST: In New Caledonia, sir, there appears to be a very<br />
real threat of violence in that country.<br />
Well it certainly was put to us at the meeting, particularly<br />
by the spokesman for Vanuatu, Father Walter Lini, that tensions<br />
were rising and that there was this possibility. And I expressed<br />
the view at the meeting of our concern of the reported contacts<br />
that had been made recently with Libya. I believe that in the<br />
analysis of recent international events and any application of<br />
good sense to this situation would show that in the intrusion<br />
of elements like that into the scene would be disastrous.<br />
Now one can recognise, and indeed all members of the Forum<br />
have sympathy with the aspirations of the Kanak people, and that<br />
is why we expressed the view in our communique that the French<br />
Government should seek to accelerate the referendum from the<br />
date of 1989 that it's talking about to try and bring it forward.<br />
Yes there is a problem, there is a danger of violence and that's<br />
why I think there is a very considerable responsibility upon<br />
us all to try and persuade the Independence Front not to boycott<br />
the election but try and remain involved in the processes in<br />
the knowledge that they do have a solid basis of sympathy and<br />
support from the countries of the region.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think the Libyan element may have been<br />
wanting to get island leaders to apply more pressure on<br />
France. Well I don't know. But as I said at the meeting I'm<br />
not one who easily responds to blackmail or threats and if<br />
people think that they're going to make Australia change its<br />
views by that sort of tactic, then they've got a surprise<br />
waiting. We don't respond to that sort of pressure. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Did you speak in favour of f ive ivember groulp.<br />
P 1" !' e211 the f . emc:: brol cr-oul), I ti" Jk r3e-a1l1y1 -cVti Opecl<br />
in so-me inI or! ri aI d iscussion, s ou t: 3.100 thI e form. a. l ses 5io n.<br />
But when it wsbrought. to our attention a . fterl..' ardcs we-wv1ere<br />
auie apny abuut J. L it didn ' t formi part of the actual.<br />
V'iclw as 0 S Cf1lC f Z1 2-1, t 5. VU SOl e n ll&amp; f CS sO<br />
and to cret anl agreed position somelc people lilko to have anot': icr<br />
ele--ent in it, that wsone. ,% nd when it was bi-oucjl tL-o my"<br />
attention I was quite happy about it.<br />
JOU. RNALIST: Have you s-poken to Mr Keating about Mr Stcone s<br />
attack on the_ Government and do VouI be~ iv tht. r Stone<br />
has forfeited the trust of the Gove rnenti L..<br />
P. M. T lhe answ., er to the first part of your que. stion is no,<br />
I haven't s-,. okecn to Kea ting. And seccondly I hae'tgot<br />
anl" desire to enter into any public debate, about the act-ions<br />
of MrStone. VIn much m ore intcrested ill the conl tinuina<br />
evidenco ofL the,; strength1 anlli"! bea nature of th. e<br />
recover y of the Atustral1ian economyw w. hich hais resultled" f rom.<br />
the imlolementation of this cvrnit' eon icdcc; z ons.<br />
JOURNALIST: mr H: Lewhen a Socreta-ry of the Treasury eqates<br />
the Prime Minister w-. ith Napoleon the Plig out of Georqe Orwell's<br />
Animal Farm, don' t you think that requ ireS aI respons-e.<br />
P. M. : If you are a tender soul perhiaps, but you thajt I'm<br />
not a tender soul. If one succum" bed to responidincj to that<br />
weewould you ( let. I1 m uch moreI nLkers ted in the pub Ii c<br />
making its judIgernents about thlt-success or otherwise of th1e<br />
econlom-ic policies that this Governiment has decided upon, p. 1o] ici es<br />
about hiCh we wer~ e certain, even if somite of our advisers<br />
were: n ' t which a re work ing effective Iy Thazt ' s what the people<br />
are concerned ( about whether the policies that we decide uponl<br />
are wrig<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime -Minister, Mr S tonle saciede very concerned0 ab-out<br />
the age grotio from 15 to 19, the pcople who couldn ' t find w.. ork-.<br />
P. M. Well he has expressed his concern. Ile is not Pobinson<br />
Crusoe. We have a ' olitical respons. ibil ity for mzakincg<br />
decisions w-hich are going to imiprove the conditions and the<br />
Possibilities for those people. W've miade them and in the<br />
relatively short p'eriod % we've been in Government the position<br />
forthse cep1 -ihs reakby poved It will continlue<br />
to do so.<br />
JO0U RNA7 LI ST: Do you think its appropri-ate for public S027vanfts<br />
to be mnaking commen,. I ts Onl policy.<br />
P. M. W-, ell I don't rea-lly want to ( jet into this controversy'.<br />
Mr Stone has made his deocision as to how hie should conduct<br />
himself. Thtsfor him. I'm not going to directly or..<br />
indirct l' er~ er that situa. tilon.<br />
JOUP ,: ALI1, S T vou an c7Y2 that Mr11S ' Lone ' r2 comi-mer. tht im<br />
tn~ ure~~ fJ u: 1 C ~ et n I a s Z,~ r atter of<br />
ex-tremC concern: 1 a! C coun id ill fatL~ sustained Cconem13 C<br />
r co \' ry. .1/ 2 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Does that now mean sir that Australia can<br />
consid erablv i nc its aid to the ; ci. fic isa<br />
It doesn't follow as a matter of logic.<br />
But let me say Australia's record of aid is a good one,<br />
you've heard it welcome today by the Prime Minister of<br />
Fiji. We know that we have done well and we're gratified<br />
that the recipients believe that Australia has acted<br />
within its capacities.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Prime Minister, going back to the Australian<br />
home scene, how is your relationship with Mr Hayden these<br />
days. It's good.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the Fijian navy has a very low<br />
opinion of the design for the patrol boat that you would like<br />
to present to the islands, that it's unseaworthy and too small<br />
and they could do a far better job here. Was that discussc.<br />
today No it was not. I mean if the feeling has been as. strong<br />
as your questioning I would have perhaps expected it to be raised.<br />
It wasn't.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, just getting back to that point about<br />
the 15 to 19 age group Mr Stone was the head of Treasury<br />
for a number of years, do you think in some way he has<br />
implemented policy which has created that position.<br />
Oh, I take the view that although there may be evidence<br />
to the contrary, that Mr Stone believes in the Westminster system<br />
and therefore it would be the case that he hasn't implemented<br />
policies in the past, Governments have done it. Now what the<br />
advice has been that he's given and whether that advice has<br />
been accepted in a way which has produced adverse results,<br />
it's not for me to say.<br />
JOURNALIST: As Prime Minister, Mr Hawke, does Mr Stone's<br />
No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think there's a need for setting up a<br />
multi defence force in the Pacific, a peace-keeping force<br />
in the Pacific<br />
No, there is no evidence of any need to do that. I mean<br />
setting up peace keeping forces because problems may arise may<br />
be counterproductive, it may help those problems to arise.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think the Pacific islands are taking a firm<br />
enouigh stand against nuclear free vessels, aga. inst nuclea fr. C<br />
testing, sorry.<br />
Yes there are things thit .' er done at the Voru.. i<br />
Firstly, the decision to set up a :-or-king party of officials<br />
on the nuclear free zone concept and that w. as unanimous / 8 </p>
<p>P. M. cont... and secondly there was acreement that ind'. vid. cal<br />
tL. is i'sue. So tat sccms to 0 to be evid'nce of tihei<br />
cor:' it'aent to and prep: aredness to act on this issue.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will Australia consider easing the imnmigration<br />
laws to allow free movement of Pacific islanders to and from<br />
Australia? The immigration policy of Australia has been quite c:. ear<br />
under a number of successive governments over recent years and<br />
that is that our immigration policy will rest upon an assessment<br />
of the economic capacity of Australia to absorb migrants that's<br />
the basic element of it. Secondly, it will have a component: of<br />
family reunion in respect of those people who are already<br />
in Australia, they will have the right to bring immediate<br />
members of the family. And third, there is a refugee component.<br />
Fourth there is a business, entrepreneurial component. Those<br />
are the elements, all of which have to fit within the basic<br />
criterion of, as I say, economic capacity. Now that by<br />
definition doesn't mean unlimited immigration.<br />
JOURNALIST; What I meant Mr Prime Minister was that Australia<br />
is now the only country in the Pacific where we need visas to<br />
travel... ( tape break)<br />
This is not a matter which I'm aware has been raised with<br />
my Government so it not having been raised as far as I am aware<br />
I haven't felt compelled to address myself to it.<br />
1( </p>
<p>4 P. M. I'm not going to conduct my analysis in respect of<br />
the Austra. lian econo., where it's been, :' here it is and<br />
in Perth. It's -oi;: t:. es to do so, i ' s c t -ro. i<br />
I will simply do as I have from the 5th of i. arch analyse<br />
with the assistance of our range of advisers where the<br />
Australian economy's been, what appears to be the necessary<br />
decisions to handle those problems and to get it on a better<br />
course. The facts show that we have been dramatically<br />
successful in the single-minded purpose that we've had in<br />
addressing these economic problems. There has never been<br />
such a dramatically successful turn around of the Australian<br />
economy as has occurred since we came in. I remind you of<br />
the elements, the fundamental elements. Economic growth zero<br />
when we came in, the most rapid economic growth in the western<br />
world. Employment we've stopped the explosion of unemployment,<br />
we've created 260,000 new jobs, we're ahead of target.<br />
Inflation we've halved inflation. Interest rates down and<br />
since we've been away, with a new bond tender, interest rates<br />
down further. Now these are the important elements of the<br />
economic situation and we have been successful on all fronts.<br />
We will continue to be successful.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, have Mr Stone's actions presented<br />
a case for accelerating his departure.<br />
No, stones roll at their own pace.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you regret keeping Mr Stone on as Head of<br />
Treasury. P. 1M.: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why<br />
Well for the reasons that I said at the time<br />
I made it clear that I welcomed Mr Stone's preparedness to<br />
express views to the Government, that if he wished to do that<br />
then all that was required was once the decisions were made<br />
by Government, that there'd be an acceptance of those. I<br />
believe that Mr Stone has helped to create a very efficient<br />
Treasury and I've had no reason to change the view that I<br />
and my Treasurer when we came to office. Now what has happened<br />
since is a matter for Mr Stone's decision and I've made it<br />
quite clear throughout this questioning that I'm not going<br />
to enter into any debate about that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think the Treasury will be a better Department<br />
because of his departure.<br />
I'm not going to make any observation on that other than<br />
to say this that I believe, as I've just said a moment ago,<br />
that the Treasury is an excellent Deoartment, there's a lot<br />
of talent there and I believe it will continue to be an<br />
ex cellent De artment. / 3 </p>
<p>JOIURN2LIS'F: Mr -xn Iicjht cf Iliwat you've said( 1 wre you<br />
surprised by the vehemenrce of his attack and secondly, 0o yIou<br />
scond for Aniima]. r'aum.<br />
~, as yo-u c~ n I'm fai'rly aa'io&gt; eu t it a4ll<br />
IMichelle. ENMD S </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
