<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5777</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/03/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005777.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 5.00 PM_<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 21 IARCH 1982<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The housing policy package announced by the Treasurer, John<br />
Howard, last Thursday confirms the Government's concern for<br />
the objective of home ownership. Inabed it is under Liberal<br />
Governments in the post-war period that the dream of home<br />
ownership has become a reality for the great majority of<br />
Australian households. Today almost 72% of Australian households<br />
own or are buying their own home, compared to around 50<br />
in the late 1940s. Among young adults, the improverents. in<br />
home ownership prospects has been even more dramatic. In<br />
the 25-34 year old age group, the proportion buying or<br />
purchasing their own homes has increased from less than 37%<br />
in the late 1940s to over<br />
For the great majority of people-' the purchase of a home is<br />
the biggest, and probably the most complex purchase they make.<br />
It involves saving for a deposit, for furniture and fittings<br />
it involves dealing with banks or building societies, with<br />
agents and solicitors, and it involves a commitment to spend<br />
the equivalent of several years of their annual income.<br />
They are prepared to do all of this because they recognise<br />
that they are not only acquiring an asset of great value<br />
in itself, but also providing for themselves and their families<br />
a basis of security and stability.<br />
Achievement of the goal'of home ownership has never been easy,<br />
and in various ways over the years governments have assisted<br />
and encouraged the growth in the level of home ownership.<br />
In recent times,. for a variety of reasons, the intending<br />
home buyer has faced increasing difficulty. Much of the<br />
discussion of these problems has focused on interest rates,<br />
but while interest rate increases have undeniably played<br />
a part, iL would be wrong to say that they have been the only,<br />
or even the most fundamental problem. Indeed for anyone who<br />
started to buy a home four or five years ago or more, the<br />
burden of meeting their repayments has declined significantly<br />
despite the increases in interest rates that have subsequently<br />
occurred. Many of the difficulties faced by more recent homebuyers, and<br />
by those now wanting to buy their first home have arisen from<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>the pressure of costs on house prices. Increases in the<br />
price of land and increases-in the cost of. home building are<br />
in part a consequence of overall inflationary trends which can<br />
only be addressed by continued firm economic policies. But<br />
the costs imposed by building regulations and servicing<br />
costs have also posed very material problems for many home<br />
buyers,. and state and local governments have a real responsibility<br />
to examine very closely their policies in these areas where<br />
they add to the ultimate cost of housing.<br />
There can, be no doubt, however, that the current world<br />
environment of high interest rates.-from which the AustraliaLn<br />
economy cannot realistically be insulated has also made a<br />
significant contribution towards difficulties which have<br />
arisen in the housing area. With institutions such as savings<br />
banks constrained in terms of what interest rates they can offer<br />
on deposits, household savers have tended to shift their deposits<br />
to other areas,-and the funds available to home buyers from<br />
the traditional home lending institutions have diminished,<br />
leaving many people unable to borrow, or forcing them to seek<br />
additional funds from other more costly sources.<br />
The package of measures announced by the Treasurer faces up<br />
to these realities, and concentrates assistance on those who<br />
really are in need.., It increases the availability of housing<br />
finance to new borrowers through the banks, which have guaranteed<br />
an extra $ 400 million on top of their normal lending in the<br />
next 12 months for housing loans. That represents over 12,000<br />
additional loans. It provides increased assistance, and<br />
more timely assistance, to families with ~ modest incomes<br />
saving to buy their first home, through a modified home<br />
savings grant scheme, which will help over 40,000 home buyers<br />
each year.<br />
It provides assistance in meeting increased repayment burdens<br />
through a tax rebate scheme for over 450,000 home buyers who<br />
first entered home ownership in the last five years, and<br />
will provide similar assistance to all new first home buyers<br />
in the future. It provides additional assistance io all home buyers iwho<br />
took out loans from the nationally operating banks in the last<br />
two years, through an agreement with the banks that they will<br />
defer increased repayments for those borrowers for two years<br />
if they wish, and the banks have agreed to develop special<br />
arrangements, including low start mortgages, to further assist<br />
new first home buyers in the early years of their loans.<br />
And it provides for special assistance through joint arrangements<br />
to be developed with the states, for low income home buyers<br />
and private renters who are facing extreme difficulty and<br />
hardship in meeting their housing costs.<br />
A't the same time we have realistically faced up to the problem<br />
that the nationally operated banks and savings banks have faced<br />
in paying for deposits to allow them to make more loans by<br />
allowing them to raise interest rates on home loans by 1<br />
percentage point to 13! Even on this level their home </p>
<p>-3-<br />
lending rate is no higher than that charged on substantial<br />
housing loans by building societies in any state, and is lower<br />
than in most. It is worth noting that the building societies<br />
and their rates are under the legislative ' authority of state<br />
governments, not of the Commonwealth. For those who<br />
bought their first home with the aid of a loan from a bank in the<br />
last five years, the cost of the higher interest rate will be<br />
offset by the new tax rebate available to them, and almost half<br />
of all borrowers from the banks will be offered the<br />
choice of deferring any consequential increase in their<br />
repayments for two years.<br />
The new deal that has been given to recent and prospective<br />
home buyers puts beyond doubt the Commonwealth Government's<br />
commitment to home ownership. Here in Victoria, Premier<br />
Lindsay Thompson and Housing Minister Jeff Kennett have<br />
welcomed the Commonwealth Government's package which<br />
they estimate will assist scme 175,000 Victorian families,<br />
and they have added to it a housing subsidy scheme of their<br />
own to assist all other family home buyers in the State of<br />
Victoria. I am sure that allhome buyers in Victoria will<br />
welcome their imaginative commitment. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
