<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9423</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP PRESENTATION OF &quot;WALKING TOGETHER:  THE FIRST STEPS&quot;, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 17 NOVEMBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009423.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A-.<br />
4, ~-1,~ A<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
PRESENTATION OF " WALKING TOGETHER: THE FIRST STEPS",<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 17 NOVEMBER 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Sir Ronald, Pat Dodson, Mr Speaker, Mr President, my colleague the Leader<br />
of the Opposition, the Leader of the Australian Democrats Senator Kernot<br />
and Ms Lois O'Donoghue the Chairperson of ATSIC, Ministerial and<br />
Parliamentary colleagues, members of the Council most particularly and<br />
ladies and gentlemen.<br />
I am very pleased to be here today for the presentation of the report " Walking<br />
Together The First Steps" which describes Australia's progress towards<br />
reconciliation after the first three years of effort by the Council for Aboriginal<br />
Reconciliation. I think the fact that has been remarked already by the President, the Speaker<br />
and Pat Dodson, that this Council was met with the approval of both houses<br />
of Parliament, of the parties in the Parliament. The Council is a broad<br />
representation of community and political interests and, of course, Aboriginal<br />
and Torres Strait Islander interests and it is a fine thing that we are so certain<br />
of the process that the Chairperson of it Patrick Dodson, can actually<br />
present with some pride the report to the Speaker and to the President.<br />
It wasn't that many years ago when Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander<br />
people had lost heart in any process of reconciliation. It wasn't that long ago<br />
when the whole notion about land rights had fizzled out to nothing in some of<br />
the places where people were still living a traditional life, in some of the large<br />
states. And, there was a feeling of despair, I suppose, about the process, but<br />
I think, that that has changed and that is the great thing. Because, something<br />
token, a token process of reconciliation is worse than no process at all<br />
because it makes a mockery of something intrinsically important.<br />
But, I think, we all think now that there is nothing token about this and, I think,<br />
that it is probably true that the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander<br />
community feel better about themselves today than a few years ago and the </p>
<p>Australian community feels better about reconciliation than it did just a short<br />
time ago.<br />
I think wherever principal strikes out, wherever a truth is spoken is like rain<br />
falling on the ground things grow, good things happen and, I think, that<br />
non-Aboriginal Australians have recognised the truth of what has happened<br />
to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islanders in this country. They recognise the<br />
deprivation and the crimes and the rest and that has been said and, I think,<br />
the High Court's decision in respect of Mabo righting a wrong, putting clear<br />
a truth that this was not a continent of no one, that there was a civilisation of<br />
people here, that there was an expropriation of their property and their rights<br />
and that later, much later indeed, the High Court recognised that Aboriginal<br />
custom and tradition would be a source of Australian common law. Now this<br />
is a significant breakthrough, but of course, as we all in this room know, that<br />
decision had legal power, but no facilitation and even in parts of it where it<br />
was clear, or unclear where the power of it was there was an obligation on<br />
the Parliament to legislate and say where it was and how it might be<br />
exercised. That has happened with the Native Title legislation.<br />
I think this community of ours feels much better about reconciliation because<br />
of the passage of that Bill. I think they think that a wrong has been set right<br />
and though there has been disagreement in a political sense about it, in the<br />
end fundamentals invariably triumph and truth prospers and I have got no<br />
doubt that our community today is more at one with itself than it has ever<br />
been not totally at one, otherwise I'm sure Pat and the Council would<br />
believe their work was finished and they couldn't possibly believe that. And,<br />
we will have much to do in developing that reconciliation further, but now<br />
there is that force to it. It is not just a Council meeting in the, sort of,<br />
amorphous problems of Australia and trying to reconcile the interests and<br />
aspirations of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people with those of non-<br />
Aboriginal Australians.<br />
Land, of course, has always been central to an understanding of Aboriginal<br />
and Torres Strait Islander culture. The Native Title Act is about land, the<br />
Land Fund Bill we are currently debating is about land for those who have<br />
long ago lost a traditional association with the land, but shouldn't be denied<br />
the right to acquire it or to live with it. So, that has got to be put right and<br />
over time there will be in these fundamental things a basis of reconciliation<br />
which we can then draw down for broader community support. I particularly<br />
noticed the report of the Centenary of Federation Advisory Committee in<br />
August which found that reconciliation is central to Australia's aspirations as<br />
we approach the next century I think, a wise observation Premiers, Chief<br />
Ministers, Opposition Leaders, RSLs, CWAs, youth councils, womens<br />
electoral lobbies, local government, religious leaders, unions and business<br />
organisations all nominated reconciliation as a major goal. This is a gigantic<br />
step forward. This wouldn't have been so not so long ago.<br />
As you know, I have just come back from a meeting of the Leaders of the<br />
Asia-Pacific area who have done an important thing in deciding to bring the<br />
Americas into a linkage with Asia so that we have an Asia-Pacific community </p>
<p>and that we don't see the world break up into three trading blocs in Europe,<br />
in the Americas and in Asia. We have had this debate all my political life,<br />
anyway, about the north south dialogue and for the first time one can see a<br />
real and tangible expression when a group sits down as this group did this<br />
week to see the big powerful economies of the United States and Japan<br />
dealing with and comprehending the problems and making arrangements to<br />
deal with them with developing countries like Indonesia and China and Papua<br />
New Guinea and some others.<br />
You get the feeling that there is something good happening in the world, that<br />
the Cold War which left these tremendous polarities and tensions, where<br />
countries were bound up by this strategic tension, that having gone what has<br />
blossomed is that which was most unlikely because this body APEC just<br />
never had to happen. There was no logical reason why it happened, there<br />
may be some logics in it, but it did happen and it has happened out of good<br />
will and co-operation. We can only play a part in it if we go to the world as<br />
one nation, as a nation united and not a nation in any way divided. That is<br />
why Australians need to be clear about their identity and proud of it. But, that<br />
identity must include the identity of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islanders.<br />
That is why you can't go hobbling to the world saying, " please put us in the<br />
big race, but by the way, our indigenes don't have a real part of it and by the.<br />
way, we are still borrowing the monarchy of another country."<br />
So, feeling good about yourself doesn't happen unless it is genuine. It can<br />
only be genuine if there is, I think, a goodness of spirit and something where<br />
things are done, things are given, concessions are made and these, I think,<br />
we are seeking to do with the Native Title Act and with the Land Fund and<br />
other things, but more obviously, perhaps, by giving of ourselves, each of us,<br />
towards something better.<br />
So, that is what it must mean reconciliation it must mean that we reject the<br />
notions that there is some sort of preordained right to the benefits of this<br />
country to non-Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Australians, that we have<br />
really got to basically do it together and in the doing of it, that the<br />
metamorphosis will mean we are a different country than the one we have<br />
always been. No longer a mono culture and particularly with our multicultural<br />
community and reconciliation with our older community we then, I think, do go<br />
as one.<br />
That means, I think, that the work can go on. Because there have been times<br />
during the Council's life where we wondered whether work would go on,<br />
whether it wouldn't peter out, just another attempt, add good will, basically<br />
drying up in the face of intransigence and bias and prejudice. Well, I think,<br />
there is enough around now and the fact that we can, in all honesty, receive<br />
this Report with what it means, and have the President and the Speaker<br />
accept it on behalf of the Parliament and the-nation is a logical interim step, a<br />
report on the progress of reconciliation.<br />
So, to all those people who have been involved the community<br />
organisations, the industrial companies, the mining companies, the </p>
<p>4<br />
pastoralists, the Land Councils, the Aboriginal and Islander communities and<br />
those who have served on the Council might I add a congratulations and the<br />
very best of good wishes for the future of the council and its important work.<br />
S' Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
