<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16739</transcript-id>
    <title>Alannah Mactiernan&#039;s candidacy for Canning preselection    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/08/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to welcome the announcement today by Alannah MacTiernan MLA of her intention to contest the Labor Party's candidacy for the West Australian seat of Canning at the next federal election. </p>
<p>Alannah MacTiernan has been a Member of State Parliament for 16 years, including serving as Minister for Planning and Infrastructure for almost 8 years. She currently serves as Shadow Minister for Regional Development; Strategic Infrastructure; and Climate Change.</p>
<p>She brings with her a strong record of local representation, and an important contribution to the infrastructure planning and investment of the State. She has also been a strong advocate of the need to act on climate change.</p>
<p>During her time as Minister in the Gallop and Carpenter Governments, Alannah oversaw significant investments in State infrastructure, including:</p>
<p>     * The Mandurah Railway;</p>
<p>     * The Perth-Bunbury Highway;</p>
<p>     * The Tonkin Highway Extension; and</p>
<p>     * The Champion Lakes Development. </p>
<p>The Australian Government is committed to investment in national infrastructure to support jobs during the global recession, and to build the infrastructure Australia needs for the future, and is taking strong and decisive action on climate change.</p>
<p>The Australian Government is delivering on this commitment in Western Australia through investment in major infrastructure such as the Mandurah Entrance Road, upgrades to the Great Northern Highway at Port Hedland, the duplication of the Dampier Highway between Karratha and Dampier and providing port access in Geraldton.</p>
<p>The Australian Government has also committed $330 million to the Kwinana Freeway Extension and Forrest Highway, and provided an additional $3.3 million to the City of Armadale for Stage 2 of the Champion Lakes Development in Canning.</p>
<p>Alannah MacTiernan brings experience, a strong record of delivering locally, and a reputation for innovation and for getting the job done, to her candidacy for preselection as Labor Candidate for Canning. I look forward to working with her in developing her strong vision for Western Australia.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
