<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6177</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR RJL HAWKE, TO THE TOWNSVILLE DISTRICT DEVELOPMENT BUREAU, TOWNSVILLE INTERNATIONAL HOTEL, 10 AUGUST 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/08/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006177.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4<br />
fU^ ktiF<br />
I TrAL<br />
AI) j.' ST kL,('<br />
PRIME MENISTER j<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR R. J. L. HAWKE, TO THE<br />
TOWNSVILLE DISTRICT DEVELOPMENT BUREAU, TOWNSVILLE<br />
INTERNATIONAL HOTEL, 10 AUGUST 1983.<br />
I AM DELIGHTED TO BE WITH YOU TODAY AT THIS MEETING OF THE<br />
TOWNSVILLE DISTRICT DEVELOPMENT BUREAU.<br />
I,; I WAS LAST IN TOWNSVILLE IN FEBRUARY JUST PRIOR TO THE<br />
LAST ELECTION.<br />
1 I SPOKE THEN OF LABOR'S STRONG COMMITMENT TO NORTH<br />
I QUEENSLAND AND OF THE RANGE OF LABOR POLICIES TO PROMOTE THE<br />
WELFARE OF THE PEOPLE OF NORTH QUEENSLAND.<br />
ALTHOUGH IT IS ONLY 5 MONTHS SINCE THE ELECTION ON MARCH<br />
WE HAVE ALREADY MADE GREAT PROGRESS.<br />
2 IN JUNE, WE ANNOUNCED WE WOULD HONOUR OUR COMMITMENT TO<br />
BUILD A COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT CENTRE HERE IN TOWNSVILLE TO<br />
HOUSE FEDERAL DEPARTMENTS.<br />
i THE CENTRE WILL BE THE FIRST FEDERAL GOVERNMENT OFFICE BLOCK<br />
BUILT IN AUSTRALIA IN THE LAST 10 YEARS.<br />
3-/ 2<br />
r t L r </p>
<p>-2-<br />
IT WILL COST ABOUT $ 12 MILLION AND ITS CONSTRUCTION WILL<br />
BOOST JOB OPPORTUNITIES BY ABOUT 300,<br />
INDEED IT WILL MAKE A CONSIDERABLE CONTRIBUT ION TO<br />
RESUSCITATING THE CONSTRUCTION INDUSTRY IN NORTH QUEENSLAND.<br />
THE BENEFITS To TOWNSVILLE INCLUDE THE PURCHASE OF<br />
EQUIPMENT AND SUPPLIES, LONG-TERM WORK FOR BUILDERS AND<br />
SUB-CONTRACTORS AND A BOOST TO THE SPENDING POWER OF THE<br />
COMMUNITY. LAST MONTH I ANNOUNCED A DECISION OF MOMENTOUS IMPORTANCETHE<br />
CONSTRUCTION OF STAGE 1 OF THE BURDEKIN DAM,<br />
THIS IS THE FIRST TIME AN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
UNDERTAKEN A PROJECT OF TRULY NATIONAL SIGNIFICANCE<br />
SINCE THE POST-WAR RECONSTRUCTION PERIOD.<br />
WE HAVE ALLOCATED UP TO $ 13 MILLION THIS FINANCIAL YEAR<br />
FOR THE DAM.<br />
PROMISES TO BUILD THE DAM HAVE BEEN MADE REPEATEDLY SINCE<br />
THE SECOND WORLD WAR.<br />
BUT FOR THE FIRST TIME, AN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
GIVEN A TOTAL COMMITMENT TO THE DAM,<br />
IT'S ALL THE DIFFERENCE IN THE WORLD BETWEEN SPECIOUS,*<br />
OPPORTUNISTIC PROMISES, AND POSITIVE ACTION. </p>
<p>IT IS DIFFICULT TO OVERSTATE THE BENEFITS THAT WILL FLOW<br />
FROM THE DAM JOBS, IRRIGATION, CONSTRUCTION, NEW<br />
CONTRACTS, DEMAND FOR MATERIALS AND TRANSPORT AND A LIFT IN<br />
BUSINESS CONFIDENCE AND TOURISMTHE<br />
DAM IS PROBABLY THE MOST SIGNIFICANT BOOST TO NORTH<br />
QUEENSLAND SINCE THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE SUGAR AND MINING<br />
I NDUSTRI ESTHE<br />
SUGAR INDUSTRY, OF COURSE, IS VITAL TO NORTH QUEENSLANDHOWEVER,<br />
IN RECENT TIMES THE INDUSTRY HAS SUFFERED THE<br />
COMBINATION OF LOW WORLD PRICES AND ADVERSE SEASONAL<br />
CONDITIONSIN RESPONSE TO THE SEVERE LIQUIDITY CRISIS FACED BY MANY<br />
GROWERS, WE PROVIDED $ 10 MILLION TO THE INDUSTRYTHIS<br />
MONEY IS BEING MADE AVAILABLE IN THE FORM OF CARRW-ON<br />
LOANS AND WILL KEEP GROWERS IN THE INDUSTRY WHO WOULD<br />
OTHERWISE HAVE BEEN FORCED OUTWE<br />
KNOW THE GREAT CONCERN NORTH QUEENSLANDERS HAVE FOR THE<br />
UPGRADING OF THE BRUCE . HIGHWAY AND THE IMPROVEMENT OF LOCAL<br />
ROAD$-</p>
<p>THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT REGARDS THE BRUCE HIGHWAY BETWEEN<br />
BRISBANE AND CAIRNS AS THE NUMBER ONE PRIORITY FOR THE<br />
ALLOCATION OF NATIONAL ROAD FUNDS WITHIN QUEENSLAND.<br />
WE REMAIN COMMITTED TO ITS UPGRADING BY 1988.<br />
THE ALLOCATION OF FUNDS FOR 1983-84 UNDER THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
BICENTENNIAL ROAD DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM AS BETWEEN STATES<br />
AND CATEGORIES OF THE PROGRAM Ib BEING FINALISED.<br />
WE EXPECT TO SPEND SOME $ 65 MILLION ON THE HIGHWAY THIS<br />
FINANCIAL YEAR AN ALL-TIME RECORD,<br />
THIS IS NOT ONLY A WELCOME INFUSION OF FUNDS TO A HIGH PRIORITY<br />
AREA BUT ALSO AN EXTENSIVE EMPLOYMENT GENERATION PROGRAM IN<br />
ITSELF. OVER 3,000 JOBS WILL BE CREATED, DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLYVIE<br />
ALSO RECOGNISE THE MAJOR DEFICIENCIES IN THE LOCAL ROADS<br />
NETWORK IN QUEENSLAND AS A WHOLE AND PARTICULARLY IN NORTH<br />
QUEENSLAND$ LOCAI. ROADS IN ALL STATIES WILL BENEFIT FROM THE 37 PER CENT<br />
INCREASE IN COMMONWEALTH ASSISTANCE IN 1983/ 84 UNDER THE<br />
COMBINED ROADS GRANTS AND BICENTENNIAL ROAD PROGRAMS.<br />
WE ARE ALSO PROVIDING $ 70 MILLION IN 1983-84 FOR JOBS O1N LOCAL<br />
ROADS UNDER OUR COMMUNITY EMPLOYMENT PROGRAM TANGIBLE EVIDENCE<br />
OF OUR CONCERN FOR THE UPGRADING OF LOCAL ROADS.<br />
OVER $ 12 MILLION HAS B EEN ALLOCATED TO QUEENSLAND AND WILL<br />
PROVIDE UP TO 1,000 JOBS. </p>
<p>WE ALSO APPRECIATE THE SPECIAL AIR TRAVEL NEEDS OF<br />
NORTH QUEENSLANDERS,<br />
I AM PLEASED TO ANNOUNCE THAT TOWNSVILLE AIRPORT'S NEW<br />
DOMESTIC TERMINAL WILL GO AHEAD,<br />
SHORTLY AFTER THE ELECTIONj MY COLLEAGUE, KIM BEAZLEY,<br />
THE MINISTER FOR AVIATION, ASKED HIS DEPARTMENT TO STUDY AND<br />
REPORT ON THE NEED FOR IMPROVED DOMESTIC TERMINAL FACILITIES<br />
AT TOWNSVILLE AIRPORT.<br />
THIS STUDY RECOMMENDED THAT NEW DOMESTIC TERMINAL FACILITIES<br />
WERE NECESSARY TO PROPERLY OVERCOME THE LONG-STANDING<br />
INADEQUACIES OF THE EXISTING TERMINAL COMPLEX.<br />
OTHER LESS EXPENSIVE OPTIONS SUCH AS A GREATER USE OF THE<br />
INTERNATIONAL TERMINAL FOR DOMESTIC TRAFFIC WERE<br />
CONSIDERED BUT WERE REJECTED, DUE TO THE CONFLICTING NEEDS<br />
OF THE DOMESTIC AND INTERNATIONAL AIRLINES,<br />
TOWNSVILLE, BECAUSE OF ITS FAVOURABLE GEOGRAPHIC LOCATION<br />
TOWNSVILLE THE GATEWAY TO THE NORTH HAS DOUBLED ITS<br />
REGULAR INTERNATIONAL SERVICES SINCE THE TERMINAL WAS<br />
OPENED AND IS NOW ATTRACTING CONSIDERABLE USE BY<br />
INTERNATIONAL COMMER! CAL AIR TRAFFIC. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
As IT IS N'ECESSARY TO CHECK ALL THIS TRAFFIC FOR CUSTOMSJ<br />
IMMIGRATION AND HEALTH REQUIREMENTS SEPARATE FROM DOMESTIC<br />
TRAFFIC IT WAS FOUND IMPRACTICABLE TO USE THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
TERMINAL FOR REGULAR DOMESTIC USE*<br />
WHAT WE ARE NOW PROPOSING IS THE UPGRADING OF THE DOMESTIC<br />
TER. MINAL AS SPEEDILY AND REALISTICALLY AS POSSIBLE,<br />
SUCH A COMPLEX PROJECT REQUIRES A GREAT DEAL OF SPECIALIST<br />
PLANNING AND DESIGN EFFORT.<br />
AND WHILE, OF COURSE, WE ALL WANT TO SEE THE PROJECT BECOME<br />
A REALITY AS QUICKLY AS PRACTICABLE, NOTHING WILL BE GAINED<br />
BY PROCEEDING ON THE OPPORTUNISTIC LINES PROPOSED BY THE<br />
PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT.<br />
FOR EXAMPLE, IT REQUIRES THE APPROVAL OF THE PARLIAMENTARY<br />
WORKS COMMITTEE, WH-ICH HAS TO CONSIDER AND REPORT TO THE<br />
PARLIAMENT ON MAJOR PROJECTS OVER $ 2 MILLION,<br />
My GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN ADVISED THAT, EVEN THOUGH A GREAT<br />
DEAL OF THE PRELIMINARY PLANNING IS COMPLETE, AT LEAST A<br />
FURTHER TWELVE MONTHS IS REQUIRED TO COMPLETE THE NECESSARY<br />
DETAILED DESIGN WORK AND SUBMIT THE PROPOSAL TO THE PUBLIC<br />
WORKS COMMITTEE FOR ITS CONSIDERATION. I HAVE INSISTED THAT<br />
THIS PRELIMINARY WORK BE COMPLETED AS SOON AS POSSIBLE.<br />
BUT I STRESS; AS SOON AS THIS PROCESS CONCLUDES, DEVELOPMENT<br />
WILL COMMENCE. s. i s7 </p>
<p>THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN ENCOURAGING THE<br />
AIRLINES TO INTRODUCE DISCOUNT AIR FARES. AT LEAST<br />
PARTLY REFLECTING THIS, ANSETT AND TAA RECENTLY<br />
INTRODUCED 45 PERCENT DISCOUNT FARES, THIS INITIATIVE<br />
SHOULD BENEFIT NORTH QUEENSLANDERS AS IT INCLUDES<br />
ROCKHAMPTON, MACKAY, TOWNSVILLE, CAIRNS AND PROSERPINE,<br />
/ 7<br />
I </p>
<p>CONDITIONS WHICH MAKE THESE FARES UNATTRACTIVE TO MULTI'-STAGE<br />
TRAVELLERS ARE BEING REVIEWED BY THE AIRLINES AT THE REQUEST<br />
OF KIM BEAZLEY, THE MINISTER FOR AVIATION,<br />
HE IS ALSO PURSUING WITH THEM THE CONCEPT OF LOW COST AIR<br />
SERVICES AS AN ALTERNATIVE TO EXISTING SCHEDULED SERVICES.<br />
ANOTHER DISABILITY TO WHICH NORTH QUEENSLANDERS ARE SUBJECT<br />
IS THE PROBLEM OF TROPICAL ILLNESS AND DISEASE,<br />
PRIOR TO THE LAST ELECTION4 WE PROPOSED THE ESTABLISHMENT OF<br />
A TROPICAL MEDICINE RESEARCH INSTITUTE AT JAMES COOK UNIVERSITY<br />
HERE IN TOWNSVILLE.<br />
THAT COMMITMENT REMAINS.<br />
WE HAVE ASKED THE COMMONWEALTH TERTIARY EDUCATION COMMISSION<br />
TO REPORT ON THE ESTABLISHMENT, TIMETABLE AND COST OF THE<br />
INSTITUTE IN SUFFICIENT TIME FOR CONSIDERATION IN THE 1984<br />
BUDGET. THIS WILL ENABLE OUR PROPOSAL TO BE CONSIDERED AND PROGRESSED<br />
ON A SOUND, INFORMED BASIS.<br />
NORTH QUEENSLAND HAS A VITAL STAKE IN THE TOURIST INDUSTRY AN<br />
INDUSTRY OF ENORMOUS POTENTIAL,<br />
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO TAKE WHATEVER ACTION IT<br />
CAN TO HELP THE TOURIST INDUSTRY ACHIEVE ITS FULL POTENTIAL. </p>
<p>OUR NATIONAL TOURIST POLICY AIMS TO GET MORE OVERSEAS<br />
VISITORS To AUSTRALIA AND TO ENCOURAGE MORE AUSTRALIANS TO<br />
HOLIDAY AT HOMEAs<br />
PART OF THIS, WE WANT TO ENCOURAGE MORE TRAVELLERS BOTH<br />
OVERSEAS AND DOMESTIC TO VISIT NORTH QUEENSLANDTo<br />
HELP MEET THIS OBJECTIVE WE WILL PROVIDE A SUBSTANTIAL<br />
BOOST TO THE BUDGET ALLOCATION FOR THE AUSTrRALIAN TOURIST<br />
COMMISSION IN 1983-84.<br />
THIS WILL ALLOW NEW INITIATIVES TO PROMOTE INBOUND TOURISM<br />
To AUSTRALIATHESE INITIATIVES INCLUDE<br />
INTENSIVE ADVERTISING IN ALL MARKETS, ESPECIALLY<br />
THE UNITED STATES<br />
EXPANDED OVERSEAS REPRESENTATION AND<br />
THE ESTABLISHMENT OF AUSTRALIAN TRAVEL CENTRES I<br />
OVERSEAS MARKETS<br />
THE GREAT BARRIER REEF IS, OF COURSE, ONE OF THE K( EY<br />
ATTRACTIONS TO NORTH QUEENSLAND FOR INTERNATIONAL TOURISTS-</p>
<p>ONE OF OUR NORTH QUEENSLAND COMMITMENTS TO PROMOTE<br />
TO URISM WAS TO EXEMPT THE GREAT BARRIER REEF ISLAND<br />
RESORTS FROM THE DIESEL EXCISE IMPOSED 13Y THE PREVIOUS<br />
GOVERNMENT, THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT HAS DECIDED TO EFFECTIVELY MEET<br />
THIS COMMITMENT BY MAKING A SPECIAL GRANT OF APPROXIMATELY<br />
$ 1 MILLION THIS FINANCIAL YEAR TO SUBSIDISE THE DIESEL<br />
FUEL COSTS To BARRIER REEF ISLAND TOURIST RESORTS.<br />
THIS GRANT WILL BE A TIED GRANT UNDER SECTION 96 OF THE<br />
CONSTITUTION, THE CONDITIONS WILL BE ANNOUNCED LATER.<br />
DIESEL IS THE LIFEBLOOD OF THE TOURIST INDUSTRY ! N<br />
NORTH QUEENSLAND, THIS IS ESPECIALLY SO FOR THE OFF-SHORE<br />
ISLANDS.<br />
POWER GENERATION, AIR-CONDITIONING AND EVEN THE BOATS THAT<br />
BRING THE DIESEL TO THE ISLANDS ARE RUNNING ON DIESEL,<br />
THESE TOURIST ISLANDS ARE NOT PART OF THE GENERAL<br />
ELECTRICAL GRID SYSTEM.<br />
THEREFORE IT IS FAIR THAT SPECIAL SUBSIDIES SHOULD BE<br />
PROVIDED AS COMPENSATION1<br />
THESE ISLANDS ARE PROVIDING THOUSANDS OF JOBS. MILLIONS OF<br />
DOLLARS IN REVENUE TO TIHE GoVERNMENT AND VIRTUALLY SUSTAINING<br />
A NUMBER OF TOWNS ALONG THE QUEENSLAND COAST. </p>
<p>1O.<br />
OUR DECISION TO PROVIDE THIS $ 1 MILLION GRANT WILL PROVIDE<br />
A WELCOME BOOST TO TOURISM IN QUEENSLAND.<br />
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENTr IS ANXIOUS TO ENCOURAGE MAN-MADE<br />
TOURIST ATTRACTIONS, INCLUDING INTERPRETATION FACILITIES<br />
AND CONVENTION CENTRES, ANDi WHEREVER PRACTICABLE, FINANCE<br />
THEM OR PROVIDE GENEROUS LOANS.<br />
ONE, IN PARTICULAR, IS GREAT BARRIER REEF WORLD HERE<br />
IN TOWNSVILLE.<br />
As SOME OF YOU KNOW, I AM FAMILIAR WITH THIS PROJECT,<br />
KNOW IT IS VERY STRONGLY SUPPORTED IN THIS CITY ANDI<br />
BELIEVE IT HAS ENORMOUS POTENTIALl<br />
THE TOWNSVILLE DISTRICT DEVELOPMENT BUREAU, OF COURSE, IS<br />
HEAVILY INVOLVED, INDEED I NOTICE IT IS CURRENTLY YOUR<br />
NUMBER ONE PRIORITY.<br />
REEF WORLD IS SUPPORTED BY THE GREAT BARRIER REEF MARINE<br />
PARK AUTHORITY AND HAS BEEN SUGGESTED FOR INCLUSION UNDER<br />
THE BICENTENNIAL PROGRAM.<br />
I FULLY ENDORSE THE COMMENTS OF MY COLLEAGUE BARRY COHEN,<br />
THE MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS AND ENVIRONMENT PROVIDED<br />
THE QUEENSLAND GOVERNMENT NOMINATES THE PROJECT UNDER THE<br />
BICENTENNIAL PROGRAM, GOVERNMENT FUNDING IS. LIKELY TO<br />
PROCEED, </p>
<p>THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT RECOGNIZES THE TREMENDOUS WORK<br />
BEING CARRIED OUT BY THE DEFE. NCE FORCES IN NORTH<br />
QUEENSLAND AND IS PROUD OF THEIR ACHIEVEMENTS,<br />
FOR EXAMPLE, 1 NOTICE LAST WEEK THE No 35 SQUADRON<br />
Ar THE R. A. A. F. BASE TOWNSVILLE WAS PRESENTED WITH THE<br />
DUKE OF GLOUCESTER' S CUP BY THE GOVERNOR-GENERAL FOR<br />
OUTSTANDING PERFORMANCE.<br />
MY CONGRATULATIONS! I AM VERY PROUD THE UNIT HAS<br />
RECEIVED SUCH A DISTINGUISHED AWARD,<br />
HERE IN TOWNSVILLE WE HAVE THE READY DEPLOYMENT FORCE,<br />
AGAIN THERE IS AN ENVIABLE STANDARD OF PROFICIENCY.<br />
AUSTRALIA MUST HAVE STRONG DEFENCES$<br />
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT UNDERSTANDS THAT AND IS DETERMINED<br />
TO MEET ITS RESPONSIBILITIES.<br />
ACCORDINGLY WE HAV'E DECIDED IN THE COMING BUDGET TO<br />
INCREASE DEFENCE SPENDING SIGNIFICANTLY IN REAL TERMS.<br />
NORTH QUEENSLANDERS ARE JUSTIFIABLY CONCERNED ABOUT THE<br />
ADEQUACY OF COASTAL SURVEILLANCE. </p>
<p>12.<br />
AGAINST TrHAT BACKGROUND WE EXTENDED THE COASTAL SURVEILLANCE<br />
CONTRACT OF REPROGRAPHICS TO MARCH AT THE COST OF AN<br />
ADDITIONAL $ 900, 000.<br />
THIS OVERVIEW OF SOME OF OUR POLICIES INDICATES IN THE<br />
CLEAREST TERMS THE FEDERAL LABOR GOVERNMENT'S COMMITMENT<br />
TO NORTH QUEENSLAND,<br />
WE ARE REWRITING THE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT OF NORTH QUEENSLAND.<br />
FOR TOO LONG NORTH QUEENSLAND HAS FAILED TO RECEIVE A FAIR<br />
RETURN FOR ITS CONTRIBUTION TO THE NATIONAL WEALTH.<br />
FRTOO LONG THE SPECIAL PROBLEMS OF NORTH QUEENSLANDERS<br />
HAVE BEEN LARGELY IGNORED By FEDERAL AND STATE GOVERNMENTS.<br />
THE FEDERAL LABOR GOVERNMENT IS STARTING TO RIGHT THAT<br />
WRONG. WE CAME TO OFFICE WITH THE GREAT AIM OF " BRINGING AUSTRALIA<br />
TOGETHER" WE ARE NOW MAKING A START IN BRINGING NORTH QUEENSLAND<br />
CLOSER TO THE REST OF AUSTRALIA AND THE REST OF AUSTRALIA<br />
CLOSER To NORTH QUEENSLAND, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
