<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1876</transcript-id>
    <title>SAIGON JOINT COMMUNIQUE  9 JUNE 1968</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/06/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001876.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VISIT TO SOUTH EAST ASIA 1968<br />
SA IGON<br />
JOINT COMMUNIQUE. 9 JUNE 1968<br />
At the invitation of the Government of the Republic of Vietnam,<br />
the Rt. Hon. J. G. Gorton, M. Prime Minister of the Commonwealth of<br />
Australia, accompanied by Mrs. Gorton visited the Republic from 7 to 9 June,<br />
1968. In Saigon, the Prime Minister was received by His Excellency, the<br />
President, and had conversations with the Prime Minister of the Republic, the<br />
Cabinet and the Presiding Officers of both Houses of the National Assembly.<br />
Mrs. Gorton visited a refugee centre and saw something of the work being done<br />
to rehabilitate the victims of communist attacks.<br />
The Prime Minister of Australia and the leaders of the Republic<br />
thoroughly reviewed the present situation. They agreed that regular consultation,<br />
S as to which the Prime Minister' s visit formed a part, was particularly important<br />
W now since, at the same time as preliminary talks were taking place in Paris,<br />
North Vietnamese attacks on civilian centres were continuing and the infiltration<br />
of North Vietnamese troops into South Vietnam was being increased. They<br />
reaffirmed their determination, expressed by all the allies at the Manila<br />
Conference, that the South Vietnamese should not be conquered by subversion,<br />
terrorism, murder, and the use of organized aggressive force, but should<br />
retain the right to choose their own form of Government and their own way of<br />
life. Mr. Gorton paid tribute to the steadfaistness of the Vietnamese<br />
Government, armed forces and people in the face of recent enemy offensives<br />
and attacks on civilians in population centres. He said that Australia and the<br />
Republic's other allies had noted with admiration the achievements of the<br />
__ Vietnamese people who, in spite of a campaign of systematic terror and<br />
Wdestruction had adopted a constitution, elected a representative Government<br />
and were laying the foundations of national reconciliation and reconstruction.<br />
The Vietnamese leaders expressed their appreciation and<br />
gratitude for the continuous support and assistance extended by Australia to<br />
their fight against communist aggression. They reasserted their position that<br />
the Republic of Vietnam should be a full participant and play a major role in<br />
any negotiations to settle the conflict. The Prime Minister and the leaders of<br />
the Republic agreed that the allied nations which have helped to defend the<br />
Republic of Vietnam should participate in any final settlement of the conflict.<br />
The Prime Minister and his party visited Nui Dat, Vung Tau,<br />
Phan Rang and Bien Hoa. These visits enabled the Prime Minister to meet<br />
Australians fighting and working in the Republic the soldiers, sailors and<br />
airmen of the Australian Force Vietnam, aid experts, and members of the<br />
medical teams whose humanitarian work exemplifies the breadth of the<br />
co-operation established between the two countries.<br />
The Prime Minister expressed his warm appreciation for the<br />
Vietnamese Government's invitation and for the arrangements that had been<br />
made to enable him to deepen his understanding of the problems and aspirations<br />
of the country. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
