<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17870</transcript-id>
    <title>Gillard Government building a skilled workforce in SA</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/05/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard today inspected new mobile training facilities and heavy vehicle simulators that will transform the learning environment for thousands of students in South Australia.</p>
<p>The Gillard Labor Government has invested $8.2 million towards the development of a state of the art training centre run by Civil Train SA which will allow civil construction students to train using technologically advanced simulators.</p>
<p>The simulators will help students learn how to drive and operate heavy machinery such as loaders and excavators.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister and Minister for Skills and Jobs, Senator Chris Evans visited the facilities run by Civil Train SA at Thebarton in Adelaide today.</p>
<p>The new equipment will also help students in regional South Australia when Civil Train SA begins operating 6 mobile units which include vehicle simulators.</p>
<p>Civil Train SA also contributed to the $12.8 million project which will enable the organisation to double its training places to more than 20,000 in three years.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government is investing directly in projects like the one at Civil Train SA to help improve the skills of Australian workers.</p>
<p>Investing in skills training is a down payment on our nation's future.</p>
<p>That's why the Budget invests more than $3 billion over six years in the Building Australia's Future Workforce package to ensure Australians of all ages are able to access the training and skills they need to get a job in our strengthening economy.</p>
<p>The Budget is focused on ensuring Australian workers have the opportunity to get the high skill, high paid jobs on offer in our nation and enjoy the dignity of work.</p>
<p>Improving the quality of the vocational education and training sector and ensuring graduates have the skills necessary to support a strong economy is a key priority for the Government.</p>
<p>The $8.2 million investment in Civil Train SA training facilities has been made through the Government's Education Investment Fund (EIF).</p>
<p>Through major capital infrastructure investment, the EIF has been transforming Australia's teaching and learning capabilities, and helping to meet the demand for skilled workers.</p>
<p>In the past three years, the Government has invested more than $4 billion in building new education, training and research facilities across Australia.</p>
<p>More information on the EIF initiative can be found at: <a href="http://www.deewr.gov.au/EIF">www.deewr.gov.au/EIF</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
