<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6451</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT, PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE WITH AUSTRALIAN JOURNALISTS, TUVALU, 2.30PM, 28 AUGUST 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/08/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006451.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STRISCRI PRI-: INlSTER S fRESS CO'FERENCE WITir AUSTr lUlS: JCjRLI S<br />
TUVALU 2.30 P. M. 28 August 1984<br />
E O E PROOF O:; LY<br />
we have a difficulty that we haven't got the draft communique<br />
available yet. I think you understand we're going to send it<br />
on to you aren't we when it's available Well I think we<br />
should say quite honestly that before coming to Tuvalu there<br />
had been so: me cn. estion mark about how. a forum meeting would<br />
go here because it was known that the facilites were rather<br />
limited but I must say that not only speaking for myself, but<br />
I would think for all participants, it has been an excellent<br />
decision to have the forum meeting here. It gives you a very<br />
insight to the nature of and the problems confronting the smaller<br />
island states in the Pacific. And they certainly cannot in any<br />
respect be faulted for the organisation, the enthusiasm and<br />
the hospitality which has been evident in the preparation and<br />
the conduct of this meeting. I certainly convey to the Prine<br />
Minister and the Government of Tuvalu our gratitude for the<br />
way in which the Forum has been conducted. If I could give a<br />
general overview of the meeting it's really fallen I guess<br />
into two parts. On the first day we were concerned with two<br />
broad political issues if you like the question of decolonisation<br />
and the developments in New Caledonia in that respect on the one<br />
hand and the question of a nuclear free zone concept on the<br />
other. I believe that the communique will reflect substantially<br />
useful discussions on both those areas. On the question of<br />
New Caledonia there was I think general agreement on these<br />
points. Firstly, of the integrity of the French Government in<br />
its desire to progress the negotiations towards independence.<br />
Associated with this, however, was the view that given the<br />
way in which tension is rising in New Caledonia acceptance of<br />
the desirability of trying to accelerate the referendum which<br />
is on current French planning set down for 1989. And while<br />
there was not agreement to the proposal that the question of<br />
New Caledonia should be reinscribed on the agenda of the<br />
Committee of 24 of the United Nations, nevertheless a number<br />
of Forum members will refer to this issue in their contributions<br />
in the debate in the General Assembly later on this year.<br />
We recognised also at a later stage in the Forum the reality<br />
that there is a very limited number of Kanaks in New Caledonia<br />
who have had the opportunity as a result of the neglect of<br />
previous French administrations to be trained professionally<br />
and technically. And the point was made at the latter stage<br />
of the Forum meeting that it would make a lot of sense for<br />
individual Forum members who had the capacity, such as Australia,<br />
to try and offer opportunities to these people to increase the<br />
number of professionally and technically trained people. So much<br />
for New Caledonia. On the question of the nuclear free zone<br />
JOUNALIST: Could I just ask you whether Australia was happy<br />
about the resolution on New Caledonia?<br />
Yes. On the ca: estion of a nuclear free zone I think again<br />
it was a very useful discussion and a very large measure of<br />
acreem'ent on the Australian proposals. And what we have done<br />
now-. and it's always useful at the end of a meeting to feel that </p>
<p>2.<br />
P. M. you just haven't talked about it and said<br />
well taat's cood we'e none concretely c. to<br />
establish a wo-kir. c art of officials to cCt as fre c: ently<br />
as possible to address themselves no'. to spcific el1er. ents<br />
of the concept legal questions, questions of the geographical<br />
limits of the zone. And with a view if possible, we don't know<br />
whether it can be done, to the presentazion of a draft treaty<br />
to next year's Forum meeting. And that proposal has been<br />
processed now on the basis of accepting the Australian approach<br />
that there should be agreement by the Forum members of<br />
opposition to nuclear testing in the area, and an expression<br />
of commitment not to acquire, manufacture or store nuclear<br />
weapons, and an expression of opposition to dumping of nuclear<br />
waste products. And secondly, within that concept, the<br />
retention of the rights of sovereign states to make their<br />
own decision as to the visit of nuclear powered or nuclear<br />
armed ships. Now those were the two matters in the first<br />
broad area of discussion in the Forum as I pointed to you<br />
earlier. The second area has more to do with internal<br />
functional matters covering a range of issues of the work<br />
of the Secretariat of the Forum and its manifestation in<br />
trade, education and fishing areas for instance and finally<br />
there was a decision to convene the next meeting of the<br />
Forum which will be in Rarotonga in the Cook Islands on<br />
4 6 August next year.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you believe that Mr Lange suffered yesterday<br />
by trying to take the Pacific states too quickly on the road<br />
to a nuclear free zone?<br />
I don't think it's a question of suffering. They had<br />
a view as to how to approach it. There came to be an acceptance<br />
that what's been done is the most sensible way of doing it and<br />
I don't believe that New Zealand is unhappy about that.<br />
JOURNALIST: proposal mightn't be approved.<br />
No there had been some discussion at the officials level.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke at the risk of dragging you over ground<br />
you've already covered the criticism over the nuclear free<br />
zone, claiming that its a paper tiger, even if it then came<br />
into force how would you defend it to that criticism?<br />
It's manifestly an absurd criticism. I'm not quite<br />
sure why you want me to go through it again.<br />
JOURNALIST: We haven't had it on television.<br />
I see. There are obviously in this world limits to<br />
what one nation or a group of nations at less than the superpower<br />
level are able to do in the field of disarmament, particularly<br />
nuclear disarai:. cnt cuestions. It would be cuite futile to<br />
suggest that you have an unli: mitoed capacity in this area. So<br />
what does make sense to do is to concentrate upon those things<br />
which are within your capacity. It is within the capacity of<br />
_ I </p>
<p>cont th e nations making up the Foru' to make dec sons<br />
as t: o t. o will o rc. r: to the _ r cc<br />
o" : uc ear eaocn-ss . : cw havo arccd that we arc opposed<br />
individually and collectively to doing that to manufacturing,<br />
using or storing nuclear weapons. And so the work that ' ill L: e<br />
done on the preparation of the treaty concept will include that.<br />
Now I believe that it's useful that nations in this area of the<br />
world should tell the rest of the world that that's their<br />
position and that's what they are going to do. It is also useful<br />
that we should collectively as well as individually express our<br />
opposition to the testing of nuclear w. eapons in our region. I<br />
think the fact that we are moving to incorporate that within<br />
a nuclear free zone concept will be useful, not decisive but<br />
useful, in bringing some more pressure on France in that respect.<br />
Also by collectively within such a nuclear free zone concept that<br />
we should express our opposition to dumping of nuclear wastes<br />
in our region. That I believe will add to the possibility of<br />
ensuring that that is not done. Now these are the things that<br />
can be achieved by a nuclear free zone treaty. It would be<br />
an exercise in absurdity to suggest that you could do other<br />
things. For instance, that you could by having a nuclear free<br />
zone conept interfere with the freedom of transit on the high<br />
seas and so we don't pretend that that is involved. Equally<br />
it would be futile to suggest that having a treaty of this kind<br />
which can achieve those very specific objectives to which I have<br />
referred, that you should seek to impose upon individual states<br />
limitations upon their right to make judgements about their own<br />
security relationships and we don't seek to do that.<br />
JOJALIST: On the question of New Caledonia, after the Forum made<br />
clear its position on was there any indication given to the<br />
Forum that the Kanak Independence Front might accept the Forum<br />
position on this and might therefore not go outside the region.<br />
Well the Kanak Independence Front wasn't represented there.<br />
JOURNALIST: I thought there might have been some indication<br />
passed on.<br />
P. M. No.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
