<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6963</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOW</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/06/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006963.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 29 June 1986<br />
As I foreshadowed in my Address to the Nation on 11 June, I have<br />
now written to business leaders and business and professional<br />
associations calling for shared restraint in incomes and prices.<br />
All told, 161 letters have been despatched.<br />
The Government has welcomed the decisions of the National Wage<br />
Bench, handed down on Thursday. These decisions were consistent<br />
with the approach suggested in my Address to the Nation and<br />
provide for firm restraint in the growth of award wages and<br />
superannuation payments.<br />
But it is only fair that, if there is to be restraint, it should<br />
be universal. I have pointed out in my letter that this requires<br />
each organisation to play its part in this national effort in at<br />
least two key areas. First, non-wage incomes such as executive<br />
salaries and directors' fees should be subject to equivalent<br />
restraint. Similarly, price increases should also be restrained<br />
to the maximum possible extent. The Government will be<br />
monitoring developments in both of these areas.<br />
Incomes policy is an integral part of the Government's broader<br />
economic strategy. As evidenced in the outcome of the recent<br />
Premiers' Conference, this includes firm restraint on budget<br />
outlays and the PSBR, which is the only effective way to address<br />
both the current account deficit and high interest rates<br />
simultaneously. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
