<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6281</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE FOR AUSTRALIAN MEDIA, CHOGM CONFERENCE CENTRE, NEW DELHI, 29 NOVEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006281.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
!, AUSTXIALIA L<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E. O. E. PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE FOR AUSTRALIAN MEDIA, CHOGM<br />
CONFERENCE CENTRE, NEW DELHI, 29 NOVEMBER 1983<br />
PM: before the end of the day Mr. Ramphal has in mind<br />
that we should have a preliminary brief meeting to work out<br />
what the future course of action should be. I expect that<br />
to happen before I leave tonight.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, are you expecting to see President<br />
Reagan, or how are you going to convey the message that<br />
Australia rejects linkage on<br />
PM: No, that Australian position has been known. It has been<br />
conveyed before. We have said that in the relevant<br />
international forums, so what I ha. e said here is not<br />
something new and it is a position which the United States is<br />
aware of. If I'm having any further discussions or when I'm<br />
having further discussions with the President I, of course in<br />
the appropriate context, would remind him of it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, in Goa you mentioned that you<br />
hoped to have the first meeting here on the Cyprus group.<br />
I gather that hasn't happened yet.<br />
PM: No, I just answered that. I said that before the end of<br />
this day we are scheduled to leave about 8 o'clock tonight<br />
before we leave we will be having a meeting of the heads of<br />
government of those five nations.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just a short summing up overall comment on your<br />
experiences in CHOGM.<br />
PM: Worthwhile for these reasonfs. Firstly, it has given me<br />
the opportunity to mneet a wide range of leaders of the<br />
Commonwealth covering aligned, non-aligned countries, countries<br />
at all stages of economic development and from all geographical<br />
areas. Now, that has been useful. It will mean on my part a<br />
greater capacity to conduct effective relations with these<br />
countries because I know the leaders personally. Secondly, it<br />
has been an occasion in which some specifically useful things<br />
have been done. Two in particular Cyprus the creation of<br />
the five nation working group to operate alongside the United<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>Nations Secretary de Cuellar. I think it adds to the possibility<br />
of resolving that matter. I'm glad that Australia is one of<br />
those five nations. Secondly, in regard to Grenada that was<br />
indeed significant to get an agreed position on that and I think<br />
the communique reflects the growth of understanding that took<br />
place here amongst the lot of us because it doesn't involve any<br />
recriminations about the past. It emphasises the need to<br />
accelerate the return to constitutional government. I think<br />
that was important. It was indeed a remarkable achievement.<br />
JOURNALIST: You were surprised at the achievement of that?<br />
PM: Yes, because when you listened to the debate on Thursday, the<br />
initial debate, the differences were so wide and deep that it<br />
seemed to me a fairly difficult task to get an agreed position,<br />
but that was achieved.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think there has been an anti-American bias<br />
here, Prime Minister?<br />
PM: It is true that some countries I don't go into names<br />
tend to view most international issues with an element of anti-US<br />
bias. I think that is true, but it doesn't dominate.<br />
JOURNALIST: that anti-American bias at this meeting?<br />
PM: People are entitled to express a view. I think what you've<br />
got to, at the end, test, Paul, is what is said and what is<br />
done and if you take, for instance, the Grenada resolution, the<br />
United States doesn't get a mention in the resolution, so people<br />
might in the course of debate express some views and give some<br />
emphases, but in the end they weren't indulging directly in an<br />
attack upon the United States. They were concentrating upon the<br />
future. So I think one understands those things.<br />
JOURNALIST: They certainly were in South Africa, though weren't<br />
they. PM: They were what?<br />
JOURNALIST: They were indulging in that sort of attack on the US.<br />
PM: Yes, to some extent. Their concern is that the linkage by<br />
the United States between the wit ' hdrawal of Cuban troops from<br />
Angola and the settlement there. They certainly reject that<br />
linkage and think that it is unhelpful, counter-productive.<br />
But, at the end there has got to be an understanding in the<br />
economic area of the vast importance of the United States to the<br />
welfare of, not only these countries but the rest of the world.<br />
It is very sensible, in my judgement, that adverse judgements<br />
that countries might want to make about the United States on<br />
particular issues should not be allowed to cloud their<br />
understanding that it is in the interests of the rest of the<br />
world to try and have as constructive relations with the United<br />
States as possible and to try and see that the United States plays<br />
as larcge a role as it can in the international. community becauLse<br />
it obviously has the capacity to determine to a very large </p>
<p>3.<br />
measure the rate of growth in trade in the world. And also<br />
it has the capacity, more than anyone else, to participate<br />
in constructive assistance to those countries of the world<br />
which most need it. And I'm conscious of that and I think<br />
they all should be. That doesn't mean that you have to endorse<br />
everything that the United States does or says, but it does<br />
suggest that one ought to be conscious of the importance and<br />
the relevance of the United States. It is rather difficult<br />
it seems to me, on the one hand totally to condemn the<br />
United States in terms of international politics and on the<br />
other side not to recognise its primary importance in the<br />
economic and development area. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
