<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7666</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF UNEDITED INTERVIEW WITH SUSANNA BIEDENKOPF, ZDF GERMAN TV, BONN, 28 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007666.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( P<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPTr OF UNEDITED INTERVIEW WITH SUSANNA BIEDENKOPF, ZDF<br />
GERMAN TV, BONN, 28 JUNE 1989<br />
E &amp; O0E-PROOF ONLY<br />
BIEDENROPF: After six years of negotiation, Australia decided<br />
rot to sign the Wellington Convention, why?<br />
PM: Because we believe in the end that it doesn't make sense<br />
if you are committed to protecting this last pristine<br />
wilderness, the Antarctic, to do it via a Minerals<br />
Convention I think that the world now at the end of the<br />
is different from the beginning of the 80a when the process<br />
was started. There is now a much greater commitment I think<br />
around the world to the causes of global environmental<br />
issues. we say no mining. We say it's appropriate to have<br />
an international wilderness reserve and that a Mining<br />
Convention is not the way to get there. So we respect the<br />
work that's been done and the intentions of everyone that's<br />
been involved. Most people have been involved in it. We are<br />
now trying to got the support that we have of France and<br />
India. I think if we can get as many more nations I'll be<br />
talking to, I'll discuss it while I'm here and hopefully<br />
we'll get support here. I think that's what the world wants<br />
and I think~ it is what is necessary.<br />
j BIEDENKOPK: But isn't one argument that the Mineral<br />
Convention is what is the best protection and ever get<br />
PM: Well it's pretty hard to say that a Convention about<br />
mining is the best way of getting protection against mining.<br />
A rather glaring lack~ of l. ogic in that situation I think. I<br />
don't believe now that it is appropriate to contemplate<br />
mining in the Antarctic region. We're getting more and more<br />
evidence of the fragility of this type of environment. One<br />
point wh~ ich is very important is that it is the last area in<br />
the world in which it' 9p~ asibie-to take measurements of<br />
changes in global climatic conditions uneffected by human<br />
activity. This is very luportant as we are now beginning<br />
more and more with the Greenhouse Effect. Now if in fact </p>
<p>-2-<br />
( PM cont) we were to allow the emergence of a situation in<br />
the Antarctic with that natural unpolluted environment which<br />
is affected by human activities, particularly by mining and<br />
anriaitd activities, then there would be some degredation<br />
of the environmental capacity to take those sorts of<br />
measurements which are going to be important for us and the<br />
world community, to understand what is happening and on the<br />
basis of understanding what is happening-, what are the things<br />
that we need to do.<br />
BIEDENKOPF: New Zealand started a similar initiative in ' 72<br />
without success. Are you pretty positive on the results of<br />
the initiatives?<br />
PM: We can't be dogmatic and say, ' you're going to succeed,<br />
you're going to try very hard'. But I think that we're now<br />
talking in 1989, that's 17 years on from ' 72. But there's<br />
one thing that we know surely is that the world is a<br />
dramatically different place, 17 years on from 1972. Part of<br />
that dramatic difference I think is an enormous acceleration<br />
in human understanding of and concern for global<br />
environmental issues.<br />
BIEDENKOPF: What other issues are you planning to talk about<br />
while you're in Germany?<br />
PM: Obviously there are bilateral issues, how can we<br />
increase trade and commerce between our two countries. There<br />
are enormous opportunties. The German firms that come into<br />
Australia, using Australia as a spring board into the Asian<br />
Pacific region. Likewise for Australian firms to come here<br />
using Germany as its very, very high purchasing power as well<br />
as a basis into this market of 320 million people after 1992,<br />
we'll be talking about that. We'll obviously be talking as<br />
well about international issues. We'll be very interested to<br />
hear from Chancellor Kohl and Foreign Minister Genscher,<br />
their perceptions of the most recent moves in the armaments<br />
field and their perceptions of developments in Australia's<br />
All these sorts Of things.<br />
BIEDENKOPF: Thank you very much. I hope you enjoy your<br />
stay. PM: Thank you very rc.<br />
ADDITOM&amp; L QUETIQN fO I J~ t" A# aIST<br />
JOURNALIST: To what extept Aq you willing to support the<br />
trade of flow but stabilising your economy, or put it<br />
differently, where do you see your currency </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM*: We floated the currency. When you float the currency<br />
you don't fix it at the level in the dollar. It'll be fixed<br />
by the flow and force of market circumstances. It's not for<br />
me to predict where it's going to be. But obviously it<br />
is down significantly from the point at which we floated it<br />
some five years ago. I see it as being at levels which are<br />
going to enable Australian industry to be significantly<br />
competitive, that's the important point.--<br />
JOURNALIST: And you would continue to keep interest rates<br />
high to fight inflation..<br />
PM: That's a very simplistic analysis of what we've done.<br />
Interest rates are high because we've got a very high level<br />
of economic activity. It's too high and we've got to cool<br />
the economy down somewhat. I've said that interest rates<br />
will stay high as long as is necessary to achieve that<br />
objective, but no longer than that.<br />
ends A -I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
