<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9105</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIP OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN, A CURRENT AFFAIR CHANNEL 9 SYDNEY 27 JANUARY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/01/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009105.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL:<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN, A CURRENT AFFAIR, CHANNEL 9<br />
SYDNEY, 27 JANUARY 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
RM: PM, thanks for your time.<br />
PM: It's a pleasure, Ray.<br />
RM: Have you had a chance to talk to Prince Charles?<br />
PM: You mean since yesterday?<br />
RM: Yes.<br />
PM: No. But I had a very pleasant conversation with him the night<br />
before, and we had a little bit of correspondence between us<br />
yesterday morning, but I haven't seen him since.<br />
RM: You haven't. Do you know whether he was concerned? He<br />
certainly looked very calm, didn't he?<br />
PM.-Oh, he's a professional at this sort of thing. He was attending<br />
functions liIke this when he was seven years of age. I think<br />
he's had more experience at these sorts of events than any of<br />
us.<br />
R ut you can't get experience with someone coming out of a<br />
crowd with a gun?<br />
PM: No, I know. But his relaxed demeanour his control in the<br />
circumstances -1 think reflected the professional attitude he<br />
has.<br />
RM: The NSW Premier's called for tighter security. Have you<br />
personally called for that?, 28. Jan. 94 7: 48 No. 001 P. 01/ 0( </p>
<p>TEL: 28. Jan .94<br />
2<br />
PM: No. 1 think one of the nice things about this country is that<br />
people are accessible. I think the important thing to record<br />
about this, is that it was not an assassination attempt it was<br />
a political demonstration. It's unfair to Prince Charles, for<br />
anyone to be reporting it as an assassination attempt, when it<br />
wasn't. It's a serious thing for somebody to be saying that<br />
somebody is out to assassinate you. This was not true, and I<br />
think that therefore the Prince's own relaxed demeanour<br />
reflected how he wished the episode to be viewed.<br />
RM: Yes, he wouldn't have known at the time though, would he?<br />
Suddenly someone comes out of a crowd with what looks like<br />
a gun?<br />
PM: Oh sure, absolutely.<br />
RM: Similarly, Premier Fahey and Ian Kiernan were quick out of<br />
the blocks a~ d _ Sh5~, f extraordinary reactions?<br />
PM: Absolutely. John's had experience on the football field and<br />
Ian's an all-round sportsman, and quick reflexes and I think<br />
everyone would have been very, very proud of their quick<br />
response.<br />
RM: Britain, America around the world that footage obviously is<br />
in the news tonight. Should we be embarrassed?<br />
PM: I think we must reflect upon this. We are all embarrassed<br />
whenever any good friend of Australia any person such as<br />
this is affronted in this way. Prince Charles is a good friend<br />
of this country and he should be treated with the respect and<br />
dignity that a good friend deserves.<br />
RM: What about the alleged reason for the demonstration?<br />
Should we be embarrassed about our treatment of<br />
Cambodian refuge es?<br />
PM: Well, we've got processes in place to deal with refugee<br />
assessment. It's not a simple issue for Australia or any<br />
country, and we've been working thrbugh these legal<br />
processes to try and resolve all these problems.<br />
RM: Children, women, men in jails, effectively for four years?<br />
PM: I know they're long, and we are trying to get them resolved<br />
and finalised. ?: 48 NO-001 P. 02/ 07 </p>
<p>TEL 228. a. Jan 94<br />
3<br />
RM: Now the speech itself the Prince gave yesterday, last night.<br />
Some papers say that Prince Charles gave his tacit blessing<br />
to the republican movement. Is that the way you read it?<br />
PM: What he said I think was, or directly said look, this is a<br />
matter for Australians. This is a matter for you people, but<br />
personally I think this debate is a sign of a mature and<br />
confident country. In other words, personally I think you're<br />
able to handle this debate, and it's a good thing you are.<br />
RM: But republicans, he said, may be right?<br />
PM: Well, I don't think I'm entitled to say that he's saying Australia should<br />
be a republic. I think he has said to us have your own debate. As a<br />
member of the Royal Family, we will accept a decision by the<br />
Australian people, and frankly, he said, it shows a sign of a mature and<br />
confident country. I mean he is giving us a wink and a nod to carry on<br />
with this debate.<br />
RM:-You know that's going to be headline tomorrow? PMV says<br />
Prince Charles gives us a wink and a nod?<br />
PM: Not for a Republic, but to have the debate. But he's certainly<br />
not giving us a wink and a nod not to move this way.<br />
RM;. I'm just looking at your speech tonight, shortly in Melbourne.<br />
You have been accused over the last couple of years by<br />
some of bashing the poms over the Singapore evacuation<br />
and Gallipoli and things like that, and yet in this speech you<br />
seem to be out there touting for British business.<br />
PM: There is a really good modern linkage with Britain of the kind<br />
we should have. What I can't stand is this tugging the<br />
forelock business.<br />
RM:-Just before we leave Britain, can I just ask: there was a report<br />
on the weekend papers that Princess Diana would like to<br />
come to Australia. As the mother of a future King would she<br />
officially be welcomed?<br />
PM: I have never seen any request from her, Ray, and naturally<br />
we would discuss that. But again, most people who want to<br />
come to Australia are welcome, that would include Princess<br />
Diana.<br />
RM: Can we leave the Brits there for a moment? We will come<br />
back and talk about other things with Mr Keating in just a<br />
moment. 7: 48 No. 001 P. 03/ 07 </p>
<p>28. Jan. 94 7: 48 No. 001 P. 04/ U?<br />
4<br />
RM.-Let's turn to the economy it has been a good year. The indicators are<br />
very good for this, can we let the good times roll?<br />
PM: Yes, b~ ut I said yesterday, and. 1, think it is worth repeating, this can't be<br />
a top end of town recovery.<br />
RMV: What does that mean?<br />
PM: We don't want to see into the stock market and people playing paper<br />
assets, or throwing paper assets around.<br />
RM: Like the high fliers of the<br />
PM: It has got to spread out into plant and equipment investment and into<br />
employment.<br />
IRMV: Can you officially say th -e re cession is behind us?<br />
PM: The recession is definitely behind us.<br />
RM: No question about that. Are you worried about interest rates going up?<br />
PM: The recession Is way behind us, accept that we have still got the carry<br />
over in long term unemployment which the Government is devoting<br />
itself to now in these next three months.<br />
RM: So that becomes a priority suddenly does it?<br />
RM: It becomes a priority from a social justice point of view and a national<br />
economic efficiency point of view.<br />
RM: What can you do about that? There is almost a million out of<br />
work.<br />
PM: Well there is about 400,000 who have been out of work for one year or<br />
more. They're the problem. The Government has got to try and get<br />
them back into the swim as well as get aggregate employment going.<br />
So it's the short-term unemployed and the long-term unemployed.<br />
RM: Someone sitting here watching this tonight and says Keating would<br />
say the recession is over but I haven't had a job for a year and a half<br />
and I'm not going to get one.<br />
PM: Well that is my point. There is a lag there. I think the word, Ray, I<br />
used it a lot with One Nation and in 1992 and in 1993, and that is<br />
Inclusion. This has to be an inclusive society. That we all move along<br />
together. And if someone does drop back, we bring them up. And not<br />
let them slip away into an underclass. </p>
<p>TEL: 28. Jan .94 7: 48 No. 001 F. Ub/ U?<br />
RM: Yeah, but clearly from this speech tonight, you are very optimistic<br />
about the Australian economy?<br />
PM: I think we have never faced in the last 25 years, a period quite like this.<br />
This is strong growth with very low inflation,<br />
RM: Is it a good time to invest in piggeries?<br />
PM: Well it is a good time to invest in Australia's comparative advantage.<br />
One Australia's great comparative advantages is food and we should<br />
all be investing in things which add value, employ people and<br />
hopefully it will lead to exports.<br />
RM: PM, how about sandwich shops?<br />
PM: Well, I think Ministers are entitled to invest in things, but they also<br />
have to be responsible for them.<br />
RM: Alright, was AllanGriffith's responsible with his sandwich shop?<br />
PM: Yes, if you have an investment you have to be responsible for, in<br />
political terms.<br />
RM: Can you tell us tonight who the new Minister is?<br />
PM: No, I haven't decided that yet, Ray.<br />
RM: Would you think, I mean, Laurie Brereton, Simon Crean, Graham<br />
Richardson, Peter Cook are the names, Is that a fair guess?<br />
PM: Well each one of those would be a competent industry Minister.<br />
RM: Does Mr Griffith, at this stage, have a political career?<br />
PM: Absolutely. He is still a Federal member of Parliament, and also while<br />
he will not be Minister for Industry, Technology and Regional<br />
Development he will still have a right to recontest a position in the<br />
ministry.<br />
RM: I know you can't speak about it, so I won't push it further, but there are<br />
reports in the press that Mr Griffith knew about these alleged Labor<br />
Party checks and about the $ 941.00 six weeks before he told you.<br />
PM: Well I am not aware of it. The first, you asked me earlier, the first I<br />
knew of any of this matter was last Friday evening.<br />
RM: Do you think, if that's the case, should you have been told six weeks<br />
ago if he knew? </p>
<p>TEL: 28.2jan. 94 7: 48 NO. 001 P. 06/ 07<br />
6<br />
PM. Well that's a matter for him, and in the end when all this comes out in<br />
the wash, and let's not presume all these things are right, then we can<br />
make judgements about that.<br />
RM. What do you think about Bronwyn Bishops line that you can't run the<br />
industry portfolio if you can't run a sandwich shop?<br />
PM-Well I think the more important line is what contribution have the<br />
Liberals got to make to modem Australia. I mean here they are, they<br />
have opposed everything last year, they tried to knock the Budget<br />
over, they have opposed Mabo for no reason other than to oppose it.<br />
They start the new year without an economic policy, I mean they are in<br />
a terrible situation. You have got Dr Hewson on the one hand, and<br />
now Senator Bishop on the other. It seems to me, Ray, it is a choice<br />
between a vacuum and a lot of hot air. I mean Senator Bishop has no<br />
policy structure in her head.<br />
RM: Do you have any fears at all about Bronwyn Bishop and the bull ring,<br />
or bull pit of the House of Reps?<br />
PM: As far as I am concerned, as they put them up we deal with them. It<br />
was Andrew Peacock, then it was John Howard, then it was Andrew<br />
Peacock, then it is John Hewson. Whoever is next we will be ready<br />
and waiting for them.<br />
RM: Does your crystal ball say she is going to be leader before the year is<br />
out?<br />
PM: Well she is going to keep on trying, even if the Party doesn't give her<br />
the job. But if they do give her the job they know in their heart of<br />
hearts that there is no structure there.<br />
RM: All right, tough question now, what's it like to be<br />
PM:* Well all those Peter Pan notions go right out of your mind. I mean I<br />
belonged to that baby boomer generation which believed it was never<br />
going to grow old.<br />
RM:. Do you feel old?<br />
PM: I don't feel old, but I know I am getting older, much older, and I am sure<br />
there Is no generation that has resisted aging more than mine. And<br />
you see them, and they are still out there, but there ranks are thinning<br />
and they are fattening up, and their hair is thinning, as mine is. So the<br />
years go on.<br />
RM: Do you qualify as a dear old thing as you have called some of the older<br />
members of the Labor Party, are you now a dear old thing? </p>
<p>TEL 7<br />
PM: Not quite, not quite, there is some cross over point, it has probably got<br />
a six in front of it.<br />
R M. You have had your real holiday, the break. What did you do? Did you<br />
read a book, or just play old rock and roll records?<br />
PM: We went to the beach, we went sailing quite a bit, I did a bit of reading,<br />
-a bit of music. I went to a bit of theatre, so, I have had a couple of<br />
weeks of sun and culture.<br />
RM: Did you play any Tom Jones records to loud for Anita?<br />
PM: Well we had Billy Joel, the kids like Billy Joel and so do 1. We meet at<br />
Billy Joel. Everything sort of after him I tend to drop off. And of course<br />
when the kids are around they monopolise all the audio visual<br />
eq~ uipment as it is called.<br />
RM: PM, thank you for your time.<br />
PM: Thank you, Ray. T2EL8:. Jan. 94 7: 48 No. 001 P. 07/ 07 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
