<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9362</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DINNER FOR MR ALBERT REYNOLDS, TAOISEACH OF IRELAND PARLIAMENT HOUSE, TUESDAY 20 SEPTEMBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/09/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009362.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4. f-Emarrgoevd'l~ j~<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DINNER FOR MR ALBERT REYNOLDS, TAQISEACH OF IRELAND<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, TUESDAY 20 SEPTEMBER 1994<br />
It is my great pleasure to welcome you to Australia.<br />
Our two countries share so much history, so much<br />
tradition and culture, so many attitudes.<br />
There is a sentiment we share.<br />
We Australians feel it when we go there.<br />
Prime Minister, we hope you feel it on your visit here.<br />
I have fond, indelible memories of my visit to Ireland<br />
last year.<br />
The day I spent in Tynagh, the place from which my<br />
forebears migrated to Australia, was quite simply one of<br />
the great days of my life.<br />
Addressing the Irish National Parliament was one of the<br />
great honours of my life.<br />
I have been to Ireland before and been enchanted.<br />
Nowhere outside Australia have I felt more at home.<br />
I suppose this is not surprising.<br />
The tragedy of Ireland in the nineteenth century was in<br />
some way's Australia's blessing.<br />
The mass migration of Irish to Australia in the 19th<br />
century and the preservation of their values in the<br />
institutions of the church, politics, the law, academia<br />
and many other other realms of our national life, mean<br />
that Irish tradition has fed and will go on feeding our<br />
own and that the friendship and affection between our<br />
two countries will always endure.<br />
Yet it would be a mistake to think that the regard in<br />
which we hold Ireland is built entirely on the past, or<br />
is nourished entirely by the past. </p>
<p>These are not dead traditions great ideas whether they<br />
are legal, political, religious or literary live do not<br />
readily die.<br />
Traditions adapt to circumstances. They find new shapes<br />
and new expressions in new places and new eras.<br />
Irish songs become Australian folksongs. Irish football<br />
becomes Australian football. The Irish St Leger becomes<br />
a practice race for the Melbourne Cup.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Down the years Ireland and the Irish have contrived a<br />
powerful place in the international landscape.<br />
They have contrived it from literature from their love<br />
of the creative and the life of the mind.<br />
They have contrived it from their energy and genius at<br />
home and abroad.<br />
We are not talking only about past glories. Irish<br />
literature continues to flourish. Films and music<br />
emerge from modern Ireland with the power to charm and<br />
excite people all over the world.<br />
The essential point is that the Irish are still creating<br />
this place in the world. on cultural and economic fronts<br />
in the European Community and beyond they are<br />
consolidating and expanding their place as never before.<br />
Ireland is becoming a modern nation a sophisticated,<br />
competitive and dynamic economy, an outward looking<br />
economy to serve the aspirations and rights of the Irish<br />
people in the next century. To bring new opportunities<br />
and prosperity to Ireland.<br />
And, what is to be celebrated most, Prime Minister, we<br />
are now seeing the creation of that on which the future<br />
of Ireland most critically depends the foundations of<br />
peace. For so long the Irish place in the world has been defined<br />
by tragedy as well as genius by inhumanity as well as<br />
humanity.<br />
For so long to think of Ireland has meant to think of<br />
violence of the violence done to the Irish and the<br />
violence the Irish have done to themselves.<br />
We now have cause to hope that those days may have ended<br />
that we might see economic modernity and integration<br />
with the world married to peace at a home, to a triumph<br />
of the Irish passion for fraternity over ancient<br />
animosities, to the Irish genius for humanity over<br />
inhumanity. </p>
<p>Prime Minister I know what a pivotal role you have played<br />
in the peace process in Northern Ireland.<br />
Your determination to succeed in this great endeavour,<br />
allied to your understanding of the human and political<br />
issues, your skills as a mediator, your courage, and the<br />
trust in which you are held, has been crucial to the<br />
progress which has been made so far.<br />
We congratulate you for this.<br />
And we also congratulate Prime Minister Major and the<br />
British Government for the constructive role they have<br />
played. The Australian Government welcomed the IRA's announcement<br />
on September 1 that military operations would cease. The<br />
Australian people welcomed it.<br />
You have said that the opportunity now exists to take the<br />
gun out of Irish politics forever.<br />
All Australians hope that the opportunity can be seized,<br />
and that peace comes to Ireland.<br />
They hope as people throughout the world would hope<br />
that the parties on whom peace depends understand that<br />
because Australians love Ireland they hate the war that<br />
goes on there.<br />
Unionists and Nationalists now have an opportunity to<br />
build relationships of trust, to pursue the goals of<br />
cooperation and reconciliation.<br />
To help this process I am very pleased to announce<br />
tonight that, following my discussions with Prime<br />
Minister Reynolds, the Australian Government will<br />
contribute $ 7 million over five years to the<br />
International Fund for Ireland.<br />
Not everyone here tonight will know about the Fund.<br />
The Fund was set up in December 1986 following an<br />
agreement between the British and Irish governments to<br />
promote in its own words " economic and social advance<br />
and to encourage contact, dialogue and reconciliation<br />
between nationalists and unionists throughout Ireland".<br />
The Fund does this by stimulating private investment and<br />
enterprise, supplementing public programs and supporting<br />
voluntary effort, including self-help schemes.<br />
The Fund's role in economic development, particularly in<br />
disadvantaged areas, will help to underpin progress<br />
towards peace and reconciliation in Ireland. </p>
<p>It is the most valuable material assistance we can give,<br />
and we are very pleased to join the United States, Canada<br />
the European Union and New Zealand among other<br />
countries in giving it.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
We have a great deal of shared history and shared<br />
traditions upon which to build our relationship.<br />
It is essential that to the warmth of our relationship we<br />
continue to add the threads which join our common<br />
interests and ambition.<br />
We need to build on those people to people relationships,<br />
especially tourism.<br />
We need more of the kind of institutional cooperation<br />
which saw that great exhibition of European Masters from<br />
the National Gallery of Ireland come to the National<br />
Gallery of Australia.<br />
We want to see the two way flow of investment grow. We<br />
are each of us primarily concerned with our own regionsbut<br />
that does not mean we turn our backs either on old<br />
friends, or on new opportunities.<br />
We hope that Irish business people will increasingly use<br />
Australia as a base for doing business in Asia and that<br />
Australia will use Ireland as a springboard to Europe.<br />
We need the sorts of exhanges which will help our young<br />
people get to know each other.<br />
And we need, Prime Minister, visits like this one.<br />
Visits which strengthen the bonds between us and remind<br />
us that we share not only an extraordinary past, but a<br />
future which really has never been so promising.<br />
I began by saying that we share so much history. It<br />
might be appropriate to this occasion and to the times we<br />
live in if I close by saying that nothing in our history<br />
is so important as the future.<br />
on behalf of the Government and people of Australia I<br />
welcome you and wish you a most enjoyable and rewarding<br />
stay. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
