<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1216</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM /1965 - REPLY TO NIGERIA&#039;S INVITATION TO CONFERENCE ON RHODESIA - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, KT, CH, QC, MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/12/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001216.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
65/! 49<br />
FOR FIdESS P. M. Np. / 1965<br />
2EPLY TO NIGFRIA'S INVITATION TO CONFENCE ON iH0DESIA<br />
( The t. H Ti.<br />
I have written to the Prime Minister of Nigeria, the 1-t. Hon.<br />
Sir Abubakar Tafawa Balewa, informing him that, under the existing<br />
circumstances, Australia is not in favour of the convening of a special<br />
Commonwealth Prime Ministers' Conference on -Ihodesia.<br />
I told Sir Abubakar that, because of our deep respect for him,<br />
and for his high character and motives, we had given careful<br />
consideration to the invitation to the Conference. I then outlined<br />
the reasons for our attitude to the proposed conference.<br />
I pointed out that we have publicly stated that we regard the<br />
Unilateral Declaration of Independence by the Smith Government as<br />
illegal. . ie have refused diplomatic recognition of the new regime.<br />
de continue to believe, and to say, that any constitutional<br />
settlement in Rhodesia must be on the basis of a steady progress<br />
towards majority rule and the removal of measures of racial<br />
discrimination. Jie believe that in preparation for the achievement of an African<br />
majority there should be an active educational programme, to which<br />
many of us might contribute.<br />
Je have strongly supported the financial and economic sanctions<br />
imposed by Britain, and have ourselves imposed sanctions covering<br />
93% of our jihodesian imports.<br />
' W7e believe that, if extensive economic measures are adopted by a<br />
sifficient number of nations, the persuasive pressure so generated<br />
will induce a return to the Conference table.<br />
But we are deeply and publicly opposed to the proposals, made by<br />
some Commonwealth members, for the use of armed force. *, Jc are not<br />
aware of any evidence that Rhodesia contemplates any armed attack upon<br />
any other country. , e would regard the assembling of non-Rhodesian<br />
forces on the fr6ntiers of Ihodesia as needlessly provocative and<br />
dangerous. The vital interests of Zambia, for example, can be protected only<br />
if peace is maintained.<br />
It is necessary to ask what the purposes or likely results of a<br />
special conference would be.<br />
The Australian Government believes that the government of Britain<br />
has behaved with firmness, expedition, and good sense; and that its<br />
resistance to the use of arms to enforce a constitutional settlement is<br />
sound. </p>
<p>a 2.<br />
But several Commonwealth countries are publicly demanding that<br />
armed force be used, and by Britain. Some of' these countries seem<br />
to have deeply and passionately committed themselves.<br />
Under these circumstances, a Prime M1inisters' Conference would<br />
in our view be unlikely to do more than record and emphasise differences.<br />
No unanimity of view could be achieved, and considerable bitterpness<br />
would be disclosed. This would be a terrible zrice to pay for the<br />
convening of a conference upon a problem in relation to which, as<br />
the la,-st Prime Ministers! Conference unanimously re-Yaffirned, " the<br />
authority and responsibility for leading her remaining Colonies,<br />
including Southern 1hodesia,. to independence miE t continue to rest<br />
wiith Britain."<br />
My Government has consistently opposed the giving of any Commonwealth<br />
orders to Britain as to how she should exercise that authority and<br />
discharge that responsibility. To have her, in effect, attacked and<br />
threatened at a special conference, would be a grave departure from<br />
proper practice in a Commonwealth g~ athering. Tt would also op'en the<br />
door to a new era in Commonwealth rel. c. tions, the abandonment of the<br />
old sound rules of non-intervention in the affairs of other Commonwealth<br />
countries, and the encouragement of those outside nations and<br />
groups which are ever ready to fish in troubled waters.<br />
My government does not, as it now sees the matter, wish to<br />
involve itself in a process which would prove so disastrous, not<br />
only to the Commonwealth but to Australia, Which would run a grave<br />
risk of having its views distorted or misinterpreted.<br />
CANBERiLI December 28, 1965. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
