<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8872</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP REVIEW OF GOVERNMENT POLICY ADVICE MECHANISMS ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/05/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008872.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I LLx I k<br />
7 PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER* THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
REVIEW OF GOVERNMENT POLICY ADVICE MECHANISMS<br />
ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN<br />
Today I have asked Senator the Hon Rosemary Crowley, Minister Assisting me on the<br />
Status of Women, to chair a review of the Government's policy advice mechanisms on<br />
thc status of women.<br />
Thic Government is proud of its successful record of reform and innovation in this<br />
important policy arca, and wants to ensure that its policy advice mechanisms remain<br />
appropriate, effective and responsive to the changing needs and interests of women. In<br />
particular the Government will review the functions of the Office of the Status of<br />
Women and the mechanisms for consulting and communicating with women in the<br />
community to ensure that women's interests are well rcpresented to govermecnt and<br />
that the Government's policy priorities are implemcnted effectively.<br />
I have asked Senator Crowlcy to advise on the functions and prioriticsof the Office of<br />
the Status of Women. Those priorities will include -monitoring the implementation of<br />
the Government's policies for women announced during thc election campaign,<br />
especially the new child-care policy. As well the Government will need continuing<br />
policy development work in the key areas affecting women economics, health,<br />
employment, education and justice ( including preventing violence against women).<br />
T'he new functions will include developing a research facility able to identify longer<br />
termi policy issues of relevance to women.<br />
In preparing the report, there will be consultation with women's and other intcrcsted<br />
organisations as well as relevant Ministers, government departments and members of<br />
Parliament. The review is expected to take about three months.<br />
CANBERRA 27 MAY 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
