<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3779</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, TO THE 1975 ANNUAL STATE CONVENTION OF THE ALP SOUTH AUSTRALIAN BRANCH, ADELAIDE, SUNDAY 15 JUNE 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/06/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003779.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE HON. E, G. lIWHITLAM, P, P,,<br />
TO THE 1975 ANNUAL STATE CONVENTION,<br />
OF THE A, L. P, SOUTH AUSTRALIAN BRANCH,<br />
ADELAIDE, SUNDAY 15 JUNE 1975<br />
FOR MANY YEARS I HAVE HAD THE PLEASURE OF ADDRESSING<br />
YOUR ANNUAL STATE CONVENTION, IT IS NOT A PLEASURE<br />
I WOULD READILY FORGO, SOUTH AUSTRALIA IS THE STATE:.<br />
THAT BEST EXEMPLIFIES THE SUCCESS OF LABOR'S POLICIES.<br />
IT'S HERE IN THIS PROGRESSIVE AND ENLIGHTENED STATE....<br />
THAT WE SEE THE REAL FRUITS OF A GREAT LABOR PARTNERSHIP.<br />
IT's A PARTNERSHIP THAT INVOLVES ALL OF US.-OUR PARTY,<br />
YOUR BRANCH, SON DUNSTAN'S GOVERNMENT, MY GOVERNMENT,<br />
OUR OFFICIALS, OUR RESPECTIVE DEPARTMENTS. YESTERDAY<br />
IN SYDNEY I FAD SOMETHING TO SAY TO THE NEW SOUTH WALES<br />
BRANCH ABOUT THE STATE GOVERNMENT'S OBSTRUCTION AND<br />
THE COST OF THAT OBSTRUCTION TO THE PEOPLE OF NEW SOUTH<br />
WALES A COST MEASURED IN POOR SOCIAL PLANNING AND<br />
DETERIORATING PUBLIC SERVICES, HERE IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
WE CAN SEE THE OTHER SIDE OF THE COIN, IE CAN SEE<br />
WHAT CAN BE ACHIEVED BY READY COOPERATION BETWEEN<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT AND THE STATES, i r </p>
<p>SINCE I LAST SPOKE TO YOU THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT HAS MADE GREAT PROGRESS WITH ITS PLANS FOR<br />
A BETTER AND FAIRER SOCIETY, I DON'T WANT TO GLOSS<br />
OVER OUR DIFFICULTIES, BUT EQUALLY THERE IS NO POINT<br />
IN UNDERRATING OUR SUCCESSES. I WAS TAKEN TO TASK<br />
IN THE PRESS THE OTHER DAY FOR POINTING TO THE REAL<br />
GAINS IN INCOMES MADE BY EMPLOYEES UNDER A LABOR<br />
GOVERNMENT, NO ONE SUPPOSES THAT MONEY INCOMES ARE ALL<br />
THAT MATTER IN DETERMINING LIVING STANDARDS LEAST<br />
S OF ALL WOULD A LABOR GOVERNMENT SUBSCRIBE TO THAT<br />
VIEW, BUT THE FACT REMAINS THAT UNDER LABOR THE<br />
REAL GAINS IN PERSONAL INCOME HAVE BEEN SUBSTANTIAL<br />
M; ORE THAN 7 PERCENT SINCE WE CAME TO OFFICE.<br />
PENSIONERS AND THOSE MOST IN NEED HAVE HAD BIGGER GAINS<br />
IN THEIR REAL INCOMES THAN EVER BEFORE. A LABOR<br />
GOVERNMENT A TRUE LABOR GOVERNMENT NATURALLY TAKES<br />
PRIDE IN ANY REAL SHIFT IN WEALTH TOWARDS THOSE SECTORS<br />
OF THE COMMUNITY WHO ARE MOST IN NEED, AND OF COURSE<br />
ALONG WITH THIS IMPROVEMENT IN MONEY INCOMES THERE HAS<br />
BEEN A VAST AND PERMANENT EXTENSION OF THE RANGE OF<br />
SERVICES AND OPPORTUNITIES AVAILABLE TO ALL<br />
AUSTRALIANS THE SORT OF OPPORTUNITIES THAT MAKE<br />
FOR A GENUINELY FAIR SOCIETY, FOR TRUE SOCIAL EQUITY, </p>
<p>WE WOULDN'T BE HUMAN IF WE WEREN'T WORRIED BY<br />
THE ECONOMIC PROBLEMS WE SHARE WITH ALL OTHER<br />
COMPARABLE COUNTRIES, IT IS NO EASY TASK TO FRAME<br />
A NATIONAL BUDGET WHILE THESE PROBLEMS CONTINUE,<br />
RECENTLY I HAVE DRAWN ATTENTION TO THE SIGNS OF<br />
IMPROVEMENT ALREADY APPARENT IN THE ECONOMY<br />
THE UPTURN IN THE DEMAND FOR HOUSING, THE CONTINUING<br />
FALL IN UNEMPLOYMENT, THE GROWTH IN CONSUMER DEMAND,<br />
WHAT WE ARE DETERMINED TO DO IN OUR EFFORTS TO<br />
BEAT INFLATION AND UNEMPLOYMENT-IS PROTECT THOSE WHO<br />
. MOST NEED PROTECTION. A LABOR GOVERNMENT IS ESSENTIALLY<br />
: A GOVERNMENT THAT CARES FOR PEOPLE ESPECIALLY<br />
. THOSE WHO STAND IN GREATEST NEED. THIS HAS BEEN<br />
.: THE THEME OF ALL OUR EFFORTS, ALL OUR MEASURES, ALL OUR<br />
PRIORITIES, WE'LL STAND BY THAT, IT'S-ALL TOO EASY TO<br />
BE DISHEARTENED BY THE PROBLEMS WE FACE, THIS IS. NOT<br />
THE FIRST TIME LABOR HAS BEEN IN POWER IN A TIME OF<br />
INTERNATIONAL CRISIS, THIRTEEN MONTHS AGO WE<br />
FOUGHT AN ELECTION IN A TIME OF IMMENSE ECONOMIC<br />
DIFFICULTY; WE WON THAT ELECTION; WE CAN WIN AGAIN,<br />
I CANNOT STRESS TOO OFTEN THE BASIC STRENGTH OF THE ECONOMY,<br />
THE STRENGTH AND ABUNDANCE OF OUR NATURAL RESOURCES,<br />
THE IMMENSE GCODWILL WE ENJOY AROUND THE WORLD,<br />
L </p>
<p>4<br />
IN PUSHING AHEAD WITH OUT PROGRAMS W\ E NEED THE<br />
COOPERATION OF THE STATES, THIS WEEK, AS YOU KNOW',<br />
I SHALL BE MEETING DON DUNSTAN AND THE OTHER PREMIERS<br />
IN CANBERRA AT THE PREMIERS' CONFERENCE. I DON'T WANT<br />
TO PREJUDGE THE OUTCOME OF OUR TALKS,<br />
BUT THE POINT TO REMEMBER IN.<br />
-THIS CONTEXT IS'JUST HOW MUCH THE? CAN SAVE, HOW<br />
.:: MUCH THEY CAN EASE THEIR FINANCIAL BURDENS, BY<br />
: COOPERATING WITH THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT IN ITS<br />
' SOCIAL PROGRAMS AND INITIATIVES, -THAT IS WHAT THE<br />
LABOR GOVERNMENT HAS DONE IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA.<br />
IT'S NOT A QUESTION OF KNUCKLIMG UNDER OR GIVING WAY<br />
TO CANBERRA, IT'S A MATTER OF GETTING TOGETHER OF<br />
HEALTHY NEGOTIATION, OF READY COOPERATION IN A<br />
SPIRIT OF TRUST AND GOODWILL. . r. s<br />
fl': r<br />
t<br />
j: -lIc: T<br />
r 1: </p>
<p>THERE ARE TWO PRINCIPAL BURDENS ON ALL STATE<br />
BUDGETS RAILWAYS AND HOSPITALS. OUR POLICIES ARE<br />
DESIGNED TO RELIEVE THOSE BURDENS. IT'S WORTH<br />
REMEMBERING THAT MEDIBANK, FOR EXAMPLE, INVOLVES<br />
MUCH MORE THAN FREE MEDICAL INSURANCE. IT MEANS<br />
A NEW DEAL FOR STATE HOSPITAL FINANCES, OFFICIALS<br />
OF BOTH GOVERNMENTS HAVE BEEN WORKING STEADILY<br />
. TOWARDS THIS AGREEMENT SINCE NEGOTIATIONS STARTED IN<br />
OCTOBER. LAST YEAR. THE AGREEMENT IS NOW READY FOR<br />
: SIGNINGA IT MEANS THAT THE NET COST OF OPERATING<br />
::: iSOUTH AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC HOSPITALS WILL BE SHARED<br />
. ON A 50-50 BASIS BETWEEN THE TWO GOVERNMENTS, I DON<br />
HAVE TO REMIND YOU OF THE BENEFITS TO THE PUBLIC<br />
OF THE HOSPITAL SIDE OF MEDIBANK FREE STANDARD<br />
WARD TREATMENT, FREE OUTPATIENT SERVICES, LOWER<br />
HOSPITAL CHARGES FOR INTERMEDIATE AND PRIVATE WARDS,<br />
AN ADDITIONAL $ 16 A DAY IN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
PAYMENTS TO PRIVATE HOSPITALS FOR THEIR PATIENTS, x J ' rc . r-<br />
1 -r-<br />
:~ I2 F~-iL; ; iS; I<br />
r<br />
TT </p>
<p>THOSE ARE BENEFITS FOR PATIENTS, FOR THE PEOPLE. THE<br />
IMPORTANT THING FOR THE SOUTH AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT IS A<br />
SAVING OF $ 28 MILLION A YEAR UNDER THE MEDIBANK HOSPITAL<br />
ARRANGEMENTS, MONEY WHICH THE STATE GOVERNMENT WILL BE<br />
ABLE TO SPEND IN ANY AREA OF ITS RESPONSIBILITY, ONLY<br />
ONE OTHER STATE TASMANIA WILL BE INTRODUCING THE<br />
MEDIBANK HOSPITAL ARRANGEMENTS FROM 1 JULY, ALL THE<br />
ANTI-LABOR STATES HAVE DITHERED AND DELAYED AT GREAT<br />
COST TO THEIR STATE BUDGETS AND AT GREAT COST TO THE<br />
WELFARE OF THEIR CITIZENS,<br />
THE OTHER AREA WHERE WE ARE EASING SOUTH AUSTRALIA'S<br />
FINANCIAL BURDENS IS RAILWAYS, THIS HAS BEEN A GREAT YEAR<br />
OF ACHIEVEMENT AND INNOVATION FOR THE RAILWAYS IN AUSTRALIA,<br />
BUT IT HAS BEEN A TIME OF SPECIAL ACHIEVEMENT FOR SOUTH<br />
AUSTRALIA, ONE OF MY FIRST ACTS AS PRIME MINISTER WAS<br />
TO WRITE TO D'C DUNSTAN SEEKING DISCUSSIONS ON OUR OFFER<br />
TO ACCEPT A TRANSFER OF THE STATE RAILWAYS TO THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT, THAT OFFER WAS MADE IN MY 1972<br />
POLICY SPEECH, ' iE MADE RAPID PROGRESS IN NEGOTIATIONS,<br />
THE PREMIER AND I SIGNED AN AGREEMENT ON 21 MAY TO TRANSFER<br />
THE NON-METROPOLITAN RAILWAYS OF THIS STATE, AND THE<br />
NECESSARY LEGI LATION HAS PASSED THE. t-HOUSEE -OF REP. RESENTATL'VES,<br />
"' I<br />
THERE WILL EE A NET FINANCIAL BENEFIT TO THE STATE'S<br />
REVENUE OF $ 10 MILLION TO BE PAID BY THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
ON OR BEFORE 1 JULY, SOUTH AUSTRALIA WILL BE RELIEVED OF<br />
CAPITAL DEBTS ON HER TRANSFERRED RAILWAYS, SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
WILL HAVE A SETTER RAILWAY SYSTEM. THE RIGHTS AND EMPLOYMENT<br />
OF EVERY RAILWAY EMPLOYEE WILL BE PRESERVED,<br />
I </p>
<p>THERE IS MORE TO TELL YOU ABOUT RAILWAYS IN<br />
SouTH AUSTRALIA, AND I SHALL RETURN TO IT IN A MOMENT,<br />
BUT THE POINT I MAKE IS THIS: IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA,<br />
WE HAVE HELPED TO RELIEVE THE STATE GOVERNMENT OF TWO<br />
OF ITS TRADITIONAL BURDENS, AND REMEBER THAT WHAT<br />
IE HAVE DONE FOR RAILWAYS AND HOSPITALS THIS YEAR WE<br />
HAVE ALREADY DONE FOR WELFARE HOUSING AND UNIVERSITIES,<br />
AT THE PREMIERS' CONFERENCE A YEAR AGO WE GAVE THE<br />
STATES A VIRTUAL BLANK CHEQUE FOR THEIR WELFARE HOUSING..<br />
NEEDS, THIS RESPONSIBILITY IS NOW SHOULDERED ENTIRELY<br />
.: BY. THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT, AT THE JUNE 1974 PREMIERS'..<br />
'. CONFERENCE,' SOUTH AUSTRALIA WAS ADVANCED $ 20 MILLION<br />
FOR THE SOUTH. AUSTRALIAN HOUSING TRUST IN 1974-75<br />
AND $ 18 MILLION FOR LENDING TO MEANS TESTED APPLICANTS<br />
FOR HOUSING LOANS THROUGH THE HOME BUILDERS' ACCOUNT<br />
UNDER THE 1973, HOUSING AGREEMENT, IN ADDITION, UNIVERSITIES,<br />
TEACHERS COLLEGES AND ADVANCED EDUCATION UNDER MY<br />
GOVERNMENT ARE N'OW ALMOST ENTIRELY COMMONWEALTH<br />
RESPONSIBILITIES. HAVE BEEN OVERWHELMINGLY GENEROUS<br />
IN FUNDING THEM, AS WE HAVE WITH EDUCATION OF EVERY KIND,<br />
I NOTICED IN THE " ADVERTISER" THIS WEEK THE PLAN FOR A<br />
NEW TERTIARY EDUCATION CENTRE ON THE SITE OF THE EAST<br />
END MARKET, IT'S A SUPERB SCHEME INCORPORATING THE<br />
COLLEGE OF ADVANCED EDUCATION AND THE INSTITUTE OF<br />
TECHNOLOGY, IT WAS ONLY WELL DOWN IN THE REPORT THAT I<br />
READ THAT THIS WAS-BEINLG FINANCED THROUGH AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT AGENCIES THE UNIVERSITIES COMMISSION AND<br />
THE COMMISSION ON ADVANCED EDUCATION IN COOPERATION<br />
WITH THE STATE GOVERNMENT, </p>
<p>LET ME DEAL WITH ANOTHER AREA WHERE SOITH<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS SHOWN HOW THE STATES CAN WORK IN COOPERATION<br />
WITH THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WHERE REAL PROGRESS<br />
IS POSSIBLE AND REAL BENEFITS CAN ACCRUE TO THE PEOPLE.<br />
TWO MONTHS AGO I HAD THE PLEASURE OF OPENING THE FIRST<br />
HOME SITES PROVIDED BY THE SOUTH AUSTRALIAN LAND<br />
COMMISSION AT HAPPY VALLEY, SOUTH AUSTRALIA WAS THE<br />
FIRST STATE TO RESPOND TO THE PROPOSALS MY GOVERNMENT<br />
MADE FOR LAND COMMISSIONS. OTHER STATES HAVE FOLLOWED<br />
SUIT WITH VARYING DEGREES OF ENTHUSIASM BUT IT WAS<br />
SOUTH AUSTRALIA THAT SHOWED THE WAY. IT'S VERY OBVIOUS<br />
WHY THIS COOPERATION ' AS NEEDED IN TACKLING THE<br />
PROBLEM OF LAND PRICES THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
THE NECESSARY FINANCIAL RESOURCES AND THE STATE GOVERNMENTS<br />
HAVE A JURISDICTION IN LAND MATTERS WHICH MY GOVERNMENT<br />
DOES NOT. ' VE HAVE SOUGHT TO BRING TOGETHER FEDERAL<br />
FINANCES AND S-ATE POWERS TO REMOVE THE EVIL<br />
OF SPIRALLING LAND PRICES AND IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA-WE HAVE<br />
SUCCEEDED IN DITNG SO, THE PRICE OF LAND IS THE SINGLE<br />
LARGEST COMPCNENT N THE COST OF A HOME, OUR LAND<br />
COMMISSION PROGRAM OPERATES ON A VERY SIMPLE AND<br />
FUNDAMENTAL PLANNING PRINCIPLE ADEQUATE LAND SUPPLY<br />
IS NECESSARY T3 PREVENT LAND PRICE INCREASES AT TIMES OF<br />
HIGH DEMAND, SOUTH AUSTRALIA HAS COOPERATED IN OUR SCHEME<br />
FROM THE START, BLOCKS OF LAND ARE AVAILABLE FROM THE LAND<br />
COMMISSION FOR ABOUT $ 1,000 LESS THAN COMPARABLE<br />
BLOCKS IN OTHER PARTS OF ADELAIDE, ,1. i' 1 </p>
<p>I DON'T THINK ANYONE WOULD ARGUE THAT RAPID<br />
URBANISATION HAS BROUGHT MANY SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC ILLS<br />
TO OUR CITIES. IT'S BEEN ONE OF THE GREAT POSTWAR<br />
PROBLEMS IN EVERY DEVELOPED COUNTRY BUT ESPECIALLY IN<br />
AUSTRALIA, TRANSPORT, SEWERAGE, LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
SERVICES HAVE BEEN MADE MORE COSTLY AND DIFFICULT.<br />
INDUSTRIES HAVE MET WITH HIGHER COSTS, THE ENVIRONMENT<br />
HAS SUFFERED, AND PREVIOUS GOVERNMENTS IN AUSTRALIA<br />
JUST HAVEN'T COPED WITH THIS PROBLEM. THEY HAVEN'T<br />
STRIED, TTr, DON DUNSTAN'S GOVERNMENT AND MY GOVERNMENT HAVE<br />
INITIATED A SERIES OF POLICIES RELATING TO LAND USE AND<br />
LAND PRICES, THE OBJECTIVE HAS BEEN TO REDUCE THE<br />
CONSEQUENCES OF TOO RAPID URBANISATION. THIS YEAR THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS ALLOCATED APPROXIMATELY<br />
$ 26 MILLION TO THE SOUTH AUSTRALIAN LAND COMMISSION,<br />
BETWEEN ITS EST. ABLISHMENT IN NOVEMBER 1973 AND JUNE 1974, ' 2<br />
IT HAS PURCHASED 1226 HECTARES OF LAND WITHIN THE BOUNDARIES<br />
OF THE ADELAIDE METROPOLITAN AREA. THIS YEAR. IT IS<br />
IMPLEMENTING A FURTHER PROGRAM TO ACQUIRE LAND FOR URBAN<br />
DEVELOPMENT AND OPEN SPACES, THE COMMISSION HAS ENGAGED<br />
THE SERVICES OF PROFESSIONAL CONSULTANTS IN THE FIELDS OF<br />
PLANNING, ENGINEERiNG, SURVEYING AND VALUING, IT'S ALL<br />
PART OF A SCHEMEi TO BRING TOGETHER THE THREE TIERS OF<br />
GOVERNMENT AND INVOLVE LOCAL COMMUNITIES THEMSELVES<br />
IN SOLVING THIS PROBLEM, IT'S A MODEL OF WHAT CAN BE DONE<br />
TO IMPROVE OUR SURROUNDINGS AND MAKE LIFE BETTER FOR<br />
AUSTRALIANS AND THEIR FAMILIES, </p>
<p>DON'T IMAGINE THAT LAND COMMISSIONS ARE ALL<br />
THAT CONCERN US IN THIS FIELD, IN MAKING AUSTRALIA A<br />
BETTER PLACE TO LIVE IN WE ARE JUST AS CONCERNED WITH<br />
RURAL AREAS. THE DEPARTMENT OFr URBAN AND REGIONAL<br />
DEVELOPMENT DEALS AS IMUCH WITH THE WELFARE OF REGIONS<br />
AS IT DOES WITH CITIES, LAST YEAR WE APPROVED THE FIRST<br />
DIRECT GRANTS EVER MADE BY AN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
TO LOCAL COUNCILS GRANTS TOTALLING $ 56 MILLION<br />
THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA, $ 4,7 MILLION IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA.<br />
ALL BUT SEVEN OF THE 136 LOCAL GOVERNMENT BODIES IN THIS<br />
STATE RECEIVED A GRANT,<br />
WE HAVE SAFEGUARDED THE NATIONAL ESTATE, THE UNIQUE<br />
AND BEAUTIFUL THINGS, NATURAL AND MAN-MADE, WORTH KEEPING<br />
IN OUR COUNTRY, IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA WORKS UNDER THE<br />
NATIONAL ESTATE PROGRAM AMOUNTING TO $ 886,000 WERE<br />
APPROVED EARL:' THIS YEAR, I'E ARE PROVIDING ASSISTANCE<br />
FOR ADELAIDE' ;-ATER TREATMENT SCHEME, WE ARE CATCHING<br />
UP FURTHER ! WITH THE SEWERAGE BACKLOG IN ADELAIDE, IN THE<br />
LAST FINANCIAL YEAR THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
PROVIDED $ 5.7 ! ILLION TO SOUTH AUSTRALIA FOR THIS PURPOSE..<br />
WE HAVE GIVEN $ 1 MILLION TO SOUTH AUSTRLIA TO DEVELOP<br />
LEISURE AND RECREATION FACILITIES, WE HAVE UNIQUE PLANS<br />
TO DEVELOP LE PARK IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA AS A MODEL<br />
COMMUNITY, IN; WHICH SCHOOLS, RECREATION AND HEALTH<br />
FACILITIES WILL BE COORDINATED AND PLANNED IN CONSULTATION<br />
WITH THE PEOPLE. WE HAVE ALLOCATED OVER $ 3 MILLION FOR THE<br />
ANGLE PARK PROJECT. I' li ci<br />
.1 L' 1 </p>
<p>OUR URBAN LOCAL ROADS PROGRAM IS DESIGNED TO<br />
IMPROVE THE QUALITY OF RESIDENTIAL STREETS AND WILL<br />
INCLUDE A NUMBER OF INNOVATIONS TO LIFT THE STANDARDS<br />
OF ROADS IN URBAN AND PROVINCIAL CENTRES, THIS<br />
YEAR AND IN THE NEXT TWO YEARS THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
WILL GRANT SOUTH AUSTRALIA A TOTAL OF $ 102.71 MILLION<br />
FOR ROADS OF ALL KINDS. WE ARE GETTING ON WITH OUR<br />
PLANS FOR A NATIONAL HIGHWAYS SYSTEM LINKING ADELAIDE<br />
WITH PERTH, MELBOURNE AND THE NORTHERN TERRITORY.<br />
NO-SERIOUS-EFFORT. WAS MADE BY PREVIOUS AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENTS TO DEVELOP A PROPER NATIONAL ROADS<br />
. NETWORK. lWE ARE THE FIRST GOVERNMENT TO GET ON WITH<br />
THE JOB AND WE'RE DOING IT BY COOPERATION WITH A LABOR<br />
GOVERNMENT IN THIS STATE, IT IS ONE MORE EXAMPLE OF<br />
WHAT WE CAN DO TOGETHER ONE MORE EXAMPLE OF A LABOR<br />
STATE, A LABOR ' SGVERNMENT SHOWING THE WAY. SOUTH<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS COOPERATED IN ALL OUR DISCUSSIONS ON<br />
URBAN ARTERIAL ROADS. IN ADDITION, SOUTH AUSTRALIA HAS<br />
READILY ENTERED INTO AGREEMENT WITH MY GOVERNMENT ON<br />
THE UPGRADING OF ADELAIDE'S PUBLIC TRANSPORT. HERE IN<br />
ADELAIDE YOU HAVE BETTER PUBLIC TRANSPORT THAN MOST STATES,<br />
BUT IT OUGHT TO BE BETTER STILL, IT WILL BE BETTER,<br />
TO DATE, URBAN TRANSPORT PROJECTS IN THIS STATE HAVE<br />
ATTRACTED MORE THAN $ 15 MILLION IN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
ASSISTANCE, </p>
<p>IN THIS CONTEXT I TURN AGAIN TO THE RAILWAYS,<br />
MORE THAN ANY OTHER GOVERNMENT, THE LABOR GOVERNMENT<br />
HAS RECOGNISED THE NEED FOR A NATIONAL APPROACH TO THE<br />
RAILWAYS THE NEED FOR A MODERN, EFFICIENT, NATIONAL<br />
RAILWAY SYSTEM, NO STATE WILL BENEFIT MORE FROM SUCH<br />
A SYSTEM THAN SOUTH AUSTRALIA ITS TRADE, BOTH EAST AND<br />
WEST, WILL BE INVIGORATED AND STREAMLINED, I HAVE<br />
MENTIONED THE TRANSFER OF THE NON-METROPOLITAN SOUTH<br />
AUSTRALIAN RAILWAYS TO THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT, IT<br />
WAS THE FIRST STEP IN THE CREATION OF A NATIONAL<br />
RAIL SYSTEM WORTHY OF A GREAT CONTINENT. THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN ' ATIONAL RAILWAYS, WHICH. WE ARE SETTING UP<br />
UNDER NEW LEGISLATION, WILL HAVE THE ORGANISATIONAL<br />
STRUCTURE AND OPERATIONAL POWERS TO CONSOLIDATE THE<br />
OLD COMMONWEALTH RAILWAYS AND THE STATE RAILWAYS,<br />
INTO A SINGLE SYSTEM, EQUIPPED WITH THE LATEST AND<br />
BEST ROLLING SETCK. E HAVE ALREADY BEGUN WORK ON TWO<br />
IMPORTANT NEW . AIL LINKS IN THIS STATE. Two MONTHS AGO<br />
I ATTENDED THE INUGURATION OF THE TARCOOLA TO ALICE<br />
SPRINGS RAILWAY, THE LARGEST RAILWAY PROJECT IN<br />
AUSTRALIA FCO OVER HALF A CENTURY. THIS YEAR, TOO,<br />
WE HAVE BEGUN 3UILDING THE STANDARD GAUGE RAILWAY<br />
BETWEEN ADELAIDE AND CRYSTAL BROOK, WHICH WILL REMOVE THE<br />
LAST BREAK CF GAUGE BETWEEN THE MAINLAND CAPITALS, r<br />
I. </p>
<p>IN NO OTHER STATES HAS THERE BEEN SUCH A<br />
MAGNIFICENT AND SUSTAINED RECORD OF ACHIEVEMENT, I<br />
COULD EXTEND THIS LIST WITHOUT DIFFICULTY THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT INSURANCE CORPORATION, THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT HOUSING CORPORATION, THE LEGAL AID OFFICE, THE<br />
CHILDREN'S COMMISSION. WE CAN BE PROUD OF OUR RECORD.<br />
IT'S ALL BEEN ACHIEVED UNDER LABOR, IT COULD ONLY BE<br />
ACHIEVED UNDER LABOR, UNDER ANY OTHER GOVERNMENT THESE<br />
THINGS WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN POSSIBLE AND UNDER ANY<br />
OTHER GOVERNMENT THEY WOULD BE CUT BACK OR DISMANTLED,<br />
WE HAVE ALL SEEN THE EVIDENCE OF OPPOSITION<br />
OBSTRUCTION IN THE PARLIAMENT, IN THE NON-LABOR STATES,<br />
IN THE COURTS, IT WAS MADE VERY OBVIOUS I N THEIR<br />
APPROACH TO THE RECENT REDISTRIBUTION AND I KNOW<br />
ELECTORAL REFORM IS A MATTER OF VERY SPECIAL<br />
IMPORTANCE TO T. E PARTY IN THIS STATE. DON DUNSTAN<br />
HAS HAD A L. NGER BATTLE THAN MOST OF US TO GET FAIR<br />
REPRESENTATICO FOR THE PEOPLE, IN THE NATIONAL<br />
PARLIAMENT WE ARE STILL FIGHTING THAT BATTLE. OUR<br />
REDISTRIBUTiON '; AS ACKNOWLEDGED TO BE THE FAIREST EVER<br />
PRESENTED TO PARLIAMENT, IT WAS BASED ON OUR LEGISLATION<br />
TO ESTABLISH ELECTORAL EQUALITY FOR EVERY AUSTRALIAN<br />
WHEREVER HE LIVED, THAT LEGISLATION IWAS PASSED<br />
BY THE JOINT SITTING OF PARLIAMENT LAST YEAR; IT WAS ONE<br />
OF THE PROPOSALS ON WHICH THE DOUBLE DISSOLUTION WAS<br />
GRANTED; IT W: AS SPECIFICALLY ENDORSED BY THE PEOPLE,<br />
YET THE LIBERALS, UNDER PRESSURE FROM THE COUNTRY PARTY,<br />
REJECTED THIS OVERDUE AND NECESSARY REDISTRIBUTION,<br />
THEY REJECTED IT EVEN IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA A STATE WHERE<br />
THE COUNTRY PARTY HAS NO REPRESENTATION IN THE NATIONAL<br />
PARLIAMENT, .. L1.<br />
II -r l! i<br />
II </p>
<p>IASK Y(. U TO REP T ' E Cz4VAIGN OF<br />
OBSTR'JCTION GOEI, ON 8-<br />
i4' E FOUGHT AND DLFEATED<br />
OVER A YEAR AGO, WE CA<br />
THAT OUR MEAURES CAN<br />
TRUE A. ND LAl BENEF<br />
WE CAN POIN-MC' &gt; Ot<br />
SHOW THE Au,--RA'? AN PIF<br />
OTHER STATESE CAN-DOB<br />
BETTER HOSPI-ALS CVEf<br />
TRANSPORT, B,* UTTER PLAV.<br />
OTH~ ER STATES CAP 4AVETiOGETHER,<br />
TFJ GRZT<br />
XCR ; mPORTA,: k7 AND)<br />
7HNit hE-DIFF-IZU63IES VF ~~ K~ AC-C OT . TRJCTION<br />
"! AT 2L . JCTION JUS-t<br />
illS2PFLE blY PROVING<br />
RMS WILl-BRING<br />
0 Vp j-y<br />
iXV e 74K_. " AN<br />
' STV% " A K<br />
FXT ~ iLR. ENT<br />
T7ME TO -It'. NL<br />
i'll ' 1L BE -REtiE. 3' zE . D ANI" Yi. ~ GEN ERA -, O~ ls<br />
jF WE STICK TCI OUR GUV, 51 $ VW5,. AS~ i-l" S<br />
'~'~ INHAND,. AND TAKE ifXP ' F Q PRCGRECS<br />
IAVE ALREADY MADE -TV STAin.<br />
7 NAT7 t4<br />
-11. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
