<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2732</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS STATEMENT NO 1 - 6 DECEMBER 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002732.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT NO. 1<br />
6 December, 1972<br />
Immediately upon the return of the Labor Government,<br />
Senator Lionel Murphy, set out to arrange for the release<br />
of seven young men serving eighteen-month gaol sentences under<br />
the National Service Act.<br />
Last night, I signed letters to the Governor-General,<br />
Sir Paul Hasluck, recommending remission of the sentences.<br />
In my letters, I said:<br />
" The effect of these decisions is that all<br />
obligations to render national service will cease and that<br />
there will be no further court proceedings against those who<br />
opposed the scheme. In the recent elections, it was a part<br />
of my party's election programme that this action would be<br />
taken and that a recommendation would be made that Your<br />
Excellency exercise the prerogative to bring about the<br />
release from custody of those offenders against the National<br />
Ser-v. ic Act who are still in custody. It may be assumed that<br />
this was endorsed by the electors and that Your<br />
Excellency's Government has a mandate to take these steps.<br />
The decision havin--been taken not to proceed with pending<br />
prosecutions, it veld not be just to keep in custody those<br />
now serv-ing pris o sentences for offences under the National<br />
Service Act." This mornng the Governor-General exercised the<br />
prerogative of mercy to release the men on my recommendation.<br />
Arrangements have now been made with prison<br />
authorities in the States for the immediate release of the<br />
sevenmen r-hrre. were serving sentences in Victoria, two in<br />
Nevy-out^ i', one in South Australia and one in Western<br />
tralia. The seven are Michael John Payne, Ian Robert Turner,<br />
i chael . h'ristonher Matteson, Michael Kocan, Robert Geoffrey<br />
Scates, Kenneth Joseph McLelland and Robert William Martin.<br />
I firmly believe that this historic decision marks'<br />
the end of peace-time conscription in Australia for all time. </p>
<p>ATTACHMENT TO PRESS STATEMENT NO. 1<br />
6 December, 1972<br />
The men who will be released from goal today, the names<br />
of the gaols where they have been held and the dates on which<br />
they were imprisoned are as follows:<br />
NEW SOUTH WALES<br />
Michael KOCAN, Mannis Afforestation Camp, 27 April 1972;<br />
Michael Christopher MATTESON, Long Bay, 9 November 1972;<br />
VICTORIA Kenneth Joseph McLELLAND, Pentridge, 8 March 1972;<br />
Ian Robert TURNER, Ararat, 21 January 1972;<br />
Robert Geoffrey SCATES, Pentridge, 26 April 1972;<br />
SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
Robert William LARTIN, Cadell Training Camp, Renmark, 25 February 1972;<br />
WESTERN AUSTRALI<br />
Michael John PAYNE, Kames Training Centre, Serpentine, 23 October 1972.<br />
i. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
