<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3748</transcript-id>
    <title>PENSION BENEFITS - 23 MAY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/05/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003748.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Z. I U Th<br />
Press Statement<br />
j w~ 23 May 1975<br />
The Prime Minister and member for Werriwa, Mr Gough<br />
Whitlam has reminded pensioners that they can soon<br />
expect lump sumR payments of pension benefit/ increases<br />
backdated to I May. The pension increases had been<br />
del. ayed by Opposition tactics in -the Senate, and<br />
reflected the low priority the Opposition parties gave<br />
to social welfare payments.<br />
" The standard rate of pension for aged persons,<br />
invalids, widows and supporting mothers has risen by<br />
a week. to $ 36 a week," Mr Whitlam said. " The rate<br />
for a married couple has been increased by $ 8.50 a week<br />
to $ 60 a week," he added. Additional payments f or<br />
children of pensioners and other beneficiaries have also<br />
been increased by $ 1.50 to $ 7 a week for each child.<br />
" Most importantly, this latest legislation has*<br />
kept the Australian Government's promise to abolish<br />
the means test for people aged between 70 and 74 years,"<br />
Mr Whi-tlam said. This meant that an estimated 56,000<br />
people in that age group who were previousl~ y ineligible<br />
for pensions under the means test were ncw entitled to<br />
draw pensions. Mr Whitlam urged people to apply to the<br />
nearest office of the Department of Social Security if they<br />
thought they were now entitled to a pension. Ile stressed<br />
that this was especially important for first-time pensioners.<br />
The full pension will also be paid to about 43,000<br />
aged between 70 and 74 who had only been getting partpensions<br />
because of -the means -test. Mr Whitlan said the<br />
full pension payments would be backdated to 1 May.<br />
However, Mr Whitlam pointed out that guardians<br />
allowances, additional payments for children and supplementary<br />
assistance would remain payable subject to existing means tests.<br />
In addition, " fringe benefits" such as entitlement to a<br />
Pensioner Medical Service card would also remain subject -to<br />
a means test.<br />
Mr. Whitlam explained that widows and supporting mothers<br />
would receive a special cheque about June 4, covering the arrears<br />
back. to the May 6 payment date. They will receive benefit at<br />
the new rate of $ 36 a week in their normal cheque on June 17. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Old ago and invalid pensioners will receive a single<br />
cheque on June 12, covering the fortnight's payment at the<br />
new rate and lump sum payment backdated to May 1.<br />
Mr. Whitlam. said he was proud that since the Australian<br />
Labor Government had been elected in 1972, the standard rate<br />
of pension had been increasad by 80% and the combined married<br />
rate by nearly 74%. Costs generally had risen only 31 .6%<br />
in that time so it meant that pensioners had more real purchasing<br />
power now. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
