<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5733</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENT OF GOVERNOR-GENERAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/01/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005733.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 13 JANUARY 1982<br />
APPOINTMENT OF GOVERNOR-GENERAL<br />
It has been announced from Buckingham Palace<br />
that The Queen, on the recommendation of Her Australian<br />
Prime Minister, has approved the appointment of The Right<br />
Honourab~ le Sir Ninian Stephen, KBE, QC, as Governor-General<br />
of Australia to succeed His Excellency The Right Honourable<br />
Sir Zelman Cowen, AK, GCMG, GCVO, KStJ, QC, whose<br />
resignation will take effect from late in July 1982.<br />
I warmly welcome Her Majesty's appointment of<br />
Sir Ninian Stephen as Governor-General to succeed<br />
Sir Zelman Cowen. Sir Ninian has had a distinguished<br />
career in the law in Australia and is at present a<br />
Justice of the High Court of Australia.<br />
Sir Ninian will be sworn as Governor-General in<br />
late July 1982, on a date to be determined.<br />
Sir Ninian came to Australia from Britain in<br />
1940. He completed his education in Australia and served<br />
for five years in the Australian Military Forces. Since<br />
then he has pursued a career in the law, being appointed<br />
Queen's Counsel in 1967, a Judge of the Supreme Court of<br />
Victoria in 1970 and a Justice of the High Court in 1972.<br />
He has for many years been a Member of the<br />
Council of International House in the University of<br />
Melbourne and is Deputy Chancellor of that University.<br />
Sir Ninian and Lady Stephen have a family of<br />
five daughters; Mary, Ann, Sarah, Jane and Elizabeth.<br />
Lady Stephen has over many years held voluntary<br />
positions in organisations concerned with the welfare of<br />
mothers and children, students and the Arts. She is<br />
presently a Member of the Interim Council of the Museum of<br />
Australia, a Member of the Board of the Melbourne Theatre<br />
Company and a Member of the Council of Lauristo-n Girls<br />
Scho6l, Melbourne. On behalf of the Government and people of Australia,<br />
I extend very sincere congratulations to Sir Ninian and to<br />
Lady Stephen.<br />
C anb err a </p>
<p>BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL<br />
The Right Honourable Sir Ninian Stephen<br />
Born 15 June 1923 at Nettlebed, near Oxford, United<br />
Kingdom, to Frederick and Barbara Stephen; only child.<br />
Educated: Edinburgh Academy; St Paul's School, London;<br />
Chillon College, Glion, Switzerland; Scotch College,<br />
Melbourne. Arrived in Australia early 1940.<br />
1941: Commenced Law, Melbourne University, while an<br />
articled clerk with Arthur Robinson Co., Solicitors,<br />
Melbourne. 1941-46: Served with the Australian Military Forces in<br />
the Pacific and was discharged with the rank of Lieutenant<br />
in 1946.<br />
1946-49: Continued legal studies, graduating LLB ( Melbourne)<br />
and completed professional qualifications.<br />
1950-51: Practised as a solicitor with Arthur Robinson<br />
Co., after admission as a Barrister and Solicitor of the<br />
Supreme Court of Victoria in 1949.<br />
1951: Commenced practice at the Victorian Bar.<br />
1967: Appointed Queen's Counsel.<br />
1970: Appointed Judge of the Victorian Supreme Court.<br />
1972: Appointed Justice of the High Court.<br />
1979: Appointed as a member of the Judicial Committee<br />
of the Privy Council.<br />
Married to Valery Mary Stephen 4 June 1949: five daughters;<br />
Mary, Ann, Sarah, Jane and Elizabeth. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
