<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11449</transcript-id>
    <title>9 June 1999                                                  TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS AT OPENING OF SARA LEE EXHIBITION                 NATIONAL GALLERY OF AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/06/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, thank you very much Kerry Stokes. To Dr and Mrs Kennedy, to</p>
<p> Mr and Mrs Murphy, to Sir Arvi and Lady Parbo, to my ministerial colleagues,</p>
<p> Richard Alston and Peter McGauran, Kate Carnell the Chief Minister</p>
<p> of the Australian Capital Territory, other distinguished guests, ladies</p>
<p> and gentlemen.</p>
<p>Tonight is really important for two reasons. It's the opening of a</p>
<p> wonderful exhibition and the huge crowd that is gathered here tonight</p>
<p> is testament to what a remarkable exhibition it is and also for the</p>
<p> tremendous support and affection that the National Gallery enjoys</p>
<p> in the life of Canberra and in the cultural life of our nation.</p>
<p>But it's also an occasion to honour a remarkable act of philanthropy</p>
<p> because what the Sara Lee Corporation is doing to mark and honour</p>
<p> the millennium is about as imaginative and as a self-sacrificing act</p>
<p> of cultural philanthropy that any company could possibly undertake.</p>
<p> In an age when there is plenty of cynicism about the behaviour of</p>
<p> corporations, much of it unjustified, at a time when it's easy to</p>
<p> take pot shots at manifestations of capitalism it really is very refreshing</p>
<p> and encouraging to be able on an occasion like this to a very, in</p>
<p> a very wholehearted and unreserved way to express our respect and</p>
<p> our admiration for what the Sara Lee Corporation is doing. And the</p>
<p> fact that we at the end of the process that we are going to be a very</p>
<p> important part and the recipient of one of the items in this remarkable</p>
<p> collection adds to our sense of connection and our sense of pleasure.</p>
<p>And to you Mr and Mrs Murphy, in particular, who have come here as</p>
<p> the representatives of the company for tonight, can I express on behalf</p>
<p> I know of all the friends and supporters of the Gallery and all of</p>
<p> the art lovers of Australia, how much we respect your company for</p>
<p> what it has done. And how much we thank you for the item that the</p>
<p> Gallery will receive from the collection and also to honour the generosity</p>
<p> and farsightedness of the Sara Lee Corporation.</p>
<p>This is a remarkable exhibition and over the next two months or more</p>
<p> tens of thousands of Australians will have an opportunity of viewing</p>
<p> it. And to appreciate in a personal way the generosity of the millennium</p>
<p> gift of the company. I think this is also an occasion, of course,</p>
<p> to celebrate the ongoing success, the continued and growing success</p>
<p> of the Gallery under the Chairmanship of Mr Stokes and also under</p>
<p> the Directorship of Dr Kennedy. I was present at the opening in 1982</p>
<p> and it is for that reason Janette reminded me before I got up and</p>
<p> said: you remember how long the speeches were on that occasion. And</p>
<p> I do indeed. So I simply want to conclude by saying one or two important</p>
<p> things about the example that I think this gift by Sara Lee is setting</p>
<p> to those who would aspire to greater corporate philanthropy here in</p>
<p> Australia.</p>
<p>The Americans can teach us a lot about corporate philanthropy. Many</p>
<p> of us have understood that for a very long period of time and so much</p>
<p> of the cultural and artistic treasure of the United States is a result</p>
<p> of that rich tradition of corporate philanthropy. And that is one</p>
<p> of the reasons why a few months ago a number of us in the Government,</p>
<p> Richard Alston and myself, and aided and encouraged by people like</p>
<p> David Gonski and others sat down and worked out how we might as a</p>
<p> Government give more incentive and more stimulus to corporations to</p>
<p> embrace the traditions of philanthropy of other countries. And as</p>
<p> a consequence of that I made some announcements which I hope will</p>
<p> represent very important taxation incentives both to individuals and</p>
<p> also to companies to make gifts of art collections, of items of art</p>
<p> and generally to move down the path towards greater philanthropy.</p>
<p>In our nation as we move forward we have a lot of challenges and there</p>
<p> are a lot of things we want to do and in reality there's no simple</p>
<p> way of saying well, all of it can be done by the Government, all of</p>
<p> it can be done by the business sector, all of it can be done by individuals,</p>
<p> all of it can be done by charitable agencies. What we really need</p>
<p> is to get all of them together to build what I often call a social</p>
<p> coalition. And the way you build a social coalition, of course, is</p>
<p> for the Government to take a lead and for the Government to remain</p>
<p> in the case of the arts a strong and consistent supporter of the arts.</p>
<p> And I think it is fair to say in this country we have developed a</p>
<p> pretty bipartisan tradition of supporting the arts in this country.</p>
<p> And a lot of people have made a contribution to this Gallery. It's</p>
<p> construction of it was commenced during the period of the Whitlam</p>
<p> Government, it was opened in a Fraser Government and I know during</p>
<p> the time of the Gorton Government the concept of a national gallery</p>
<p> was very much in the minds of the members of that Government.</p>
<p>So it's very much a commitment from the Government level. We have</p>
<p> a growing number of people who are demonstrating all around the world</p>
<p> the rich artistic talent of this country. We need to encourage the</p>
<p> business community more, many have been generous without tax deductions</p>
<p> and without tax encouragement. And I record my appreciation on behalf</p>
<p> of you all for that great generosity.</p>
<p>But as a result of these changes which will encourage greater corporate</p>
<p> philanthropy I believe that we can enter a new era and we can begin</p>
<p> to build in this country some of the pattern of corporate giving to</p>
<p> the arts and corporate philanthropy, which has been taken for granted</p>
<p> for decades in the United States.</p>
<p>Sara Lee has demonstrated to us how it can be done at its pinnacle</p>
<p> and at its best. And it is a wonderful millennium gift to the art</p>
<p> lovers of the world. We are honoured to have the exhibition here.</p>
<p> We thank the company for what it is doing, we thank the company for</p>
<p> the gift that it will make after July of next year to this Gallery</p>
<p> and it will be a permanent reminder to all who come here of the greater</p>
<p> generosity of the Sara Lee Corporation.</p>
<p>I therefore have very great pleasure, ladies and gentlemen, in declaring</p>
<p> the exhibition open. I wish it well, it will be a resounding success</p>
<p> and it is yet another demonstration of the great relevance and the</p>
<p> great inspiration of the National Gallery of Australia to the cultural</p>
<p> life of our nation. Thank you.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
