<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4719</transcript-id>
    <title>SIR ROBERT MENZIES MEMORIAL TRUST, 23 MAY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/05/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004719.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4JAUS RL IA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 23 MAY 1978<br />
SIR ROBERT MENZIES MEMORIAL TRUST<br />
The question has arisen as to the way in which, as a nation,<br />
we might best mark and commemorate, now and for posterity,<br />
the great contribution of the late Sir Robert Gordon Menzies<br />
to the nation.<br />
There has already been enthusiastic and helpful discussion on<br />
this by some public figures and by some newspapers, and I am<br />
indebted to them.<br />
A preparatory Committee has already begun work, directed to the<br />
creation of a special appeal and fund to be known as the<br />
Sir Robert Menzies Trust and I am happy to announce to the<br />
House the general direction and scope of the arrangements that<br />
are in mind.<br />
The Appeal will be established on an Australia-wide basis and<br />
the funds resulting will be applied to objectives of a practical<br />
and continuing kind within the particular interests of<br />
Sir Robert Menzies. He had no static view of Australia and he<br />
would wish, as those who contibute will, that the funds should<br />
be spent in terms of future benefit to Australia.<br />
The objectives are still to be finally determined but it can be<br />
said already that the fund will be desianed to assist<br />
Australians of all ages but especially the young, to obtain in<br />
serious and worthwhile directions, academic training or practical<br />
experience or opportunities to compete which they might otherwise<br />
be unable to obtain.<br />
Some of the particular interests identified with Sir Robert<br />
Menzies and which might therefore be drawn within the purposes<br />
of the fund are the law, with particular reference to<br />
constitutional matters and Federal/ State relationships.; studies<br />
concerned with Austrlaia ' s role within the British Commonwealth<br />
and with Australia/ Britain relations; studies of Australia and<br />
the United States; studies of relations between Australia and<br />
the Pacific N~ ations.<br />
Another possibility which would have been of interest to<br />
Sir Robert Menzies and from which major benefit would accrue is<br />
to bring to Australia, for public meetings or special consultations,<br />
speakers of distinction or young persons of promise and interest<br />
to us. </p>
<p>And there are two other matters at least, one is the development<br />
of skills in the use of the English language, since we all know<br />
he loved the English tongue. The other is sport of many kinds<br />
because as he watched it and took interest, it gave him a<br />
particular and agreeable relaxation and companionship.<br />
Although much more discussion will be needed, I am able to<br />
say now that the Appeal and the fund will be under the<br />
authority of a National Comittee and a series of State<br />
Committees. It is my honour to have been asked to accept the office<br />
of National President. Leading Australians will be invited<br />
to accept office with me in connection with the Trust. It will<br />
be necessary, in addition,. to have a strong and operative<br />
executive National Committe-e and a series of State executive<br />
committees. I am pleased to announce that Sir William Vines has accepted office<br />
as Head of the National Committee with the title of National<br />
General Chairman. Sir William Vines has a high record of<br />
achievement in Australian commercial and agricultural<br />
communities and of service to Government, both Commonwealth and<br />
State, involving all political parties over a long period. He<br />
will be assisted as Deputy National General Chairman by<br />
Sir Walter Leonard.<br />
The other members of the Executive Committee will be similarly<br />
distinguished people, representative of the States as well as the<br />
Commonwealth, and, it is hoped, form a variety of callings and<br />
backgrounds. To assist this Committee, a distinguished public<br />
servant and close confidant of Sir Robert's for many years-<br />
Sir John Bunting will be co-ordinator.<br />
Sir Robert Menzies was the Leader of one political party.<br />
But he was, at the same time, a representative and a Leader<br />
of all the people. He sought to serve the whole communityas<br />
the fund now in mind will do and in fact must do. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
