<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6339</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THIRD AUSTRALIA-JAPAN BILATERIAL CONFERENCE OF EDITORS AND PUBLISHERS, 8 MARCH 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006339.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED AGAINST<br />
DELIVERY CHE3CK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THIRD AUSTRALIA-JAPAN BILATERAL CONFERENCE<br />
OF EDITORS AND PUBLISHERS 8 MARCH 1984<br />
Mr Chairman, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
It gives me great pleasure to be here with you this morning<br />
to open the third Australia-Japan Bilateral Conference of<br />
Editors and Publishers.<br />
To have in Australia so many leading representatives of the<br />
Japanese media is a very real plus for both our countries.<br />
You, individually and collectively, have an important role<br />
to play in contributing to the further development, of the<br />
Australia-Japan relationship.<br />
The media, editors, publishers, and writers today make a<br />
major contribution to shaping the views of the general.<br />
public and their perceptions of the relationship between<br />
nations. You have all now seen something of our country and our<br />
society and met with many prominent Australians.<br />
You will obviously draw your own conclusions.<br />
On one thing I am sure you will agree relations between<br />
our two countries are as close now as they have ever been.<br />
There is a very real warmth of feeling between our<br />
countries. My own recent visit to Japan brought home to me how close<br />
and how important our countries have become to each other.<br />
Indeed that visit was significant in anotbher sense: it laid<br />
the basis for a revitalization of the relationship between<br />
our countries new directions and new emphases appropriate<br />
to the chanqing national and international circumstances of<br />
our countries were mapped out ar1ffgiven substance.<br />
There is without doubt substantial goodwill in Japan<br />
particularly at the highest political level towards<br />
Australia. if W </p>
<p>This was also apparent in the attitudes of the leaders of<br />
industry and of Japan's financial community whom I met<br />
during my recent visit.<br />
I can assure you the same goodwill exists towards Japan<br />
among Australian Government and business leaders indeed it<br />
is something which now extends deep into the Australian<br />
community. I know you would all have recognised and<br />
appreciated this during your current visit.<br />
Australia and Japan have substantial and shared interests in<br />
the trade and economic fields.<br />
The interdependence between our countries is widely<br />
recognised it stems directly from the complementary<br />
character of our two economies. The stability and quality<br />
of the economic relationship has contributed directly to the<br />
close political relationship that has grown up between our<br />
countries. That relationship hinges on mutual trust and an<br />
awareness of the importance of each of our countries to the<br />
other. It is against this background that the Joint Statement<br />
issued following my discussions with Prime Minister Nakasone<br />
assumes a particular significance.<br />
In that statement both Prime Minister Nakasone and I<br />
reaffirmed the immense importance to both our countries of<br />
our bilateral relationship. We reaffirmed our common<br />
commitment to the ideals of freedom and democracy and the<br />
commitment of both our countries to further strengthening<br />
our co-operation with other countries in the region to<br />
ensure peace, stability and prosperity.<br />
Both Prime Minister Nakasone and I were in particularly<br />
strong agreement on the need for liberalisation of<br />
international trade. I was strongly supportive of Prime<br />
Minister Nakasone' s call for a new round of multilateral<br />
trade negotiations. Prime Minister Nakasone in turn<br />
endorsed my 22 November 1983 Bangkok call to countries of<br />
the region to work together to secure. generally agreed<br />
objectives in such negotiations.<br />
I am pleased to say my Bangkok initiative is now being<br />
translated into concrete action with a meeting of senior<br />
officials likely to take place in an Asean country in early<br />
May to address the issues involved.<br />
This meeting is a crucial step, providing as it will an<br />
opportunity for countries of thel~% gion very deliberately<br />
and methodically to identify their concrete interests in a<br />
multilateral round and to consider how best to secure<br />
attention to those interests. The long-term benefits to the<br />
region of this workman-like, co-operative approach will I<br />
believe be very considerable. </p>
<p>The assurance given me by Prime Minister Nakasone that Japan<br />
would not solve its trading problems with third countries at<br />
the expense of Australia-Japan trade is of critical<br />
significance to a number of Australian trading interests. I<br />
recognise the considerable pressure being applied by some<br />
others for major trading concessions by Japan. The<br />
assurance given by Prime Minister Nakasone and reiterated<br />
by him in a telephone discussion we have had following my<br />
return to Australia represents, however, a recognition<br />
both of the enduring qualities of Australia as a reliable<br />
and competitive supplier and the dangers posed to orderly<br />
international trading arrangements of any surrender to<br />
bilateralism. Trading arrangements struck on the basis of<br />
anything other than the competitive edge of suppliers are<br />
inherently fragile and destructive of good relations between<br />
countries. These principles find immediate application in the talks<br />
between Australian and Japanese officials about Australian<br />
access to the Japanese beef market in 1984/ 85 and beyond.<br />
Australia is naturally concerned to maintain its position in<br />
the Japanese beef market. Indeed Australia should like to<br />
see Japan be somewhat more forthcoming on these negotiations<br />
than they have been to date. As a reliable and competitive<br />
supplier I believe Australia can expect to sustain its<br />
position and see continued growth in its beef exports to<br />
Japan. This is not to say that there is no scope for change in the<br />
pattern of Australia's trade with Japan. Indeed one of the<br />
dominant themes of my recent visit to Japan was an<br />
acknowledgement of the need to diversify Australian trading<br />
interests in Japan to broaden the basis of our trading<br />
relationship.<br />
The face of Japanese industry is changing and with it<br />
Japanese industries' resource requirements. The adjustment<br />
of Japan to a lower long-term GDP growth path also imposes a<br />
need to review established assumptions about traditional<br />
trading patterns with Japan.<br />
The Australian Government, and I believe many of our<br />
exporters, recognise this and are % oving to make the<br />
necessary adjustments.<br />
Action is already underway to develop newwmarkets for<br />
Australian products in Japan. Japanese consultants have<br />
already been engaged by the Australian Department of Trade<br />
to assist in the identification of areas where Australia<br />
should be targeting its marketing-qffort in the future. We<br />
recognise that Japan is a specialised market with problems<br />
of trade penetration quite different from those in other<br />
traditional Australian overseas market. </p>
<p>Already, we see prospects in Japan for increased Australian<br />
exports of manufacturing goods, services and processed<br />
foodstuffs.<br />
We also aim to take full advantage of Japan's import<br />
expansion scheme. With this in mind Australia will this<br />
year be sending a senior trade mission to Japan. We expect<br />
as well a Japanese import expansion mission similar to those<br />
that have gone to the United States and EC to come to<br />
Australia. There is then considerable momentum in the efforts now<br />
underway to expand and diversify Australia's trade links<br />
with Japan.<br />
The trading relationship will be further enriched by changes<br />
now taking place in Australia's own economic situation.<br />
Economic recovery is now well underway here in Australia.<br />
Real Australian GDP is now expected to grow by 8 per cent<br />
this financial year. Inflation has dropped from over 11 per<br />
cent to 8.6 per cent and will fall further; employment is<br />
growing and unemployment has fallen to 9.5 per cent.<br />
Critical to this recovery has been the Prices and Incomes<br />
Accord agreed between my Government and the Australian Trade<br />
Union movement. Adherence to the Accord by all parties<br />
gives confidence of restraint in wage demands and underpins<br />
a more orderly pattern of Australian industrial relations.<br />
Indeed in the 12 months period to November 1982 the number<br />
of days lost due to industrial disputes dropped by over<br />
per cent and was at the lowest level for 15 years. This<br />
trend can only serve to reassure Australia's trading<br />
partners of her reliability as a supplier.<br />
With economic recovery and with the quite deliberate<br />
attention the Australian Government is giving to securing<br />
conditions conducive to medium and longer-term growth you<br />
can also expect to see a healthy measure of industrial<br />
restructuring taking place here in Australia.<br />
Already my Government has put into place a steel industry<br />
assistance plan which has assured the survival of the steel<br />
industry as a viable, efficient and critically important<br />
Australian industry. In the process we have put in place<br />
arrangements designed to sustain employmeat within the<br />
industry and ensure its long-term competitiveness. This was<br />
achieved through the combined efforts of Government, unions<br />
and the industry itself. Government provided constructive<br />
assistance, industry the needed TMTVestment and unions<br />
productivity guarantees.<br />
Both the objectives and approach adopted in this case stand<br />
as precedent for the manner in which the Government is<br />
addressing the problems of the Australian motor vehicle<br />
industry. </p>
<p>Our own experience in this area served as useful background<br />
to the discussions I had in Japan about Japanese experience<br />
in industry restructuring. Those discussions were a<br />
particularly valuable feature of my recent visit to Japan.<br />
An especially stimulating account of Japanese experience was<br />
given me by Mr Amaya, formerly Vice Minister for<br />
International Trade and Industry. I am pleased that he has<br />
been able to accept our invitation to visit Australia,<br />
probably next month, to discuss further Japanese experience<br />
in the handling of issues involved in restructuring.<br />
For Australians the inevitability of gradual change in our<br />
industry structures poses the particular challenge of<br />
anticipating that change rather than merely reacting to it.<br />
It will be individual firms which will take the crucial<br />
decisions upon which Australia's competitive edge will<br />
hinge; it is not for Government to get into the business of<br />
picking " winners" and " losers"<br />
But Government can provide a framework, can define more<br />
precisely the context within which industrial change will<br />
occur. Already work has been set in train through the<br />
Economic Planning Advisory Council ( EPAC) to establish the<br />
necessary data base on macroeconomic and industry trends. I<br />
have also formed a committee of Cabinet Ministers under the<br />
chairmanship of the Minister for Industry and Commerce,<br />
Senator Button, to consider what policy instruments need to<br />
be developed and to see that required integration of the<br />
diverse policy elements education, trade, industry, and<br />
finance takes place.<br />
I believe there is a role, and an important one, in this<br />
area for the Australian media. Let me comment on this point<br />
more generally.<br />
I was struck in Japan by the extent to which the media is<br />
accepted as an integral even if at times highly critical<br />
part of the process of developing community understanding of<br />
policy issues.<br />
I have long thought the media has a vital role to play in<br />
ensuring public awareness of the issues involved in<br />
Government policy. Particularly wh~ re change is involved,<br />
it will only be managed satisfactorily if underlying<br />
community attitudes and assumptions shift to meet it. This<br />
presumes understanding both of the consequences of change<br />
and of the costs likely to be associated with failure to<br />
meet it.<br />
This is not to suggest that the m~ ia adopt the role of<br />
apologist. Rather it is an invitation to a more analytical,<br />
more involved approach from the media. </p>
<p>A far more intimate relationship exists in Japan between<br />
Government policy makers and the media than i the case here<br />
in Australia. Tn part this reflects different institutional<br />
traditions traditions I am certain we cannot and should<br />
not try to emulate here in Australia. But as a well<br />
developed system of access to the decision-making process<br />
and of responsibility in the handling of this access, the<br />
Japanese pattern makes for both a healthy openness in<br />
Government and for greater community awareness of the basis<br />
or background to options for decision.<br />
This of course does not guarantee immunity from criticism<br />
n" orr oosth-obuilndd iintg." , Tdhoiess phroowceevsesr, heclapll enda rrion w Jadpiafnf er" ennecmeasw asahnid" or<br />
contributes to the building of a national consensus on<br />
matters of long-term significance.<br />
Crucial to this process is public access something my<br />
Government has appreciated from the outset.<br />
Indeed the Australian Labor Government has been more open<br />
than any before it. Whether in economic policy, foreign<br />
policy, industry policy, education policy, or welfare policy<br />
to name but a few areas we have laid out our assumptions<br />
and proposals and invited community response before<br />
definitively locking policy decisions into place.<br />
The role the media can play in exposing these assumptions<br />
and in communicating what is proposed is critically<br />
important. It is also a heavy responsibility one I am<br />
sure none of you would underestimate.<br />
But, Mr Chairman, understanding between nations hinges on<br />
more than this.<br />
Cross-cultural links and exchanges between our peoples are a<br />
particularly effective method of strengthening relations.<br />
In the case of Japan and Australia, working holiday schemes<br />
and personal initiatives have seen substantial numbers of<br />
our young people, including my own daugher, go to each<br />
other's country with lasting benefits in terms of a<br />
greater understanding of our diffeifent cultures. A frequent<br />
exchange of visits by parliamentary delegations,<br />
journalists, trade union leaders and other special overseas<br />
visitors also ensures that the depth of contact between our<br />
two nations increases each year.<br />
Evidence of the importance of these visit schemes was the<br />
fact that most of the leaders I r~ rt while on my recent visit<br />
to Japan had visited Australia during the past decade or so.<br />
There is, however, as both Prime Minister Nakasone and I<br />
agreed, scope for development of still closer political<br />
relations between Australia and Japan. </p>
<p>7.<br />
Prime Minister Nakasone and I have established a " hot line"<br />
between us. Beyond this we also intend significantly to<br />
extend the range of contact and consultations between our<br />
Governments on matters of common political interest. This<br />
will be the case on particular crises whether regional or<br />
global as they arise, as well as on matters of broader<br />
policy interest such as disarmament.<br />
Indeed on disarmament I was impressed by the degree or<br />
coincidence between Australia's and Japan's views. Both our<br />
countries attach great importance to securing progress in<br />
arms control and disarmament negotiations and will be<br />
co-operating in our efforts to find ways of reducing<br />
existing nuclear arsenals and limiting the horizontal<br />
proliferation of nuclear weapons.<br />
The United Nations and other relevant multilateral fora will.<br />
be the obvious place to focus this collaborative effort.<br />
Indeed in those fora I should expect the pattern of<br />
consultation to extend beyond disarmament issues alone into<br />
a wide spectrum of issues of mutual interest. We are, after<br />
all, both countries sharing a deep concern and involvement<br />
with the interests of the Asia/ Pacific region. As such<br />
there is a natural basis for co--operative endeavour a<br />
. basis which should advantage not only Japan and Australia<br />
but also be of benefit to all countries within the region.<br />
Even where differences exist, we have been able to discuss<br />
them constructively. On the matter of the dumping of.<br />
nuclear waste in the Pacific, for example, Prime Minister<br />
Nakasone and I discussed frankly Japan's concerns regarding<br />
safe disposal of waste from its nuclear industry. I made<br />
clear Australia's and the South pacific region's strong<br />
concern about the proposals for ocean dumping, welcoming at<br />
the same time indicatio ' ns that the Japanese were exploring<br />
other possibilities for disposal. Australia certainly hopes<br />
that land-based nuclear waste disposal methods continue to<br />
be pursued.<br />
Mr Chairman<br />
It will be obvious from what I havd said that between<br />
Australia and Japan today there is a rich and diverse<br />
relationship.<br />
Neither country can afford to be complacent about the<br />
relationship; but if my recent visit is any guide, I think<br />
we can be confident that all concerned are working together,<br />
both here in Australia and in Ja M to consolidate and<br />
extend the already strong bonds which exist between us.<br />
This is as it should be and augers well for the future<br />
prosperity of both our countries. </p>
<p>8.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen, I wish you every success with vour<br />
conference, and our Japanese visitors a memorable stay in<br />
Australia. It gives me much pleasure to declare this Conference open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
