<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4253</transcript-id>
    <title>IVOR GREENWOOD</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/10/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004253.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 13 OCTOBER, 1976.<br />
IVOR GREENWOOD<br />
Mr Speaker: It is with great sadness that I inform the House<br />
that Ivor Greenwood, Senator for Victoria, died this morning.<br />
Ivor Greenwood's death is a tragedy that has made a heavy impact<br />
on all Members of this Parliament. Ivor Greenwood was a man of<br />
very great ability, at the height of his powers, with a major<br />
contribution to make to his country.<br />
I know that I speak for all Members of this House when I express<br />
our deepest sympat'-hy to his family to his wife and children.<br />
These last mon-ths have been a terrible period for them all, and<br />
they have our deepest regrets.<br />
All of us who knew Ivor Greenwood respected him as a man of integrity<br />
and high principle a man who sought unswervingly to do what<br />
he believed to be right. He could always be relied upon to state<br />
his views strongly and openly. Hie was a most valuable contributor<br />
to debates in the Cabinet.<br />
Ivor Greenwood was a man of courage. Even if some view he adopted<br />
was unpopular, he refused to be deflected from his stand if he<br />
believed an important point of principle was involved. Throughout<br />
his life, Ivor Greenwood pursued all his interests with intensity<br />
and purpose.<br />
Ivor Greenwood was born in Melbourne in 1926. His early schooling<br />
was at Hartwell State School and Mont Albert Central. He won a<br />
scholarship to Scotch College for the last four years of his.<br />
secondary education. Later, at Melbourne University he combined a<br />
study of Law with an active interest in politics.<br />
Perceptive in politics from an early age, he joined the Liberal Club<br />
and became its President in 1947, at the age of 21. Two years-later<br />
he became President of the University's Students Representative Council.<br />
His career in the Law was a distinguished one. He first became<br />
Associate to Sir Frank Kitto on the Highi Court, and later to<br />
Sir Owen Dixon. He was admitted to the Victorian Bar in 1951.<br />
From then on, he pursued his two interests, the Law and politics,<br />
with significant achievement in both. The year after his admission<br />
to the Bar he became a member of the Victorian Liberal Executive,<br />
serving there from 1952 to 1966, when he became Vice President<br />
of the Liberal Party in Victoria. .2/<br />
Jj 11 S T It A 1. 1 A, Pr </p>
<p>2.<br />
While his legal career progres. 3ed principally in equity<br />
and commnercial cases he entered vigorously into the<br />
affairs of the profession, becoming secretary to the Law<br />
Gountil of Australia, a position he held from 1963 to 1968.<br />
In 1969 he took the silk.<br />
Ivor Greenwood always had a genuine interest in helping<br />
younger members of the Liberal Party to improve their<br />
understanding of, and effectiveness in, politics. I<br />
know his interest was greatly appreciate by them.<br />
Ivor Greenwood entered the Senate in 1968 and was elected<br />
and re-elected in 1969, 1970, 1974 and 1975.<br />
His great ability was rapidly recognised and he became<br />
Minister for Health in 1971, and then Attorney Ge: neral<br />
in .1971/ 72.<br />
During the Liberal Party's period in Opposition, 1972/ 75,<br />
Ivor Greenwood was one of those who worked hard to equip<br />
the Party with the policies it needed to return to Government.<br />
He became Deputy Leader of the Opposition in the Senate<br />
in 1972.<br />
After the Liberal Party returned to Government he became<br />
Minister for Environment, Housing and Cormmunity Development.<br />
He undertook his new portfolio with enthusiasm and dedication.<br />
Throughout his life, Ivor Greenwood had a consuming passion<br />
for j ustice..<br />
He was dedicated to the rule of law because he believed that:<br />
it was only the law which protected the weak from the<br />
powerf ul.<br />
He believed that the law and regard for the law was the<br />
greatest safeguard of liberty.<br />
He was profoundly disturbed whenever he believed that the law<br />
was being flouted or denied.<br />
Ivor Greenwood was a man who obtained great respect from his<br />
colleagues. His was a life that stood courageously for<br />
principles of justice and fairness for all.<br />
His death is a great loss to the Parliament and to the nation.<br />
Mr Speaker: I move that this House expresses its deep reg-ret<br />
at the death, this day, of Senator the Honourable Ivor John<br />
Greenwood, Queens Counsel, Senator for the State of Victoria<br />
from 1968, a Minister of the Crown from 1971 to 1972 and<br />
from 1975 to 1976, Deputy Leader of the Opposition in the<br />
Senate from 1972 to 19,75, and Deputy Leader of the Gov. ernmnent<br />
in the Senate from 1 975 to 1976, places on record its<br />
appreciation of his long and meritorious public service and<br />
tenders its profound sympathy to his widow and the members ofE<br />
hi-s family in ' Eaeir : avmrt. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
