<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7447</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007447.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AL04<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 13 DECEMBER 1988<br />
The minister for Science, Customs and Small Business,<br />
Mir Jones, has made a convincing case for early consideration<br />
of initiatives to enhance the Government's science policy.<br />
Senior officials had identified concerns of the research<br />
community, in a report prepared for Cabinet consideration.<br />
The officials' report followed an intensive round of<br />
consultations with peak academic, research and union groups<br />
in the science and technology field. It found a high level<br />
of support for the Government's basic objective of aligning<br />
public sector research efforts more closely with Australia's<br />
economic strengths and national priorities, and of<br />
increasing the R and D effort of the private sector and<br />
their involvement with the public research institutions.<br />
we are all now better informed. Mr Jones' task will be to<br />
take the options identified by officials and structure them<br />
according to national priorities.<br />
Other Ministers, including Mr Kerin, Dr Blewett, Mr. Dawkins<br />
and Senator Richardson will be consulted.<br />
Mr Jones' Submissions will be dealt with early in the New<br />
Year. The Government recognises that there are particular problems<br />
with career structures for researchers, post-graduate<br />
stipends, and the generally poor level of private sector<br />
research funding.<br />
Mr Jones has forcefully argued these points.<br />
The Cabinet will look at these areas, together with early<br />
assistance measures but we are not after a ' quick-fix'<br />
package. The importance of research to Australia's future<br />
industrial structure is too important for that.<br />
Long-term approaches agreed as a result of Mr Jones'<br />
Submission will be given high priority in the 1989-90 Budget<br />
process.<br />
4282 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
