<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4202</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AT THE NATIONAL PRESS CLUB, WASHINGTON - 29 JULY 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/07/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004202_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Jj4US R4LI(<br />
V PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AT THE<br />
NATIONAL PRESS CLUB, WASHINGTON -29 JULY J. 976<br />
Thank you for having me as your guest. I am<br />
pleased to celebrate with you a remarkable two centuries<br />
and what is perhaps the greatest venture in popular<br />
government the world has known.<br />
Part of the reason why your nation has been so<br />
successful is because your Founding Fathers saw clearly<br />
the necessity for a balance of power and interest.<br />
Your Constitution is the product of their<br />
recognition that liberty's best safeguard lay in distributing<br />
power as widely as possible and in achieving a balance<br />
between the different regions of the country, and between<br />
the different arms of government.<br />
Today I would like to talk about balance in<br />
domestic and international affairs and as it relates to<br />
the domestic situation in Australia.<br />
In both domestic and international arenas, in a<br />
pluralist and imperfect world, a stable balance of forces<br />
provides our best hope for stability and peace. In the<br />
international context such a balance implies not only an<br />
equality of physical and technical capability but also an<br />
equality of will. That is the only sure foundation on<br />
which to establish procedures which will stabilise<br />
relations and contain conflict.<br />
Much depends on the people conducting international<br />
affairs. Their constant task must be to maintain balance and<br />
to strengthen the fabric of peace and stability. In this,<br />
their efforts to improve personal understanding are, I believe,<br />
of very great importance. ooo/ </p>
<p>Balance in the international arena stablised<br />
by realistic discussions and negotiations works to<br />
prevent the dominance of one nation over others, and to<br />
create the conditions in which all nations can work out<br />
their future in the interests of their own people.<br />
Our major foreign policy effort is naturally,<br />
directed to areas close to Australia.<br />
In South East Asia our main concern is to<br />
support the ASEAN countries in their efforts to promote<br />
internal development in the region, and to ensure that<br />
great power competition in the region does not frustrate<br />
these goals or upset the existing equilibrium. We believe<br />
that the ASEAN countries are making significant progress<br />
to these ends, and that it is vital to maintain the<br />
conditions which will allow this progress to continue.<br />
Australia stands at the confluence of the Indian<br />
and Pacific Oceans. Crossing these oceans are trade routes<br />
which are of vital strategic and economic significance not<br />
only to Australia but also many other nations including<br />
Japan. In the Pacific area there are many independent<br />
and soon to be independent countries. Australia wants to<br />
work and co-operate with them and believes that they should<br />
be enabled to pursue their own development free from<br />
outside interference. The idea of the Indian Ocean as a ' Zone of Peace'<br />
is a noble idea. It is difficult to see the circumstances<br />
in which it can be achieved. Consequently my Government<br />
has supported the extension of facilities in Diego Garcia<br />
by your Government and offered to your Navy access to our<br />
naval facilities in Western Australia, which we are expanding<br />
for our own Australian purposes.<br />
Here, as elsewhere, we believe that balance-is a<br />
precondition for stability0 We are also concerned that<br />
further efforts by the U. S. S. R. to enhance its strategic<br />
status in the Indian Ocean should be discouraged or<br />
adequately matched.<br />
I have previously stated our attitude towards the<br />
growth of the military power of the Soviet Union. Recent<br />
NATO communiques have expressed a concern similar to ours<br />
in almost identifical terms. I only want to add here that<br />
if the concern we have expressed on the evidence before us<br />
is misplaced, it is within the means of the Soviet Union to<br />
make this clear. We fervently hope that it will do so. oo ./ 3 </p>
<p>3.<br />
Australia desires nothing more than friendly<br />
and co-operative relations with a Soviet Union whose<br />
basic purpose is world peace and stability. We already<br />
have important and extensive relations with the Soviet<br />
Union on which we place considerable value, and we would<br />
wish to extend these to our mutual advantage.<br />
In our foreign relations we deal with other<br />
countries not on the basis of their ideology but on the<br />
basis of common interests. We believe that in the end,<br />
relations based on common interests are the only relations<br />
that can be depended upon.<br />
We believe that there is considerable scope for<br />
more extensive discussions between nations. Such<br />
discussions are essential to secure a stable international<br />
balance. Last month I visited Japan and China to further<br />
extend Autai' relationship with these two major Asian<br />
powers. Japan has a role of great importance and even<br />
greater potential in our quarter of the globe0 She is<br />
Australia's major trading partner: we are the principal<br />
supplier to Japan of many vital raw materials: we both<br />
have defence treaties with the United States: trade between<br />
Australia, Japan and the U. S. is complementary. Japan's<br />
treaty with the U. S. is of great importance for stability<br />
in the North West Pacific as is the Australian and New<br />
Zealand treaty with the United States for the Pacific0<br />
Both Japan and Australia are determined to do what<br />
we can acting in our own ways to advance the economic<br />
interests of the region0<br />
It is only recently that Australia established<br />
diplomatic relations with China. For too long, China has<br />
not been adequately involved in discussions and communications<br />
with the wider international community0 The fault, I suggest,<br />
was not solely China's. We are seeking to play our part in<br />
redressing that situation as a matter of greatest importance.<br />
The purpose of my visit to China was to learn<br />
and to improve communication between our two countries.<br />
This might sound a very limited purpose but given the<br />
differences in our history and cultures and a long period<br />
of non-communication, it is a very necessary beginning.<br />
We do not expect any dramatic results or any vital<br />
changes next week, next month, next year0 We are prepared<br />
over decades if necessary to seek to build relations and<br />
consultations which develop a greater understanding between<br />
our two governments and our two peoples. .14 </p>
<p>In our discussions the Chinese leaders made it<br />
plain that they regarded the broad international situation<br />
as being of greatest importance in their relations with<br />
the United States and other nations. This followed from<br />
the way they expressed their views on the Association of<br />
South East Asian Nations, the United States, on government<br />
to government and party to party relations and the nature<br />
of their support for the objective of an Indian Ocean Zone<br />
of Peace. Whatever view one takes of China's ideology, it<br />
is clear that Chinese society manifests a sense of purpose<br />
and self-reliance. A stable equilibrium in international<br />
relations is not possible unless China is more fully<br />
involved in the international community. Agreements<br />
reached, for example, between the Soviet Union and the<br />
United States, which affect other major states, the<br />
European Economic Community, or China, will only be<br />
workable if these are seen as protecting the interests<br />
of these other states.<br />
Our most important relationship with a great<br />
power is our relationship with the United States of America.<br />
America plays a vital, an irreplaceable role in maintaining<br />
the balance of power and in preserving world peace and<br />
stability. It is not only in politics that the U. S. has<br />
a major role the U. S. produces about 40 per cent of the<br />
0. E. C. D. Gross National Product.<br />
As free peoples with common philosophical commitments,<br />
the United States and Australia will often have a common view<br />
and co-operate in the pursuit of common goals0 But we do not<br />
expect the American people to accept responsibilities which<br />
other nations disavow0 You have just passed through your<br />
Congress a very large Defence Budget. We are supporting an<br />
expanded Five Year Defence Programme0<br />
This relationship between a country of Australia's<br />
size and position with a super power like the United States<br />
may be misunderstood by some at home and abroad who<br />
believe that concurrence and common action means subordination<br />
to the larger nation0<br />
Such problems have always existed in relations<br />
between the largest states and others such relations must<br />
be treated with some sensitivity. Australia's policies are<br />
basedon a fully independent assessment of Australia's national<br />
interests. The problems of balance in international relations<br />
relates not only to politics instability . can arise also.<br />
from lack of balance in economic relations. </p>
<p>There is such an imblance in the international<br />
economic system between the deve]. oped and the developing<br />
nations. The causes of this imbalance lie not so much in<br />
the economic system as such but in the policies pursued<br />
by some nations. Many developed countries seem more<br />
concerned with pursuing freer trade in the products in<br />
which they excel, than in opening their markets to the<br />
products of the developing countries,<br />
An improvement in trade would make a major<br />
contribution to lifting standards of living in the<br />
developing countries. It would enable countries to<br />
concentrate on the things they can do best.<br />
Equally there is a need to focus on policies<br />
aimed at the creation of wealth rather than its<br />
redistribution. Redistribution alone can provide no<br />
real solution to economic problems. There are no panaceas.<br />
Encouraging inappropriate policies and raising expectations<br />
which cannot be fulfilled only add to instability in<br />
economic relations. This applies within countries as it does<br />
internationally. Sustained domestic economic growth<br />
requires a balance between public and private expenditure,<br />
between wages and profits.<br />
We have recently experienced the effects of such<br />
imbalance in Australia. Between 1972 and 1975 government<br />
expenditure in Australia increased dramatically The<br />
Australian economy, which incidentally was largely insulated<br />
from the oil crisis, was thrown out of balance. In one year<br />
federal government outlays increased from 24 per cent of<br />
G. D. P. to 30 per cent.<br />
Excess expenditure was financed by deficits of<br />
an unprecedented magnitude0 There was an inflationary<br />
growth in the money supply. These domestic problems were<br />
of course not helped by international economic developments0<br />
Most other countries were pursuing similar domestic policies.<br />
These led first to inflation and then, inevitably, to world<br />
recession. Against this background, my Government found when<br />
it came to office that people had naturally tended to draw<br />
into themselves, to become cautious, to lose their initiative.<br />
We have moved to reverse this0 Government<br />
expenditures are now being firmly and substantially controlled0<br />
Our purposes is to bring down the Government's share of<br />
resources so as to make room for people, for individuals, </p>
<p>I 6.<br />
for businesses: to give the productive sector of the<br />
economy confidence and the room to breathe. The number<br />
on the Governmient' s paty roll has been substaLntil Ly<br />
reduced for the first time in 24 years, In 1975 the<br />
money supply grew at a rate of 20 per cent. This year<br />
it has grown at less than half that rate 9 per cent0<br />
This i s higher than we wool d 1like hb0 ,1 ini economi~ c mn.; totrs<br />
changes in direction cannot hie -too sudden or-too swif-t0<br />
We have also taken action to restore profits. Without<br />
adequate profits there will not be enough investment.<br />
Without investment there won't be enough jobs. The<br />
dramatic fall in profits and in G. D. P. which followed the<br />
great rise in government expenditure and the rapid growth<br />
in wages, was a major factor in the rise in unemployment<br />
to the highest levels since the great depression.<br />
There are now increasing signs in Australia that<br />
the inter-relationship between excessive wage increases,<br />
inflation and unemployment are being recognised. There are<br />
also encouraging signs of a downward trend in both wage and<br />
price increases. A year ago inflation was running at<br />
14 per cent per annum. In the June quarter, inflation was<br />
down to an annual rate of 10 per cent.<br />
Overcoming inflation is essential to the balance<br />
and health of the Australian economy. It is prerequisite<br />
for renewed growth and the development of our great natural<br />
resources. Both Australia and the rest of the world need<br />
that development. We need overseas capital to develop our natural<br />
resources and that is why we welcome overseas investment in<br />
Australia. Our policy is to obtain joint ventures in<br />
partnership with Australian concerns0 My Government's<br />
attitude to foreign capital differs substantially from that<br />
of our predecessors0 We understand the benefits it can<br />
bring and take a more balanced view of its costs. Our<br />
foreign investment guidelines reflect this and they have<br />
been deliberately kept flexible so that we can take up<br />
proposals that will help us develop our resources0<br />
But we know that it is not only our attitude to<br />
foreign investment that is important to foreign investors0<br />
I hope it will be clear that the whole thrust of the policies<br />
I have mentioned is directed at improving the investment<br />
climate in Australia, for foreign and domestic investors<br />
alike0 I know there has been considerable interest in<br />
our exchange rate policy, There has already been a downward<br />
trend in wage and cost increages. With recovery overseas 000a/ 7 </p>
<p>strengthening our external prospects are swinging back<br />
into balance. A downward movement in the exchange rate<br />
would have inflationary effects contrary to our primary<br />
domestic aim. I do not think I need say any more on that.<br />
Our whole economic policies are directed to<br />
achieving stability and restoring balance between the<br />
private and public sectors. In domestic politics, in<br />
international politics and in economics our purpose is<br />
the pursuit of an appropriate balance.<br />
The purpose your Founding Fathers sought to<br />
enshrine in their Constitution still states in the clearest<br />
possible terms the nature of the objectives which politicians<br />
in free societies should pursue0 Without power there can<br />
be no balance, but a balance of power is not the only one<br />
necessary. There is a need for a balance between realism<br />
and aspiration, Means must be appropriate to objectives.<br />
Nations pursue their own interests, but they must always<br />
strive to give effect to their ideals0<br />
Finally, in a world subject to accelerating change,<br />
there must be a balance between tradition and innovation0<br />
In a little more than a generation, the world's population<br />
will have doubled. There will be profound techn6logical<br />
changes expanding the limits of the possible and creating<br />
new problems of control and co-ordination.<br />
Your country's role in this world will be crucial0<br />
For your country, 1976 is not only the end of two centures<br />
but the beginning of a decisive quarter century, one in<br />
which your vision of a better world and determination to<br />
work for it will be more important than ever before0 </p>
<p>A<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AT THE NATIONAL PRESS<br />
CLUB, WASHINGTON QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS 29 JULY 1976<br />
Q. You arrived here with the headlines describing<br />
you as one of the world's most outspoken anti-Russian leaders.<br />
Since arriving you have been careful to keep such views<br />
under your belt. Do your accurately-recorded anti-Soviet<br />
views still hold? Have you changed them as a result of<br />
your talks this week? Have you been silent out of deference<br />
to your host Government?<br />
A. I dont think my views have changed I think<br />
maybe that reputation preceded me because the views expressed<br />
in Australia on the 1$ 4J une might have surprised Australians<br />
and Australian commentators who were not aware that the<br />
views I was expressing on behalf of the Australian Government<br />
were, virtually, identical to the views that had previously<br />
been expressed by the NATO powers, which, of course, as<br />
everyone knows, includes at least three socialist governments.<br />
But these reports, and no doubt communiques, had not been<br />
widely reported and not known when I was still in Australia,<br />
and the changed attitudes that I believe have come to be<br />
accepted in much of Europe, and given a voice to, and<br />
perfected in the communique between your President and<br />
myself was something that Australians maybe were not aware<br />
of. That I think is why that reputation of a particular kind<br />
preceded me my views have not changed and I also believe<br />
they are in line, and expressed in almost identical terms,<br />
with those of the NATO powers.<br />
Q. Would you agree that it was in Australia' s interest<br />
to be friendlier with both China and the Soviet Union than<br />
either is with each other?<br />
A. Well, we try to be as friendly as we can be with<br />
everyone. But with China, of course, there needed to be a<br />
shift because there had not been communication, so we wanted<br />
a closer relationship than there had been. But with the<br />
Soviet Union, we wanted to make quite sure that we understood<br />
each other and that there were no mis-apprehensions about<br />
each other's attitude. / 2 </p>
<p>I 2.<br />
I think that also works towards more realistic faces than<br />
pretending that certain realities of the world situation<br />
don't exist. It would not be very difficult to be more<br />
friendly with both, than either is at the moment with each<br />
other.<br />
Q. How do you believe the Soviet Union can be<br />
discouraged from building up its forces in the Indian Ocean?<br />
A. Probably only by the knowledge that it will not be<br />
allowed to dominate the area and therefore it is not worthwhile<br />
starting.<br />
Q. Would Australia object to the US supplying India<br />
with additional nuclear fuel? Does Australia consider<br />
safe-guards adequate to prevent diversion to Indian military<br />
uses?<br />
A. We are very much opposed to the proliferation of<br />
nuclear weapons and would very firmly want to support all<br />
measures designed to reduce nuclear proliferation. There<br />
are considerable uranium resources in Australia, and, depending<br />
upon the results of an environmental enquiry, we would be taking<br />
the most rigid controls in accordance with international<br />
practice and guidelines, to make sure that exports from<br />
Australia do not add to the possibility of nuclear proliferation.<br />
But I must say that determination of future Government policy<br />
is dependent upon a Royal Commission and that Royal Commission's<br />
environmental report.<br />
Q. Does Australia have diplomatic relations with Taiwan?<br />
Do you believe the United States should withdraw its<br />
Ambassador there?<br />
A. The previous administration withdrew recognition<br />
of Taiwan and it was the considered judgement of my Government<br />
that the decisions, once taken, and in the necessity we<br />
believed for greater communication with China, and greater<br />
understanding between China and Australia, and for that<br />
matter China and many other countries, would not merit any<br />
attempt to alter the terms of that recognition that was<br />
earlier consummated. I dont really think that at this<br />
particular time it is appropriate for me to comment on what<br />
the United States ought, or ought not, to do.<br />
Q. What effect will United States' recognition of<br />
Peking have on the security of Asia and the Pacific, if it<br />
is done at the cost of breaking the US defence treaty with<br />
Taiwan?<br />
A. Again, I think that this is a question that is<br />
really seeking comment on United States' policy, or certain<br />
aspects of ./ 3 </p>
<p>United States' policy, and I really do believe that this is<br />
anl illappr') priate year in which a stranger shoul. d malie comnierts<br />
oil that, Sort of thing.<br />
Q. From this perspective, a question arises Australia<br />
and New Zealand seem to have so much in common politically,<br />
economically and strategically, is there a prospect of an<br />
Anzac-Federation?<br />
A. I think the first part of the qucstion might also<br />
appropriately have been directed to the kind of relationship<br />
between Canada and the United States. I think the independence<br />
of New Zealand is assured and the independence of Australia<br />
is assured. We co-operate and work closely together but I<br />
think that's the way both countries want it to be. Of course,<br />
there is always room for closer consultation, closer cooperation.<br />
Both the New Zealand Prime Minister and myself<br />
are determined to try and achieve that.<br />
Q. It is common knowledge that the Whitlam Government<br />
was opposed to the friendly association between Australia<br />
and the United States, Worn during the Holt/ Johnson years.<br />
Can you please give a reason for such opposition?<br />
A. Well, I did give reasons for that during the election.<br />
Again I dont really want to export Australian politics to<br />
this forum any more than I want to comment on United-States'<br />
policies in this particular year.<br />
Q. What is the Australian Government's present<br />
position regarding immigration of Americans to Australia?<br />
A. We would be delighted to see you.<br />
Q. Do your immigration laws limit Japanese, Chinese,<br />
Blacks? A. There is no discrimination on the grounds of race,<br />
colour, creed, or nationality of any kind and we recently,<br />
in relation to Japan, signed a special treaty of friendship<br />
aneW understanding which is designed to achieve greater<br />
co-ope~ ration an., understandling of two peoples whose cultures<br />
and bac': grounds are very ( ifferent. There has been a close<br />
and strengthening comme~ ccial .&amp; elationship, but both Ja!. an and<br />
Australia now belit~ vc that commercial relationship alone is<br />
not enough and that we ought to try and develop the<br />
circumstanices in which there can be the same in-depth<br />
understanding as I believre there is between Australia and the<br />
United Kingdom or Australia and Canada, or Australia anld the<br />
United States.<br />
0. What is Australia's position on the future of the<br />
control of the Panama Canal as a vital trade link between the<br />
Atlantic and Pacific Nations? / 4 </p>
<p>A. Well, I havent swam through it, but again, I seem<br />
t o dle tee t, ( J iat thIi re is it n (' rIive 1. o I Un i Le d S taL e.&amp;<br />
p) olitics in this par-ticular matter. I have hieari the subject<br />
mentioned over the last few ( lays, but I don't consider myself<br />
well enough informed -to offer a view.<br />
Q. Does Australia plan to increase its production of<br />
peanuts? Applause. A. Mr Adermann, the former Minister for Primary<br />
Industry, in an earlier coalition Government, was a member<br />
of that profession, Mr Petersen, Premier of Queensland,<br />
is also a member of that profession.<br />
Q. When can we expect the Australian Government to<br />
announce their policy on export of uranium?<br />
A. We have quite deliberately refained from taking<br />
any policy ( decisions in relation to this matter until we<br />
have the report of a Royal Commission in the hands of a most<br />
significant member of the judicial community of Australia<br />
it's an environmental enquiry and its important to get<br />
his Honor's report before the Government makes decisions<br />
in these particular matters. We ought to have that report<br />
within a few weeks and it will enable us to make policy<br />
decisions. We recognise that there are many countries interested<br />
in Australia's longer term objectives and policies in these<br />
particular areas. We'll certainly lose no time in making<br />
decisions based on Mr Justice Fox' report.<br />
Q. Is there an Australian counterpart to the US<br />
criticism of big Government and, if so, what is your<br />
Government doing about it?<br />
A. Well, we're trying to abolish it.<br />
The circumstances in Australia have been that about 80 per cent<br />
of all revenues came to be collected by the Federal Government.<br />
A fair bit of that is given back to the States but often with<br />
tags tied to it you know, you've got to spend it this way,<br />
the way we believe is right. State Governments therefore<br />
were able to say in Australia, well they can't do this and<br />
they can't do that, the Commonwealth collects all the money,<br />
we've got no independence of our own. Local Governments<br />
were in a very similar position. We've looked very closely at<br />
what Canada has done in relation to the tax-sharing and we've<br />
already come to agreements with the states along similar<br />
lines to those that have applied in Canada for some time,<br />
designed to provide a greater financial basis for the states<br />
so that Governments with direct responsibility for providing<br />
services can also have a greater responsibility for raising<br />
the money to pay for th'ose services. We strongly believe that<br />
politicians who spend money ought also, to the maximum<br />
extent, be responsible for raising that money, then they have<br />
to weigh the balance of both sides of the coin. The popular<br />
side of providing the service, the unpopular side of taxing to<br />
pay for it. </p>
<p>Q. Mr Prime Minister, does your Government plan to make<br />
the income tax rebate provisions of law applicable to nonresidents,<br />
as well as residents of Australia?<br />
A. I'd have to defer to a Treasury adviser before I<br />
could give a proper answer in relation to that. I'm sorry.<br />
Q. Do you have or contemplate any incomes, policy, or<br />
wage and price controls?<br />
A. The industrial power of the Commonwealth Government<br />
is one that enables us to establish a body to settle industrial<br />
disputes and then only disputes which are national or interstate<br />
in character. So it is a very limited power. Such a body has<br />
always been part of the Australian scene and the theory of<br />
it is that both sides get an argument of case before the<br />
Arbitration Commission as its' called: there is<br />
a determination which both sides are meant to accept as<br />
industrial matters there are no absolute laws and both sides<br />
haven't always accepted the determinations of the Arbitration<br />
Commission. But the Commonwealth's role in these matters is<br />
to argue what it believes to be right in the economic<br />
circumstances of Australia and we have achieved some significant<br />
changes in the guidelines being used in the wage-fixing<br />
process over the last six months which will help significantly<br />
to wind down inflation. But I think that one of the main<br />
motivating forces, apart from wages and inflation, in Australia<br />
is the rate of increase in Government expenditures, which I<br />
think I might have mentioned, went up 46 per cent one year<br />
to the next, and Govejnment expenditures and the budget to<br />
be revealed on the 17' August will indicate an increase in<br />
Government expenditure of a mere fraction of that. So there<br />
are many things that we have to do to overcome inflation.<br />
There is a prices Justification Tribunal but we dont, in fact,<br />
have rigid price and wage-fixing powers and, therefore, whether<br />
or not they should be used has not really been a matter of<br />
consideration. The constitutional power does not exist.<br />
Q. A listener, hearing your answer that you would abolish<br />
big Government or are trying to abolish big Government in<br />
Australia asks me to explain how you would cut down the<br />
size of Government in Australia.<br />
A. By having policies, I believe, that encourage<br />
the independence of people. It is very easy to have welfare<br />
programs, for example, that are based solely on spending more<br />
of other people's money. But that is not always a solution to<br />
problems of poverty or difficulty within a community. The<br />
problems are sometimes more a problem of human relationships,<br />
lack of capacity to operate within a modern and complex society<br />
and, therefore, the solution is much more complex than merely<br />
one of spending money and having a Government program designed<br />
to do it. Our policies are designed to encourage the independence<br />
and strength of the individuals in the Australian community. o0a./ 6 </p>
<p>That does not mean to say that for those who need some<br />
special help that could not be provided in full measure<br />
but because of the policies that we are seeking to introduce<br />
that will enable us to be in a better position to do more<br />
for those who are really disadvantaged and who deserve extra<br />
help. Q. In light of the recent general strike called by the<br />
Australian Council of Trade Unions over the Medi-bank issue,<br />
what if any, legislative action will your Government be<br />
proposing in the area of Industrial Relations?<br />
A. Industrial Legislation has already been passed<br />
and is being proclaimed for the future elective officials<br />
in the trade unions will need to be elected by secret ballots<br />
in the past some unions have followed that practice in a<br />
proper and very adequate manner but there are some significant<br />
trade unions where people have not really had a free<br />
opportunity to vote. In one significant, and to a certain<br />
extent militant, union, a significant official was elected on<br />
a massive vote of 1.8 per cent of the union membership. We<br />
believe that secret postal ballots, properly applied will give<br />
people a greater say in determining their own union's affairs.<br />
That particular national strike did not get all that much<br />
national support. A large number of people did not obey<br />
the directions of union officials. In the heavy industrial<br />
areas, of course, where people would find it more difficult<br />
to operate on production lines is where you find pretty well everyone<br />
turning up. Those who obeyed the strike order would have<br />
been in the majority but over many areas of Australia, despite<br />
the call for a national strike, life operated in a pretty<br />
reasonable manner. I don't think those who called the strike<br />
would take a great deal of heart from the degree of support<br />
it got. In polls conducted about the week afterwards, they<br />
indicated that between 75 and 80 per cent of the Australian<br />
community felt that the trade union movement had too much<br />
power and disapproved of the strike. More industrial legislation<br />
is in contemplation, some of it in part borrowed from the<br />
study of American practice.<br />
Q. Mr Prime Minister. Has industrial unrest inhibited<br />
foreign investment in Australia.<br />
A. I think it can, but I would believe that inflation<br />
has probably been one of the major factors but also it has<br />
come at a time when there hasn't been a great deal of foreign<br />
investment in any country because of the world recession<br />
and one of the things of which I have been advised is<br />
that the United States recovery is likely to lead to a revival<br />
in demand for additional resources and that therefore more<br />
investment is likely to flow. Indeed some significant coal<br />
projects where agreement has already been reached, should<br />
go ahead. Their development would involve some hundreds of<br />
millions of dollars and this I think is an indication of<br />
what is likely to come in the future. As world recovery proceeds<br />
I beleive we will see more foreign investment in Australia<br />
and I have found from people I have met in this country foreign<br />
investment guidelines are understood and fully accepted. / 7 </p>
<p>a. 7.<br />
Q. You stated that your party welcomes foreign investment<br />
and yet the opposition feared environmental damage to the<br />
natural resources. Has your party taken any steps to safeguard<br />
the natural resources from foreign investors?<br />
A. Well I think there are two elements to that question.<br />
Perhaps if we believe that a particular project can affect the<br />
environment there is a capacity to have an environmental<br />
inquest statement so that it can properly be assessed. It<br />
would not be our intention that that should be a device to<br />
hold up particular matters but merely to make sure that all<br />
factors are taken into account before major developemental<br />
projects proceed. And there are guidelines for foreign<br />
investment which are intended to preserve a õ ignifici. nt<br />
degree of Australian equity in new ventures and partnerships<br />
but some projects are so large that Australia certainly is not<br />
able to supply all the capital that she wants for the development<br />
of natural resources and other matters and very significant<br />
overseas investment is required. I believe that not only in<br />
Australia's interest but in the interest of other countries<br />
who would want more iron ore and bauxite and natural gas and<br />
other matters that are waiting for development.<br />
Q. Australia has ordered new warships from the United<br />
States. The cost growth of these ships has been great. Will<br />
Australia still be able to afford them?<br />
A. Oh we will be able to afford them, yes. We would<br />
like to see the United States if she could, place some orders<br />
for some more things in Australia. There is a trade balance<br />
in the United States' favour. I already mentioned that the<br />
defence vote is going to increase steadily over the next few<br />
years because we believe that is necessary. I don't think<br />
you need have any fear the bills will be paid.<br />
Q. Would you make an assessment of the agricultural<br />
situation in Australia. Do you expect Australian grain and<br />
beef exports to continue to come into competition with<br />
American products in the world markets.<br />
A. Yes. I don't know how much wheat we will have<br />
for export next year as there has been a very severe drought<br />
in many of the wheat producing areas and many of the sheep<br />
producing areas which hadn't broken when I left Australia<br />
and in a number of wheat growing areas the grain had been<br />
planted dry and as farmers would know that is a risky<br />
proposition. There is a real possibility that the wheat crop<br />
will be very significantly down although we wont know that<br />
probably for the next three or four weeks when we will be<br />
able to get fairly accurate estimates. We had a capacity<br />
to supply beef to the United States and at any time that you<br />
are willing to take a larger share of Australian beef I think<br />
o o/ 8 </p>
<p>is 0 0 0/ 9<br />
8.<br />
we would be very happy to make it available to you. After<br />
all, it -is only repaying some kind of a debt that T think we owe<br />
as there was a starving colony in about 1792 and it was<br />
probably saved from starvation by a shipment of United States meat<br />
well cured over the nine months trip in a ship called<br />
' Philadelphia'. Well that is a debt we feel we have an<br />
obligation to repay and to go on repaying.<br />
Q. During your visit have you made any progress on<br />
the beef carry over dispute with the United States?~<br />
A. I think that, I can say, is an area where two good<br />
friends are having a vigorous discussion. The vigor of that<br />
discussion will continue.<br />
Q. Following the Stonehouse affair has any action<br />
been taken to restrict the right of free access hitherto accorded<br />
Members of Parliament from the United Kingdom. That is are<br />
they now required to complete the same immigration formalities<br />
as other aliens?<br />
A. Well, I believe that everyone should really comply<br />
to common rules in these particular matters and that is the<br />
general thrust of our policies.<br />
Q. In Australia do environmental impact statements<br />
embrace economic impact considerations. Is the economy in<br />
other words considered a major component of the environment<br />
legally, or is it a matter of policy?<br />
A. Well in any project that is being undertaken obviously<br />
the economy is very much a part of it, but the environmental<br />
impact statements as such are more related to the natural<br />
environment or to the human environment and the way the<br />
particular projects or developments are likely to have an<br />
impact on that. I think the economic element tends to be<br />
assessed separately.<br />
Q. How will Australia escape the cycle of wage increases,<br />
more inflation and then more wage increases?<br />
A, By continuing to support the policies of the present<br />
Government in Australia.<br />
Q. One more beef question. How does American beef<br />
compare in tenderness, taste and flavour to Australian beef?<br />
A. Well I think that depends upon habits and practice<br />
and we are probably each entitled to our own national<br />
prejudices. There are some things I could say about this but<br />
again it could perhaps be an intrusion in this particular year.<br />
President of the National Press Club then said:-<br />
Before the final question I would like to present to<br />
you Mr Prime Minister the National Press Club Certificate of<br />
Appreciation.<br />
Thank you. </p>
<p>'' 0 And also for your trout fishing trip to Great<br />
Slave Lake in Canada we have the coveted National Press Club<br />
Windbreaker in the extra large size especially for Australian<br />
Prime Ministers.<br />
Qo And now for the final question. Are you the same<br />
Fraser who used to play on the Australian Davis Cup team?<br />
A. Well you know, after I had been a member of Parliamemt<br />
for about ten years one of my constituents came up to me and<br />
said: " Don't know how you do it. You are in Parliament,<br />
you report weekly to your Electorate and I get reports every<br />
few minutes that you are here and there playing tennis in<br />
the United States and Britain and you had a wonderful match<br />
last Saturday but I thought you were down at that tea party<br />
opening a new hall." I don't think we are any more related<br />
than Smiths are related to Smiths. We are not. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
