<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2402</transcript-id>
    <title>INTEGRATION OF ABORIGINALS IN QUEENSLAND</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/04/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002402.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: PM No. 44/ 1971<br />
INTEGRATION OF ABORIGINALS IN QUEENSLAND)<br />
Following a meeting today in the Premier's Office between the Prime<br />
Minister ( Mr. M cMahon) and the Minister administering the Department<br />
of the Vice President of the Executive Council ( Sir Alan Hulme) representing<br />
the Commonwealth and the Premier ( Mr. Bjelke-Petersen) and the Treasurer<br />
( Mr. Gordon Chalk) representing Queensland, agreement was reached about<br />
the unresolved issues relating to integration of aboriginals into the Australian<br />
community difficulties which might possibly have required legislation by<br />
the Commonwealth. The Prime Minister came to Queensland at the invitation of the Premier<br />
and said his visit provided an early opportunity to seek to resolve the unsettled<br />
issues. In a joint statement issued following the meeting, Mr. McMahon and<br />
Mr. Bjelke-Petersen said<br />
" We now have a full appreciation of each Government's<br />
problems and we discussed the various matters needing<br />
resolution." Mr. McMahon outlined those in which the Commonwealth was especially<br />
interested and Mr. Bjelke-Petersen indicated proposals which his Government<br />
was ready to make.<br />
After discussion, arrangements acceptable to the State and in accord with<br />
the principles and objectives of the Commronwealth were agreed to.<br />
Broadly, the matters considered encompassed questions relating to<br />
Freedom of movement off Reserves;<br />
Control, through Reserve Councils, of access to Reserves;<br />
Control of property freedom of choice will be allowed but<br />
with provision for consultation with the Council and/ or the<br />
Administration as a safeguard against exploitation;<br />
Control of transactions arrangements as in the case<br />
of control of property;<br />
Liquor Canteen System freedom of choice to Reserve<br />
residents to decide whether or not liquor will be permitted<br />
on a particular Reserve. e / 2 </p>
<p>Torres Strait Islanders a separate Act of Parliament;<br />
Vagrancy Laws : Paragraph ( ii) of Section 4( l) of the<br />
Vagrants, Gaming and Other Offences Act will be<br />
repealed; Wage Rates special consideration will be given to<br />
inexperienced, slow or retarded aboriginal workers;<br />
Reserve Councils native representation will be<br />
reviewed.<br />
Full details will be spelt out later.<br />
It was recognised that the existing Queensland legislation was designed<br />
to assist in protecting persons who, without guidance and assistance, could<br />
be subject to exploitation and that it was not, therefore, to be seen as<br />
discrimination against aboriginals.<br />
But both the Prime Minister and the Premier indicated that there<br />
was a willingness on the part of both Governments to do all that was possible<br />
to meet the desires of the aboriginal people.<br />
Mr. Bjelke-Petersen added that he was now in a position to confirm to<br />
his Minister in charge of Aboriginal Affairs the general lines already laid<br />
down for the preparation of draft legislation to be introduced at the next<br />
Session of the Queensland ParliamEnt.<br />
BRISBANE 8 April 1971 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
