<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4378</transcript-id>
    <title>HEADS OF GOVERNMENT AGREEMENT - PRICES AND INCOMES PAUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/04/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004378.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A US I( AL<br />
PROME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 25 APRIL 1977<br />
HEADS OF GOVERNMENT AGREEMENT<br />
PRICES AND INCOMES PAUSE<br />
The Prime Minister today sent the following message to all<br />
Premiers: On 13 April, the Heads of Government in Australia:<br />
* agreed to call for a three month halt in price<br />
and wage increases<br />
* agreed that such restraint was urgently needed if<br />
Australia is to overcome its current economic problems<br />
* committed themselves to work for this voluntary pause.<br />
We believed our agreement, with the backing of all seven<br />
governments and the goodwill of all major parties for the<br />
future well being of Australia, offered a chance to rE-solve<br />
Australia's economic problems more rapidly. Our agreEtment was<br />
unprecedented. We put aside political divisions in the<br />
interests of the community as a whole.<br />
All Heads of Government also agreed that this " vital endeavour<br />
to help overcome inflation" could founder if steps for its<br />
implemenitation were delayed. It was for this reason that we<br />
all agreed that a national conference should not be<br />
convened.<br />
Despite this agreement, three State Governments saw fit in<br />
proceedings before the Commission on 19 April, and without any<br />
prior consultation with the other Heads of Government, to support<br />
a trade union proposal for a national conference. Moreover,<br />
that proposal was for a conference to discuss the state of the<br />
economy, and not the implementation of the prices and wages<br />
pause called by all Heads of Government. Indeed, the: total<br />
proposal, incorporating as it did the concept of application of<br />
the March Quarter CPI movement or equivalent direct tax cuts,<br />
was a complete denial of the prices and incomes pause envisaged<br />
under the Heads of Government agreement. / We made </p>
<p>-2<br />
We made it clear from the outset, in discussions with employer<br />
and employee groups, that agreement in principle with the Heads<br />
of Government Agreement was vital if the prices and wages pause<br />
on a voluntary basis is to be successful. Without that commitment<br />
in principle to the objectives of the Agreement no pause could<br />
work; no conference could have any hope of success. The unions<br />
have specifically refused to give that agreement in principle.<br />
Union leaders have refused to commit themselves to the principle<br />
even on a personal basis.<br />
It is a matter of extreme regret that the trade union proposaland<br />
its endorsement by three State Governments followed upon<br />
the union advocate's pouring scorn on the Heads of Government<br />
Agreement and all who had signed it.<br />
In their agreement, the Heads of Government also agreed:<br />
" Governments would not expect either the business organisations<br />
or the union organisations to agree to such voluntary restraint<br />
arrangements without agreement by the others."<br />
You are aware and indeed have stated the fact that a large<br />
measure of business support has been shown for the voluntary<br />
pause. Th'e Conciliation and Arbitration Commission itself<br />
stated on 19 April: " Employers generally have agreed with the<br />
Governments about prices"~ You will also appreciate that the<br />
general support achieved for a prices pause can be eroded if<br />
Governments' support for a wages pause is weak.<br />
It is for this reason, and consistent with the Coimonwealth<br />
Government's committing itself to working towards achievement of<br />
the objective of the Heads of Government Agreement that I telexed<br />
you on 20 April stating, inter alia:<br />
" In view of unwillingness and inability of peak employee<br />
councils to agree on wages pause, would you be prepared<br />
to join in an approach to the Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
Commission to use its good offices to assist in achieving<br />
the prices and incomes pause envisaged by our agreement".<br />
My intention here was to ask the Commission to use its good offices<br />
to assist in obtaining union agreement, at least in principle, to<br />
the initiative which you and all other Heads of Government in<br />
Australia agreed was urgently needed if our current economic<br />
problems were to be overcome. Without such agreement in principle<br />
there would clearly be no chance of Heads of Governments Agreement<br />
objective being achieved.<br />
If we do not take this action, we will not, in my view, be carrying<br />
out the commitment we freely made on l3-7-ril, and we will be<br />
letting down those very substantial members in the community who<br />
have responded positively to the initiative to which we all agreed.<br />
The Commonwealth Government is not prepared to treat its commitment<br />
lightly. It is not prepared to '-sregard the wide public support<br />
already achieved.<br />
I again ask you: would you please advise me urgently whether you<br />
are prepared to join in an approach, as outlined, to the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Commission. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
