<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4977</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/03/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004977.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P79/ 37<br />
AUS f'R. LIA<br />
FOR PRESS 4 MARCH 1979<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
All Australians want the opportunity to plan ahead and make<br />
the most of their talents. We are a people that reject the<br />
unnecessary intrusion of Government.<br />
That is one reason I made it clear this week that the Coalition<br />
Government was flatly opposed to the introduction of a Capital<br />
Gains tax. This is a tax that would stifle incentive, stifle<br />
development. A Capital Gains Tax would not only hurt large companies, but<br />
would devastate hundreds of thousands of Australian farmers,<br />
small businessmen, shop keepers and the like. It would cast<br />
a blanket over initiative and enterprise.<br />
Over the last few days the Australian Labor Party has reaffirmed<br />
its commitment to introducing such a tax if given the chance.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition repeated in the plainest terms<br />
Labor: s determination to introduce such a confidence destroying<br />
tax.<br />
Apol-gezically, he says such a tax would not include many people.<br />
He f gqets that tens of thousands of farmers alone with capital<br />
stock, equipment, plant, land and the farm homestead itself,<br />
would become instantly eligible for Labor's special Capital<br />
Gains Tax. This would be a farmers tax.<br />
The far-ming community and business, large and small, are now<br />
just starting to get back on their feet after many lean years.<br />
Yet " r H-avden wants to weigh in with the killer punch a tax<br />
on = tal gain the very essence of a free enterprise society.<br />
I do nc believe that the Leader of the Opposition can deny<br />
categorically that no pensioner, no small businessman, no<br />
householder or no owner of a farm under 100 acres would not<br />
be affected by his Capital Gains Tax scheme.<br />
A tax on capital is a tax on enterprise. It is a tax on job<br />
creation. Taxing the income generated by capital is a fair<br />
and proper means for government to raise money. But to tax<br />
the capital itself is to launch a tax on employers in the<br />
cities and on the land, and to strike at their ability to<br />
ovide jobs. </p>
<p>2<br />
It is a pity that Mr Hayden and Mr Willis, the ALP's Shadow<br />
Treasurer who this week also called for a tax on capital,<br />
failed to heed the advice of a former Labor Treasurer,<br />
Mr Crean.<br />
In 1974 Labor announced that it would introduce a Capital<br />
Gains tax. Mr Crean could not say how much it would raise,<br />
gave no estimate of the possible revenue, and admitted that<br />
its introduction would be delayed because " There are many<br />
complex technicalities involved and extensive anti-avoidance<br />
provisions will be required." Eventually the whole misconceived<br />
idea was abandoned.<br />
Your Government has firmly rejected such a tax but the<br />
Labor Party continues to espouse failed tired old policies<br />
that almost wrecked Australia. They are still talking about<br />
abandoni-g the investment allowance that has done so much to<br />
help industry. They are still talking about a resources<br />
rental tax and a tax on capital gains.<br />
This is the kind of thinking and the kind of economic<br />
management that killed off development of our mineral<br />
resources and bought the search for oil and gas to a standstill.<br />
They are the kind of policies that destroy initiative, enterprise,<br />
investment and development. They are the kind of policies<br />
Australia can do without.<br />
Australia today is moving ahead with purpose and confidence.<br />
Manufacturing industry is becoming competitive again, mining<br />
investment is moving forward, oil exploration and development<br />
is taking place because of the Government's crude oil pricing<br />
policies. At the same time, this activity tbis confidence in the<br />
Government's economic management is creating new and<br />
permanent job opportunities for Australians. A return to<br />
the Labcr recipe, to Labor's high taxes, would put us back<br />
to square one. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
