<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5005</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH RICHARD COLVILLE - &#039;SUNDAY REPORT&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/03/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005005.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
f-v C<br />
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT 30 MARCH 1979<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RICHARD COLVILLE " SUNDAY REPORT"<br />
Question: Prime Minister, on the Postal Workers' dispute, a lot of people<br />
have called your action during this dispute as highly provocative.<br />
Why did you find it necessary to do what you did?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well, I didn't think that the action was provocative for one<br />
moment, and when you say a lot of people, it might be just one<br />
or two union people who have done that. But the government has<br />
taken as a general policy line the view that if people are not<br />
doing their full work, if they are placing bans or limitations on theii<br />
work * with resulting inconvenience for the public, that they<br />
ought to be stood down, or, no work, no pay. And I would have<br />
thought that's eminently reasonable. Indeed, as I'm advised,<br />
people are thoroughly fed u. D with the inconvenience from actions<br />
in the trade union movement.<br />
Now, the government expressed a view, but the actual action in<br />
this matter was taken as a result of a decision<br />
by the Postal Commission and Telecommunications Commission.<br />
Certainly the government had been in touch with them, but, I<br />
don't think many people really believe that a person should be<br />
able to turn up to work, get his full pay but then decide to do<br />
perhaps only half his job. Now, people either do their jobs<br />
or they don't do them, and if they're not going to do them,<br />
they're not going to be paid, and, if necessary, they'll be<br />
stood down.<br />
Question: The union said the action was provocativie because the matter's<br />
still being negotiated it's before arbitration and they<br />
say that action shouldn't have been taken<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Yes but there used to be a practice once that when things<br />
were before arbitration, the arbitration process was allowed<br />
to work in a reasonable way. Now we have a number of unions<br />
that, as soon as they get to arbitration, also start to<br />
threaten that arbitral decision by imposing bans, or having<br />
a strike one day a week other actions which are designed to<br />
use industrial muscle, again, at great inconvenience to the<br />
public, and designed to influence the arbitrated decision.<br />
That again is not through arbitration, that's negotiation under<br />
threat, and it's time that a stand was made against that kind<br />
of practice.<br />
Question: Does this herald a harder line by your government in disputes ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
like this when public services are threatened?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
We're certainly looking to see whether there should be some<br />
basic change in the attitude that we would take, but let me<br />
make something quite clear. None of what we've done, or would<br />
do, stands in the way of the industrial process of arbitration.<br />
We support it even when we don't like the decisions we support<br />
arbitration, and what we want is for other people, for the trade<br />
union movement, to support arbitration, to give it a real<br />
chance to work without inconveniencing the Australian public.<br />
Now, more and more we've seen in recent times, " let's strike<br />
first, impose bans first, limitations on work first, and we'll<br />
negotiate, arbitrate, second". That attitude just isn't good<br />
enough, and the government will not continue to tolerate it.<br />
Question: On another subject, during the past week, there has been a lot<br />
of speculation and discussion about the future of energy resources.<br />
I think probably a lot of people are becoming concerned about<br />
the future, particulary of our oil supplies. Is there any real<br />
need for concern, do you think?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I've said, and Kevin Newman has said, not in the immediate<br />
future, but in the second half of this year, there remains<br />
doubt as to the effect the Iranian position will have on<br />
world oil supplies. That I suppose is from June onwards.<br />
But I think that it mightn't hurt to restate the basis of<br />
government policy in this area oil search, exploration<br />
and development had ceased when we came into office, They'd<br />
ceased because of pricing policies which meant that Australian<br />
oil was well below world parity, was more profitable for companies<br />
to explore and develop in other parts of the world than in<br />
Australia, or off-shore around Australia. Now that had to be<br />
altered. At the same time, because petrol was cheap in Australia,<br />
more petrol was used, more oil was used, than would be the case<br />
if it were priced on a rational economic basis. So we decided<br />
over a period,*: and that was hurried up in the last budget, to<br />
go to world parity pricing, virtually in one step -that's what<br />
happened in the end. As a result of those policies, we now<br />
have greatly increased oil search and oil development.<br />
Two countries alone have committed $ 1 000 million to exploration<br />
and development, and by the middle 1980s, about a third of the<br />
oil that Australia will be using, will come from reserves that<br />
have been proved and developed as a result of our oil pricing<br />
policies, that just wouldn't have been available if those pricing<br />
policies hadn't been put in place. The number of exploration<br />
wells this year, will be the highest for maybe 7, 8 or 9 years<br />
on even the lowest estimates of what will happen. Now, world<br />
parity pricing, therefore, achieves two objectives over the longer<br />
term people move to a more rational use of energy resources, a<br />
more rational judgement between oil and coal,' and natural gas.<br />
But at the same time, that same world parity pricing policy,<br />
encourages exploration and development, and therefore increases the<br />
-43 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
total oil available to Australia from Australia's own sources.<br />
That again makes Australia more independent of what happens<br />
in other countries. Quite plainly, if there are OPEC price<br />
changes which appear quite irrational and unreasonable, the<br />
government ' would have to access their impact under the policy.<br />
Kevin Newman is preparing a paper for cabinet on the oil<br />
position, the forward position, and we'll be examining that<br />
shortly. But the basic thrust of the policies must be maintained<br />
because they're rational, sensible policies.<br />
Question: Does the latest OPEC price change appear to you to be reasonable?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Oh, it doesn't appear to be reasonable, no, but I think that<br />
it's impact also might well have been over stated in some<br />
quarters, and I wouldn't want that to herald a change of view<br />
or a change of policy as a result of that particular decision.<br />
There's another element in this. There is a capacity in Australia<br />
to use more liquid gas. This is another policy matter that is<br />
being pursued by the government much greater increase into<br />
alternative uses of coal for different forms of energy.<br />
Quite a significant number of Commonwealth cars have been<br />
converted to natural gas in Melbourne, and I wouldn't be at<br />
all surprised if that didn't continue with a large number<br />
of taxis, for example.<br />
If that move gathers pace, and it's also a move that helps<br />
with pollution problems pollution problems in cities if<br />
that move gathers pace, it obviously helps get a total fuel<br />
usage into a more rational pattern.<br />
Question: Getting back to the OPEC . situation, you said that you would<br />
maintain the parity link if the OPEC changes appeared reasonable.<br />
What about this present case?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I can't commit the government to any position in relation to<br />
this until we've considered it.<br />
Question: It's not an automatic flow-on?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
These matters are considered. Always they're considered, and it's<br />
not an automatic flow-on in the sense that,.' tlaere' s an OPEC<br />
change, then there's a change in the Australian price. You see,<br />
world parity prices are determined at a price a year, and therefore<br />
there's no automatic flow-on in the sense Of OPEC today,<br />
Australia tomorrow. And that does give a time for the government<br />
to make a rational judgement in relation to the matter. But<br />
again, the basic thrust of world parity pricing policies for<br />
oil, must be maintained, because it's a rational policy, and it'$<br />
4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
well worth noting, I think, that all other countries, especially<br />
some major countries, had the same policy, then there may well<br />
be no crisis at the moment, because in some countries, the price<br />
of oil is well below world parity pricing, therefore consumption<br />
is much higher than it would otherwise be, and they use, therefore,<br />
much more than their fair share of a finite energy resource.<br />
So, if a particular country has unireal pricing policies, that's<br />
not just a matter of concern to that country, it's a matter<br />
of concern to all oil-consuming countries.<br />
Question: There has been also a lot of speculation about the effect<br />
of this latest oil price rise on various other services,<br />
and on inflation. You said earlier that you thought there had<br />
been an over reaction. Was this what you were referring to?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Oh~ in some areas I think there certainly has. I saw one<br />
scare headline which indicated some fantastic increase<br />
in the household bills of every family. It grossly oiver stated<br />
the position. If Australia's policy is irrational, we're<br />
helped very greatly by having a real de-gree of self-sufficiency<br />
through our ownm supplies, and certainly there's some impact<br />
but there'll be much greater impact in some other countries<br />
that are more dependent on imported fuel, and to that extent,<br />
Australia is fortunate. We can also look forward confidently<br />
into the future because we are re-establishing a very positive<br />
exploration and development programme for oil around Australia<br />
as a result of the totality of our policies. And as far as<br />
looking forward to the 1980s, Australia is one of the countries,<br />
I think, that can do so with a real degree of confidence and<br />
optimism. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
