<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>420</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 61/1961 - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/12/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000420.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBAR~ GO: Not for publication or broadcast befo, 6,, 1 -p~ m.<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. R. G. MeRZies<br />
The Government now has a majority in the House of<br />
Representatives, and the probability of a stronger position in<br />
the Senate than at one stage seemed likely.<br />
Ministers met yesterday. They frankly reviewed the<br />
election and its results, and the causes of the set-back the<br />
Government sustained, particularly in Queensland and New South<br />
Wales. Subsequently, we had a meeting with private members, and<br />
were supported in the views which we had formed.<br />
In this brief statement, therefore, I speak with the<br />
authority of all Ministers and Members on the Government side.<br />
. We acknowledge with gratitude and appreciation tbhe<br />
support which we received from those who stood behind us in<br />
difficult and unpopular policies, These policies have already<br />
had, in importLnt fields of the national economy such as the<br />
trade balances anc the arresting of boom inflation, notable<br />
results. But we are quite prepared to face the facts of the<br />
ele ction. It is clear that we have been opposed in the<br />
electorates by many people normally our supportcrs. They<br />
appear to have felt that our economic measures of last year were<br />
too severe; that we acted in too much detachment from those<br />
actually engaged in industry and banking and commerce generally;<br />
that full weight was not given to human considerations; and<br />
that we were not sufficiently conscious of unemployment. W4e<br />
pleaded and plead ' not guilty' to these charges; but the verdict<br />
of the jury almost went against us.<br />
Facing the position in a realistic and democratic way,<br />
we do not propose to take up rigid attitudes, or to ignore the<br />
currents of public opinion. This does not mean that we will<br />
abandon the twin policies of stability and national development<br />
which we have been applying, with, we believe, benefit to<br />
Australia, for the last 12 years. They are vital to true human<br />
progress. But in the application of those policies, modificatia. is<br />
of method and approach should clearly be made.<br />
To this end, we will at the earliest practicable date<br />
set up closer contac ts and discussions with leaders in the<br />
manufacturing and business and banking fields, to secure their<br />
first-hand views on their prob-lems and those of the men and<br />
women employed by them, and their suggestions on how they can be<br />
solved, i'Ie will particularly desire to discuss with<br />
manufacturers the problem of tariffs and imports.<br />
We continue to desire to have full employment, and<br />
will give special and urgent attention to ways and means of<br />
getting rid of such unemployment as now exists.<br />
The question of Northern Development is one on which<br />
there has clearly been great public confusion and misunderstandkr,<br />
I hope that we may have an early opportunity of personal<br />
discussions with State Ministers on this important problem.<br />
We will of course, devote the closest attention to<br />
the problems involved in the Common Market negotiations, with<br />
the object of safeguarding the rural industries, whose<br />
prosperity is so vital for the nation. </p>
<p>2,<br />
Complete economic recovery depends upon the restoring<br />
of private industry to full activity. As the spirit of private<br />
enterprise is the dynamo of national progress, we will look to<br />
the encouragement of that spirit by such means as are available.<br />
The issue still remains a liberal economy or a socialist<br />
economy and we will fight it out with vigour and determination.<br />
We are confident that 1962 can be a great year of advancement<br />
for all. These general observations will, of course, be given a<br />
more detailed expression and application as soon as possible in<br />
the New Year.<br />
CANB.' JRA, December, 1961. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
