<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5132</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY RURAL WRITERS, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/08/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005132.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT WEDNESDAY 29 AUGUST 1979<br />
PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY RURAL WRITERS<br />
CANBERRA Question The President of the Wheatgrower's Federation in Toowoomba<br />
yesterday criticised the Government for not having a cogent<br />
policy onl the supply and regulation, prices, for the<br />
wheat industry. Can you give us-<br />
Prime tMinister<br />
Of fuel?<br />
Question Of fuel, yes.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well, there is a policy, and a comprehensive energy policy,<br />
in broad terms, based on the conservation of a scarce resource<br />
and the promotion of alternative energy forms and the promotion<br />
of maximum exploration and development within Australia. That<br />
has already led to much greater reserves. World parity pricing<br />
is an essential tool in achieving those three policy objectives.<br />
I can well understand the wheat industry, or any rural industry,<br />
any other industry for that matter, the very real need to have<br />
available fuel supplies if there is if you are going to<br />
harvest your crop or you want to spray a cotton crop or you<br />
want to sow your wheat crop yo've just got to have the fuel to<br />
do it.<br />
Question But can you guarantee supplies?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I believe that industries will get the fuel that is necessary.<br />
When ycu say guarantee, nobody can totally guarantee what is<br />
going to happen politically in the Middle East. Now, the<br />
assessments available to us at the moment are that the general<br />
world supply situation is easing a little. That is carried<br />
forward into the coming months. It would be a bold person indeed<br />
who would guarantee there would be no further political instability<br />
in the Middle East. If that happened, nothing on earth would<br />
guarantee supplies. In those circumstances, of course, we would<br />
have to have very firm allocation systems within Australia which<br />
gave priorities in appropriate cases.<br />
All the forecasts we have is that that sort of situation will<br />
not arise. But, you asked me a question of guarantee and you<br />
can't guarantee Middle East politics.<br />
Question What priority would you give, though, to the rural industry. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I have said on many occasions, and I said as much as a month,<br />
six weeks ago, that essential industries would obviously be<br />
given priority. The wheat industry is plainly an essential<br />
industry. There is no doubt about that. We will be announcing<br />
very shortly an industry government committee which will have<br />
a job of recommending supply, or drawing up a national system<br />
of supply and allocation, if. there should be a more stringent<br />
supply situation than we at present believe is likely to emerge.<br />
Question If the demand for fuel continues, have we got sufficient supplies<br />
to meet these demands?<br />
Prime Minister-<br />
What do you mean if the demand continues?<br />
Question We are looking at an increase of 15% 1 think for this, compared<br />
to the first quarter of this year.. Other fuel supplies, the<br />
demand is increasing. Whether people are hoarding or not I<br />
don't know.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
It's not demand increasing by anything like that extent. With<br />
some exceptions, and Avgas is the major one and for reasons which<br />
we are all well aware of, the supply situation has been met.<br />
Now, I have said that the world supply situation over coming<br />
months on present estimates is likely to ease. There always<br />
-has to be . the proviso about political instability in major oil<br />
exporting countries because nobody can guarantee that.<br />
Question The wheat industry, and all our rural industries use fuel of<br />
course for export industries, and they are facing the Canadian<br />
and the Am-erican situation where fuel is cheaper to their<br />
farmers. Is there going to be any moves by your Government<br />
at all to make fuel<br />
Prime Minister<br />
In North America they are starting a system of increasing the<br />
price of fuel and they have announced a policy of introducing<br />
world parity pricing. They are very slow to achieve it. But<br />
there won't be a fully fledged energy policy in North America<br />
until they do. With fuel priced as it is, it is obviously<br />
going to be used much more abundently in a whole host of ways<br />
than if it is priced on a world basis. I think it is worth<br />
noting that some recent sales of wheat which have been undertaken<br />
are pretty much at world record prices. The outlook for the<br />
wheat industry is good, dependent upon seasons. Rains over the<br />
last week have helped ten days have helped in many areas.<br />
But the season has been touch and go through the winter. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Question But will you ever consider having some sort of a price<br />
preferential for the export-orientated industries, as the<br />
price goes up?<br />
Prime minister<br />
It is not only a question of export-orientated industries,<br />
because there are some domestic industries which are just as<br />
important to us as export industries. Some local industries who<br />
operate on a import replacement basis, they'dmake it unnecessary<br />
to import. And other industries and a number of decentralised<br />
industries.-If you were talking about preferential treatment<br />
for industries probably have just as much grounds for claims<br />
-on support as export industries. So once you start down that<br />
path, it becomes very difficult. Nobody has recommended it<br />
to nobody within the Government has recommended it. The<br />
point that ought to be made is that the best part of $ 50 million<br />
is spent on freight equalisation. -There is a further commitment<br />
there. That will be met, which would in fact more than double<br />
Itth ath asc onmomti tmbeenent opno sstihbe lei nittoi ailn tfriogduurcees thtahta t wwiet hihna vet hihsa d. B* udget<br />
but the first part of the commitment, equalising freight to<br />
within 4 a gallon has been met. It is worth noting that<br />
in many cases in inland Australia the price is much more than<br />
that above capital city prices. Where that occurs it is because<br />
the retailer's margin is very much more than the margin in<br />
capital cities. Now we don't have powers to do something about<br />
that, but if any State Government wanted to, they could.<br />
In some cases the retailer's margin is a very high one indeed.<br />
Question<br />
Can you foreshadow when ( inaudible) might be allocated?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The first step for Stage Two no I can't, but that's<br />
a commitment and I am saying that commitment will be met.<br />
There is no doubt about that.<br />
Question During your present term?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
That was the commitment, yes.<br />
Question There has been criticism of the fuel policy from the National<br />
Farmer's Federation and others that more revenue-raiser that the<br />
crude oil levy is more a. revenue-raiser than a conserver of fuel.<br />
If I could lead on to that, that the jump, direct jump into<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Question ( continued)<br />
world parity pricing compared with the gradualism in the<br />
Crawford Report where there won't be ( inaudible) the need<br />
for adjustment, there won't be an IAC reference relating<br />
one, the IAC won't report until the mid-1980s. There seems<br />
to be a real contrast to the Goverment's approach. Is it<br />
anything to do with the $ 2,000 million that is hooked up<br />
in the revenue.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No. It was mainly to do with the fact that until you get<br />
to world parity pricing you can't have an energy policy.<br />
To make a decision you need an energy policy now, as opposed<br />
to having an energy policy in three years time or whatever.<br />
Clearly you've got to go to world parity pricing. It's through<br />
that mechanism that you can achieve greater exploration and<br />
greater development. It's through that mechanism that you<br />
will encourage people to divert into other forms of energy.<br />
It is through that mechanism that you will encourage conservation<br />
of a scarce resource. You are not going to achieve any of<br />
those three major objectives without world parity pricing.<br />
There are other things, obviously, in tax incentives and<br />
investment incentives to encourage people to move away from<br />
oil fuels, oil-based fuels. There have been a number of elements<br />
in the total energy policy which are moving in that direction.<br />
Question If the farmers do go over to other forms of energy, will there<br />
be moves by<br />
Prime Minister<br />
It's not just a question of farmers. There obviously,<br />
because I think in many parts of rural Australia the capacity<br />
to go to other forms of energy is pretty limited. I am well<br />
aware of that.<br />
Question If they go to gasahol there is a problem of excise. Is your<br />
Government doing any about the alcohol excise, because if they<br />
make stills they are contravening the excise, customs...<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well, they are not at the moment. Nobody is making it.<br />
Question They are going to be. There was a report in yesterday's paper<br />
that there is a still going to be marketed in the next couple<br />
of months in Australia and there is<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well, I haven't seen a report of that. </p>
<p>Question So nothing is being done at the present moment to make it<br />
legal for people to make their own fuel, help pay an excise.<br />
Prime minister<br />
Alcohol? Question<br />
Alcohol. Pri= me Minister<br />
Well I haven't heard that proposed.<br />
Question Could I move onto the Crawford Report It s eems that there<br />
is never a right time to reduce protection and while the<br />
Government has embraced the thrust of the Crawford Report.,<br />
the Government isn't apparently grasping the nettle, at this<br />
time. Is there ever a right time to reduce protection?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
You can never take dramatic steps in that area unless you<br />
are prepared to pay a very high price for it. in terms of<br />
jobs lost and dislocation to industry. We are not prepared<br />
to pay that sort of price for it, no. I don't think any<br />
Australians would wan t to. One of the best markets for<br />
Australi-a's exporters, or primary producers, is the domestic<br />
market. If you are not going to look after that domestic<br />
market and make sure the domestic market grows, then the<br />
position of Australia's rural producers will certainly be<br />
weakened. So that's one point. I don't think Australia's<br />
farmers want us to say New Zealand lamb can come in without<br />
any restraint, New Zealand butter can come in without any<br />
restraint. There is an unwritten agreement, or understanding,<br />
between ourselves and New Zealand in these particular matters.<br />
that New Zealand iJs not going to put our farmers under too<br />
pDr essure in these areas. New Zealanders sometimes wonder<br />
why they should be under that restraint. The question of<br />
protection can work in more than one way.<br />
Question A lot of people argue, a lot of industry argues, that protection<br />
per se does not protect jobs. In fact counterproductive.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I know people argue that.<br />
Question Bradmill? ./ 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think a lot of this depends upon degree. If you take<br />
these arguments to the extreme I think they will all become<br />
false.<br />
Question But in the textile industry, big companies like Bradmill<br />
apparently are grasping the nettle and they've seen the writing<br />
on -tne wall and they are moving in the sort of direction<br />
which critics like the National Farmer's Federation would see<br />
as th'-. e right direction.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well, they are moving in the right direction but I don't think<br />
they would be wa nting to operate with no protection.<br />
The other side -to this coin of course, is that in terms of<br />
world protection Australia is one of the lowest protected<br />
countries in the world. That might be hard for some farmers<br />
to accept, but when you look at the new forms of protection<br />
in Europe and ! Lmerica and Japan which are not practiced in<br />
Australia, then what we might do with tariffs or quotas can<br />
be quite puny by comparison with the totality of the protective<br />
devices used in many countries of the world.<br />
T. 1he other way we can look at this question of course is access<br />
to our markets. ASEAN countries, developing countries, have<br />
a better access to this market than they do to any other<br />
developed country.<br />
Question wonder if 1985 is just a bit too far away to expect<br />
the IAC to bring down a report and the Government to consider<br />
that report.<br />
Question 1935 is not ver-y far away~ but is it as far off as that?<br />
Question<br />
Why the timing?<br />
Question It won't get a reference until 1981. I am told it will take<br />
two or three years to ( inaudible).<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think it's too early to make that sort of judgement.<br />
Matters are under reference by the IAC and the Government took<br />
the view that we ought to have those reports and be able to<br />
make decisions on those before further references are made.<br />
./ 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
In all of this, the primary industries need to understand<br />
that the maip protection we can provide them is access to<br />
markets overseas through trade negotiations. We've been<br />
remarkably successful in that. And making sure that inflation<br />
stays as low as we can get it, certainly below that of our<br />
major trading partners. They are the things of greatest<br />
importance to rural industries. On top of that, other forms<br />
of taxation incentive, investment allowance, abolition of<br />
probate and gift duties so far as the Commonwealth is concerned.<br />
These are all benefits to the rural industries of a kind that<br />
T h-n have not been equalled by any other Government. In<br />
addition to that, it is worth noting the special depreciation<br />
allowance has reappeared in the last Budget. in relation to<br />
( inaudible) conservation. Special depreciation allowances<br />
was one form of benefit which farmers certainly appreciated<br />
very much before it was knocked off by the Labor Party.<br />
Question It was being criticised in the last week as coming too late<br />
because there was an excess, particularly in wheat, on production<br />
last year which meant they had to make a storage last year not<br />
this year.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
If they get another good harvest this year, they might have to<br />
make more storage. I've got no doubt that every benefit<br />
would be a greater benefit if it was introduced earlier, but I<br />
doubt-if any farmer would say they would prefer to be without<br />
benefit now that it has been introduced. If they want to, it<br />
is perfectly open to them to ask their tax accountants<br />
not to make allowance for it when they put in their tax returns.<br />
I don't really think anyone will do that.<br />
Question In the Budget, with reference to the fact that the Wheat Board,<br />
may again be asked to go commercial... ( inaudible).<br />
Prime M, 4inister<br />
It may well be, but it won't be at any cost to wheatgrowers<br />
and ( inaudible). It is an important instrument in monetary<br />
control.<br />
Question Do you see this as a forerunner of any further steps in<br />
that direction?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
What do you mean any further steps?<br />
Question Is it likely that the Wheat Board may be asked to go commercial<br />
permanently, on a permanent basis? / 8 </p>
<p>-8<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think it is useful to have it as a flexible ingtrument<br />
in monetary control. It is helpful in the fight against<br />
inflation. It is a very large increase in the money supply,<br />
as it was done in the past. The main thing in the Government's<br />
view, is to protect wheat farmers against any additional cost.<br />
Well, they have been fully protected so as far as the Wheat<br />
farmer is concerned, I can't see cause to worry one way or the<br />
other. You ought to prefer us to do it in the way that contributes<br />
best i-n the control of inflation.<br />
Question Next week, next Thursday, the counter-cyclical talks with the<br />
Un ited States will be held. What sort of stance are we going<br />
to take. Are you going to be adamant about requiring the<br />
1.3 billion.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
We will be arguing for it as firmly as we can. I don't think<br />
we can disclose what we are going to do or what we are going to<br />
say before we get into the negotiations.<br />
Ques-t--ion<br />
( Inaudible) Australian Wool Corporation, the Chairmanship,<br />
would you be seeking a grower or a public servant.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The best possible person for the job. I am not putting a tag on<br />
it or a label on it. The best possible person for the job. It is<br />
a--very. important job. -The WooV-Corporationisoneof the-great<br />
-success stories which had full support from the Government, where<br />
it didn't get very much support from the previous Government. I<br />
think everyone remembers the time when it needed that support<br />
and the price was lowered by 5O in a most damaging way. But the<br />
confidence that has been shown by giving it support, and taking<br />
that supportIL forward into the future, has built up an underlying<br />
strength_ 4n the 7market, or contributed to building up because many<br />
other things are also involved, which has put a strength in-to<br />
the wool market and as we believe at the moment, a stability which<br />
hadn't been there for a very very long while.<br />
Question Do you think it is possible to increase the type of money offered<br />
to say the Chairman of the Wool Corporation, to attract a better<br />
sort when I say better sort of man, a man from outside? / 19 </p>
<p>9-<br />
Prime Minister-<br />
I haven't heard that that is going to be a problem in<br />
getting a good man. Obviously you've got to do what's<br />
necessary in getting the best person for the job. But I<br />
haven't heard that put as a problem.<br />
QuestLLion There is some concern in the rural sector that the $ 4 billion<br />
in short-term overseas borrowing, for the short term deficit<br />
problem, if that's not repaid soon well if the Governmnent<br />
doesn't have to repay there will be some sort of Federal<br />
revaluation. Could you give us some guidance-<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I'm not going to speculate one way or another about the value<br />
of the dollar, but it ought to be noted I think that the<br />
mechanism for management of the dollar has been altered~ over<br />
the last couple or three years. It now happens smoothly, and<br />
gently. The alarms and excursions and speculations of past<br />
days seem to be gone. I think it is again one of the great<br />
success stories. The dollar is much stronger and I would hope<br />
everyone would welcome that. I well understand the concern<br />
of exporters in relation to these matters, but I am not going<br />
to enter into speculation about the dollar. We all ought to be<br />
encouraged by the fact that the dollar has strengthened, which<br />
means that overseas confidence in Australia is much greater.<br />
Still, 1 the most important policy for farmers is a policy to<br />
ficht inflation anda policy to make sure that what inflation<br />
we do have is less than a number of other major countries<br />
overseas. We have been successful in that. In addition, we've<br />
developed a range of special policies to assist Australia's<br />
farmers and pastoralists which I believe have not been equalled<br />
by any other Government. 0 00---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
