<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5663</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/10/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005663.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 5: 00 pmn<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, .11 OCTOBER, 1981<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
We live in a troubled and uncertain world, in which it sometimes<br />
seems that stability and a clear sense of direction are almost<br />
the exception rather than the rule.<br />
The assassination of President Sadat is not only a tragedy for<br />
his country and for stability in the Middle East, but it also<br />
serves to remind us of the damage that is caused when<br />
unreasonableness and division are allowed to take first place in<br />
human affairs.<br />
In 1977, after 30 years of continual warfare in the Middle East,<br />
President Sadat made his historic and courageous visit to<br />
Jerusalem to address the Knesset, and thus opened the path to<br />
negotiation in the quest for peace. And then in 1979, the<br />
Egyptian/ Israeli peace treaty Teas signed. I said at the time<br />
that the world hoped that work on a comprehensive Middle East<br />
settlement would proceed in the aftermath of that treaty.<br />
But now, while itis obviously too early to assess the full<br />
consequences that will flow from President Sadat's assassination,<br />
the world clear!-, has to cope with the aftermath of a tragedy.<br />
Not everyone, as we know, agreed with what President Sadat was<br />
doing, although everyone must surely respect him for his courage<br />
and his objectives of peace and stability and certainly no<br />
benefits will follow from what has taken place.<br />
The assassination of President Sadat is not an isolated incident.<br />
There have been at least five other assassinations and attempted<br />
assassinations of world leaders during this year. It is never easy<br />
to learn lessons or draw conclusions from this kind of madness<br />
and terror. Some say thaL the world has lost its way and certainly<br />
there are many people in the world who are disturbingly uncertain<br />
about where-the course of progress really lies. But by the same<br />
token, there are other people who are so fanatical in their own<br />
convictions and aspirations that they lack a sense of balance.<br />
In a troubled world, we surely need a sense of our own direction<br />
and objectives as a nation, and we need above all to be realistic.<br />
Wie need to be willing to face up to problems, and confront issues<br />
head on. There is a need for firmness, together with an open<br />
and frank approach. PRIME MINISTER / 2 I ' S </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The civilised discussion of major hriman issues requires more<br />
support than ever before. That is why the value of meetings<br />
such as the Commonwealth Heads of Government in Melbourne<br />
cannot be over-estimated. The Commonwealth is, as President<br />
Kaunda of Zambia said in Melbourne, a civilised association<br />
of nations. Around the conference table and in private<br />
discussions, more than a quarter of the world's leaders proposedI<br />
and considered ways of making the world -a better place to live iun.<br />
The Commonwealth has, over the years, and particularly in relation<br />
to Zimbabwe and Namibia, displayed vision and courage in<br />
seeking practical means for the settLlement of international<br />
conflicts. At the Melbourne meeting, difficult-rnd contentious<br />
issues were tackled and firm specific statements resulted.<br />
There was a real commitment to build on the good will that exists<br />
within the Commonwealth, in order to bring practical proposals<br />
to the dialogue about issues of poverty and development and<br />
to other problems as well.<br />
I am proud that such a successful conference was held in 0<br />
Australia, and our visitors so enjoyed the friendliness which<br />
they encountered here that they have become ambassadors for<br />
Australia. The Commonwealth leaders, with their determined practicality,<br />
their refusal to be distracted from the central themes, and<br />
their willingness to discuss issues openly with each other,<br />
have set an example for others'to follow in the vision and<br />
sincerity of their leadership. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
