<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10966</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS AT THE FOUNDATION SERVICE                ST JAMES CHAPEL, ANGLICAN RETIREMENT VILLAGES                CASTLE HILL, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/04/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much, Mrs Hewetson; to your Grace, the Archbishop of</p>
<p> Sydney; to Bishop King. to Mr Brunsdon and to other distinguished</p>
<p> guests, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>Janette and I are particularly happy to share this very special occasion</p>
<p> with you because it marks a very important project which is a very</p>
<p> impressive part of a long tradition of service to older Australians.</p>
<p>And I want, on behalf of the Government, to pay tribute to the work</p>
<p> of Anglican Retirement Villages, to salute the place of what used</p>
<p> to be called and commonly understood in Sydney as the Mowll Village</p>
<p> but is now broadly understood as Anglican Retirement Villages, the</p>
<p> tremendous contribution that you have collectively made to the quality</p>
<p> of providing a secure, compassionate, supportive environment for older</p>
<p> Australians.</p>
<p>I don't think one could find, anywhere in our country, a better</p>
<p> example of enlightened, compassionate care and a congenial, supportive</p>
<p> community environment for older people than you can find here at Castle</p>
<p> Hill. It brings together the tradition of Christian caring with a</p>
<p> recognition of the importance of maintaining links with family, friends</p>
<p> and the community.</p>
<p>As the representative of the Government, as the Prime Minister of</p>
<p> Australia, let me say to all of those involved with Anglican Retirement</p>
<p> Villages and particularly those associated with the splendid new state-of-the-art</p>
<p> nursing home, whose foundation of which we mark today, can I say a</p>
<p> very warm word of thanks and gratitude for what you have done to set</p>
<p> an example to so many others in the aged care sector with the sort</p>
<p> of work and the sort of complex that you began to establish here just</p>
<p> 40 years ago and has now grown to, here at Castle Hill, something</p>
<p> that care for, in the order of 1,500 people. And throughout Australia</p>
<p> generally, Anglican Retirement Villages cares for some 3,500 Australians.</p>
<p>Caring for our senior citizens, older Australians, whatever description</p>
<p> we may choose to use, is very much a shared endeavour. The Government</p>
<p> cannot do it on its own. The churches and their welfare arms cannot</p>
<p> do it on their own and individuals cannot do it on their own either.</p>
<p> And what we need is a partnership, a shared endeavour, between those</p>
<p> three arms of activity.</p>
<p>The Government has ongoing and basic responsibilities. Community organisations,</p>
<p> particularly the churches, do a magnificent job bringing their special</p>
<p> skills of compassion and care and understanding and those things related</p>
<p> to the human spirit, which are so important in providing a rounded,</p>
<p> caring environment. And then, of course, we need the contribution</p>
<p> of individuals. But the three have to work together.</p>
<p>There are some in our community who can make a contribution to their</p>
<p> caring. There are many who can't. And we must always have an</p>
<p> approach to aged care that looks after those people who cannot afford</p>
<p> to support themselves in any way. And that is what makes the approach</p>
<p> of Anglican Retirement Villages such a fine example of aged care within</p>
<p> our community. You have, I understand, here at Castle Hill some 30</p>
<p> per cent of your residents who, because of their circumstances, do</p>
<p> not make any personal contribution. And that is how it should be in</p>
<p> any kind of decent, caring, compassionate society.</p>
<p>A few days ago I launched, on behalf of the Government, a $270 million</p>
<p> commitment to the aged care sector which is designed to do a number</p>
<p> of things and particularly designed to provide more assistance for</p>
<p> those Australians who wish to remain longer in their own homes. And</p>
<p> that is an example of one feature of our responsibility in the aged</p>
<p> care sector. We have a responsibility - and let me say to you that</p>
<p> we will always discharge it faithfully and fully - we have a responsibility,</p>
<p> and we'll always meet that responsibility, to support the provision</p>
<p> of high quality aged care, residential facilities for those Australians</p>
<p> who want it. And the example of your village is one that we would</p>
<p> like to see duplicated all over Australia.</p>
<p>We also have a responsibility to provide additional resources and</p>
<p> additional services to those Australians who wish to remain in their</p>
<p> own home environment as long as possible. And what you need is a blended,</p>
<p> united approach towards aged care within our society. An approach</p>
<p> which recognises the changes that have overtaken society, that recognises</p>
<p> that where as 50 years ago large complexes of residential care were</p>
<p> not something that we had contemplated. But over the passage of a</p>
<p> couple of generations they have come to be part and parcel of our</p>
<p> life. And what we must do is to make them congenial and give them</p>
<p> a great communal spirit, which is so obvious here at Castle Hill.</p>
<p> And it's the example of that caring, communal environment and</p>
<p> the countless examples I have, as a politician, of people saying to</p>
<p> me how they have found so much friendship and so much support and</p>
<p> so much caring and so much love and compassion in retirement villages</p>
<p> of this kind. And it is a very important off-shoot of the life of</p>
<p> Australia and the caring for the elderly in Australian community of</p>
<p> the last couple of generations.</p>
<p>We are, as a society, living longer, We're healthier. Our aspirations</p>
<p> of life in our retirement years are greater and our horizons are broader</p>
<p> than used to be the case. And that is something that we should all</p>
<p> welcome. And can I say, as an Australian who grew up in the 1950s</p>
<p> and somebody who is a little younger than many of your here but not,</p>
<p> perhaps, as young as some others in the audience, can I say how much</p>
<p> I believe that my generation and younger generations of Australians,</p>
<p> how much we owe to the generation which is so largely represented</p>
<p> in this congregation today. Because in the main, you are the generation</p>
<p> that sustained and defended and protected and saved our nation during</p>
<p> World War II, whether it was on the battlefield or on the home front.</p>
<p> And the generations of Australians that came after you owe you a debt</p>
<p> of gratitude that can never be fully repaid. And one of the small</p>
<p> ways in which that debt of gratitude can be repaid is, of course,</p>
<p> to ensure that the choices that you want and your generations wants</p>
<p> for aged care, whether it be in your own home or be in a marvellous</p>
<p> retirement village such as this, that those choices are fully available.</p>
<p>Can I salute, on behalf of the Government, the work of the Anglican</p>
<p> Church, the work, in particular, of Anglican Retirement Villages.</p>
<p> Giving good government and delivering a good and fair society, which</p>
<p> is what all of us want as we move into the 21st Century, does involve</p>
<p> that shared endeavour of which I spoke. No government has either the</p>
<p> wit or the resources to do all of it on its own. No individual can</p>
<p> survive the ups and downs and the turmoil of life without companionship</p>
<p> and support from others within the community. And no organisation,</p>
<p> no matter what the strength of its spiritual being and essence might</p>
<p> be, can do things all on its own without the support of individuals</p>
<p> and without, where necessary, the support of its government. So we</p>
<p> do need that shared endeavour. And the care of the aged is an area</p>
<p> where we can give expression to that shared endeavour, that partnership,</p>
<p> with each of us playing its rightful role.</p>
<p>I thank the Anglican Church on behalf of the Government and the people</p>
<p> of Australia for the magnificent contribution that it is making to</p>
<p> the aged care sector. I say, on behalf of the Government, that we</p>
<p> will always play our role to the full, we will always be generous,</p>
<p> we'll always be compassionate and supportive and we'll always</p>
<p> understand the importance of the lives of older Australians of the</p>
<p> kind of environment that is so evident here.</p>
<p>I congratulate the Anglican Retirement Villages. I thank you for your</p>
<p> contribution. I wish all of you well. And, particularly, I wish all</p>
<p> of those associated with the magnificent new nursing home project</p>
<p> which will provide state-of-the-art care and facilities that I know</p>
<p> that all Australians would hope to see available to their parents</p>
<p> and their loved ones. And I thank you very warmly for having me amongst</p>
<p> you today.</p>
<p>Thank you</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
