<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6065</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENT OF PERMANENT HEADS AND HEADS OF AUTHORITIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/03/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006065.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 25 MARCH 1983<br />
Appointment of Permanent Heads and Heads of Authorities<br />
The Executive Council has today approved the following<br />
appointments:<br />
Mr W. A. McKinnon, CBE, formerly Chairman of the Industries<br />
Assistance Commission, has been appointed Secretary,<br />
Department of Immigration and Ethnic Affairs, replacing<br />
Mr J. L. Menadue whose appointment as Secretary, Department<br />
of the Special Minister of State, has already been announced.<br />
Mr M. H. Codd, formerly Secretary, Department of Employment<br />
and Industrial Relations, has been appointed Chairman of the<br />
Industries Assistance Commission.<br />
Mr H. B. MacDonald, formerly Deputy Secretary, Department of<br />
Administrative Services, has been appointed Secretary,<br />
Department of Sport, Recreation and Tourism.<br />
Sir Peter Lawler, OBE, formerly Secretary, Department of<br />
Administrative Services, has been appointed Special Adviser,<br />
Department of Administrative Services pending appointment to<br />
a diplomatic post.<br />
Mr K. N. Jones, CBE, formerly Secretary, Department of Education<br />
and Youth Affairs, has been appointed Secretary, Department<br />
of Administrative Services.<br />
Dr P. S. Wilenski,. Professor, Social Justice Project,<br />
Australian National University, has been appointed Secretary,<br />
Department of Education and Youth Affairs.<br />
The vacant positions of Secretary, Department of Housing and<br />
Construction and Secretary, Department of Employment and<br />
Industrial Relations'<br />
will be the subject of a further announcement. Meanwhile,<br />
Mr R. M. Taylor will continue to act as Secretary, Department<br />
of Housing and Construction and Mr A. D. Fogarty, currently<br />
Acting Deputy Secretary, Department of Employment and Industrial<br />
Relations, has been appointed Acting Secretary.<br />
I., </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
