<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>334</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES, AT CIVIC RECEPTION, TOWN HALL TOWNSVILLE, ON 20TH JUNE 1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/06/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000334_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEiECI 3Y ñ THE PRIME MINISTE~ R TKE RT. HON.<br />
ii 1' iE. NZIES~ AT .,* rVIC RtiCEP'lION, TdN<br />
HALL, TOJ1{ AIILLE, ON 20TH JUNE. 161<br />
Sir, There is just one thing that you said in your very generous<br />
speech to which I take e.
said. ( Laughter) N ow i wouild have you know that I am a sort of<br />
expatriated Victoifian beclUnse I live in Canberra, but Australia is my<br />
PLarisif. Thie i-r-ime M. inister of Australia must be a ueenslandec, a<br />
New 3outh . Jelshrnan, a 3outh itustraiian, a Vict6rian and so on right<br />
round the Corm~ onwealth. So let'' s , et thie record straight. My<br />
responsibilities in r.' l ition to queensiand are every bit as . gre-t as<br />
my rcsporisibilities Lo any other part of the Commaonwealthi. Indeed,<br />
they are rather retrbecause 1* ha-ie always, as you know, believed<br />
profoundly ;:: hat the develop. ent of this J3tate wh-ich is relatively an<br />
unde-. eloped 3-Gale, is one of the great, exciting tast~ s of the future.<br />
It becomes all the more e citing as the character of our<br />
economy chan!, es. ' Aheirc vas a time, well withain my memory at any rate,<br />
when we exported urimary products in a fairly orthodox fashion, we<br />
imported lot of m: nrnf uactured -oods, a-nd we madb some ourselves, But<br />
as t*( he years hLave _. one by and as thie pressure of events hAas developed,<br />
this country of ours 1 as uecome a remarkably viell-b~ al ' ncedl one<br />
economically. 0Oir Industrial develo,), enL has been p) henomenal; and<br />
beczcuse it iias be * n neloi, unal we iioif have ti capa_, city Lo iti-stand the<br />
stres.-es of int., rnitiorial 3conoiriic ev,. ents .! iuch :-rEat. er thian wel1ad<br />
years ago. tiat is r,-y Iconsta; Itly ant to remind ieonle that the<br />
greaL depression of thle ttiirties *. rhiich did not oe--in in " tustralia hi<br />
in the United Jt:: uces ofL J_ r_ oic r-easons thiat i co-iid -liscuss with<br />
yoll, couald not hap) pen tLoday. It could not h appen and I don't say<br />
that simply becaus I f. -rime M, 1inister it could not h-afpen under<br />
any Government t. hat took advantag e of the knowledge that hnas been<br />
gained over the intervening_ period, and . cooLk advon , a e of the fact<br />
that we are now a rirxiydevi/ eiopeu. Couzitry Onl both primary and<br />
secondary sides of idstry.<br />
But t1ie ! gr at t'ltat no; J -uts imiore and wiore, pressure on<br />
our minds is how we can :-void tu--e pi) i," odical rises in th,, e bala~ nce of<br />
paymients, the fluctuatios in our overisoas ' unds. Thtie re are two or<br />
three bankers here t iis ;: orin en, se -1 h-aie met them, and if they<br />
were hc--vin g an u~ o~ cLi! 2uoment ! id not just saying " No, !' in sorry,<br />
it's the credit suueozety odtell yo itat tne move . Aent up and<br />
do-vn ofc our int(-rn ulinal reserves has at direct acid profound effect on<br />
La n'-in-poli,-cy inside A trla-bec:,. ase it affects the liquidity of<br />
th1e7 ban!-, s. .1' ien You a~ thJ a run-down of your overseas funds, you will<br />
expect liquidity of thie ar.. zs to oe teiidin g to dry up in<br />
Aus tralia. So we !-ll hra ie a tremendoiis inter~ est in ( ureserJ: Ln ga<br />
reasonable balance of .' aYiients in our trade . zith th:-e rest of the world.<br />
And our trade aith uh.-, e rest of thie cforld is enormous. ihere is no<br />
other country in t. he voend that could compare, peir capita, withair<br />
trade with the rest', of tnie world not one. Our export u. rade, our<br />
import trade, are both en) ormously sigiificant in world terms, ta<br />
absolute terms. Plore and more, its ftou dy this problem, we realise,<br />
don't we, that w., e must liave more ex ports, a -greateir va: riety of<br />
exports. You must, so far-as you can, insulate yourself ag_, ainst the<br />
violen't fluctuation that ., ay be produced by drought or by a<br />
fluctuatuion in the world's wool price. . iVe are doin-g what we can<br />
about that. 0,1l, in thi-e last 48 hiours have I been p-utting myself in<br />
communication w. ith the administration of the United States on the old<br />
question of the American tariff on Australian waool, which I venture to<br />
describe as a perfectly foolish tariff since it protects an American<br />
wool-growing industry w'iich-is not tremendously efficient that is the<br />
understatement of the year. It protects it at the expense of<br />
Australia, the ctreatestwo-rwn nation, the -reatest grower of<br />
fine wool in the wJorld. And to hiave a tariff on our wool passing into<br />
the United States is really very foolish. I hope that having regard </p>
<p>to current neg-otiations the light lay be seen in that great and<br />
generous country. If '. ie could secur1-some m., odification of that tariff<br />
we would in one stroke do a great deal to improve a little andidien to<br />
staullize the price of wool in Austvr,-, lia. This would be tretmendous.<br />
Jut tliere Lre two other iterts on which our export income can<br />
be built up, I believe, in the relatively shnort term, very<br />
s i~ ni f icar t ly. 0Oie is in miinerals; " ite othler is in the exp ort of<br />
M eat. ; And both of thfes; e concerin ! 4iueensland as perhaps they concern,<br />
to 4th e samte de free, no ot; her Sta-t; e.<br />
d ent P) iomt sa. 11m excited about Nit. Isa. I think<br />
thiis is a phnenomenal clevelopL,,. ent.. 3ut wo t're o:, ly scratching'-the<br />
surface of our rric~ i rEso ~ rces yet. 8~ y t: ie time the geophysicists<br />
and w. e neologis -s t elone Their stuff I believe that are . oing<br />
to ex fiose ; mineral 1veso : Ces 1i ljstrali1a i iicii ., ill be t-uite<br />
t r, idou s. In 2 VeCA,; i~'. . n inl t'a of lead itad zinc, we<br />
thin. i_ erfls of pop-per, ! e 1t inki. in tern-) of bauIxite; -ie are<br />
be -in i i to) ti&gt; if. tent..:-Of ; Jatritd 1' e ha-s, ultimately of<br />
metol" Llc aiunrinitz:. Wh'. ese thiin,; s, :) rcvJded we have thie n! t a-d<br />
Timaginat ion to cope tht.; it emri ll ei produce a-deve-, lop.) ent<br />
not on-'! y Ill 1t.: e SKrAu ~~ P,. Lf&gt; IS ve~ ry importa.-ut, Lout a<br />
d , vlo;,, ent in thie intarn e: ein i . i-ch J ll rcitove rom<br />
Austrclia this partic-olar ( uroblem of the,( fluctuatin-* balances of<br />
payments nd t ; e b., lances of intern, icnal reserves. This, I { hink,<br />
is tremendously important. And when a born Victori-an tnd an Fedopted<br />
Canberran comes up to th-e noith: uenmsland you maustn ' t thn: that he<br />
is bein. g entirely uns3elfi. sh I kno; youi : tould neveiT Laccuseany<br />
politici,. n of that ustn't hei is 9: tirely unselfsh: the<br />
fact is he is ; Avlono l: over &amp; iv L rt of iuthc li e<br />
believes viil]-yield, inie2ure n o h reatest dividends for<br />
th!, e riatioi,. Lou i. ustn't 50 eio ile LutC iet, " InacL tnis is mt in<br />
our .1inds: it is iaosere nt fron zm-y own. mind for more thlan 24+ hours.<br />
tiosw . urnin--2ua our Iocl-1 newspaper and Iread it<br />
wvith ~ radv;: inta . go. I tookl lile to * 2-omiiiment ', dito.-oecause<br />
it h&amp; an imi ense . y 1.111_ e OVV 1u, so . tas c+, oncecrned, seemed<br />
to hiave an u1. comiutonly, -ii -i~ e o * ac: c' o -~ elilco wvs like<br />
mysel e noL 1 dc-u'I I.~ e d ocil : 4 iery * htfu leading<br />
artcleon thie questio' ' oc O1cnt jjt h o. censusso2-1. rether<br />
conice. n _ ny Xustraliaci , b ecl-1) rts LtLCg 20 &gt; 0o inket'S of<br />
th-e old * corld: o :~ n;~ tso ~ oe<br />
1 rIi sñ tri rPSed1,7 I to roln : u. lf 6t ozen<br />
newspa s tl It4 ir0 tj I-. ro o :-ii. he i-t: ln nited<br />
ingdo;-. sivoull -ntoe-iry Oari Jrtion i, ket is sonet viag hat h-as<br />
suddenl: iJsen. I Asueyou i, 3I-~ dnl isen. I know<br />
there iL. s an ' r: vetin the " ouse of ' Ji: OiSTe oth2_ i day nd this<br />
ga~ ve rise, very propeirly, to 6ret. e:-. 1 of'L specIUltir about it.<br />
3J_ 1t i f i t is aiv co,. fori; to _. nyboDdy 1' 3. :, ua. ld tell y ou t ha t th i s i s a<br />
L~ roblein -hat hias been .4iUC! . cssi-, a. jsct. ieen t+, y 6ovcarxalen aid the<br />
. iovercn: m-ent of the riite'J 1ing: daim, A-11 . ie last tlhrec years. Iis a<br />
problem that I have i-iyseif discussed in !) erson witi . denauer in<br />
German and witlh de + daul'le in 1'' rance, atnd *: iith representatives of the<br />
Governmaent in Italy. The last timie T was in London w., e hadI L. v. ery<br />
zpc. lconfer-ence about it. It i! s as a r-! sult of th-at ( coli1-vre,<br />
some mionths go, that. at this very ii _ tent. Astralian offlicialsane<br />
sittin. downm with thne United :, ingdom officials dis.: ussin-'. he essential<br />
details of this mattter. ^-ll this was atrra nged sotme t(. ime a: o. I-t is<br />
perhaps my fault thlat -then -7 nae r g. ents to onduct wihanother<br />
Governm-Pent in th. a Aritish, '_' OfEll' : 2Jaltii I lilke to conduct them<br />
priv-ately and not . ioli ely. They . tre vary familiar ,-ith our lbs.<br />
I attended ( a contference in Loildon this lasL'* tiine andnede<br />
two tiiin-s per ~ ectly cle, r. Tihe firsl, is thlat thle Unrited iigo<br />
sh-ould not agree, even in pjriinciple, to go in to thie Lmropean mmon </p>
<p>Market without haviri,-prior effective consultation with the<br />
Comonwcalth countries concerned, incltudinz, in particular, Aun ralia.<br />
That is agreed, an. tiere will be rio commitment, even in principle,<br />
. until these consulta : ions ha ve -oncluded.<br />
In the second pl.. ace I said th-at in order to bring the<br />
GLeneral problem dotmi to brasis taicks it ,-ias essential that component<br />
officials of theirs n' 1 of o irs shiould, in fact, ' ork out in detail<br />
uha intcres ts of ours iniight ba affected, wiliat e/. orts of ours might<br />
be concrrnedl tfh,-t -,: rice ue t oulo. require to be paid in ter-ms of<br />
entry to the 3uropean marle-P aiid to tile market in tUhe United Kingdom<br />
before we % ri ld : say " Yes". iJou. r tiis is a very practical approach.<br />
What I wiould iil-e to emolmhsise to you is that t'ie problem<br />
is not problem of * h'iolesaie diiscuss. io, ut of ratail discussion.<br />
' here ., rc very good reasons Zo iited ii! dorn should iant to be<br />
in the Eu. iropean area.<br />
( Tapn! i,. comv'ie: Ie) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
