<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41461</transcript-id>
    <title>Governor General to Deliver Australia&#039;s National Statement to the United Nations Human Rights Council</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/02/2018</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>We are pleased to announce that the Governor-General, His Excellency General the Honourable Sir Peter Cosgrove AK MC (Ret’d) will travel to Switzerland from 25 to 28 February to represent Australia at the High-Level Segment of the 37th session of the United Nations Human Rights Council in Geneva.</p>
<p>The Governor-General will deliver Australia’s National Statement to the High-Level Segment during our first session as a new Human Rights Council member. The High-Level Segment is the most prominent event on the Council’s annual calendar.</p>
<p>Australia took its seat on the Council, which is the world’s peak body responsible for promoting and protecting human rights, on 1 January 2018.</p>
<p>Through our membership Australia will deliver on its commitments to advance human rights globally. Our priorities will include empowering women and girls to reach their full potential; freedom of expression; and promoting good governance and democratic institutions.</p>
<p>The Governor-General will also meet United Nations Secretary-General His Excellency Mr António Guterres and United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights Prince Zeid Ra’ad Al Hussein.</p>
<p>As part of a wider bilateral visit, Sir Peter will meet with the President of the Swiss Confederation HE Dr Alain Berset. The Governor-General will also attend a commemorative service at the Commonwealth War Graves in Vevey, visit the European Organisation for Nuclear Research (CERN) in Geneva and meet with Australian business representatives in Zurich.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
