<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7374</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPENING OF THE BURDEKIN FALLS DAM BURDEKIN - 14 AUGUST 1988 </title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/08/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007374.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING OF THE BURDEKIN FALLS DAR<br />
BURDEKIN 14 AUGUST 1988<br />
For almost a century the dream of a dam upon the Burdekin<br />
River has inspired generations of people with the promise of<br />
new prosperity for North Queensland.<br />
Today we mark the realisation of that dream the completion<br />
of the Burdekin Dam and the formal opening of a new era for<br />
the people of this State.<br />
In opening this dam today I pay unreserved tribute to all<br />
those who have planned and built it.<br />
And I take unqualified pride in the fact that throughout the<br />
long saga of the Burdekin Dam, it wad'Federal Labor<br />
Governments which have led the way, and which have paid the<br />
bill, in the interests of North Queenslanders.<br />
In 1889 that is, ninety nine years ago W. H. McKinnon<br />
presented his engineer's report which for the first time<br />
proposed a large dam on the Burdekin river to irrigate the<br />
surrounding land.<br />
It was the Chifley Labor Government which set up a joint<br />
Commonwealth-State Ministerial Committee to investigate<br />
northern development. That was in 1945 ninety nine years<br />
after the Burdekin was discovered and named by Leichardt.<br />
Chifley's committee selected the proposal for a dam at the<br />
Burdekin Falls as the one most suited for further<br />
development. But various promises by successive conservative Governments<br />
came to nothing.<br />
It was not until 1974 that, with the decision of the Whitlam<br />
Labor Government, the first Commonwealth funds were granted<br />
for water resource development in the Burdekin region.<br />
Three million dollars was allocated for the building of the<br />
Clare Weir, a pilot scheme-for future large scale<br />
development. A further one million dollars was allocated to<br />
investigate the Burdekin Basin's potential for development. 1093 </p>
<p>2.<br />
in 1976 a Townsville resident and Labor Alderman called Ted<br />
Lindsay helped establish the Townsville-Burdekin Regional<br />
Water Committee which went on to play a major ro lei n<br />
advancing the cause of the Burdekin Dam.<br />
It must be a matter for great satisfaction for Ted, who is<br />
of course now my colleague the Member for Herbert, to be<br />
here today to witness this ceremony in the knowledge that<br />
his hard work and dedication helped bring it about.<br />
Because in 1983 the ALP promised to build the dam, and when<br />
we were elected to office we reaffirmed and subsequently<br />
fulfilled that commitment.<br />
In 1984 the Burdekin Falls Agreement was signed by senator<br />
Peter Walsh, the then Minister for Resources and Energy, and<br />
Sir Joh Bjelke-Petersen, the then Premier of Queensland.<br />
Less than three years later the dam wall was finished a<br />
year ahead of schedule due to the good industrial and<br />
meteorological climate that prevailed.<br />
Now in 1988, thanks to the recent cyclone, the dam is full<br />
and North Queensland is about to receive the benefits of<br />
this great achievement.<br />
I say great, because the dimensions of this Dam beggar the<br />
imagination. The dam wall is 876 metres long, with a spillway of half a<br />
kilometre, rising 37 metres above the river bed, holding<br />
1.85 million megalitr~ es of water, inundating 22,000 hectares<br />
of land and drawing on a catchment area of,* nearly 115,000<br />
square kilometres, or about half the size-' of the State of<br />
Victoria. The Dam will provide some 850,000 negalitres of water to<br />
convert through irrigation some 50,000 hectares of grazing~<br />
land into 500 new farms capable of producing crops of the<br />
highest quality.<br />
And 130,000 people in Townsville and Thuringowa will receive<br />
a water supply that is guaranteed and pure.<br />
No wonder the dream of a Dam inspired so many people for so<br />
long. No wonder the Federal Government is proud to say we have<br />
fully funded the realisation of the dream, to the tune of<br />
$ 129 million.<br />
No wonder Ted Lindsay looks pleasedi<br />
Back in September 1983, in Question Tine in Parliament, I<br />
was asked a question about whether the Dam would be<br />
completed by 1988 the question, I hardly need add, came<br />
from the Hon. Member for Herbert, Ted Lindsay.<br />
1094 </p>
<p>3.<br />
1 said then that the Federal Government was totally<br />
committed to building the Dam and that we were aiming to<br />
finish it in 1988 our Bicentennial year.<br />
It was clear even then that the opening of the Burdekin Dam<br />
would be a major event of our Bicentennial celebrations. It<br />
is a tremendous symbol of the reconstruction of the<br />
Australian economy which has occurred under this Government.<br />
And it is, in anyone's book, a significant achievement of<br />
nation building something for which future generations<br />
will be indebted and grateful to us.<br />
Many people can share in the glow of this achievement:<br />
the workers whose efforts saw the dam completed ahead of<br />
schedule; the contractors involved in the project, especially<br />
Leightons Contractors who won an Australian Federation<br />
of Construction Contractors, Engineering Award of<br />
Excellence for their innovative engineering which<br />
hastened the speed at which concrete was placed;<br />
the Queensland Government which is to pay for irrigation<br />
works and a number of other associated infrastructure<br />
projects; Senators Peter Walsh and Gareth Evans, the Commonwealth<br />
ministers responsible for the dam since 1983 amd the<br />
Queensland ministers Mr Coleby, Mr Martin Tenni, and<br />
Mr Don Neal; and<br />
the former and present Commissioners of the Queensland<br />
Water Resources Commission, Mr Don Beattie and Mr Tom<br />
Fenwick, and all Commission staff who administered the<br />
project.<br />
It is a project which underlies the commitment of this<br />
Federal Government to the well-being of the people of North<br />
Queensland. And it is a project which proves again the truth that,<br />
through constructive cooperation, Australians can perform<br />
great tasks and complete great achievements. 1095<br />
cm L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
