<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4733</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH LA MONDE - PARIS - 13 JUNE 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/06/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004733.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
INTERVIEW WITH TAT MONDE -PARIS -13 JUNE 1978<br />
QUESTION. I would like firstly to know if you could tell us about<br />
the aims of your vi sit, if it is mainly economic, and what<br />
do you expect to achieve and perhaps what you think you have<br />
achieved so far.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
1978 is a particularly important year in terms of world<br />
economic and trading relationships. It is important for a<br />
number of reasons the Tokyo Round Trade discussions are<br />
designed to come to a conclusion in July; there will be a<br />
Bonn Summit also in July. For a number of years now, but<br />
especially over the last year, many nations have been pointing<br />
to the Tokyo round and their conclusion this year in 1978<br />
as--a matter of some importance. While people have been<br />
pointing to July as the concluding date, over the last twelve<br />
months there has been a growth of protectionist pressures<br />
in a number of countries we have seen a number of actions<br />
that have been taken. We have also seen that governments<br />
have been able to point to MTN and have been able to use<br />
that as a defence against a too greater move towards protectionist<br />
measures. With the levels of unemployment that there are<br />
in a number of countries and with the concerns that there are<br />
with the world trading scene, there are clearly greater<br />
protectionist pressures now thdn I think there have been<br />
for a very long while. Against that background, the decisions<br />
made at the Bonn Summixit, the decisions made at MTN are<br />
vastly important. We have got the choice of taking a forward<br />
looking step of-' freeing trade, of seeing that the benefits<br />
of that freer trade are distributed as widely as possible<br />
amongst nations. Or we have got the possibility-of not<br />
recognising the needs of the present, and moving back to a<br />
1930' s type protectionism which would be disastrous for France,<br />
Australia and all significant trading nations, with damaging<br />
consequences to the standard of living of all of us.<br />
About six weeks ago I visited Prime Minister Fukuda in Japan<br />
to discuss these matters with him and found a broad identity<br />
of view, and discussions with Vice-President Mondale of America<br />
and Trade Negotiator Strauss, Prime Mi nister Callaghan and<br />
your Prime Minister because I wanted to assess for myself<br />
the possibilities of successful trade and to see how other<br />
nations were regarding 1978 in terms of trade and the economic<br />
situation. I am heartened to the extent that I have found that<br />
every nation shares my concern. They share my concern that<br />
there should not be a reversion to protectionism. I find<br />
differing views-about the prospects of success, either at the<br />
Bonn Summit or at MTN. To try and provide some shot in t'he<br />
arm for MTN, but at the same time recognising the limits<br />
of Australia's influence, we have designed to adopt the formula<br />
approach even though we know quite well it is not structured<br />
to meet the needs of the Australian economy as it is structured<br />
to meet the needs of Europe and North America. / 2 </p>
<p>We will be pressing our views vigorously at MTN forums, we will<br />
be pressing for progress in relation to agriculture and<br />
through UNCTAD in relation to the Common Fund.<br />
The industrial tariff proposal covers less than 20 percent of<br />
world trade, and it will result in a half a percent a year<br />
reduction for eight years from 1980, and it is very unequal<br />
in its effect 40*-percent of Europe's exports, and five percent<br />
of Australia's, and many developing countries, much less than<br />
that. So to have a MTN that distributes benefits reasonablevenly<br />
amongst different groups and categories of trading<br />
nations it is going to be very important to make progresz:<br />
not just on the indtistrial tariff proposals, but on agriculture<br />
and also on Common Fund proposals for developing nations<br />
Australia quite deliberately moved'away from the B-Group of<br />
countries, and took'a step . in the direction of the developing<br />
nations, because we felt both groups were too inflexible<br />
in their positions and that there needed to be movement,<br />
so that we can try and move things at least a stage nearer<br />
agreement. I am glad to say that amongst both developed and<br />
developing nations with whom I have directly spoken I do<br />
detect a willingness to move. There is a recognition of<br />
the fact that nations will have to be practical and that<br />
there will have to be a movement away from rigid positions<br />
if there is to be an advance and an agreement.<br />
I am here at the moment'because I believe all of these things<br />
are vastly important, and if in 1978 you make the wrong<br />
decision, we are probably not going to have a chance to<br />
undo those decision for quite some time, in other words,<br />
with all the history that has led up to this year, the<br />
decision taken in 1978 will prqbably set the pattern for<br />
many years ahead.<br />
QUESTION So you discussed the main problems you have with the EEC,<br />
in broad terms, but you have specific problems with the EEC..<br />
PRIME. MINISTER<br />
These have mostly been handled by Mr Garland, our Special<br />
Trade Representative, but at the same time I have in both<br />
Britain and here, stressed in the strongest terms<br />
the complete inadequacy of the Community's response.<br />
Twelve m~ onths after discussions were opened, when I was in<br />
Brussels a year ago., the Community has not yet been able<br />
to put its view to us in writing, which I find very hard to<br />
understand. They have said that in a number of areas there<br />
will be progress at the Multi-lateral Trade Negotiations, and we<br />
will test the validity of what the Community has said to us,<br />
we will be in there negotiating at the Multi-lateral Trade<br />
Negotiations, we will be developing the concept of joint<br />
disciplines of our own, because it is possible to see the nature<br />
of-joint disciplines that would allow a real prospect of<br />
growth and development in trade in a responsible way that<br />
is not disruptive; or it would be possible to see under<br />
joint disciplines rules drawn up that did not allow any possibility<br />
of trade. Therefore it is necessary for Australia to test the<br />
validity of what the European Commission has put to us in the </p>
<p>MTN forum. We will be continuing to press our view bi-laterally<br />
with the Coffmission with indi~ vidual Community countries,<br />
because the matters are of great importance to us.<br />
It is not generally understood that a number of Australian<br />
industries began in Aurstralia because there were markets<br />
in Europe, and Europe wanted us to supply them.<br />
Then 1, ecause of the advent of the European Econoriic Commuv'ity<br />
the policies developed that pushed Australia out of those<br />
markets. Now we recognise the'right of France to protect<br />
French farmers, we don't challenge that we would be<br />
very foolish to. But we do believe that it is possible to<br />
protect French farmers in a way that allows the prospect of<br />
some trade instead of no trade. People concentrate on beef.<br />
We used to have quite a health and vigorous wine export industry<br />
to Europe that might seem to strange to France, renowned<br />
for its wine, but we used to export quite a lot t;-o France<br />
as well we import from France in addition and import.<br />
substantial quantities. Our wine industry is a good one<br />
and the wine established new rules which over the last 12-18<br />
months have halved wine, because of arbitrary changes in rules,<br />
this has halved the wine we can export to the European<br />
Community. I think that is an example of unequal and not<br />
responsible trade behaviour which we just cannot afford.<br />
There is strong agreement between the Prime Minister and<br />
myself that a trade war, a reversion to protectionism amongst<br />
major trading nations is going to damage standards of life,<br />
everywhere. We will be needing to test the validity of<br />
what has been put to us.<br />
QUESTION Do you intend to have some retaliation if you are not<br />
heard here?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I hope that it won't have to come to that. We have said<br />
that if we can't make progress we will have to reexamine<br />
our commercial and trading policies, with Europe. i<br />
I hope very much that the European Community will not push us<br />
to that course. Having said that, it shouldn't be taken<br />
as any weakening or lack of determination on Australia's part.<br />
We are very determined indeed that countries which can do<br />
things best should be allowed to trade in those commodities<br />
not in a disruptive way. We don't seek revolution<br />
and disruption to trade because we know what damage that<br />
can do to have no prospect of trade, because it will<br />
deny the possibility of trade; or to have export subsidies<br />
which can destroy a -market you have spent 25 years developing<br />
this has happened through the policies of export subsidies<br />
of restitution. When the Community has said, where is a market<br />
we have a surplus product, and they provide the subsidy necessary<br />
to take that market. That is very disruptive to other<br />
countries trade and it is a fact of life that a country such<br />
as Australia does n~ ot want to and cannot enter the competitive<br />
subsidy business of 260 million people in the European<br />
Community. </p>
<p>QUESTION Regarding uranium. Do you think you have any plans of<br />
using uranium for other<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
We have international obligations with uranium to accept<br />
safeguards for the * trade and to give people confidence<br />
confidence that our uranium won't be used for proliferation<br />
purposes. We have re sponsibilities internationally to<br />
provide energy in-an e . nergy-short world no countries<br />
want to diversifytt h eir sources of energy. But I hope very<br />
much that because wex. ecognise those international responsibilitie<br />
that other countries won't want to push us too far in directions<br />
in which we would be most reluctant to go. I would want<br />
to keep Australian uranium separate from the general thrust<br />
of the particular bi-lateral arguments we have. We are<br />
probably shortly going to be ready to sign a safeguards<br />
agreement with Britain a draft has been agreed between<br />
officials, and that would clearly open the way to commercial<br />
discussions and negotiations. rh-at is as it should be.<br />
While we have got inter national obligations in relation to<br />
that trade, we also have obligations to very large geographic<br />
areas of Australia, which have been put into a state of<br />
depression and despair, which is totally misunderstood in<br />
Europe. In our beef growing areas you get country towns<br />
which are dependent upon the beef industry almost entirely.<br />
You get total communities dep'endent and built up on that<br />
industry. The industry developed over a long period to<br />
supply the European market, and other markets.<br />
And then it finds that the European market is closed to it,<br />
and the towns start to die people leave their properties,<br />
in some cases they cut fences, have somebody to look after<br />
the watering points, this is in the large back-country<br />
areas which it is hard to conceive, although you night be<br />
carrying one cow to the square mile. It is flat country,<br />
difficult country America has got some of the same.<br />
It can still produce ? jood and by world-standards well-priced<br />
beef. In the markets for some commodities the products<br />
are particularly atuned to the needs of the technologically<br />
advanced democracies, and beef is one such commodity<br />
rice is a different matter, atune to. different markets,<br />
you can sell rice in many different countries.<br />
In some areas if Australian industries are to return to a<br />
degree of profitability we need access to the large-scale<br />
affluent markets, of which Europe is clearly one a very<br />
large one and a very significant one. All of that is just<br />
stating a fact of life, quite apart from the fact that we<br />
think that the sorts of rules which have been applied to<br />
agriculture, and to find this of all the rules of fair and<br />
reasonable trade, and of everything that we have been<br />
fighting for when I say we, I mean trading nations<br />
collectively in terms of responsible trade, in all the<br />
years since the war.-I have got great respect for the<br />
economic policies that the Prime Minister of France has been<br />
introducing over recent times. I recognise the courage with </p>
<p>which they are pursued. * As' we see it from a distance<br />
I would think they are much to the long term<br />
best interests of France. So too it is in the interests<br />
of all of us trading nations to establish the circumstances<br />
in which countries which can do things best and cheapest<br />
in the total world environment have a prospect of trading<br />
in that particular commodity, The way rules are applied in<br />
relation to trade in agriculture, there are some commodities<br />
to which that just can'. t happen at the moment.<br />
QUESTION I suppose you have raised this question with our Prime Minister.<br />
PRIME MINSITER<br />
The heart of these issue s has been put to the Prime Minister.<br />
I asked to see him because of my concern with the broad-based<br />
multi-lateral issues.: Our concern is a parallel concern,<br />
and it is a serious one. The concern I have that MTN<br />
be a success a little later this year is very great indeed.<br />
T1hat is the reason why I am over here at the moment.<br />
I am glad to say that the Prime Minister made it perfectly<br />
plain to me that he doesn't want to see a reversion to the<br />
protectionist policies of Past years. He recognises the damage<br />
it would do to this great nation, and all the trading world.<br />
QUESTION Do you believe your meeting with was successful?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I believe it was a useful meeting, not unsuccessful.<br />
The real test will depend on what happens in Geneva at MTN.<br />
QUESTION I understand that your Government wants to open Australia to<br />
more foreign investment.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
We have modified the foreign investment rules and guidelines.<br />
If you wish to pursue this I would like you to speak to<br />
John Stone, who would be technically expert, because they are<br />
technical expert. In broad terms we welcome foreign investment<br />
particularly in partnership with Australia. There are rules<br />
there are objectives of seeking to achieve 50 percent Australian<br />
equity in projects, but if that can't be achieved we wculd-*<br />
not want to hold up a good and worthwhile project on that account.<br />
There has been French investment in Australia. Our inflation<br />
rate is falling substantially, the last quarterly figure was*<br />
1.3 percent. We are going to continue with policies that<br />
will bear down on inflation and establish a good climate for<br />
investment. We would like to see more and interest from<br />
France in joint enterprises. It would be very welcome.<br />
We don't req~ rd D~ f it as a dirty t erm, it is an honourable term'<br />
Without prof its Elfere would be no investment. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
