<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6385</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT, &#039;PRESSURE POINT&#039;, 26 APRIL 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/04/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006385.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PROME MINIS7ERI<br />
TRANSCRIPT ' PRESSURE POINT' 26 APRIL 1984<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY'<br />
EVANS: Prime Minister, it's not a gala occasion, it's not a<br />
glittering one, it's the ABC, but I'm glad you 6ould make it<br />
to the first night of this new series of the Pressure Point<br />
program. It's a pleasure Huw.<br />
EVANS: Can I ask you if you're going to spell out the pattErn<br />
of bias that you ' ye expressed about the ABC in recent times.<br />
I'm notgoing to do anything publicly about it Huw. I<br />
believe that perhaps the management and the board of the ABC'<br />
may like to speak to me. If they do I'm more than happy to speak<br />
with them. I'm certainly not in the business of applying any<br />
public pressure.<br />
EVANS: Ken Myer said that he's not prepared to talk to you about<br />
a general allegation of bias. Would you be prepared to spell out<br />
the details to him in the formal way I suppose in which<br />
If he'd like me to' yes. That's easily done.<br />
EVANS: Do you want him to take the initiative and ask you to?<br />
I think there's-been some initiative already taken bu~ t<br />
I don't think that the interestsof the ABC or anyone else are<br />
assisted by a public canvassing any further of the issue.<br />
EVANS: But presumably you're concerned that the issue isn't<br />
taken to the point where you're accused of trying to intimidate<br />
the ABC. Oh absolutely. Because I have historically been a friend<br />
of the ABC, of the institution, of the concept. I remain so. I've<br />
said that doesn't mean that it should be immune from criticism.<br />
I've referred to it. I don't want to pursue it publicly. I think<br />
it could be of assistance -if they'd like to hear my views I've got<br />
in detail and the spelling out what I see as examples of what I've<br />
been talking about. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
EVANS: Your Goverment brought in the legislation and appointed<br />
a Board. I've heard a senior Minister express doubts about that<br />
Board. Do you have any doubts?<br />
I'm not going to pursue that issue publicly..<br />
EVANS: You've set out to bring about a . process of reconciliation<br />
when you won Government just over a year ago.<br />
Yes.<br />
EVANS: Has that been accomplished do you-think?<br />
To a large extent Australia is a much more cohesive<br />
and reconciled community in April 1984 to the country that -we<br />
came to govern in March 1983.<br />
EVANS: Do you think you've got more than just good will there?<br />
Do you think people are prepared to make sacrifices in the long<br />
term interests of where you want to take us?<br />
The first thing is. that they are prepared to talk and<br />
communicate and co-operate with one another. And out of that<br />
process will come, and has come to some extentthe sort of<br />
concessional approach that you refer to in your question.<br />
What Iwas trying to say to Australia in February/ March of<br />
last year was that our capacity to develop had been seriously<br />
diminished by the dissipation of energy and resources in<br />
confrontation. which unfortunately had been nurtured by the<br />
previous Government. And that I was trying to make it clear<br />
to business and to the trade union movement that they each had<br />
legitimate aspirations for business to increase profitability<br />
and for the trade union movement to protect and through time<br />
improve the standards of the people they represented. And what<br />
they had to understand was that these are not mutually conflicting<br />
aspirations, that indeed aspirations which were more likely to be<br />
achieved if there was a qreater degree of co-operation.<br />
EVANS: Do you believe people really are aware though where you<br />
are taking us to. Imean in a sense you have calmed the fires, if<br />
you like, but do you think that they really understand where it<br />
is that Hawke and the Labor Government are taking us to.<br />
No, I don't think the community yet has a detailed vision<br />
of the future and nor are they to be blamed for that Huw.<br />
Because these things, if they're going to work don't involve<br />
a snap of the fingers and say hey Australia, here we go, that's<br />
the path, there's the picture. Life isn't like that. Not if you're<br />
.3 </p>
<p>3.<br />
serious. But what they do understand is that we are trying<br />
to get together a coherent policy in which-what you do in the<br />
general field of macro-economics, what you're going to be doing<br />
in the education field, what you're going to be doing in the<br />
international relations field are all melded together to try<br />
and ensure that we get the highest possible rates of growth<br />
and do it in a way which enmesh this country into our region<br />
and that is necessary for the facts of geography and geo-politicS.<br />
Now I think that we can say one very specific thing that we<br />
have achieved in that part. YOU will recall that before we<br />
came to office the basic debate in this whole area that we're<br />
talking about is the extraordinarily sterile and ultimately<br />
useless debate about protection whether we're going to have more<br />
protection or less protection. Now we jumped that hurdle. As a<br />
result I think basically of that recent visit to Asia there's been<br />
an acceptance of what I've been saying that Australian industry<br />
must restructure and through time that's going to involve<br />
a gradual lowering of protection and the discussion now in<br />
our country is how we go about that restructuring.<br />
EVANS: Has it really been accepted as widely as YOU suggest it<br />
has -Imean there's quite a lot of resistance from people in tie<br />
heavy manufacturing sector. who fear that their jobs would be at<br />
risk. No you're in the media you've got to make the<br />
distinction between a person getting a headline because<br />
he makes a reactive shout and the considered opinion of<br />
the wider constituency of which he's part. Now true it<br />
is that a couple of trade union people did give a knee-jerk<br />
reaction. But the fact is that the ACTU at the Economic Planning<br />
Advisory Council meeting after my return said there in that body<br />
we've studied what the Prime Minister has said, we support him.<br />
EVANS: You said you don't really approve of the Party's gee whiz<br />
approach to where we're going.<br />
I don't.<br />
EVANS: But in the case of manufacturing industry, for<br />
example, I think people would like to see some kind<br />
of a Picture of what Australia's going to be like in five or t'en<br />
years hence. What sorts of industries are we going to be doing<br />
without? Where will people be working? What will they be doing?<br />
Let me give you the background statistic so that WE: can<br />
get the right context. In 1966 26% of employment was in<br />
manufacturing. Now in February of this year that's down to just<br />
under 18%, so there's been a massive restructuring and charge<br />
in Australian industry that's-takenplaceAnd unless we understand<br />
that the discussion is pointless. It starts from the basis that<br />
everything has remained unchanged but suddenly we' 1re going to0 do<br />
something different. The point Of my Government's approach is </p>
<p>4.<br />
P. M. cont.: this that that change that' s taken place<br />
has been unstructured, un-thought through, unplanned, it hasn't<br />
involved trying to make sure that we do the things most that<br />
we can do best. and most efficiently. Now what we;-are about is<br />
perhaps best illustrated here by what we've done in the steel industry.<br />
When we came to office the threat was that the steel industry<br />
was going to disappear from this count~ ry. Now that was an<br />
unacceptable stupidity as far as I was concerned and I said it<br />
wouldn't happen. We would involve the'. aovernmnent in'the reStructurLr<br />
approach. Now what we did was to sit down with BHP and the unions<br />
and ourselves and we got a commitment from each to make sure that<br />
the industry became more efficient. That involved the industry<br />
undertaking a commitment to invest $ 800 milli~ n over a period of<br />
four years. It involved the unions undertaking to change their<br />
work practices to increase productivity and on our part it meant<br />
assistance via bounties.. to reduce the adverse downstream cost<br />
effect. Now in the result the Australian steel industry has<br />
not only survived, but it's become more profitable and more<br />
efficient. I've just recently been in Newcastle and it -was a matt,<br />
of enormous satisfaction to me to go out to the steel mill and<br />
have the workers and management just saying to me, the thing is<br />
working now, it's more efficient, it's better for all of us.<br />
bounties<br />
EVANS: But can we afford/ for all sorts of industries if they're<br />
going to run into that kind of problem. There are going to be quite<br />
a few. Not necessarily. But let me give you the next example<br />
of what we're working on.-the vexed motor vehicle industry.<br />
Before this year is out, well before it's out, we will' have in<br />
place a new plan for the post-84 period. And that will involve<br />
the emergence of an industry which through time will become<br />
more efficient, more competitive and one which will over all<br />
contribute more to the Australian economy. And we will do that<br />
in the same way essentially through talking with the companies anc<br />
the unions, and John Button, my Minister for Industry and Commerce,<br />
is just going overseas to Japan in particular to talk to the<br />
companies over there.<br />
EVANS: Will it involve those same elements of requiring the<br />
industry to invest and to increase its efficiency and unions<br />
to make sacrifices.<br />
I don't like the word sacrifices because if you talk to<br />
the workers up in the steel mill they won't talk about it . now in<br />
terms of sacrifices.<br />
EVANS: They're still in work.<br />
They have got jobs and they are happier. I was talking to<br />
one and he said look, my job is to be in charge of the actual<br />
industrial relations situation in these sections. He said we<br />
used to be having a stoppage a month. He said now we've had<br />
twelve months no stoppage.<br />
EVANS: Wle have been inefficient in large measure. What chance<br />
do we have of moving in as you've suggested and enmeshing ourselves<br />
in Asia in that particular field where! there's so much<br />
competition? </p>
<p>41* 5.<br />
We have very good chances because we have demonstrated<br />
one doesn't have to be hypothetical about this Australian<br />
manufacturing industry has shown its capacity to compete in the<br />
toughest markets in the world against the toughest competition<br />
because as Australians we mustn't get this idea that we have<br />
some inferior capacities. Our pure research will match up<br />
to just about any in the world. Where our problem in the pAst<br />
has been to a large extent is in applying that researdh into<br />
industry and making sure that we've got the infrastructure<br />
to take advantage. But we've shown that we can do that.'<br />
EVANS: We've talked about restructuring industry. It's going to<br />
be a slow process, it's going to be a gradual process. But what<br />
are the other changes in our society. I mean for example we've<br />
got to meet our daily bills, we've got to provide our welfare-and<br />
so on. The Australian community has invested in you, and<br />
very obviously they have, a great deal of qood will. Are theie<br />
sacrifices that they now need . to make in order to tide us through'<br />
this time of change, till we reach some kind of economic equilibrium?<br />
To somae extent. And that's happening. It's always been<br />
the attitude, for instance, of the trade union movement that<br />
w4&amp; ve been fashioned in this great period of post-war years<br />
that they could look each year to significant real increases<br />
in standards. Now they understand I think that what we've really<br />
got to do as Australians now is not to be in the immediate<br />
term looking for significant increases in our standards. It's<br />
a legitimate aim to try and maintain what we've got and that's<br />
what the operation of the accord is about now. And I think that<br />
their cnitnent to that accord, of not trying to use their muscle<br />
in areas of emerging prosperity involves a sacrifice and I welcome it<br />
as I welcome the great co-operation of the business community. In<br />
other words economics really and economic development is about your<br />
time scale. You have got to understand that if you are really going<br />
to have a substantial basis upon which to get improved standards<br />
you've got to lay the economic framework for doing it over the longer<br />
period and that may mean postponing your immediate satisfactions.<br />
Now, I think that essentially that is what Australia is about at the<br />
present. EVANS: Do you believe there's a need at<br />
this time to restate the aims of the Summit, perhaps even<br />
focussing the public mind with a similar kind of approach.<br />
We'renot having another Summit, but. I think we may give<br />
some public expression to what the accord. has been about and<br />
what it's achieved. There's been suggestions from both sides<br />
of industry that we should do that because it's worked so well<br />
for them both. And if I can just complete the point that I was<br />
* making about your general question about are we now involved in<br />
getting a new relationship the answer is yes, because you're<br />
having industry and the unions and governments meeting together<br />
and working together now in a way they've never done before.<br />
And they are getting the habit of co-operation and the attitude<br />
of co-operation and that's essential. </p>
<p>6.<br />
EVANS: Do you think business has responded in the way you<br />
wanted it to in terms of investment or is that yet to be tested?<br />
Yes, it is the case in economic recovery and the economic<br />
cycle that private business investment tends to omel in the latter stages<br />
of that recovery. W~ hat we've done is create the ideal<br />
environment for further investment. That is by bringing down<br />
interest rates and gradually we'll be withdrawing proportionately<br />
from the capital markets:' and our demands upon them. With interest<br />
rates down, inflation down, unit labour costs now have com'e<br />
down to a point where they are getting by the end of this year unit labour<br />
costs will be down to what they were at the base period of 1966-72.<br />
And so when you take all those things into account the environment's<br />
there and I believe private investment will start to provide that<br />
surge for further growth.<br />
EVANS: To what extent do you agree with the proposition that i't<br />
was in fact the previous government's wage pause rather than your<br />
wage accord which. provided much of the impetus that, has resulted<br />
in the good figures of the country's..<br />
Well if you'Ire going to talk about their wage pause what ycu ' ye<br />
got to remember is that it was their criminally irresponsible wages<br />
policy in the period ' 80, ' 81, ' 82 which led to an unsustainable<br />
wages explosion which brought about the severest recession in this<br />
country since the Great Depression. And to talk about the pause<br />
that they then imposed on that situation, as though that<br />
was the stroke of economic genius does less than justice to the patterni<br />
of their economic approach. Now we realised that what You've<br />
got to do in government is to build a wages policy not just<br />
for a recession, in a sense you didn't need the wages pause because<br />
the recession would have Virtually done it anyway. What's necessary<br />
for the future of this country is to have a wages policy for<br />
recovery and growth. And that's what we've done. We've got the<br />
habit of commitment of the trad dinion movement to a centralised<br />
system which is going to./ wag s explosion because as we now come<br />
into this high growth period which we are in, that if you didn' t<br />
have such a policy of restraint would mean that you'd get back<br />
to what you in 80/ 81/ 82 which would have wages going through<br />
the roof, which would guarantee the end of expansion.<br />
EVANS: But this high growth rate isn't going to continue next<br />
year is it.<br />
Of course and we've said quite clearly you can't expect<br />
to continue 10% through the year growth, the highest in the world.<br />
EVANS: What are we expecting for the next year or two in the growth<br />
p. m. Well it will be a low rate of growth, but it will be a' significant gIrowth<br />
rate which what we aim to have is high enopugh gradually to make a dent<br />
in unemployment because you get your growth in the workforce and<br />
so you've got to have a high enough growth rate to cover<br />
productivity and the growth in the workforce. So you need growth<br />
Of the order of 4 to 5 per cent to start to make that dent. And<br />
I'll believe we'll achieve that. </p>
<p>EVANS: What's going to'happen at the Conference later on this year.<br />
Have you got it all tied up so you're not going to have any<br />
problems. Are-they going to tear themelves apart or are they goingr to<br />
agree sweetly? There will never be, I hope, a Labor Party conference<br />
where there are no problems. We ' d all die of heart attacks arid"<br />
shock. But what there will be I think is a conference where the<br />
overwhelming majority of delegates will be committed to acquiring<br />
good sense, to recognising the very significant achievements of<br />
this government in office and to try and far as possible to get<br />
agreed positions. Now that doesn't mean that there won't be<br />
some argument about issues. For instance, on uranium<br />
I believe that the Government's position will be sustained buz,<br />
those who don' t agree entirely with that will certainly be putting another<br />
position. But the great thing about the end of last year and<br />
into this year within the Party has been that this debate f<br />
is now at a much more rational level than it's ever been before.<br />
EVANS: You say it will be sustained but do you believe that the policy will<br />
be altered sufficiently to allow greater flexibility On muining and export of uranium.,<br />
Well the position that the Government has adopted will allow<br />
the development of Ro-. cby.<br />
EVANS: I mean going beyond that<br />
Well, yesJ. think that the conference is really going to<br />
be looking at this issue of uranium in the broader sense. I think<br />
this has been reflected what's been happening in the community in<br />
recent months. You will notice that even in the great rallies<br />
that occurred just in the last weekend or so that the focus was<br />
more on disarmament than on uranium as such. And that's right<br />
because this Government has done more in its year of office<br />
positively in the area of disarmament than any other Government's<br />
done before and it's always been an issue of fundamental<br />
importance to me and it is to my Ministers. So that we will be<br />
concentrating on the need to prevent the proliferation of nuclear<br />
weapons horizontally.<br />
EVANS: ARe you going to get a nuclear weaporn free zone in this<br />
area. Well we've* advocated it strongly. Last year at the South<br />
Pacific Forum we got the support of basically the countries Of<br />
the area. I put it directly to the President * of the United<br />
States and his administration there that we intend to press for<br />
it and they understand. that. We will press for that in all<br />
relevant forums. It's not something again which you achieve<br />
overnight. EVANS: What's a reasonable time frame? You sound hopeful.<br />
Well I don't believe in giving people false expectationS.<br />
All I can say is that we will raise it again at the Forum in<br />
August of this year and I don't know how long it will take. But<br />
in all forums, in the United Nations, in other international<br />
meetings we will be doing what I've done during this year at<br />
the CHOGM conference in Dehli I took a le ' ading role in pressing<br />
the importance of the non-proliferation of nuclear weapons. I had<br />
a pretty hefty' go i-n with Mrs Ghandi on this issue and they<br />
don't believe in the non-proliferation treaties. I do and we do<br />
and we're going to continue to press for that. </p>
<p>EVANS: What do you think of being called by Helen Caldicott the<br />
most dangerous Prime Minister Australia's ever had.<br />
I'm not going to engage in a public airing of my views about<br />
Dr Caldicott. If she wants to do that that's her business.<br />
EVANS: Do you expect a debate at that level at the Conferen~ e at all.<br />
It will be, with all due respect to Dr.' Caldicott, it~ will<br />
be a more rational and sensible discussion than she's enabled the<br />
Australian community to have.<br />
EVANS: The draft platform on the economy that's comre from Mr Keating for<br />
the Conference does seem to point to a number of things<br />
it points to restraint, it points to expectations being geared<br />
over time, but it also points I think to the possibility of the<br />
Government looking for more an alternative area! of taxation,<br />
in the indirect tax field. Is that something which really aify<br />
Government would have to fall into.<br />
Any government which is sensible about thinking of,) the<br />
future of this country has got to look at: the revenue base.<br />
To assume that the mish mash of revenue measures which comes -to<br />
make up the current total, efforts by government to get its revenue,<br />
to assume that that is ideal is an exercise in lunacy. Of course<br />
it's not ideal. So what we're doing within EPAC and in general<br />
discussion in the community is try and examine where we are,<br />
whether there are better more efficient and more equitable ways<br />
of providing Government. with its revenue to assist the community<br />
with the doing of the things that the community wants done.<br />
And so we've got to get rid of this concept that we as a Government<br />
are taxers n hr are taxpayers that pay. What Government is about. is a<br />
transfer of revenue from the -community in various . ways so tha-:<br />
the Government can do the things that thE! community wants. And<br />
so the sensible thing to do is to have an interaction with the<br />
community and its representatives to see from their point of view<br />
how they think it's -most efficient and equitable to make tha:-<br />
transfer so that we can do the things they want.<br />
EVANS: A. lot of people believe that your Government hasn't really bitten<br />
the bullet hard enough on'that in transferring, tor example, in-the<br />
distribution of wealth. question whether you've letthe wealthy* get<br />
Off a bit too lightly. so far.<br />
Well you sa h s me pe ) le say that. I suppose you'll always<br />
have some critics/ IT 9 MoM90.-All I can say is that I'm prepared<br />
and more than happy to point at what we've done in our first year<br />
in office in the welfare area ~ with the very stringent circumstances<br />
economically that we've inherited. We targetted in on those areas<br />
most in need and so you have the single dole that will have gone<br />
up by 20 percent by May of this year, the benefit. The benefiLt<br />
for those recipients of welfare with dependant children have gjone<br />
up by 20 percent. So we've targetted in with our limited resources on'those<br />
areas in greatest.. need and we are now undertaking in all the areas<br />
of welfare and tax related areas studies as to what are the most<br />
appropriate areas in the future to provide assistance. Ourl rec-ord<br />
will stand up with any Government in the post-war period.<br />
EVANS: This country's fascinated with you at the moment. Its<br />
Popularity rating of you is enormously high. I wonder if in any<br />
way you feel. that that gives you a leg-in, if it gives you an<br />
advantage does it make governing easier, does it mean in a sense<br />
that you have a responsibility to the people that goes beyond that<br />
to the Party. </p>
<p>9.<br />
There are a bag of questions'in that Well let me<br />
say these things which I think are relevant to the various points<br />
you raised. I guess any po~ litical leader would prefer to have<br />
a higher rating than a low one and anyone who says the opposite, thin),<br />
is not telling the truth. Obviously I am happy about the high<br />
ratings, but also that the rating that the Government gets, it indicate<br />
to me that people approve of the sort of approach that. I'm<br />
adopting and that gives you confidence to go on with that sort<br />
of consultative approach that I have. It gives me the feeling<br />
that that's what they want and so in that sense it makes it easier.<br />
It does have this aspect to it Huw that it gives you a considerable<br />
sense of responsibility that you know that you've got that -confidence<br />
and you mustn't abuse that it and I try not to.<br />
There are those who<br />
EVANS: / wonder how you'd be if you didn't have that popularity.<br />
rating, whether you'd ' go nasty on us.<br />
No, I'm by nature a decent sort of bloke, you know I uiLdn't do<br />
that.<br />
EVANS: You do think long term. You're obviously planning on being around<br />
for the bicentennial.<br />
I hope that our Government will be there and that I'll be<br />
leading it.<br />
EVANS: How long would you like to go, have you thought about that?<br />
Well, I don't know whether most politicians think like this<br />
but I think one of the reasons why I rate pretty well is that<br />
people know that they can trust me and believe me and I can tell<br />
you that I haven't thought, and don't think in terms of personal<br />
ambitions for breaking records in office and so on. I really have<br />
an ambition to be able to say at the end of my term of office<br />
that we had changed this society and made it a better more cohesive,<br />
happier, better-structured society one which is going to be better<br />
for the next generation of Austral. ians and if that can be done<br />
in eight years, ten year, whatever it is, then that's what I'mn about.<br />
It's certainly encompasses the bicentennial period.<br />
EVA~ NS: No doubt. To exceed Menzies, the single longest<br />
of course you'd have to still be here by 2,000 you'd be over<br />
Not a prospect? I haven't addressed my mind to that yet.<br />
EVANS: Prime Minister thank you for talking with us on this our<br />
first edition of Pressure Point. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
