<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3519</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL W9MEN&#039;S YEAR - PRIORITIES AND CONSIDERATIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003519_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
INTERNATIONAL WOMENTS YEAR:<br />
Priorities and Considerations<br />
Statement prepared for the information<br />
of the Parliament and tabled by the<br />
Honorable E. G. Whitlam, M. P.,<br />
Prime Minister.<br />
4 December 1974 </p>
<p>INTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S YEAR<br />
It is a basic human right that neither women nor<br />
men should be excluded in law or in fact from the political,<br />
social, economic or cultural life of their country.<br />
This Government has long recognised that<br />
discrimination against women is incompatible with human<br />
dignity and the well-being of society.<br />
For the first time in the history of Australia,<br />
a national government has made a conscious.-and genuine attempt<br />
to overcome the decades of neglect from which womnen have<br />
suffered, to give to women and to men the ability to freely<br />
choose that way of life best suited to them individually.<br />
International Women's Year 1975 will provide an<br />
opportunity to stand back and assess what has already been<br />
achieved a4 well as enabling the initiation of further<br />
programs based on a deep commitment to -these basic human<br />
rights.<br />
Background On 18 December 1972 the United Nations General<br />
Assembly adopted the following resolution ( 3010 ( XXVII))<br />
proclaiming 1975 as International Women's Year: </p>
<p>2<br />
The General Assembly,<br />
Considering that twenty-five years have elapsed<br />
since the first session of the Commission on the Status<br />
of Women was held at Lake Success, New York, from 10 to<br />
24 February 1947, and that this is a period which makes<br />
it possible to take stock of the positive results obtained,<br />
Bearing in mind the aims and principles of the<br />
Declaration on the Elimination of Discrimination against<br />
Women, adopted by the General Assembly in resolution<br />
2263 ( XXII) of 7 November 1967,<br />
Recognizing the effectiveness of. the work done by<br />
the Commission on the Status of Women in the twenty-five<br />
years since its establishment, and the important<br />
contribution which women have made to the social,<br />
political, economic and cultural life of their countries,<br />
Considering that it is necessary to strengthen<br />
universal recognition of the principle of the equality<br />
of men and women, de jure and de facto, and that both<br />
legal and social measures have to be taken by Member<br />
States which have not yet done so to ensure the<br />
implementation of women's rights,<br />
Recalling that its resolution 2626 ( XXV) of 24<br />
October 1970, containing the International Development<br />
Strategy for the Second United Nations Development<br />
Decade, includes among the goals and objectives of </p>
<p>-3<br />
the Decade the encouragement of the full integration<br />
of women in the total development effort,<br />
Drawing attention to the general objectives and<br />
minimum targets to be attained in the course of the*<br />
Second United Nations Development Decade, as defined<br />
by the Commission on the Status of Women and adopted<br />
by the General Assembly in its resolution 2716 ( XXV)<br />
of 15 December 1970,<br />
Considering that, with those ends in view, the<br />
proclamation of an international women's year would<br />
serve to intensify the action required to advance the<br />
status of women,<br />
1. Proclaims the year 1975 International Women's Year;<br />
2. Decides to devote this year to intensified action:<br />
To promote equality between men and women;<br />
To ensure the full integration of women in the<br />
total development effort, especially by emphasizing<br />
women's responsibility and important role in economic,<br />
social and cultural development at the national, regional<br />
and international levels, particularly during the Second<br />
United Nations Development Decade;<br />
1( c) To recognize the importance of women's increasing<br />
contribution to the development of friendly relations and<br />
co-operation among States and to the strengthening of<br />
world peace; </p>
<p>-4<br />
3. Invites all Member States and all interested<br />
organizations to take steps to ensure the full<br />
realization of the rights of women and their advancement<br />
on the basis of the Declaration on the Elimination of<br />
Discrimination against Women;<br />
4. Inr1A" iite Govelrnmnsta have * not y et'doie so<br />
to ratify as soon as possible Convention ( No. 100)<br />
concerning Equal Remuneration for Men and Women Workers<br />
for Work of Equal Value, adopted by the International<br />
Labour Organisation in 1951;<br />
Requests the Secretary-General to prepare, in<br />
consultation with Member States, specialized agencies<br />
and . interested non-governmental organizations, within<br />
the limits of existing resources, a draft programme for<br />
the International Women's Year and to submit it to the<br />
Commission on the Status of Women at its twenty-fifth<br />
session in 1974.0<br />
This resolution stresses the need to promote<br />
equality between women and men and to ensure the full<br />
integration of women in the total development effort. it<br />
invites member governments and interested organisations to<br />
take steps to ensure that appropriate measures be taken to<br />
abolish sexually discriminatory laws, customs and practices;<br />
to educato public opinion; to eradicate prejudiced ideas<br />
concerning the inferiority of women; to ensure equal access<br />
to education and equality of opportunity and earnings in the<br />
workforce. </p>
<p>aawl" O* hnn ami w<br />
h . oh UI ' W w V. i. A ~ r k301'' U J 7 Z. 0 1 2 ic o<br />
Q. </p>
<p>5<br />
The Australian Prime Minister, in a statement to<br />
mark International Women's Day on 8 March 1974, announced<br />
that the Government was preparing an official program for<br />
International Women's Year. The Prime Minister paid tribute<br />
to the work of women's groups throughout Australia in seeking<br />
to use International Women's Day and International Women's<br />
Year to draw attention to the achievements of women and to<br />
the need for continued efforts to remove discrimination<br />
against women. On 24 July 1974 the Prime Minister announced in<br />
the House of Representatives that a National Advisory Committee<br />
would be established composed of individuals from the community<br />
whose differing backgrounds could assist the Government in<br />
the formulation of a program for the year. He went on to say<br />
that the Government had already established a Secretariat<br />
withii, the Department of the Special Minister of State an.<br />
that an Interdepartmental Advisory Committee would b ior d<br />
whose task it would be to develop and co-ordinate the activitico3<br />
of government departments and agencies.<br />
The Prime Minister himself has taken ministerial<br />
responsihility foK the year, assisted by tne Special Miris-er<br />
of State in his role as Minister Assisting tne PL_<br />
In the same statement the Prime Minister also<br />
announced that the Premiers of each State had been approached<br />
and that he confidently expected that both state and local<br />
governments would be glad to participate in this program. ./ 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
In the Budget Speech on 17 September 1974 the<br />
Treasurer announced that two million dollars had been set<br />
aside for International Women's Year activities in the<br />
financial year 1974-75.<br />
National Advisory Committee<br />
The members of the National Advisory Committee for<br />
International Women's Year were announced on 11 September 1974.<br />
They were selected to ensure a blend and balance<br />
between skills and interests in the total group. The Prime<br />
Minister invited on to this Committee individuals with<br />
differing backgrounds, differing experiences and differing<br />
expertise rather than using the more traditional method of<br />
seeking a representative from different organisations or<br />
sections of the community. The hope was that by bringing<br />
together people with practical experience the gap between<br />
understanding a problem and finding ways of lessening it could<br />
begin to be bridged.<br />
Ms Elizabeth Reid, the Prime Minister's Adviser on<br />
matters relating to the welfare of women, was appointed<br />
convener of the Committee; its other members are:<br />
Ms Shirley Castley child welfare officer in Tasmania<br />
Mr Barry Egan trade unionist<br />
Ms Irene Greenwood lifetime fighter for women's rights<br />
in Western Australia<br />
Ms Ruby Hammond member of various South Australian<br />
aboriginal committees ./ 7 </p>
<p>7<br />
Ms Jeanette Hungerford<br />
Ms Caroline Jones<br />
Mr James Oswin<br />
Ms Maria Pozos<br />
Ms Ruth Ross<br />
Ms Diana Waite<br />
Mrs Margaret Whitlam Queensland occupational therapist<br />
extensive media experience<br />
Secretary, Department of the Media<br />
active amongst migrant women in<br />
Victoria physiotherapist, active in many<br />
voluntary and women's groups in<br />
the Wollongong area<br />
experience in problems of women in<br />
remote areasi particularly the North<br />
West of Australia<br />
journalist and former social worker.<br />
It is not the role of the National Advisory Committee<br />
to impose upon the women of Australia a predetermined program.<br />
It is their hope that all women in Australia will speak out<br />
their ' h'ughts, their needs, their worries, their hopes and<br />
their dreams for the future. It will be the women o lustialia,<br />
be they Aboriginal or newcomers, young or old, English speaking<br />
or non English speaking, married or unmarried and so on, who<br />
will determine Australia's program for this year.<br />
In his speech at the inaugural meeting of the National<br />
Advisory Committee 11 September 1974, the Prime L said:<br />
" One of the regular and often unnoticed<br />
activities of the United Nations is its designation<br />
of International Years for the purpose of drawing<br />
attention to matters of human significance. For </p>
<p>-8<br />
instance, in the past decade there have been<br />
proclaimed such years as<br />
International Co-operation Year ( 1965)<br />
International Year for Human Rights ( 1968)<br />
International Education Year ( 1970)<br />
International Year to Combat Racism and<br />
Racial Discrimination ( 1971)<br />
World Population Year ( 1974)<br />
In the past, in Australia, these Years have<br />
been celebrated within the community through the<br />
activities of various organisations,. but rarely<br />
have governments taken these Years seriously<br />
enough to plan far-reaching and imaginative programs<br />
aimed at achieving the objectives of the Year.<br />
* My Government has decided that there is much<br />
more that can be done, at a national level, to<br />
assist and co-ordinate the celebration of these<br />
Years. The struggle for universal human rights is<br />
a protracted and perhaps an unending struggle.<br />
International Women's Year is considered to be<br />
especially important in that the Government is<br />
determined that its actions and philosophies<br />
adopted in the international forum be matched<br />
with those pursued at home. In the United Nations,<br />
Australia is becoming known as an outspoken<br />
contender for basic human rights. We acknowledge a / 9 </p>
<p>9<br />
that we have a continuing obligation to do all<br />
in our power to promote respect for human rights.<br />
To my mind, the Universal Declaration of<br />
Human Rights is one of the most significant and<br />
enlightened achievements of the United Nations,<br />
and it is from this fundamental commitment to<br />
the dignity of people that 1975 was unanimously<br />
proclaimed on 18 December 1972 by the United<br />
Nations General Assembly to be International<br />
Women's Year.<br />
It is worth considering the fact that it<br />
was thought necessary to nominate a year for all<br />
nations to make a concentrated effort towards<br />
ensuring that women enjoy the dignity of basic<br />
i,. iman rights, that they are integrated into<br />
society and that there is a recognition of the<br />
importance of their contribution to society.<br />
It is worth considering this fact because<br />
it is a sobering thought that women throughout<br />
L. world have to be granted an uptirtunity to<br />
be heard. The formation of a National Advisory Committee,<br />
and this its inaugural meeting, is an insurance ./ 1o </p>
<p>10<br />
that Australia will face the responsibility that<br />
this year places upon us.<br />
It is my hope that you will be able to<br />
marshall, co-ordinate and encourage the dedication,<br />
energy and enthusiasm of organisations and<br />
women within the community, and that in addition<br />
you will provide a national direction to this<br />
activity so that 1975 is not only a year of<br />
significance in itself but that it will have<br />
made a lasting contribution towards reducing the<br />
prejudices and lack of opportunity from which<br />
women suffer. It is also my hope that this year<br />
will ensure a lasting recognition of the great<br />
contribution that women have made, and continue<br />
to make, to Australian society.<br />
Government legislation can only achieve so<br />
much and I shall not pretend to you that any<br />
Government can achieve immediately for Australian<br />
women the revolution required to allow them to<br />
ievelop fully as individuals.<br />
For instance it must be said that, even if<br />
we were to remove all ti&gt; inequalities of opportunity<br />
and of status, it still would not be enough. We<br />
have to attack the social inequalities/ the hidden S./ 11 </p>
<p>11<br />
and usually unarticulated assumptions which<br />
affect women not only in employment but in the<br />
whole range of their opportunities in life.<br />
This is not just a matter for governments<br />
and for action by governments it is a matter<br />
of changing community attitudes and uprooting<br />
community prejudices, and in so far as this<br />
requires a re-education of the commuInity then<br />
clearly governments alone cannot be expected to<br />
do the whole job.<br />
You are probably aware of what we have done.<br />
One of the purposes of the Human Rights Bill was<br />
to permit Australia to ratify the Convention on<br />
the Political Rights of Women, which was adopted<br />
by the United Nations in 1952 and came into foice<br />
in July 1954. Australia is not a party to the<br />
Convention on the Political Rights of Women as<br />
there is still legislation in two States, South<br />
Australia and Tasmania, that does not yet fully<br />
conform with the requirements of that Convention.<br />
The Convention provides that women shall be<br />
entitled to hold public office at Australian and<br />
State level on equal terms with men, without any<br />
discrimination. Action has already been taken<br />
to amend Australian legislation relating to the ./ 12 </p>
<p>12<br />
Public Service to remove provisions that offend<br />
against this Convention. It is expected that<br />
Australia will ratify or accede to that Convention<br />
after these defects have been overcome, either<br />
as a result of the proposed Human Rights Act or<br />
by the enactment of specific legislation on the<br />
subject.* My Government has already established a<br />
National Committee on Discrimination in Employment<br />
and Occupation. Other actions taken by the<br />
Government in the area of women's employment<br />
include: Successful intervention in December<br />
1972 in proceedings before the<br />
Australian Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
Commission to have established the<br />
principle of equal pay for work of<br />
equal Value. Consultations with<br />
State Governments have led to most<br />
States agreeing to this principle.<br />
The two governments are now amending the legislation.<br />
Australia, therefore, will deposit an instrument<br />
of accession to the Convention on the Political<br />
Rights of Women with the United Nations on the<br />
December 1974, the 26th anniversary of the<br />
Universal Declaration of Human Rights. In Geneva<br />
on the same day Australia will ratify the International<br />
Labour Organization Convention No. 100,<br />
The Equal Remuneration Convention, 1951. ./ 13 </p>
<p>13<br />
The provision of training opportunities<br />
for women wishing to enter or re-enter<br />
the labour force after a period of<br />
domestic responsibility.<br />
This coming year will also see the beginning<br />
of the implementation of the Government's new<br />
program for the care and education of young children.<br />
In no other country in the world has such an<br />
ambitious program been attempted. This program<br />
recognises the need for educational, health and<br />
welfare components in child care; it recognises<br />
the need for these same services for children<br />
whether they be looked after at home or elsewhere.<br />
It will break down the traditional distinctions<br />
between occasional care and regular care, between<br />
Are-school education and child minding. All<br />
children whether they be looked after at home or<br />
elsewhere will have access to local centres designed<br />
to take care of their educational, health,<br />
psychological and other needs. The implementation<br />
of this program will place Australia amongst those<br />
c, ntries most genuinely concerned with welfare of<br />
the young. Furthermore, the Schools Commission has<br />
established a committee to look into the relation / 14 </p>
<p>14<br />
between social change and the education of women<br />
and girls. Recommendations from this committee<br />
will be included in the report to be presented<br />
to Parliament in the course of next year. Its<br />
terms of reference are far-reaching and its task<br />
a difficult one, for not only must it pinpoint<br />
those areas of education within which women are<br />
disadvantaged, but it must also make specific<br />
recommendations for future action.<br />
Many other Government departments have<br />
programs planned for the coming year.<br />
In the field of women's health, the first,<br />
and basic, initiative taken by the Government has<br />
been the establishment of the Leichhardt Women's<br />
Community Health Centre in Sydney. The aim of'<br />
this centre is to meet a need expressed by women<br />
for a health service staffed by women directed<br />
solely towards the special health needs of women.<br />
This is a significant initiative of a completely<br />
new dimension deriving directly from the Australian<br />
Government's broad policy perspectives and the<br />
Community Health Program will be actively developed<br />
to give it priority. 4 </p>
<p>Gi-eater participation by women at il levels<br />
of health care planning, delivery and administration<br />
is being actively promoted and this policy is<br />
providing women with increasing opportuuiities cf<br />
influencing the direction which health care i<br />
taking in the community.<br />
In the field of Aboriginal health, Aboriginal<br />
women arc being involved to an increasing degree<br />
in the delivery of health care to their own people.<br />
The initiative of my Government which may<br />
have the most far-reaching consequences is the<br />
establishment of a Royal Commission into Human<br />
Relationships. It is the task of this Commission<br />
to investigate the stresses that society places<br />
" non relationships between people, in what ways<br />
inadequate housing, insufficient money, too many<br />
or too few children, the vajlabilJty or otherwise<br />
of contracentive counselling and the adequacy of<br />
medical care affect people and their r&amp;.~ t[ on<br />
This Commission has been asked to present regular<br />
i. ' Prim reports and hence will also c: Q'-ibute to<br />
the success of the coming year.<br />
We must however acknowledge that the inequality<br />
of women's position in society is deeply embedded not<br />
just in the institutions but also in the psychology / 16<br />
1; 5 </p>
<p>16<br />
of the society. In this respect those women's<br />
organisations are correct which say that the first<br />
and fundamental step towards freedom is awareness<br />
by women themselves of their real inequality, of<br />
the extent of their social, political, economic<br />
and cultural discrimination and deprivation.<br />
I have mentioned the general responsibility<br />
that the National Advisory Committee has for<br />
developing themes and programs for the year which<br />
will be of benefit to all women in Australia,<br />
whatever their education, their cultural background,<br />
their economic status, their occupation, their<br />
beliefs or their way of life. In so doing you<br />
also have the opportunity to tackle this basic<br />
problem of embedded attitudes, not only by<br />
encouraging the growth of community activity in<br />
areas affecting women but also by giving a<br />
significant boost to the level of cwareness amongst<br />
women and men of the extent of these problems.<br />
It is for this reason and because of our<br />
coimmitment to, change in this area tnai my<br />
Government is determined that sufficient time<br />
and funds be availo j] to achieve these ends<br />
and it is also for this reason that much time<br />
and thought went into the membership of the<br />
National Advisory Committee. We wanted, and we / 17 </p>
<p>17<br />
have, a group of people whose unique expertise<br />
and experience is deeply grounded in their<br />
understanding of and demonstrated commitment to<br />
Australian women, their present and their future."<br />
Objectives In light of this brief the National Advisory<br />
Committee at this inaugural meeting formulated the overall<br />
objectives of International Women's Year for Australia as:<br />
We live in a changing society and women are now<br />
being offered a unique opportunity to contribute<br />
to influencing the course of the changes which are<br />
taking place, the ultimate goal being a society<br />
based on the dignity of women, men and children.<br />
A framework was developed to be followed in Australia during<br />
1975 and, hopefully, beyond. It involves a three part approach:<br />
Change of attitudes<br />
Institutional changes may no-be beneficial<br />
unless based on real and thorough-going<br />
attitudinal changes in the society. This<br />
involves not only the way men see women but<br />
also how women see themselves. Clearly there<br />
is a need for an educative process of some<br />
considerable dimension directed towards<br />
examining and reassessing the beliefs that<br />
society holds about the capacities,* potential ./ 18 </p>
<p>18<br />
and life patterns of women and giLis. As<br />
well as directing attention to adults there<br />
needs to be a special and concerted approach<br />
to the attitude formation of children and<br />
young people.<br />
( ii) Areas of discrimination and suffering<br />
There needs to be an identification of areas<br />
of discrimination against women in our society<br />
and a concerted attempt to solve the problems<br />
this creates or at least point the direction<br />
which possible solutions may take. Moreover<br />
there needs to be a recognition of the special<br />
problems facing women as women and a sympathetic<br />
and enlightened attempt to overcome them. For<br />
women to take their place in society on a basis<br />
* of dignity and equality as human beings w6 must<br />
remove discriminations made against them<br />
of their traditional sex/ propertv function<br />
Moreo7er we must go beyond this to recognise<br />
the special needs of women with a view to meeting<br />
these needs and overcoming the I-. icEps, thereb.<br />
enabling a full and free opr..-Hni. ty for<br />
individual expression.<br />
( iii) Creative aspects<br />
The year is seen not merely as designed to<br />
overcome disabilities but also as emphasising<br />
and giving opportunity to the creative aspects / 19 </p>
<p>19<br />
of women in<br />
human race.<br />
be a joyous<br />
which bring their uniqueness within the<br />
It is intended that the year<br />
one and that celebrations occur<br />
out these aspects.<br />
The Program Within this framework the Committee is seeking<br />
during 1975 to have initiated and encouraged activities such<br />
as the continued establishment of a network of<br />
community centres to respond to women's problems<br />
and encourtahgee ir activities<br />
and encourage their activities<br />
health, rehabilitation, crisis<br />
e. g. health, peri-natal, etc.<br />
Sshelter/ refuge<br />
crisis counselling<br />
post-rape assistance<br />
( ii) developmental/ creative<br />
containing for example<br />
collections ( books, magazines, documents,<br />
films, videotapes etc.)<br />
. study facilities ( reaair.. rooms, audiovisual<br />
equipment)<br />
Sfacili: ies for meetings and discussion gri.-<br />
workshops creche<br />
Sreferral service on legal matters, employment<br />
and other social problems </p>
<p>20<br />
sponsoring of research projects, e. g.:<br />
male/ female stereotypes<br />
* effect of current education system and<br />
texts on children<br />
* effect of literary stereotypes on the<br />
development of women's self image<br />
* reflection in language of male perspectives<br />
( ii) the isolation of women<br />
( iii) victimology, including rape situations<br />
( iv) formal and informal barriers to women's full<br />
participation in existing socio-political<br />
institutions e. g. political parties, churches, local<br />
government, etc.<br />
undertaking an education program aimed at en,<br />
men and women<br />
e. g. films, including TV films<br />
" radio programs<br />
" pamphlets/ booklets<br />
" lectures<br />
convening woJ--shops, seiginars, conf-renceF znuA<br />
discussion groups covering regions beyond the<br />
capital cities ./ 21 </p>
<p>21<br />
festivals/ cultural activities focussing on women<br />
e. g. . special celebrations for International<br />
Women's Day in 1975<br />
* sponsoring festivals, exhibitions and<br />
performances<br />
* sponsoring theatre productions<br />
* sponsoring festivals<br />
International -hosting of a U. N. inter-regional seminar entitled<br />
The Communication of Attitudes: Women, the Arts<br />
and the Media<br />
-development of strategies for the integration<br />
of women into international plans for economic<br />
development<br />
Activities Consistent with the principles accepted by the<br />
United Nations for International Women's Year it was also<br />
decided that Australia adopt its own symbol embodying its<br />
particular objectives.<br />
The Committee has sought the views of a wide range<br />
of individuals and organisations. Letters pointing out the<br />
importance of the year and calling for suggestions for themes<br />
and activities were sent to all women's groups, both young and<br />
old, ethnic organisations, professional organisations, ./ 22 </p>
<p>22<br />
educational institutions, trade unions, business organisations,<br />
art galleries, music schools, and so on.<br />
The initial response to the public. sing of<br />
International Women's Year has been a steady tiickle, fast<br />
turning into a flood, of submissions requesting funds or<br />
correspondence seeking information on closing dates or the<br />
sorts of projects to be funded. The costed submissions so<br />
far received total around $ 3.5 million, but the bulk of<br />
submissions are still to come or to be costed.<br />
Many of the submissions received are for projects<br />
that fall within the responsibility of existing government<br />
departments or other institutions. It is not a proper<br />
function of the National Advisory Committee to be an alternative<br />
funding agency for projects which the responsible departments<br />
or a:, ncies do not wish to handle or which fall through e<br />
bureaucratic grid because the nature of the project<br />
clearly within the province ) f any one department of<br />
Alternative funding will only push women's problems into th'.<br />
cracks and spaces between existing departrf ts and institr<br />
, c would be far better and have much more far-reaching<br />
conse,.-" nces to attempt to change the d ides of peop<br />
within these institntions rather than to byao,<br />
is a way of attempting to ensure that our ob3)-ivw.: coI.-<br />
after 1975. / 23 A </p>
<p>23<br />
The National Advisory Committee will act as a focus<br />
for the demands that are coming in from women all over<br />
Australia, channel these demands into the appropriate<br />
departments, argue the need, the facts and the pro's and<br />
con's with the departments and act as a catalyst for action.<br />
Simultaneously, it can perform an educative role for the<br />
women or groups who have sent in submissions by, for example,<br />
informing them which government departments and authorities,<br />
state and local governments or other institutions have the<br />
responsibility for their projects and of progress and impedimehts.<br />
Unless women gain political education and expertise<br />
their ability to bring about the changes they want will not<br />
be increased. This latter must be an important task for the<br />
Year. * The sorts of projects which lie within the<br />
responsibility of existing institutions are, for exa-iD!-. ld<br />
care centres, women's health centres, women's refuges,, iamily<br />
planning clinics, sex education programs, retraining schemes,<br />
legal aid, distressed housing, adult education, English<br />
1 t. iguage courses, rape crisis centres, intc. Lpreters for nc<br />
Engl*-h speaking people, town planninr-, pensions, consumre&gt;<br />
standards, counselling centres, sport, voca-L..<br />
and so on. Such projects must be an integral part of any<br />
government planning if governments are to respond to the ./ 24 </p>
<p>24<br />
needs of the community as a whcle. They require a colmmitment<br />
to ongoing funding running costs and the like. This is a<br />
commitment that the National Advisory Committee is not in a<br />
position to give. Its direct funding must primarily be<br />
restricted either to once only funding or to commitments that<br />
can be fulfilled within its life span.<br />
Women must be given more freedom within their<br />
chosen life patterns and more freedom in choosing alternative<br />
life patterns. They are at present bound in networks of<br />
limitations affecting their whole lives, bound by the range<br />
of possibilities open to them, by their immediate situations.<br />
The funds which are available to the National Advisory Committee<br />
must go towards activities that will help re-form or form anew<br />
the way things are in such a way as to re-affirm basic human<br />
values: sensitivity to people's needs, thoughtfulness, space<br />
and t. ra-e to develop one's potential, support and encourag( ent<br />
rather than competition. Our primary purpose must bE 1-o c<br />
attitudes, to give the world little shove in the righdirection.<br />
Some Considerations The question the lives of wi-. LA. women and how<br />
many will be eased by a project must be the<br />
asked. As choices will h-a~ re to be made between proposals<br />
are certain considerations which must be taken into account:<br />
that in the course of the year we must reach<br />
most if not all women either through projects<br />
potentially of benefit to all women or through </p>
<p>projects which specifically relate to<br />
areas of distress, suffering or discrimination<br />
that no group of women should advance or gain<br />
benefits at the expense of any other women or<br />
group of women<br />
that the proposal must be able to be implemented<br />
in the present social, political and economic<br />
climate<br />
Not only those sectors of society which are<br />
articulate that is, able to write submissions, approach<br />
governments, etc. should benefit by the Year.<br />
There are further considerations which are also<br />
important: that the proposal must increase the possibilities<br />
of individual change and growth<br />
( ii) that it must help women to gain self reliance,<br />
self confidence, self pride ai. d independence<br />
( iii) that wherever possible and relevant it should<br />
increase women's knowledge of the structure of<br />
the existing institutions and increase their<br />
political awareness ./ 26 </p>
<p>26<br />
( iv) that whilst it is important to build a women's<br />
culture this should encompass and be accessible<br />
to all.<br />
However, there must be an awareness that not all<br />
proposals, no matter how initially attractive, will be to the<br />
benefit of women or indeed of society in general. Thus, for<br />
example, the fight for protective legislation for women:<br />
although this legislation in the short term may have been<br />
beneficial, in the long term it has worked to the disadvantage<br />
of women in the workforce and ensured the continuation of<br />
unequal employment opportunities. These, in turn, have ensured<br />
the continuing existence of low paid, low status jobs which<br />
inevitably become women's jobs.<br />
Hence, each proposal must be carefully considered,<br />
the aavantages argued and the harmful effects weighed. At<br />
the same time, it must also be recognised that differ"-t wo n<br />
or groups of women will have different ways of working to<br />
achieve our objectives.<br />
There is, however, another important consideration.<br />
Whatev-. life women choose for themselves it is essential<br />
that the value of this life be neither undermined rt,, vorlooked.<br />
It is essential that women have a sense of self pride and of<br />
independence. Government handouts or " gifts" do not necessarily<br />
instil this. Thus funding should be on a percentage basis, / 27 </p>
<p>27<br />
with, wherever possible, the rest of the funds obtained from<br />
other institutions or raised by the women themselves. The<br />
former will bring other authorities to recognise the needs of<br />
women and accept responsibility for them. These activities<br />
can also increase women's confidence in their ability to<br />
achieve the changes they want and provide opportunities to<br />
develop new skills and gain more knowledge.<br />
The Committee intends to concentrate on funding<br />
projects which will change people's attitudes, force them to<br />
question and re-think their assumptions, beliefs, prejudices..<br />
and opinions about women, their " proper" roles and their<br />
capacities and force them to become aware of their attitudes<br />
and responses.<br />
Priorities trhere are certain areas which affect or potentially<br />
affect every girl and woman in our society, whatever brr<br />
education, her cultural background, her economic status, her<br />
beliefs, her occupation or her way of life. These are:<br />
health and welfare<br />
child care<br />
* education work creativity general community attitudes ./ 28 </p>
<p>28<br />
There are many projects which fall under the first<br />
five which are the responsibility of existing government<br />
departments or instrumentalities. However ( with the possible<br />
exception of child care, for which a totally integrated and<br />
all-embracing $ 75 million initial program is under way) there<br />
are many other important projects for which International<br />
Women's Year funds could be used and which would help people<br />
gain more information about existing services or programs,<br />
would help women to gain the self-confidence, information and<br />
knowledge necessary to lessen areas of distress, discrimination<br />
or suffering. Some or all of these projects, e. g. the provision<br />
of extensive support services for migrant women, will, hopefully,<br />
as they educate the community, begin to challenge the accepted<br />
attitudes and myths which are prevalent in our society. Not<br />
only the projects funded by International Women's Year will<br />
have this impact. Those projects which are the resl sib ty<br />
of existing Government departments, once integrated within<br />
their administrative responsibility, will provide the broad<br />
base of support, self-confidence and security which, in the<br />
past, has been largely lacking for women, and without which<br />
any specific moves aimed at attitudinal change ( such as<br />
International Womer's Year) would fail.<br />
In many instances, projects will fall within more<br />
than one of the areas singled out above. Further, specifying<br />
these areas is not meant to exclude any other area of need that<br />
is known to exist or which comes to light in the course of our<br />
activities. / 29 </p>
<p>29<br />
These areas have been singled out in orderto<br />
give direction to our initial decisions on activities and<br />
funding. It is our belief that when interpreted broadly<br />
education as a life long process; health as including the<br />
problems of isolation and breakdown of attitudes of women<br />
to their bodies and doctors to women; work including that<br />
done at home as well as in the paid workforce that these<br />
are the areas that affect, at some time in their life, all<br />
women. Obviously there must be priorities within these<br />
areas and certain activities will be funded initially. The<br />
considerations which will guide these decisions have been<br />
set out above. Projects funded must not only be in line<br />
with our objectives but, whenever appropriate, must ensure<br />
that every effort is made to involve or reach all the<br />
immedi. ateiy relevant sectors of the community and, where<br />
appropriate, must maximise the possibility of contir ' ng<br />
and increasing benefits arising out of it. This latter can<br />
be achieved, for example, by including in the project the<br />
teaching of the skills necessary for this to occur or by<br />
recording successful projects in such a way that other groups<br />
can ñ;. arn from the experience and carry the project out<br />
elsewhere. The former point about involvemet nt<br />
because there are many people in our society who whilst bei; iv<br />
interested may be reluctant to participate because of, for<br />
example, the unfamiliarity of the surroundings, feeling of<br />
inadequacy particularly where skills are involved, lack of<br />
self confidence, a disparity between the languages, culture, </p>
<p>30<br />
socio-economic levels, etc., of the organisers and the<br />
community or many other factors.<br />
As well as the specific community assumptions and<br />
attitudes which lie behind and aggravate many of the problems<br />
in these areas there are also more general community attitudes<br />
which show up in the way women are spoken about or ignored,<br />
depicted in comic strips, advertisements and books, omitted<br />
from history and other areas of research, stifled in their<br />
creative potential, encouraged to be dependent or irresponsible,<br />
assumed to be unreliable in the paid workforce or assumed to<br />
have an easy life at home.<br />
These attitudes too must be challenged and re-examined.<br />
To do this properly there is a need to have much more information,<br />
facts and statistics available and to stimulate much more<br />
research not just into the gaps in our knowledge but also into<br />
the determinants and consequences of changes in wome ' s st . us<br />
and roles. There will be a publicity campaign and in this as<br />
in all activities for the year every care must be taken about<br />
the , L rs used. To claim that the money spent on educating<br />
girls is waL; ted if they only become receptioi. t<br />
on the awfulness of housework is to insult and humiliate c] us.-<br />
women who are receptionists or who earn a living by cleaning<br />
up the messes of other human beings. To argue that all women<br />
should be in the workforce is not only to turn a blind eye to<br />
/ 31 </p>
<p>31-<br />
the problems and suspect values of the present workforce but<br />
is to induce feelings of guilt and inadequacy in those women<br />
who may have chosen to ( and are able to) live a different<br />
life style. To keep on and on about the exhaustion, the<br />
frustration and the limitations of being at home with young<br />
children may merely increase these feelings without offering<br />
any solution: to offer congratulations on doing a highly<br />
skilled, complex and, at times, impossibly difficult job may<br />
begin to place value on a task which up until now has been<br />
both economically and socially undervalued.<br />
Funding The $ 2 million which has been set aside for the<br />
1974/ 75 financial year is to be spent in the following ways:<br />
direct funding of groups or individuals<br />
financing of special activities by departments<br />
administrative costs and the costs of those<br />
activities which the Committee itself organises<br />
and carries out.<br />
Since the main thrust of our activities is towards<br />
attitudinal change ' ere will be significant expenkv.~ Lrc -) r<br />
such things as a newsletter, a research task force, publicity,<br />
the convening of conferences, workshops, seminars, the<br />
employment of consultants and of community catalysts. / 32 </p>
<p>32-<br />
Whilst the setting of a closing date or dates might<br />
make the administrative burden easier, it is clearly preferable<br />
that submissions be able to continue to come in as needs arise<br />
or are recognised and also that submissions be not hastily<br />
written or ill-conceived because of the stricture of an early<br />
closing date. Moreover continual funding allows the reviewing<br />
of priorities and decisions in the light of experience as the<br />
year progresses. It will also enable submissions not originally<br />
funded because of a lower priority to be later reconsidered.<br />
In summary then the strategy for funding will becontinuous<br />
funding with initial funding being<br />
according to priorities in the areas outlined<br />
above<br />
( ii) continuous review of priorities and contin~ ous<br />
assessment of the worthwhileness of funded<br />
activities<br />
( iii) reassessment of submissions in light of ( ii).<br />
This strategy enables immediate funding, particulr',<br />
of p. _-sals requiring early attention, t,. d also allows. i<br />
progressive receipt1k examination and decisio. is u<br />
There is a need to ensure proper stewardship of<br />
Government monies. There is also a need to ensure the<br />
technical competence of an applicant to receive a grant and<br />
to ensure that any project funded is carried out in the best </p>
<p>-6 33<br />
possible way. Hence it i: proposed that ai-seriously<br />
considered applicants be interviewed by CommiLLee members,<br />
members of the Secretariat or other appropriate persons.<br />
Conclusion The above are the priorities and considerations<br />
which will guide the Government's activities and decisions<br />
during the coming year.<br />
The program which will arise out of them will<br />
inevitably reflect our concern that each member of our<br />
society be allowed the freedom necessary to develop within<br />
and participate in that society. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
