<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4432</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S ADDRESS TO THE NATION, 3 JULY 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/07/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004432.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Embargoed until delivery F 77/ 142<br />
1FOR PRESS JULY .19.77<br />
PRIME. MINISTER'S ADDRESS TO THE. NATION : 3 JULY .19.77<br />
It was good to return to Australia last Tuesday after discussions<br />
in the United Kingdom, Europe and in the United States. I would<br />
like to take a few moments to touch on three aspects: the<br />
Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in London, relations<br />
between the United States and Australia, relations between the<br />
European Economic Community and * Australia, and their importance<br />
to Us.<br />
At the Commonwealth Conference there was a valuable opportunity to<br />
meet and get to know the leaders of about a quarter of the world's<br />
population. The discussions there centred to a large extent on<br />
the prQblems of developing~ co * untries, which is not surprisIng<br />
because about 900 million of the world's people have incomes of<br />
Australian or less a year. Australia committed herself to a<br />
substantial increase in food aid, but however important aid might<br />
be, fairer and more equitable international trade is likely in the<br />
longer term to be much more helpful.<br />
Many developing countries depend upon one or two commodities<br />
such as sugar for their overseas income. In recent years the<br />
prices of commodities have Varied very widely. Commodity prices<br />
have tended to fall in relation to other goods, making it hard for<br />
developing countries to pursue their own development plans in a<br />
reasonable way. If we cannot achieve better trading arrangements<br />
and more stable prices at reasonable levels for the developing.<br />
countries, there is going to be a great deal of disillusion.<br />
Australia has extensive experience to offer in this area. We<br />
have participated in international agreements for sugar and for<br />
wheat in the past, and I therefore suggested that a technical<br />
working group should be established to work out what progress can<br />
be made within a reasonable time frame. The Conference accepted<br />
that suggestion, and such a working group will be set up.<br />
At the Commonwealth Conference, much time was also spent discussing<br />
the problems of Southern Africa. Apartheid is a pernicious and evil<br />
doctrine which has long been condemned from Australia. Sir Robert<br />
Menzics condemned apartheid as early as 1961, indicating that in his<br />
view it was a policy that would end~ in the most frightful disaster.<br />
The problems of Zimbabwe Rhodesia. are very real and they are<br />
urgent. The British Prime minister indicated that it was his<br />
Government's objective to have Zimbabwe seated as an independent<br />
state at the next Commonwealth Conference in 1979. / The United States </p>
<p>The United States is lending its support to the United Kingdom's<br />
efforts. I believe that there is now greater hope that a negotiated.<br />
solution will be reached in relation to this very difficult problem.<br />
I also think time is running out for those who want a negotiated<br />
settlement a peaceful settlement. The longer a settlement is<br />
delayed, the more people will come to believe that the only solution<br />
will be through some violent means that would leave scars on the<br />
face of Africa, scars between countries, that we could well do<br />
without. For Australia, I spoke with a clear voice on these issues, supporting<br />
the efforts of the United Kingdom and of the United States, because<br />
it is important that countries such as Australia speak plainly about<br />
these issues. It is important that those supporting the white<br />
minority government in Rhodesia, in Zimbabwe, know that they have<br />
no international support. If they know they have no international<br />
support, there will be a great likelihood of achieving a peaceful,<br />
negotiated, solution.<br />
It was also important for the Commonwealth Conference to condemn<br />
what is happening in Uganda, and President Amin's regime was overwhelmingly<br />
condemned by the Conference. I believe everyone<br />
recognised that it would have been one sided to take the attitudes<br />
that were taken in relation to Rhodesia, to Zimbabwe, while<br />
remaining silent in relation to Uganda. But the Commonwealth<br />
did speak, in forthright terms, and in strong terms. Thus the<br />
Commonwealth's own reputation as an organisation with concern for<br />
human decency was enhanced. It expressed its views fairly and<br />
fearlessly. In the United States, I emphasised the importance that Australia<br />
attaches to making progress on the issues of race in Southern<br />
Africa. I also emphasised the importance of the grave economic<br />
issues affecting the developing world. Beyond that, with President<br />
Carter and other officers-of his administration, there were very<br />
full discussions on the political and strategic matters affecting<br />
the Western Pacific, South East Asia and the Indian Ocean.<br />
Concerning the Indian Ocean, I found an identity of interest on<br />
the need to stabilise the situation. Our views are being taken<br />
into account very fully in the consultations now going on between<br />
the Soviet Union and the United States and our views will be fully<br />
taken into account before any eventual agreement.<br />
President Carter is in many ways initiating a new and exciting era<br />
in international politics. For too long in the past democracies<br />
have been on the defensive. They have been reactive to events,<br />
on the defensive in relation to material matters and in relation<br />
to ideas. Of all the political philosophies, democracy ought not<br />
to be on the defensive because the very idea of a free people uniting<br />
tthoagte thtehre wion rlgdo vhearsn mesneten . i s tBhuet miots ti s nnobelcee sseaxrpye rifmoern td emino crgoavteircn mleenatd* ers<br />
to proclaim the value and virtues of democracies.<br />
President Carter understands this, and he expresses it very well<br />
indeed. What he is doing in relation to human rights, nonproliferation<br />
and United States-Soviet relations, demonstrates<br />
very real concern for matters of importance. / It is </p>
<p>3<br />
It is important from Australia's point of view that President<br />
Carter, himself and his administrators, want to hear our views<br />
on matters of common concern before pol. icies are decided. I<br />
know very well that if a matter is important enough there is<br />
immediate access to the White House in matters that affect<br />
Australia's national interest.<br />
Now I would like to talk for a moment about our relations with<br />
the European Economic Community a group of 260 million people,<br />
perhaps the wealthiest, the most scientific and technologically<br />
advanced group that the world has seen, and certainly a very powerful<br />
trading group. The European Community has had a reputation for<br />
being in favour of low levels of protection, almost for being free<br />
traders. They have had that reputation despite the fact that in<br />
agriculture their policies of protection have made it almost<br />
impossible for products from countries like Australia to be sold<br />
in Europe. We have lost many markets because of their agricultural<br />
policies of high protection. They have not only done that, but<br />
have also subsidised their surplus products for sale on other<br />
markets, thus disrupting the traditional markets of Australia<br />
and other countries. While these policies applied only to<br />
agricultural produce, they seemed to be able to get away with<br />
this, and still have their reputation for favouring low levels<br />
of protection.<br />
Recently we have seen a very disturbing development with these<br />
policies of high levels of protection being applied to manufactured<br />
goods from Japan, or to Australian steel. I was very surprised to<br />
learn in Europe that they regarded Australia as an unfair competitor<br />
in steel, and that they wanted us voluntarily to restrict exports<br />
to Europe. Their definition of unfair competition seems to be<br />
competition which harms European industry. If this is allowed<br />
to continue, it is going to have very serious consequences for<br />
international trade.<br />
Our manufacturing industry has a base market of about 14 million.<br />
people compared to Europe's 260 million people, and that is why,<br />
in many instances, we do need higher levels of protection than does<br />
Europe. But even when our industries are harmed by international<br />
trade, we have still allowed access to our markets, and market<br />
penetration has often increased despite some damage to Australian<br />
industries. If we'acted as Europe acted in those circumstances,<br />
we would say imports must cease entirely. But we have not done this.<br />
We have taken a responsible course. These are serious matters and<br />
there are going to be discussions in coming months between the<br />
European Community and Australia, and between France, Germany, and<br />
the United Kingdom and Australia. At these discussions the<br />
totality of our commercial and trading relations will be<br />
discussed, and I would hope that we would reach some solution<br />
for these very difficult and important problems.<br />
In Europe I found that the main matter they wished to discuss<br />
with me was uranium. They look upon Australia as a potential<br />
reliable supplier of energy for the homes, for the factories of<br />
Europe, so that their people can be employed, and so that their<br />
standard of life can be maintained. We sometimes forget that<br />
Europe is short of energy and desperately wants secure and<br />
reliable supplies, not for a few months, but for years ahead.<br />
/ I made </p>
<p>4<br />
I made it plain that my Government has yet to make a decision<br />
whether or not uranium exports will be allowed, but it is a<br />
very important matter from their point of view as well as from<br />
ours. I make the point now, as I made it to them; that if<br />
Europeans want stability of access to supplies of energy, to<br />
supplies of uranium, it is reasonable enough for us to seek to<br />
have that principle of stability applied to access to their<br />
markets. Stability is a principle that cannot just apply to one part<br />
of trade between nations. It ought to apply to supplies of<br />
raw materials and to access to markets, and I believe that<br />
Europeans are coming to understand that. Therefore, I hope<br />
very much that the discussions that we will be having will lead<br />
to the acceptance on both sides of some sensible principles<br />
which will lead to a better and a more reliable trading<br />
relationship. The discussions overseas were timely. They will have made it<br />
possible for Australia to contribute more effectively to<br />
international peace; to advance sensible trading relations;<br />
and at the same time to advance Australia's own national<br />
interest. 1. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
