<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3314</transcript-id>
    <title>NEW LAND DEAL FOR NORTHERN TERRITORY ABORIGINALS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/07/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003314.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 281<br />
2 July 1974<br />
NEW LAND DEAL FOR NORTHERN TERRITORY ABORIGINALS<br />
The Prime. Minister, Mr Whitlam, today announced that<br />
Cabinet had accepted in principle the recommendations made in<br />
the Second Report of the Aboriginal Land Rights Commission.<br />
, Mr Whitlam said that the recommendations provided for<br />
full Aboriginal ownership of all existing reserves in the<br />
Northern Territory and certain other lands and for the establishment<br />
of a Land Commission to enquire into Aboriginal land claims and<br />
land needs outside the Reserves. Aboriginal Regional Land<br />
Councils and Land Trusts would be incorporated to hold title<br />
and administer land matters.<br />
Cabinet authorised preliminary drafting of a comprehensive<br />
Aboriginal Land ( Northern Territory) Bill with a view to the<br />
Minister for Aboriginal Affairs introducing the Bill into the<br />
Parliament during the Budget Sittings. Final drafting must,<br />
however, await full consultation with the Northern Territory<br />
Aboriginals through their Land Councils, which are at present<br />
considering the Report's recommendations.<br />
Cabinet also authorised the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs<br />
to appoint an Interim Land Commissioner, in order to hasten action<br />
on suchmatters as the provision of land for the Gurindji of<br />
Wave Hill and for Aboriginal groups in towns. Any such<br />
appointment would be without prejudice to the outcome of discussions<br />
with the Aboriginals.<br />
Drafting of Bills to provide for the incorporation of<br />
Aboriginal groups and communities, and for the establishment of an<br />
Aboriginal Land Fund is already well advanced. The Aboriginal<br />
Corporations Bill will allow the incorporation of Aboriginal<br />
Councils, some of which could hold land in accordance with the.<br />
Commission's recommendations. Other lands would be held by<br />
Trusts to be established under the proposed land legislation.<br />
The Land Fund will provide for the purchase of lands in<br />
the Northern Territory as recommended by the proposed Aboriginal<br />
Land Commission. It is proposed, however, that the Fund should<br />
be used for land purchases in the States as well as in the<br />
Northern Territory.<br />
ThXe Minister for Aboriginal Affairs will be discussing the<br />
Commission's Report with State Ministers responsible for<br />
Aboriginal affairs. This matter was discussed at the recent<br />
Premiers' Conference.<br />
CANBERRA. ACT. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
