<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8302</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LAUNCH OF THE ENVIRONMENT MANAGEMENT INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 30 MAY 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/05/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008302.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
t! Wt! W k( nkTMT1 MT. YIMOV ' WQ1utrInfl IVKM'TT. n7T. TuIDv'<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIM KINISTERt<br />
LAUNCH OF THE K IRONMENT MANAGEENT<br />
INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 30 MAY 1991<br />
Environment management is an industry that clearly will<br />
assume greater importance in coming years. Equally clearly-,<br />
this association we are launching today will play a key role<br />
in ensuring the industry can meet its new responsibilities<br />
and take up the many opportunities that will emerge.<br />
The formation of your Association is another indication of<br />
the rapid changes taking place in the attitudes of<br />
Australians to environmental matters.<br />
We are growing acutely aware that much of our landscape<br />
bears the mark of human activity, and that this has wrought<br />
permanent environmental change and, not infrequently,<br />
degradation. Australians are coming to grips with our<br />
responsibility to care for and to protect the unique<br />
landscape that is our national home.<br />
For industry, this poses the double challenge: to be not<br />
only economically competitive but also ecologically<br />
sustainable. We must conserve our finite resources, reduce<br />
polluting emissions and preserve our natural environment in<br />
a way which enables us to satisfy integrated economic and<br />
environmental objectives.<br />
Meeting this challenge will demand we seriously rethink the<br />
way in which we, and the rest of the world, carry on our<br />
agriculture and other primary activities, undertake our<br />
manufacturing processes, build our homes and plan our<br />
cities. But at the same time this double challenge brings with it<br />
new commercial opportunities. It is highly significant<br />
that, even in difficult economic times, Australians are<br />
demanding more and better environmental management services.<br />
You are, indeed, an industry with a future.<br />
The Government has, of course, responded to changes in<br />
community attitudes by putting in place many environmental<br />
initiatives. For your Association, none is more important<br />
than our initiative. to develop strategies to achieve<br />
ecologically sustainable development. </p>
<p>Last year we released a paper on Ecologically Sustainable<br />
Development as a stimulus for discussion on this issue.<br />
Since then, nine sectoral working groups have been<br />
established to help translate the concept of ESD into<br />
effective strategies.<br />
The working groups are to complete their reports by October,<br />
for consideration at the Special Premiers' Conference<br />
planned for November.<br />
Given the complexity of the issues and the often conflicting<br />
interests involved, I am encouraged by the progress that is<br />
being made. The outcome of the process will provide a sound<br />
basis for us to achieve ecologically sustainable<br />
development. But clearly, government can only do so much in achieving<br />
ESD. The bulk of the task rests with the community and the<br />
private sector.<br />
Environment management industries and their new<br />
association can contribute in a major way to achieving the<br />
goal of ecologically sustainable development and, at the<br />
same time, helping make Australia a ' clever country'. Your<br />
industry can help to demonstrate that ecologically<br />
sustainable development is consistent with strong economic<br />
growth. This is an area where Australia has the potential to develop<br />
a world class industry, capable of producing services and<br />
products which the rest of the world will increasingly<br />
demand. In particular, the possibilities for developing<br />
industry opportunities in the Asia-Pacific region are<br />
enormous, as standards of living rise and, with them,<br />
demands for effective environmental management.<br />
In many ways you are the focal point for the interaction of<br />
those who face environmental problems and those who possess<br />
the skills, technologies or products to solve them. This<br />
will help the industry and, through the removal of<br />
environmental problems, it will help the people of Australia<br />
and the world. Your Association can also be the catalyst<br />
for the development of networks within the industry with the<br />
size and skills to tender for, and to win, overseas<br />
contracts. I might mention that at the meeting of my Science Council<br />
earlier this month, industry representatives identified<br />
several impediments to further growth of the waste<br />
management industry in Australia an industry which is<br />
estimated to be worth some SUS 200 billion a year world<br />
wide. Members of the Science Council were impressed by the<br />
export opportunities that exist if we have the courage and<br />
the commitment to seize them. </p>
<p>3.<br />
As a result of that meeting, Ministers who are members of<br />
the Council undertook to examine carefully the<br />
recommendations put forward by the industry. A working<br />
party, with industry representation, will be set up to<br />
examine the specific recommendations made to the Science<br />
Council and to develop appropriate policy strategies to<br />
enable Australia to capture those export opportunities.<br />
These will then be referred to the Cabinet Sub-committee on<br />
sectoral industry initiatives that I announced in my<br />
Statement to Parliament on 12 March.<br />
Progress on some matters that have been raised will not be<br />
easy. But I want to assure you that my Government will do<br />
all we can to remove impediments and to provide a framework<br />
in which the full potential of the waste management industry<br />
can be realised.<br />
So for many reasons the creation of this Association is a<br />
welcome development. I congratulate your Steering Committee<br />
and interim Council for the excellent job they have done. I<br />
appreciate also the role that has been played by the Clunies<br />
Ross Foundation in supporting the formation of the<br />
Association. It is with pleasure, and with good wishes for the future,<br />
that I now launch the Environment Management Industry<br />
Association of Australia.<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
