<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22642</transcript-id>
    <title>Financial Support for Victorian Bushfire Victims  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/12/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Overnight the devastating bushfires in Victoria's Gippsland and north-east have claimed a life and destroyed a number of homes.  Prime Minister John Howard and Premier Steve Bracks express their sympathies to the family and friends of the man who lost his life fighting the fires.</p>
<p> The Prime Minister and Premier have agreed to provide more than $800,000 in additional funding to help families, business and primary producers recover from the devastating bushfires.</p>
<p>The agreement establishes a $700,000 Community Recovery Fund with equal contributions from the State and Commonwealth.  This is over and above the support the Commonwealth government provides under the enhanced Natural Disaster Relief Arrangements.</p>
<p>The Community Recovery Fund would be used to address the needs of the community as they arise and to assist the region to recover fully from the fires.</p>
<p>The funding would support grants of up to $15,000 for charities, small business and primary producers to assist with costs that are not covered by insurance arrangements.</p>
<p>Arrangements for the payment of funding under the grants are expected to be in place by Monday, 18 December 2006.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth and Victoria have also agreed to contribute $50,000 each to the Red Cross Bushfire Appeal to assist families, small business and communities affected by the bushfires in Victoria.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister and Premier pay tribute to the efforts of all firefighters, emergency services and community groups working together to fight these fires.  The Prime Minister and Premier are committed to working together and with local communities to provide any assistance wherever possible.</p>
<p>The Victorian Premier, Steve Bracks welcomed the increased funding which is in addition to the significant commitments the Victorian Government had already made to its bushfire recovery programs.</p>
<p>The funding will be jointly administered by the State and Federal Governments and both governments are committed to a quick and smooth approval process for the new Community Recovery Fund grants.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth and Victorian Governments will consider further assistance for the regions once the full extent of the damage from the current bushfire has been assessed.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
