<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2159</transcript-id>
    <title>Visit of US Vice-President - Presentation of Apollo 11 Flag and Moon Rock in Parliament House, Canberra</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/01/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002159.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>14 January 1970</strong></p>
<p>Mr Vice-President and Colonel Stafford:</p>
<p>It is with a considerable amount of pride that on behalf of the Parliament and people of Australia I accept what you have brought back from one of man' s greatest adventures.</p>
<p>When the first successful landing on the moon took place, I described it as a dramatic fulfilment of man's urge "to go always a little further, to explore and know the formerly unknown, to strive, to seek, to find and not to yield". I think it was this desire of the human spirit which was exemplified by this co-operative effort, a co-operative effort for peace, a co-operative effort to find out more, to know more, so that we in this world might in the future be the better off.</p>
<p>It is very appropriate that you should have given us two photographs, one of Australia, the other a photograph of the North American continent, because I think you would agree it is true to say that part of the success of this historic mission was due to people from the North American continent and to people from Australia. And how appropriate it is that there should be here today so many men and women engaged in work at those tracking stations which were an essential and integral part of this great adventure.</p>
<p>We thank you -  I do on behalf of the Parliament and the Australian people -  for the moon rock and for the flag of this country which you took on this mission. On behalf of the Parliament and the Australian people, I thank too all those Australians and Americans who were engaged in being such an essential part of this magnificent enterprise.</p>
<p>We all thank you, Sir, and may these first trips be only the beginning of a continuing adventure for mankind and for both our countries in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
