<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8744</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP TO THE WALKEY AWARDS PRESENTATION DINNER - ANA HOTEL SYDNEY, 27 NOVEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008744.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I:.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ. KEATING, MP<br />
TO THE WALKLEY AWARDS PRESENTATION DINNER ANA HOTEL,<br />
SYDNEY, 27 NOVEMBER 1992<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
It is a great pleasure to be here tonight.<br />
It is always a pleasure to be among the nation's press.<br />
I have only a hazy idea of why this is so.<br />
But that is better than the Leader of the Opposition who has no idea at all.<br />
Let me get the politics over with early. I don't share this Nixonian you won't have me to<br />
kick around any more attitude.<br />
I like engagement.<br />
The Garboesque has no attraction for me. I don't want to be alone.<br />
I ask myself these days does this make me peculiar?<br />
That I like to talk to the press?<br />
That, wrong-headed or inconvenient as they sometimes are, like journalists?<br />
That like politics?<br />
Am I wrong to believe that for all the inevitable imperfections this is one of the world's<br />
better democracies and Australian journalists are a powerful reason why this is so?<br />
I don't think I IM wrong.<br />
I think it must be a kind of cultural attraction that you have for me.<br />
I see the press down the back of the plane on overseas trips fierce and hungry, like<br />
grizzly bears on a package tour of the Orient.<br />
There are members of my staff who are too frightened to walk down the aisle between<br />
them to go to the toilet. 4423 </p>
<p>They wait till nightfall and tiptoe down when they're all asleep little knowing that<br />
journalists ame at their most dangerous after dark.<br />
Yet I can't resist going down for a yarn..<br />
I think the reason I enjoy the company of journalists, even when I can see by the look in<br />
their eyes that they would like to tear me limb from limb, is that Ilactually like democracy.<br />
It has its problems, democracy.. It doesn't always turn up the results we want. It can be as<br />
frustrating to those of us who want change as it is to conservatives who want the world to<br />
stand still.<br />
But it's far and away the best form of government anybody has ever come up with, and I<br />
must say I think it is my natural habitat.<br />
In fact it seems to mec that in Australia we probably don't sufficiently appreciate the facts<br />
of our democratic achievement that this is one of the great democracies of the world<br />
and, we shouldn't forget, one of the oldest.<br />
Those who complain about politics and politicians in Australia have a point. The number<br />
of our governments creates a demand for good politicians in excess of the supply.<br />
And the good ones have to learn to live in a maelstrom which is often made more by<br />
media forces than by political or policy ones.<br />
Televising parliament has dramatically increased that tendency and set all sorts of new<br />
ii-iWa'o-i &amp; litical success.<br />
For every politician who thrives in this environment there are others who drown, or who<br />
merely cling to the sides, or stay forever unnoticed, tucked up in the vortex.<br />
There is a lot of room for improvement. It does get a bit rugged, and, no doubt, dispiriting<br />
for electors.<br />
But so long s! iQuestion-Time is the televised spectacle of questions without notice being<br />
fired at ministers in the hope of getting them to publicly slip up, there will be severe<br />
pressures on nicety and decorum.<br />
And so long as it is also the forum in which the great questions of the day are fought out, it<br />
will be more than a game of croquet. It will be very often verbal war and no one<br />
prepared to go to war should fight it with less than total commitment.<br />
And really, while it is more public now than perhaps it used to be, the House of<br />
Representatives has always been a rugged place.<br />
Since Federation since parliaments began there has been sniping and pantomime in<br />
styles as various as the human personality.<br />
There has been absolute savagery sometimes.<br />
And we Australians are not alone in it.<br />
4424 </p>
<p>Few Australian politicians have declared their loathing of their opponents in the terms that<br />
Winston Churchill did.<br />
" I hate the Tory party" he said " their men, their words, and their methods."<br />
rye always had a soft spot for Churchill.<br />
That was the same Winston Churchill who, in the House of Commons, called Ramsay<br />
MacDonald " the boneless wonder".<br />
Yet in Australia, which is said to be such a rough-house, it would be considered a bit<br />
beyond the bounds of decency in Australia to say you actually hated the Opposition.<br />
At the very least you would have to be funny about it.<br />
And I know if I called someone " the boneless wonder" on a day when there was not much<br />
other news around, you could be sure that night there would be a fair bit of pious clicking<br />
of tongues in the vicinity of television screens.<br />
Particularly because the grab, almost certainly, would be taken out of its context.<br />
Context is everything.<br />
What Churchill described to the House was how he had been taken to the circus as a child,<br />
where the advertised exhibit which most interested him had been the one described as Thse<br />
Boneless Wonder.<br />
He went on to say " My parents judged that the spectacle would be too revolting for my<br />
youthful eyes and I have waited fifty years to see The Boneless Wonder sitting on the<br />
Treasury Bench".<br />
You would never get all that on the TV news.<br />
It would just be a grab of me shouting over the din of the Opposition " I've waited fifty<br />
years to see The Boneless Wonder". And a cut-away to Peter Reith feigning hurt and<br />
outrage. Lloyd George once described the House of Commons as being to, a politician what a pub<br />
is to a drunkard meaning that it is their natural envirornent and source of happiness,<br />
however perverse.<br />
I would say much the same about the House of Representatives or any great democratic<br />
chamber. And I'd also say to those who believe that the standard of the place will be raised by<br />
replacing the politicians with some species of non-politician that it would no more do<br />
that, than a pub would be improved by having a clientele of wowsers.<br />
Or a newspaper would be a better newspaper for being written by people without a taste<br />
for politics and people.<br />
Better to have better politicians. Ones who have enough faith in the strength of this<br />
democracy to be prepared to push changes. Tough ones. Passionate ones. Ones who<br />
understand politics and power. 4425 </p>
<p>And better to have journalists who understand these things too.<br />
And proprietors who understand them.<br />
There is a cast to Australian democracy which is unique, and which has given us, I<br />
believe, unique advantages.<br />
The principal thing to understand is that it conmes from the bottom up it is not imposed<br />
from the top.<br />
And I believe that its a source of strength.<br />
If the democracies have been the successful societies of the past century, the most<br />
successful democracies have been the social democracies.<br />
The ones that have not feared the inclusion of the less well off in the social system, or<br />
discarded the social net: but who have seen their strength in it, the source of their selfesteem,<br />
the measure of their worth and national achievement.<br />
If you measure the achievements of Australia, this is where they principally lie. They are<br />
democratic achievements, or, at least, they are cast in a democratic mould.<br />
The fundamentals were laid down at the time of federation or before.<br />
And since then, from the principles of arbitration and the basic wage to the development<br />
of social services with few rivals in the world, the cast of politics in Australia has been<br />
democratic. It underpins the success of multiculturalism, no less than it underpinned the ethos of the<br />
first AIF and the legend it created.<br />
These are out of the egalitarian stamp of Australia.<br />
The same thing underpins the Accol. It underpins our recently revived reputation for<br />
advanced social legislation.<br />
It underpins, I would say, the decision to abolish the discrimination against homosexuals<br />
in the armed force.<br />
It is decisions like this which keep us in the front rank of democracies.<br />
When people say they want to break the mould of Australian politics would say watch<br />
out! Because you can't break it without threatening the mould of society too you can't break<br />
it without threatening the democracy.<br />
And that I think is why it is the case that those who are talking about breaking the mould<br />
of politics carry with them policies to break the mould of Australian society.<br />
Perhaps they fail to understand that the two can't be separated.<br />
Perhaps they understand it very well.<br />
4426 </p>
<p>Perhaps they don't understand that, of all the values and traditions which bind Austraia<br />
those of the people are the strongest and the most important.<br />
Perhaps they confuse tradition with class and caste and official ritual.<br />
it would not be surprising if it was simple confusion: becaus the conservatives in this<br />
country have very often been confused about the fact that our institutions and traditions<br />
belong to the people they made the best of them and if they need changing they will<br />
change them.<br />
I will forgive them their ignorance, of course.<br />
But I doubt if Australians will when they get their chance to judge.<br />
And that, rm inclined to think, is what politicians and political journalists have always to<br />
remember. That politics doesn't start in Canberra. It ends there.<br />
And, just as it does politicians good to escape the unreal world of Canberra, it would do<br />
the political culture no harm if the gallery sometimes extended the peripheries of their<br />
vision. There is a culture in Canberra which encourages politicians and press alike to see only the<br />
links and not the chain.<br />
T7hey are very small links in a very long chain.<br />
They are no more than each day in the political life of the country.<br />
it seems to me that this is one of the reasons why journalists often feel obliged to<br />
editorialise in news stories: it is the only way to make sense of what is more often than not<br />
an uncompleted story.<br />
Too often I think.<br />
I do believe Australians have to pick their way through too much opinion to get to the<br />
news. in fact the opinion becomes part of the news the news today is that Michelle appears to<br />
have changed her mind. Or Geoff has not changed his. Or the jury's still out on what<br />
conclusion Peter will come to.<br />
I do think the Australian news is over interpreted.<br />
I know Gerard Henderson has been saying lately that journalists should improve their<br />
knowledge of history and I agree with him.<br />
He also reckons I should improve mine and I don't agree with him.<br />
But the point is well taken. 4427 </p>
<p>It's not to sy I don't thoroughily enjoy the daily meal the gallery makes of our activities, to<br />
acknowledpe that the democratic culture would be better served by mome of the broader<br />
style of political journalism, and more matter of fact reporting of political events.<br />
I think the bers could hunt in a bigger circle the bigger circle of Australian democracy,<br />
the provenance of our institutions and traditions and ideas.<br />
But I think with equal certainty that what is done now is essential and is done remarkably<br />
well. It is literally true that democracy is impossible without a free press.<br />
And it is literally true, and patently true every day of the political year, that the democracy<br />
which is practised in Canberra would be impossible without the free press which operates<br />
there.<br />
Thank you for having me here.<br />
4428 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
