<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1733</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM. NO. 132/1967 - SENIOR GOVERNMENT APPOINTMENTS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001733.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: 1 L 1Bj RV PM. No. 132/ 1967<br />
SENIOR GOVERNMENT APPOINTMENTS<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr Harold Holt<br />
Sir Edwin Hicks, Secretary to the Department of Defence,<br />
will become Australia's High Commissioner to New Zealand early next<br />
year. He will be succeeded by Sir Henry Bland, at present Secretary<br />
to the Department of Labour and National Service. S11ir Henry's appointment<br />
will be from 3th January, 1968.<br />
Sir Edwin has distinguished himself as one of the Commonwealth's<br />
most able administrators during his eleven years as Permanent<br />
Head of the Department of Defence and, prior to that, when S3ecretary to the<br />
Department of Air from 1951 to 1956. During a period of increased defence<br />
activity, Sir Edwin served in the finest traditions of the Public Service and<br />
the Government Is fortunate that his valued service and advice will be<br />
retained through his acceptance now of the post of High Commissiloner to<br />
New Zealand. Sir Edwin's intimate knowledge of a wide spectrum of<br />
Government policy should prove invaluable In his new post.<br />
The new Secretary to the Department of Defence, Sir Henry<br />
Bland, Is also one of Australia's foremost administrators. A graduate in<br />
law from Sydney University, he was formerly Agent-General for New South<br />
" Hales in London. He joined the Department of Labour and National Service<br />
in 19,46 and, in 1952, at the age of 42, became Cecretary to that Department.<br />
S ir Henry has led numerous A us tralian delegations to conferences of the<br />
International Labour Organization and has had wide and lengthy experience<br />
in public administration. It Is expected that Cabinet will tomorrow have discussions<br />
directed to. the appointment of a successor to the post of Fecretary to the<br />
Department of Labour and National Service.<br />
CANBERRA, 6 December, 1967 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
