<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3260</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EC WHITLAM QC MP, HANDBOOK ON AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT ASSISTANCE TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT PROJECTS - 13 MAY 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003260.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A-IWtA I I 13 May 1974<br />
S'AVEMNT BY THE! PRIME~ MINISTER, ' H110 IN. E. G. WIIITLAM, Q. C. M. P.<br />
HANDBOOK ON AUSTRALIAN GOVER14MENT ASSISTANCE TO LOCAL GOVERN4MENT<br />
PROJECTS 13 MAY 1974<br />
The Australian Government is determined to ensure that<br />
local government plays a full role in our three-tier,<br />
federal system of government, and as part of this we will<br />
see that it is given adequate access to the nation's<br />
finances.<br />
As a major step in enabling local government to obtain the<br />
financial help to which it is entitled, the Department<br />
of Urban and Regional Development has prepared a handbook<br />
for local government and community groups. Entitled<br />
Australian Government Assistance to Local Government Projects<br />
the booklet is a guide to sources of funds and explains,-how<br />
to apply for them..<br />
Local Government in the past has had to battle with a<br />
Cinderella-like existence, starved of funds and with its<br />
significance largely ignored. As if this were not difficult<br />
enough, it has also found itself cut off from assistance,<br />
simply through lack of information about its entitlements.<br />
It is not good enough just to institute programs to assist<br />
the community. Information on these programs must be<br />
easily accessible.<br />
My Government recognises the importance of communication,<br />
and we see the publication of this handbook as a positive<br />
contribution to the kind of open government and citizen<br />
participation to which we are committed.<br />
The handbook, which is being circulated to councillors, local<br />
government officials and to community groups throughout<br />
Australia, describes the wide range of activities which are<br />
eligible for finance and the forms of assistance available<br />
for each one. A brief description is also incorporated of<br />
the existing financial arrangements between the Australian,<br />
State and Local Government.<br />
It is just one of a series of actions and programs through<br />
which my Government has shown its determination to upgrade<br />
the role of local government. Other initiatives include<br />
ensuring that local government was represented at the </p>
<p>' br-' Constitutional Convention, restructuring the Grants Commission<br />
to allow local government to apply for assistance and holding<br />
a referendum to give voters the opportunity to allow the<br />
Commonwealth to grant financial assistance directly to<br />
local government bodies which request it.<br />
I asked the Minister for Urban and Regional Development,<br />
Mr. Uren, to prepare the booklet following a meeting with<br />
the Lord Mayors of the capital cities last December.<br />
During our discussions it emerged that there was considerable<br />
misunderstanding outside Canberra about just what kinds of<br />
Australian Government assistance were available to local<br />
government and local projects.<br />
We have aimed to gather together all the major sources of<br />
this assistance in one easy reference document. Councils or<br />
local groups wanting help will now be able to refer to the<br />
booklet when they want to discover what funds are available<br />
and from whom and how to set about applying for them.<br />
Such a booklet may appear to some a rather dry listing of<br />
Government programs. But its very existence will help to<br />
bring into being many of these programs, in areas like health,<br />
Aboriginal welfare, housing and employment. And these<br />
projects when implemented make a vital difference to the<br />
lives of the people they affect.<br />
Some examples of projects for which assistance is available<br />
include housing of Aboriginal employees, bridging<br />
finance for the development of essential amenities in new<br />
estates, assistance to local governing bodies in providing<br />
a variety of welfare services and grants for new education<br />
projects. With reliable data on just what assistance is available<br />
from the Australian Government for particular projects,<br />
local government and community groups will be able to make<br />
more informed decisions on%. ways to improve the lives of<br />
their communities.<br />
To a certain extent, many of the programs described rely<br />
for their success on active community involvement. We hope<br />
the existence of booklets like this will stimulate community<br />
and local government groups to take new initiatives.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
