<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10921</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS TO THE TOWNSVILLE CHAMBER OF                COMMERCE AND INDUSTRY                SHERATON HOTEL, TOWNSVILLE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/08/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..............................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, thank you very much Mrs Barker. To my parliamentary colleagues</p>
<p> Peter Lindsay, and Ian Macdonald, to the many other distinguished</p>
<p> guests, ladies and gentlemen. Gee this is a terrific venue for a lunchtime</p>
<p> meeting. It is absolutely magnificent and how marvellous it is to</p>
<p> be here in Townsville and how marvellous it is to have an opportunity</p>
<p> of saying a few words about the Government's taxation plan for</p>
<p> the next century. There have been many descriptions given about the</p>
<p> plan and there have been many attempts to put a label on it. Some</p>
<p> talk about a GST, some talk about the tax cuts, some talk about this</p>
<p> or other aspects of the plan that we unveiled last Thursday, but above</p>
<p> and beyond individual sections of the plan, I want, and the Government</p>
<p> wants this to be seen as an integrated attempt to deliver for the</p>
<p> benefit of Australia and for all Australians a taxation plan, a taxation</p>
<p> reform that will sweep away the existing system and replace it with</p>
<p> one that is modern, is contemporary, is relevant and will be in the</p>
<p> long-term economic interests of Australia.</p>
<p>I don't find many people in Australia defending the existing</p>
<p> taxation system. Even those who have criticised the present system,</p>
<p> criticised our plan, will acknowledge, when you talk to them, they</p>
<p> will acknowledge that the present system is out of date. We share</p>
<p> in company with countries such as Botswana and Ghana the maintenance</p>
<p> of a wholesale tax system that was devised in the 1930s when the great</p>
<p> bulk of the Australian economy was based on manufacturing, when the</p>
<p> wholesale sales tax may conceivably have made some sense. Everybody</p>
<p> acknowledges that the present system is flawed, is frail, and is badly</p>
<p> in need of replacement  wholesale replacement.</p>
<p>I've said frequently in the past few days that I was elected</p>
<p> to Parliament in 1974, half-way through the Whitlam experiment. And</p>
<p> within a year of my being in Parliament there was a report tabled</p>
<p> called the Asprey report and it was a report shared by a former judge</p>
<p> of the New South Wales court of appeal into Australia's taxation</p>
<p> system. And you know what the report recommended, and this is in 1975</p>
<p>  23 years ago  the report recommended that we should introduce</p>
<p> a broad based indirect tax and it should apply to virtually everything</p>
<p> and it should replace the existing tax system and it should be accompanied</p>
<p> by reductions in personal income tax. Now, it recommended a lot of</p>
<p> other things that we haven't picked up but that was the essence</p>
<p> of that recommendation, and now, 23 years later, the need for that</p>
<p> kind of fundamental reform that was identified in the mid-1970s is</p>
<p> more pressing, more urgent and more desirable. Now , I know it is</p>
<p> not easy and I have no shortage of people saying to me over the past</p>
<p> couple of weeks, you shouldn't be attempting a change of that</p>
<p> magnitude - it's too risky. Well, let me say in response to those</p>
<p> people, it is necessary to take risks of a personal political kind</p>
<p> in the long term national interests of Australia and the Australian</p>
<p> people. And that is why we are putting this forward as an integrated</p>
<p> plan. We don't believe the Australian people will respect a proposition</p>
<p> that says oh look you don't need to reform the present system,</p>
<p> but we'll offer you a tax cut. I mean, a lazy tax cut has no</p>
<p> credibility at all, but a personal tax restructure that is part and</p>
<p> parcel of an aggregate reform to the Australian taxation system, I</p>
<p> believe, will win very wide support in the Australian community.</p>
<p>Now, there is no one interest group in Australia that has got everything</p>
<p> it wanted out of this tax plan. We didn't set about to satisfy</p>
<p> every individual interest group. What we set out to do was to design</p>
<p> a structure that would deliver a more productive, more efficient Australia</p>
<p> and would be beneficial to the Australian community. We took account</p>
<p> of the views of interest groups, we didn't seek to produce a</p>
<p> plan that aggregated all of their demands. Now you ask me what is</p>
<p> good for Australia about this plan. The best thing about this plan</p>
<p> for Australia is that it reduces the cost of producing goods and services</p>
<p> within our community. It represents the biggest single proposition</p>
<p> by any Government in Australia since World War II to reduce the cost</p>
<p> of doing business.</p>
<p>The introduction of a goods and services tax, to replace the wholesale</p>
<p> sales tax, the financial institutions duties and bank account debit</p>
<p> taxes where they exist, stamp duty on business conveyancing, stamp</p>
<p> duty on shares, stamp duty on promissory notes, cheques and bills</p>
<p> of exchange, the massive reduction in fuel costs which I'll come</p>
<p> to at the moment which is so important to the bush to regional Australia.</p>
<p> All of those things together mean that when this plan is introduced,</p>
<p> the costs of doing business on an annual basis in Australia will be</p>
<p> reduced by approximately $10,000 million. It represents the most generous</p>
<p> export market development grant that any government has offered to</p>
<p> the exporters of Australia, because it will take $4.5 billion off</p>
<p> the costs of exports. There will be no GST on Australian exports and</p>
<p> all of the taxes paid on exporters inputs will be fully rebatable.</p>
<p> It will mean that exporters from this country will be able to compete</p>
<p> on an equal footing with those from other countries seeking access</p>
<p> to the same markets. I often get requests from people in exports saying</p>
<p> why don't you have a special incentive for exporters.</p>
<p>I can't think of a more special and better incentive for exporters</p>
<p> than to take $4.5 billion off their export costs by the introduction</p>
<p> of this plan. It will of course, by delivering a more efficient, a</p>
<p> less costly method of production in this country, it will of course</p>
<p> open up the opportunities for greater job generation. I did a local</p>
<p> press conference this morning, and I was asked by a young lady from</p>
<p> the university, what is this plan going to do for the university students</p>
<p> and my answer was that it will increase your chances of getting a</p>
<p> job when you leave university, because it is going to take costs off</p>
<p> the back of business which haven't been proposed before. Now,</p>
<p> it doesn't take all the costs off the back of business that they</p>
<p> would want but it takes more costs off their back than has ever been</p>
<p> offered in the past. And of course the plan does contain some very</p>
<p> particular provisions which are of enormous long term importance to</p>
<p> people who live in the bush, to people who live in regional Australia.</p>
<p>I've been coming to Townsville now for, as a politician, for</p>
<p> almost 25 years, and I can't remember a visit to Townsville that</p>
<p> hasn't involved somebody complaining to me about the relatively</p>
<p> high cost of delivering goods to this part of Australia compared with</p>
<p> some of the major population centres. So what we have done in this</p>
<p> package and we have done spectacularly is to attack the tyranny of</p>
<p> distance which bedevils the costs of operating businesses and keeping</p>
<p> households together in regional areas of Australia. But what we are</p>
<p> doing is to reduce the business, we are reducing by about $3.5 billion,</p>
<p> the cost of fuel in this country. We are doing it in a number of ways.</p>
<p> The first thing we are doing is we are going to reduce from 43 cents</p>
<p> a litre to 18 cents a litre the excise on diesel used by heavy load</p>
<p> vehicles and the same concession will apply to rail, exactly the same</p>
<p> concession.</p>
<p>In addition we are going to extend the, maintain and slightly extend</p>
<p> the existing exemption in relation to the use of diesel for off-road</p>
<p> purposes, and that will continue and slightly expand the concession</p>
<p> that is now available for primary producers. And a like concession</p>
<p> will apply in relation to ferry and tour boat operators using equivalent</p>
<p> fuels so it is not something that is simply limited to one particular</p>
<p> of the community. Now the impact that this will have on reduced transport</p>
<p> costs around Australia is quite enormous. Many people talk to me about</p>
<p> prices in supermarkets under a GST and they say quite wrongly oh everything</p>
<p> is going to go up by 10%. That's wrong. A lot of things won't</p>
<p> go up by 10%, in fact the average increase will be about 1.9% and</p>
<p> the reason that things won't go up by 10% is that a lot of goods</p>
<p> in supermarkets, a lot of things you buy now are subject to wholesale</p>
<p> sales taxes which are much higher than 10%, a whole range of detergents</p>
<p> and soap powders are taxed at rates of in the order of 22%. There's</p>
<p> a 12% tax now on flavoured milk and some kinds of biscuits and on</p>
<p> orange juice concentrate. There's a 22% tax on the family motor</p>
<p> car, and so the list goes on and on and on.</p>
<p>But there's another component to this argument and that is that</p>
<p> for every item that is delivered on to a supermarket shelf about 20%</p>
<p> of the cost of that item is accounted for by transport costs. You've</p>
<p> got to deliver things from markets, you've got to deliver things</p>
<p> from wholesale warehouses, and all of that involves transportation,</p>
<p> and all of that is very expensive, and if you reduce dramatically</p>
<p> the cost of that transportation, particularly when the goods are delivered</p>
<p> to remoter areas of Australia, particularly when the goods are delivered</p>
<p> to North Queensland, you will get an enormous additional benefit and</p>
<p> it has been calculated at about 20% of the total cost of every item</p>
<p> you take or buy off a supermarket shelf is accounted for by the cost</p>
<p> of transport. So this diesel concession is of huge benefit to the</p>
<p> bush, it is of huge benefit to regional Australia and I should remind</p>
<p> you, although it hasn't been my intent to make an excessively</p>
<p> partisan political address, I will nonetheless take the opportunity</p>
<p> of reminding you that the environmental spokesman for the Australian</p>
<p> Labor Party, Mr Duncan Kerr, has attacked the proposals we have in</p>
<p> relation to diesel excise because he thinks they would be bad for</p>
<p> the environment, and he has made it very very clear that the Labor</p>
<p> Party is opposed to those particular concessions. But there's</p>
<p> another little rub, and a very nice little rub in relation to the</p>
<p> cost of fuel and that is that every business operator, quite apart</p>
<p> from whether you are involved in diesel or on-road or off-road, will</p>
<p> now be able to buy their petrol effectively at 7 cents a litre cheaper</p>
<p> because under the new proposal we are going to reduce the petrol excise</p>
<p> by the extent necessary to allow in the 10% GST, and because the GST</p>
<p> will be fully rebatable for business purposes in the way that petrol</p>
<p> excise is not, you will effectively find that your, for business purposes,</p>
<p> and I stress that, you will find that your petrol for every business</p>
<p> purpose is 7 cents a litre cheaper because you will be able to obtain</p>
<p> a full rebate of it.</p>
<p>Now I mention these things ladies and gentlemen because one of the</p>
<p> aspects of the plan is that there are different parts of it that have</p>
<p> a different impact on different areas of the Australian economy, but</p>
<p> I stress again that the great appeal, the great virtue, the great</p>
<p> strength, is that this is a plan for Australia's future. It is</p>
<p> not a lazy attempt to nibble at the edges. It is not an attempt to</p>
<p> say to the Australian public, you can have the benefit of a personal</p>
<p> tax cut without the necessary reform to strengthen the Australian</p>
<p> economy. We all know that that option is no longer really available.</p>
<p> We had that tried in 1993 when Mr Keating and Mr Beazley said, oh,</p>
<p> you can't have Hewson's GST, we'll give you a tax cut,</p>
<p> we'll make it L-A-W law, what happened after the election was</p>
<p> that the tax cut disappeared and every individual sales tax went up</p>
<p> by 2%, and that was very regressive. And there was no compensation</p>
<p> for the pensioners in 1993, there was no compensation for them, and</p>
<p> there were no special arrangements, and the impact of that increase</p>
<p> in indirect tax was infinitely more regressive than would have been</p>
<p> the case if the Hewson plan had been endorsed by the Australian people.</p>
<p>I notice this morning that the ACOSS, speaking as it claims on behalf</p>
<p> of a number of welfare bodies, has attacked the plan, and I want to</p>
<p> say in reply to ACOSS that we, of course, reject the calculations</p>
<p> that they have made in relation to the price effect of the plan. We</p>
<p> repeat the guarantee that is contained in the announcement last week</p>
<p> that the pension and other benefits enumerated in the document will</p>
<p> increase up-front by 4% on the 1st of July in the year</p>
<p> 2000 and thereafter we guarantee that there will be a 1.5% add-on</p>
<p> to any CPI increase that occurs after that date. And the purpose of</p>
<p> that will be to ensure that the pension is always in real terms 1.5%</p>
<p> ahead of increases that occur in the consumer price index. And that</p>
<p> is the essence of the guarantee we give, so if people say: well we</p>
<p> don't think that 1.9 is right, my reply to that is: it is right.</p>
<p> But even if it weren't right and the rise happened to be 3% you'd</p>
<p> have 1.5% on top of that. And that is the nature of the guarantee</p>
<p> that is contained in the Government's proposition because we</p>
<p> have no desire to see the less well off in the Australian community</p>
<p> effected adversely by this plan.</p>
<p>And I took the opportunity yesterday when I visited a retirement village</p>
<p> in Brisbane to enumerate that there were ten individual elements of</p>
<p> the plan that were of direct relevance to pensioners and self-funded</p>
<p> retirees in the Australian community. And they include a special one-off</p>
<p> untaxed payment of $1000 in relation to investment income for all</p>
<p> pensioners and others in the community 60 years and over. Another</p>
<p> $2000 on top of that for self-funded retirees of pensionable age.</p>
<p> The introduction of refundable imputation credits - sounds complicated</p>
<p> but anybody who's got some shares and whose marginal tax rate</p>
<p> is lower than 36% will understand the value of refundable imputation</p>
<p> credits. They are little rippers, that's all I can say in relation</p>
<p> to people who are going to get the benefits of them.</p>
<p>And then going on from that you have the introduction of a 30% tax</p>
<p> rebate for private health insurance. If you've got a $2000 policy,</p>
<p> doesn't matter what your income is, from the 1st of</p>
<p> January next year you'll be able to get that $600 back from the</p>
<p> tax man or if you can't wait for the tax refund you can take</p>
<p> the receipt for the health insurance premium along to the Government</p>
<p> office and they'll write out a cheque for you on the spot for</p>
<p> $600. And that is going to be available from the 1st of</p>
<p> January next year. And that is going to be available without an income</p>
<p> test, there won't be an income text on that.</p>
<p>And I'm particularly proud of the changes that we've made</p>
<p> in relation to personal income tax. I make no apology for the fact,</p>
<p> although it may disappoint some in the community, that we haven't</p>
<p> reduced the top marginal rate. But we have increased the point at</p>
<p> which that applies. We've increased that to $75,000. But what</p>
<p> is very very appealing, most appealing of all about the restructured</p>
<p> income tax scales is that between $20,000 and $50,000 of income there</p>
<p> will be a constant uniform rate at the margin of 30%. In other words</p>
<p> 81% of Australian wage and salary earners, 81%, and we should always</p>
<p> keep these figures in our minds so that we have a true perspective</p>
<p> of how these things impact on the great bulk of our fellow Australians.</p>
<p> 81% of wage and salary earners in Australia will be on a top marginal</p>
<p> rate of 30% or less.</p>
<p>And those of you who employ people and have had the experience, they</p>
<p> may be earning $30,000 a year and you want them to do some overtime</p>
<p> and they express some doubts and the grumble say: what's the</p>
<p> point? The tax man will take half of it. Now under this plan, if you</p>
<p> are anywhere between that band of $20,000 and $50,000, or indeed if</p>
<p> you are $20,000 a year, you'll be able to earn as much overtime</p>
<p> as you like up to an aggregate of $50,000 without passing into a higher</p>
<p> taxation bracket. And that does represent a very very significant</p>
<p> change to the taxation system, of enormous importance to the great</p>
<p> bulk of the Australian community. And what it effectively does is</p>
<p> to abolish that thing called bracket creep which the economists keep</p>
<p> talking about. That is when you get flung into a higher tax bracket</p>
<p> because your income goes up. It effectively abolishes bracket creep</p>
<p> between $20,000 and $50,000 a year.</p>
<p>And I'm also very proud of the changes we have made to family</p>
<p> tax arrangements. There's been the odd journalist who's</p>
<p> been running around the country saying that Howard wants women to</p>
<p> do this or that, he wants them all to stay home. Nothing of the kind.</p>
<p> What I want is to give Australian parents a choice about how they</p>
<p> organise their lives when they've got young children. What we</p>
<p> have done is to give a greater recognition to the right of Australian</p>
<p> parents, particularly in the middle-income area, to exercise a choice</p>
<p> when their children are very young about the participation of either</p>
<p> or both of them in the work force on either a full-time or a part-time</p>
<p> basis. It's not my job or my desire to impose some kind of stereotype</p>
<p> on Australian families. It's my desire to give the maximum amount</p>
<p> of choice to Australian families within and through this taxation</p>
<p> system.</p>
<p>Could I just say one other thing that was raised by ACOSS in its response</p>
<p> this morning which I think we should all bear in mind. And that is</p>
<p> that ACOSS is arguing that we should exclude food from the operation</p>
<p> of the goods and service tax. Now the problem with doing that of course</p>
<p> is that once you decide to exclude fresh food you then come under</p>
<p> enormous pressure to exclude things that are closely aligned to fresh</p>
<p> food. In Canada I think it is, they have an argument because the GST</p>
<p> applies to a heated pie bought in a take-away shop but it doesn't</p>
<p> apply to a frozen pie bought in a supermarket. One is regarded as</p>
<p> not quite food in the sense of the GST definition and the latter one</p>
<p> is regarded as in that definition. Now what would happen in this country</p>
<p> is that if you left out fresh food, you'd then have people saying:</p>
<p> well hang on, if you're going to leave fresh food out, you've</p>
<p> got to leave out Hungry Jacks, you've got to leave out Pizzas,</p>
<p> you've got to leave out McDonald's. And if you leave them</p>
<p> out you'd have to leave out every restaurant in the country as</p>
<p> otherwise you would be setting up absolutely unreasonably barriers</p>
<p> and artificial distinctions. And once you start doing that you are</p>
<p> back with the same problem that we have with the present system. And</p>
<p> I can't think of anything that would be more, in relative equity</p>
<p> terms, I can't think of anything that would be more beneficial</p>
<p> for the rich in Australia than to take a decision in the name of helping</p>
<p> the poor that ended up leaving restaurant meals completely out of</p>
<p> the operation of a GST yet you're imposing it on other sections</p>
<p> of the Australian community.</p>
<p>Now ladies and gentleman, as I said at the beginning of my speech,</p>
<p> not everything in this tax plan is acceptable to everybody in Australia.</p>
<p> We didn't set out to try and satisfy everybody on everything</p>
<p> they want. That is absolutely impossible and governments that set</p>
<p> out to try and do that are doomed to failure and doomed to disappointment.</p>
<p> But what we did set out to do as we come towards the 21st</p>
<p> century, as we come towards the third millennium, is to say to the</p>
<p> Australian people something that they all deep down know, and that</p>
<p> is that the present tax system is unsustainable. The present tax system</p>
<p> is increasingly unfair. The present tax system is increasingly in</p>
<p> disrepute. The present tax system holds back the productive sector</p>
<p> of the Australian economy. And we haven't sought to insult the</p>
<p> Australian people with just the offer of a lazy tax cut and say: oh</p>
<p> we'll try and bribe your support by offering you a tax cut out</p>
<p> of the surplus. We haven't done that. What we have tried to do</p>
<p> is to say to the Australian people, before the election and not after</p>
<p> it, before the election, we believe that in the interest of the country</p>
<p> and in the interest of Australian families we need taxation reform.</p>
<p>Part of tax reform is lower personal income tax, but that's only</p>
<p> part of it. A part of tax reform, and it's essential, is the</p>
<p> introduction of a goods and services tax and the replacement of all</p>
<p> those existing indirect taxes. Part of tax reform is to reduce fuel</p>
<p> costs because this is a very big country. Part of tax reform is to</p>
<p> end the annual unseemly wrangle between the Federal Government and</p>
<p> the State Governments over the division of the total amount of revenue</p>
<p> collected in Australia and we've done that. Part of tax reform</p>
<p> is to get rid of the poverty traps in the existing income tax system</p>
<p> and give poorer families a greater incentive to work and to get off</p>
<p> welfare. Part of tax reform is to give people a greater incentive</p>
<p> to take out private health insurance. Part of taxation reform is to</p>
<p> have a more uniform treatment of the taxation of different business</p>
<p> entities whether they be trusts or companies or other business entities.</p>
<p> In other words, we have tried to take an aggregate approach for the</p>
<p> aggregate interests of the Australian people. We haven't set</p>
<p> out to add up all the complaints and all the logs of claims of individual</p>
<p> interest groups, rather we have asked ourselves: what is the sort</p>
<p> of tax system that the Australian community wants as it goes into</p>
<p> the 21st Century? And that is what we have sought to deliver.</p>
<p> I don't under estimate the fight ahead but I'm greatly enthused</p>
<p> about it because I believe it is good, I believe it is right, I believe</p>
<p> it is in the interests of all of the Australian people and that if</p>
<p> we can get this plan accepted by the Australian people it will be</p>
<p> of enormous long-term benefit to the economy of this country. And</p>
<p> I ask the Australian people to judge it in the national interest rather</p>
<p> than in the sectional interest. I ask the Australian people to see</p>
<p> it for what it is. It is a bold courageous visionary plan to give</p>
<p> this country a tax system fit for the 21st Century.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
