<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7172</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN MINING INDUSTRY COUNCIL ANNUAL DINNER CANBERRA - 7 MAY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007172.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
AUSTRALIAN MINING INDUSTRY COUNCIL ANNUAL DINNER<br />
CANBERRA 7 MAY 1987<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
within a relatively short time we will be celebrating our<br />
Bicentenary. Undoubtedly this will be an occasion of great<br />
enjoyment. But the Bicentenary also offers the opportunity<br />
for serious reflection about our national achievements<br />
over our first two hundred years and about the national<br />
challenges that await us in the future.<br />
it is important as we approach the Bicentenary that we make<br />
use of this opportunity. For we meet tonight in a period of<br />
great challenge and of great opportunity for the nation as<br />
a whole. and, certainly, for the mining industry in<br />
particular. If together we prove we are capable of meeting that<br />
challenge and exploiting that opportunity, we will move into<br />
Australia's second two hundred years as a competitive,<br />
productive nation able to provide jobs for its people and<br />
exports for its region and the world.<br />
if however we fail, Australia risks being left behind by the<br />
world, weighed down with an imbalanced economy whose<br />
capacity to provide jobs and security for our people has<br />
fallen permanently below its potential.<br />
The theme of this seminar is " Mining Still the Backbone of<br />
Australia". As a description o f the current position, that assertion is<br />
incontrovertible in economic as well as geological terms.<br />
mineral and metal exports now account for about half of<br />
Australia's total merchandise export earnings. In other<br />
words, your industry makes an indispensable contribution to<br />
underpinning the living standards of the Australian people.<br />
International commodity markets are, however, weak,<br />
including the markets of most of the minerals Australia<br />
exports. The continued overcapacity on world markets in<br />
recent years and the resultant depressed prices are problems<br />
that most commentators agree are likely to persist into the<br />
1990s, despite the important exceptions of gold, mineral<br />
sands and diamonds. t., </p>
<p>And our major resource buyer, Japan, is facing enormous<br />
pressure to restructure its economy following the strong<br />
appreciation of the yen. That is having a harmful impact on<br />
Japan's capacity to buy Australian mineral products.<br />
The mining industry has reacted with great determination to<br />
those difficult circumstances.<br />
However the assertion that mining is still the backbone of<br />
Australia must not become a self-satisfied description of an<br />
assured future.<br />
If the industry is to remain the nation's economic backbone<br />
it must continue determinedly to confront an unfavourable<br />
trading environment. Further, the industry must play a<br />
central role in the process of massive restructuring which<br />
the Australian economy is undergoing a process which will<br />
change forever many of the economic assumptions on which<br />
Australia relied during its long easy decades of<br />
commodity-based wealth.<br />
Clearly that is a long term strategy. At its most basic, it<br />
must involve a willingness to seek out and to take advantage<br />
of all the opportunities our economy and our region offers.<br />
It also requires the mining industry to expand and diversify<br />
its market base. Both traditional raw materials processing<br />
and the exploitation of high technology to manufacture new<br />
materials must increasingly supplement the export of<br />
unprocessed minerals. The Government has recently asked the<br />
Basic IMetals Industry Council to review policies to promote<br />
the processing of minerals and metals within Australia.<br />
It is in this sense that your industry, far from being a<br />
spent force, is what Gareth Evans describes as a bridge to<br />
the future.<br />
The Federal Government is determined, within the realities<br />
of the international commodities market, to create the best<br />
possible macro-economic environment so as, among other<br />
things, to allow the mining industry to achieve this<br />
transformation. I<br />
Principal among these policies is the task of economic<br />
reconstruction facing Australia.<br />
The slump in Australia's terms of trade meant that a<br />
temporary reduction in domestic living standards was<br />
necessary, and that the task of economic restructuring had<br />
to be thoroughly addressed after decades of neglect by<br />
conservative governments.<br />
I outlined this task in my Address to the Nation last June.<br />
No-one would have been more acutely aware of the dimensions<br />
of the task than you who earn your livelihood in the mining<br />
industry. </p>
<p>The Government took steps to reduce inflation and preserve<br />
international competitiveness; to dampen growth of domestic<br />
demand to facilitate increased net exports and lower<br />
domestic expenditure; to increase domestic savings; and to<br />
encourage the development and manufacture of new products,<br />
employing the talents of our skilled workforce and capable<br />
of finding new export markets.<br />
Tight fiscal and monetary policy and continued wage<br />
moderation were necessary to achieve our policy objectives.<br />
There car. be little doubt that these policies are producing<br />
the desired results.<br />
As we predicted in the last Budget, the slowing in the<br />
economy then evident was short lived. The December quarter<br />
saw a return to strong growth in Gross Domestic Product with<br />
an increase of 1.1 per cent.<br />
Latest estimates of the 1986-87 current account deficit are<br />
of he order of $ 1 billion less than the Budget forecast of<br />
$ 14-billion.<br />
Moreover net exports are expected to contribute<br />
substantially more to growth than the 1 ecnaepit<br />
forecast at Budget time. 4pecnaeoit<br />
Weaker than forecast consumption growth a desirable<br />
development in present circumstances has also greatly<br />
assisted this turnaround in the current account.<br />
It should be noted that interpreting the current account<br />
trend over the coming months is likely to become more<br />
difficul-as the seasonal increase in the deficit begins to<br />
inflate the monthly statistics.<br />
However the underlying improvement in the current account is<br />
now well established and is expected to continue in 1987-88.<br />
As for GDP growth overall, it appears likely to be rather<br />
weaker for 1986-87 as a whole than we forecast at Budget<br />
time, essentially because of the slower growth of<br />
consumption. Employment growth has however exceeded our expectations.<br />
In the six months to April, employment grew by 1.4 per cent.<br />
This means just over 100,000 new jobs, bringing the total<br />
number of jobs created under my Government to over 780,000<br />
the highest rate of employment growth in our post-war<br />
history. More than any other statistic, this robust employment growth<br />
demonstrates the underlying strength of the economy and the<br />
success of the Government's economic policies.<br />
lIt demonstrates too that we are making progress in achieving<br />
our social goals. </p>
<p>We are and we remain committed to the creation of a fairer<br />
and more compassionate society and no better solution<br />
exists to poverty than the creation of jobs.<br />
We can confidently-expect inflation to decline over the<br />
course of the coming year or so, given continued wage<br />
restraint and currency stability.<br />
Interest rates, which have been high for some time, have<br />
begun to decline. This is partly in anticipation of further<br />
responsible fiscal measures and lower inflation, partly<br />
because of the progressive reduction in our current account,<br />
and partly because of greater overseas interest in $ A<br />
assets.<br />
We are determined to preserve and build upon these gains.<br />
Our commitment to that goal will be reaffirmed in next<br />
week's May Statement and in the Premiers' Conference later<br />
in May.<br />
There is always a danger at a time like this of unrealistic<br />
expectations being created. But those who would set<br />
impossible targets for this, or for any Government, must be<br />
able to answer this question: how should we balance our<br />
economic responsibilities with our responsibility for the<br />
poor and the disadvantaged?<br />
This Government has a proud record of being able to strike<br />
the right balance and we will do so again on Wednesday<br />
night. The May Statement will reinforce the Commonwealth's efforts<br />
to cut public sector demand and reduce our national need to<br />
borrow abroad to finance domestic expenditure.<br />
But we cannot do the job by ourselves. The reality is that<br />
the total Public Sector Borrowing Requirement must decline<br />
as a share of GDP and not simply the Commonwealth's share<br />
of it. The States will be required to play their part.<br />
Wage moderation will also continue to be a crucial element<br />
of our economic management.<br />
The new two tier wages system is designed to continue the<br />
wage restraint which has seen a 6 per cent fall in real unit<br />
labour costs since we came to Government.<br />
But it can only do so if each party is prepared to play its<br />
part constructively and within both the letter and the<br />
spirit of the Commission's principles.<br />
Productivity offsets are central to the operation of the<br />
second tier. I am aware of many instances in this industry<br />
in which workers and management have co-operated for their<br />
mutual benefit to raise productivity and to preserve<br />
competitiveness. I </p>
<p>The new two tier structure provides a further opportunity to<br />
secure increased productivity at all levels of the<br />
enterprise, from pit-face to desk top.<br />
We remain committed to the centralised wage fixing system.<br />
But we are also determined to make whatever sensible reforms<br />
are necessary to ensure it remains a relevant and useful<br />
element of the Government's economic policy.<br />
The Government will next week be introducing into Parliament<br />
a new Industrial Relations Bill based on the Hancock Inquiry<br />
which will contain a number of reforms to enhance the<br />
centralised system.<br />
On the matter of sanctions, I can assure you that the new<br />
legislation will ensure the effective operation of the<br />
industrial relations system, and will include appropriate<br />
penalty provisions and means of redress.<br />
I am sure that when they have studied it both unions and<br />
employers will generally recognise the inherent good sense<br />
and equity of the new Bill.<br />
Having discussed the macroeconomic environment, let me now<br />
turn to some matters of specific relevance to the mining<br />
industry.<br />
We recognise that State taxes and charges on the industry<br />
are in urgent need of rationalisation. The Federal<br />
Government favours the application of profit-related taxes<br />
rather than the more inefficient production-based ones.<br />
The Resource Rent Tax for the petroleum industry, which is<br />
currently before the Senate, provides a good balance between<br />
on the one hand providing an appropriate incentive for<br />
exploration and, on the other, protecting the community's<br />
interests in obtaining a fair share of the profits derived<br />
from the exploitation of a non-renewable resource.<br />
Let me add that after a review of the taxation arrangements<br />
for the gold mining industry, we decided not to remove its<br />
current income tax exemption so as to encourage exploration<br />
and development and to maximise production and export<br />
income.<br />
The NSW Government recently introduced some welcome relief<br />
for the coal industry but other State charges Queensland's<br />
rail freight charges being a particular case in point are<br />
in need of further examination.<br />
My government also has a very positive record in terms of<br />
eliminating unnecessary regulatory burdens on the industry.<br />
We have given particularly close attention to reducing<br />
export controls. Where they no longer serve useful<br />
purposes, we are reducing them. In September last year I<br />
announced some major changes in this area. </p>
<p>The controls on coal, bauxite and alumina, and crude oil<br />
surplus to domestic needs were substantially streamlined or<br />
relaxed. The controls on tungsten were terminated.<br />
In addition to these very significant reforms, we have also<br />
established a Business Regulation Review Unit which imposes<br />
strict disciplines upon the Government to scrutinise<br />
carefully the costs and benefits of all proposed<br />
regulations. A special Sub-Committee of Cabinet has been<br />
formed to consider a number of areas in which action could<br />
be taken to reduce impediments to trade competitiveness.<br />
We are also taking steps to reduce controls on foreign<br />
investment. Last week Paul Keating announced further changes to foreign<br />
investment policy. These will remove Foreign Investment<br />
Review Board control over proposals for takeovers of<br />
businesses with total assets of less than $ 5 million.<br />
Takeovers within a number of industries, including resource<br />
processing, will now be approved unless they are judged<br />
contrary to the national interest.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I opened this evening by talking of the challenge which<br />
faces your industry and the nation as a whole.<br />
So far I have addressed issues which go to the economic<br />
aspects of Government policy. But I would not want it<br />
thought that I see the challenge as relating purely to<br />
dollar issues, or the contribution to the nation by the<br />
mining industry as being purely an economic one.<br />
The truth is as AMIC recognises that the mining industry<br />
has a vital role to play in the determination of social<br />
issues in Australia.<br />
At a time when the nation urgently needs export income,<br />
there is a clear cost incurred from not exploring or<br />
developing a particular mineral deposit.<br />
But in some instances the social cost of proceeding with a<br />
project is too high particularly in terms of its effects<br />
on the environment or on Aboriginal interests.<br />
To fully meet the challenge of our future we need to strive<br />
together to balance the legitimate interests of all parties,<br />
so as to maximise mineral exploration and development in<br />
this country while being sensitive at the same time to<br />
environmental and Aboriginal interests.<br />
For my part, I firmly believe economic development is<br />
compatible with the environmentally sound management of<br />
Australia's resources.<br />
Some recent decisions by the Government illustrate the way<br />
in which wie have found that balance. </p>
<p>In the case of the Shelburne Bay sandmining proposal, the<br />
Government concluded that as the project would not be of<br />
major economic importance, the economic and commercial<br />
advantages flowing from it were insufficient to offset the<br />
adverse impact on-the environment of the Cape York<br />
peninsula. In the case of the Stage 3 extension of Kakadu National Park<br />
the Government has also struck a balance between its<br />
considerable Aboriginal and environmental sensitivity and<br />
its high mineral prospectivity.<br />
A basis for mineral exploration in the Kakadu Conservation<br />
Zone is currently being developed. The Government remains<br />
unequivocally opposed to mining in Stages 1 and 2 and the<br />
remainder of Stage 3 which, apart from uranium, are not<br />
considered to be areas of high mineral prospectivity. our<br />
policy on uranium remains unchanged.<br />
The Government is also aware of the mining industry's<br />
concern ab3out the implications of areas being listed on tho-<br />
Register of the National Estate.<br />
However, concerns that listing on the National Estate will<br />
necessarily result in the permanent locking up of the<br />
resources in an area are misplaced. Listing on the Register<br />
is not in itself incompatible with development proposals.<br />
It does however serve the useful purpose of focussing<br />
attention on the broader environmental and heritage issues<br />
involved.<br />
As for issues of Aboriginal land rights, I know Gareth Evans<br />
outlined to you today the details of the Government's<br />
proposed nevy legislation covering exploration and mining on<br />
Aboriginal land in the Northern Territory.<br />
Gareth introduced the new Bill into the Senate this evening<br />
and I don't want to dwell on the specifics of it at present.<br />
I do however wish to draw out a very important principle<br />
from it.<br />
What we have seen has been an outstandingly successful<br />
process of negotiation which has reached a proper and<br />
honourable consensus.<br />
The legislation demonstrates that conflicting interests on<br />
sensitive dcvelopment issues can be balanced to the<br />
satisfaction of all parties. -Wliat is needed to achieve that<br />
balance and what was present at all stages of this matter<br />
is genuine and committed consultation and negotiations by<br />
the parties involved.<br />
I was personally involved in discussions with<br />
representatives of the Land Councils and put to them what we<br />
proposed. I also arranged for them to meet Gareth Evans,<br />
Clyde Holding and a committee of MPs to discuss the proposal<br />
further. </p>
<p>The consensus that was reached reaffirms two principles:<br />
the ability of aboriginal land owners to protect their land,<br />
if they wish, from any developmental intrusion; and the<br />
desirability, in the national interest, of facilitating and<br />
maximising mining activity.<br />
We reached that goal without confrontation and without<br />
acrimony and, indeed, with unanimity.<br />
The commitmient to the process of consultation which this<br />
process displayed has been a hallmark of our government over<br />
the last four years.<br />
It is my hope that future issues will be able to be resolved<br />
with a comparable spirit of co-operation.<br />
For make no mistake, we will face difficult decisions as we<br />
confront the economic challenge ahead of us.<br />
But this government has a clear strategy to meet that<br />
challenge.<br />
That strategy has four elements:<br />
We will continue to restructure the economy.<br />
We will continue to govern with fairness and compassion.<br />
We will continue to provide stability and strength in<br />
government.<br />
And we will continue to govern for the long-term future even<br />
at the expense of copping some of the flak for decisions<br />
which do not please everyone along the way.<br />
I know that this is the final day of Sir Bruce Watson's<br />
presidency of AMIC. Let me take this opportunity to thank<br />
him for his work and to express my best wishes to Mark<br />
Rayner of Comalco who is taking Sir Bruce's place. I look<br />
forward, and I can speak on behalf of all Ministers who will<br />
deal with AI4IC, to a continued constructive relationship.<br />
Within the framework of that strategy, and with your<br />
assistance, Australia will emerge with renewed<br />
competitiveness and renewed confidence for a productive and.<br />
prosperous future. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
