<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10057</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE - PARLIAMENT HOUSE </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/07/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010057.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>17 July 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE PARLIAMENT HOUSE<br />
E O E<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, the situation after today's meeting of the Police Ministers is that<br />
there is total agreement in relation to everything except a proposal regarding<br />
modification of which I will come to in a moment. The Commonwealth has indicated a<br />
willingness to help generously in relation to the cost of administration of the gun buy<br />
back and the new registration system. We have agreed on a very limited exemption<br />
uinder Category C to ensure that Australians can effectively compete in clay target<br />
sports in the Olympic, international and national context and the model rules in relation<br />
to that are going to be drawn up in consultation with representatives of the various<br />
jurisdictions. There was a proposal put to the meeting for what amounted in the words<br />
of some of its proponents the re-manufacture of the magazine of a semi-automatic or<br />
pu~ mp-action shotgun to reduce, so it was argued, permanently its capacity to two<br />
cartridges. For a combination of reasons a majority of the jurisdictions represented at the meeting<br />
indicated that they were unwilling to support that. Queensland, Western Australia and<br />
the Northern Territory their representatives at the meeting have said that they would<br />
take this matter back, and in particular, the majority view in relation to that proposal<br />
for consideration by their respective cabinets, all of which will meet next Monday and<br />
the final position of those three jurisdictions in relation to the majority view of the,<br />
majority indication of the meeting, including of course the Commonwealth, will be<br />
known next Monday.<br />
I want to take this opportunity to thank thle State governments of Australia and the<br />
Territories of Australia for the tremendous co-operation so far in relation to the goal<br />
that is still very much within our grasp, of uniform, tough, effective national gun laws.<br />
Thus far we have achieved what many would be described as 80 90% of what was<br />
sought. I would like to achieve 100%. 1 believe the overwhelming majority of<br />
Australians would like to achieve 100% and that is their fervent desire but there are<br />
proper democratic consultative processes within a federation and those processes must </p>
<p>be worked through, and they are being worked through, and in relation to the Territory<br />
and the two States I mention this matter will be referred back to their Cabinets and<br />
each of them will meet on Monday and their final position in relation to the matter will<br />
be known next Monday.<br />
Are there any questions?<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, how did you convince the three States that didn't want to agree to<br />
your position, what did you use to convince them that they should?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, I don't sort of get into putting, you know, descriptions and commentaries on<br />
things. Everybody has a strong view on this issue and we talked it through and I<br />
recognise that despite the clear evidence of a majority Australian opinion on this issue,<br />
there are various parts of the country where strongly held views by people of decent<br />
intent who are very good Australians exist and you have to respect that and you have<br />
to allow the proper democratic process to take its place. I mean, we are talking here<br />
about an area that's unresolved which is a very small percentage of what was originally<br />
set out to be achieved on the 10th May.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could I ask a question of the WA representative?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
You can ask any question you like to anybody.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is it correct that the Prime Minister threatened a referendum if States could not come<br />
on board in terms of his position?<br />
BOB WIESE:<br />
The question of a referendum was obviously, was mentioned. We have indicated in<br />
Western Australia that we will be going back to our Cabinet for some final resolution<br />
on this matter at our meeting on Monday.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is it correct that the Prime Minister raised the issue of a referendum?<br />
BOB WIESE:<br />
That's correct. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, Monday, if the Cabinets in the respective States and Territories don't<br />
agree to come on board, are you prepared to go for a referendum at some stage?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look our response, if we don't achieve 100% uniformity next Monday is a matter that<br />
I daresay we'll consider on Tuesday which happens to be when Federal Cabinet next<br />
meets. Obviously having a referendum is a possibility. I want to make that very clear<br />
and to suggest that a reference to a referendum is a threat is highly amusing. The idea<br />
of a referendum has been in the ether for quite some time and it is clearly a possibility<br />
but referendums are not to be embarked upon carelessly or lightly or capriciously but<br />
very soberly because they're significant events in the life of a Commonwealth but this<br />
is a very significant issue and people have very strong views about it and people are<br />
passionate throughout Australia to have uniform tough gun laws and that's the bottom<br />
line of any political analysis of this issue. They are passionate about that. Now,<br />
obviously a referendum is a real possibility but let me make it clear, I am not<br />
committed to anything other than continuing to work effectively with the states to try<br />
and achieve in a co-operative federation the spirit and the letter of what was agreed on<br />
the 10Oth May, so I still have very great faith in the co-operative federalist approach.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have the Ministers from the two States and Territory agreed to argue the majority of<br />
the case or simply to take the majority case back to their Cabinets?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I think they can speak for themselves Michelle. I wouldn't presume to speak for<br />
them. Well, that's up to them. Mr Stone's got something to say.<br />
SHIANE STONE:<br />
We will take back in the case of the Territory the views that I said all along, that it was<br />
a matter for the Police Ministers. A majority of the Police Ministers have rejected the<br />
crimping option and also the modified magazine. I will be taking that back to my<br />
Cabinet colleagues.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will you be advocating the majority position or simply saying, well this is what they<br />
said. It's..<br />
SHANE STONE:<br />
I'll be taking back the substance of what was discussed in the course of the meeting. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: And you will be advocating it?<br />
SI-ANE STONE:<br />
Well, I will be taking back what was discussed in the course of the meeting.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you be a bit more precise?<br />
SHANE STONE:<br />
Well I've been as precise as I'm going to be. I will...<br />
JOURNALIST: So in other words you're not going to advocate it?<br />
SH-ANE STONE:<br />
No I'm not saying that either. I am taking back the substance of what was discussed in<br />
the meeting so that my colleagues can come to a view on this, guided by my particular<br />
views. JOURNALIST: Is it your expectation that if you don't go along with the majority position, then the<br />
Prime Minister will proceed with a referendum?<br />
SHANE STONE:<br />
Look, a referendum is clearly an option. It's always been an option and I would take<br />
the view that the pulling on of a referendum by any State or Territory would be both<br />
reckless and irresponsible. It's quite clear to me that all of Australians including<br />
Territorians, would vote overwhelmingly for these national proposals.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, is it possible in your view to have effective national gun laws if they<br />
are not uniform laws on this issue?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
They will be diminished in their effectiveness if there is not uniformity on this issue but<br />
I stand by what I said earlier, a great deal of common ground, an enormous amount of<br />
common ground, way beyond what's already been achieved has already been achieved </p>
<p>so I don't, you know, one's got to keep a sense of proportion about it but I would like<br />
to see it at 100% rather than 80 or<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Cooper. what's the Queensland position? What will you actually be saying to your<br />
Cabinet colleagues on Monday and do you expect your Cabinet colleagues to agree to<br />
a majority position?<br />
RUSSELL COOPER:<br />
I have spoken to Premier Borbidge several times this evening and he and I both agree<br />
that this matter should be properly brought to the Cabinet on Monday and that's<br />
exactly what we'll do.<br />
JOURNALIST: What's your recommendation going to be?<br />
RUSSELL COOPER:.<br />
I will just be reporting to the Cabinet on what has occurred here today.<br />
JOURNALIST: And Mr Wiese, will you be doing the same thing?<br />
BOB WIESE:<br />
I will be doing exactly the same thing.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, is it the case that after the early session of today's meeting all of the<br />
states indicated the willingness to accept this new modification proposal but later<br />
changed their mind after their first meeting with you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I never go into the details of private discussions. I think the only way that meetings<br />
like this can work effectively is for there to be periods when the members of<br />
governments who have executive responsibility could talk directly and confidentially<br />
with each other and I for one won't be canvassing the details of any of those<br />
discussions except to say that they were conducted in a very direct and co-operative<br />
fashion and I have appreciated the input of all of the Ministers, and I accept without<br />
qualification that all of them are seeking to achieve the optimum result according to<br />
their particular assessment the situation of what's fair and what is politically desirable<br />
and what is politically achievable. This is not an easy issue. I mean, it's very simple </p>
<p>for those who write about it to say at the flick of a finger that you can have uniform<br />
this and that and why don't you do this and that.<br />
We are a federation and you have to achieve things in a patient, exhaustive, cooperative<br />
fashion and can I say again that I appreciate the co-operation of the States. I<br />
also appreciate the co-operation across the political divide of Mr Beazley and Senator<br />
Kernot and of State Opposition Leaders around the country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, are you absolutely convinced if you went to a referendum you would<br />
win? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, look, to answer that question sort of assumes that we are already doing it. I<br />
mean, let's do one thing at a time. We've had a discussion today. People in three<br />
areas are going back to their Cabinets on Monday and they'll be reporting in the terms<br />
that they themselves explain, not what I explain. I hope that after Monday through the<br />
cooperative process we will have achieved nationally uniform tough effective gun laws.<br />
I acknowledge that a referendum is a possibility. I do not want to start speculating<br />
about the outcomne except to repeat what I said earlier that the thing that cuts through<br />
to me above everything else in this debate is that passionate desire of Australians of all<br />
walks of life across all party allegiances to have tough effective national gun laws. But<br />
referendums are not things likely to be embarked upon and it is easy when you don't<br />
have to make the decisions on it to call for them and I note with interest the calls that<br />
have already come for referenda, it's a bit like Ministerial resignations when you are in<br />
Opposition.<br />
JOURNALIST: How much money is the federal Government prepared to give to the States for the cost<br />
of administration. Is that in addition to<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We will demonstrate our unfailing generosity.<br />
JOURNALIST: But is that in addition to the $ 500 million?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes of course it is. The $ 500 million is the dough for buying back the guns. This is in<br />
relation.... I mean, we are not saying we are picking up every last dollar, I mean, hang </p>
<p>SHANE STONE:<br />
But you'll be generous.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We'll be characteristically generous.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Wiese, is it correct that the Federal Attorney General initially supported your<br />
position in relation to the re-manufacturing option?<br />
BOB WIESE:<br />
As Mr Howard has said, I don't think it is proper for us to be discussing the matters<br />
that were discussed within the meeting that we've just held. Let me say that we<br />
haven't.., let me say that we will be taking back, we haven't reached total agreement.<br />
Western Australia will be going back to our Cabinet to see where we go from here.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, could you explain why you rejected the re-manufactu ring option?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, we had a meeting on the tenth of May which said that crimping that never<br />
mentioned crimping. We said we'd look at crimping. We looked at crimping and we<br />
found that it was not irreversible and then another proposal comes up. I mean there<br />
has got to be a point at which you draw the line and I think the Australian public is sort<br />
of starting to imagine that it is a thing the line isn't drawn and if things continue to<br />
go on we'll have a never ending succession of proposals for this or that modification.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Williams were you overruled by the Prime Minister on the South Australia's<br />
proposal after you accepted the re-manufacture of a magazine?<br />
ATTORNEY GENERAL:<br />
Look, I think what you are asking me to do is to enter into a discussion about what<br />
was discussed behind closed doors. The Commonwealth position was quite clear at all<br />
times to my colleagues I understood.<br />
JOURNALIST: But there was a report on the wire service saying that you were overruled. It's already<br />
been written </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well if it is in the media it has to be right doesn't it?!<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister could you explain how you intend exemptions for competitive<br />
shooters? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
You mean the Olympic people?<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes. Would they have to be only at an Olympic level?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look it is going to be very very narrow, so that you don't have a ridiculous situation<br />
where foreigners competing in Olympic sports for example... I mean, the thing that<br />
provoked this was I got a letter from the people tied up with the Olympic shooters and<br />
they'd had an inquiry from the Olympic 2000 saying is the thing still okay. And we<br />
don't want a situation where Australians are prevented from competing on equal terms<br />
with foreigners.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister was there any discussion today about whether farmers could have<br />
access to the Category<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Ohl the Category D thing has all been fixed up. I'm sorry, I should have mentioned<br />
that. You'll remember a proposal was put forward by Queensland in relation to that<br />
and we considered it and indicated that we were prepared to go a certain distance. I<br />
don't think, to be fair, quite as far as had been asked by Queensland but essentially to<br />
thle effect of what now operates in the Northern Territory and that was accepted as I<br />
am told, I wasn't there when it was discussed and I'm told that was accepted by all<br />
jurisdictions. So there's complete agreement on that. I mean, there's just this one area<br />
and we have three jurisdictions who want to further discuss before committing<br />
themselves either way. Now I accept that and that's a proper part of the process and I<br />
think people should understand that in something as complicated and difficult as this<br />
where views vary a bit around the country, that that is a proper working out of the<br />
federal system. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Can I ask a question about an area of agreements? Have you now, the Ministers, have<br />
you all agreed on the actual schedule for compensation of weapons and when will that<br />
be made available?<br />
ATTORNEY GENERAL:<br />
There is a broad agreement on the timetable. It will need to be flexible because of the<br />
need for each state to put legislation in place in its jurisdiction. But in general terms it<br />
should be under way within four to six weeks on a national basis.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard you've made it clear to the representatives of Queensland, Western<br />
Australia and the Northern Territory that if they don't support uniform national gun<br />
laws on Monday the federal Cabinet will consider a referendum on Tuesday. Is that a<br />
fair sumnmary?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, I've made clear what I've been willing to say I've made clear tonight. I<br />
mean, look, we had a very long discussion. I'm not going to go into the detail of that.<br />
They are meeting on Monday as part of their ordinary proper processes. It so happens<br />
that we will meeting the following day. There haven't been any threats made. I don't<br />
deal in threats. That's not the issue. We have a goal. We have a goal of tough<br />
national gun laws, and that's what the Australian people want, and that's my goal and I<br />
am working through the federal process to try and achieve it. And inevitably there are<br />
disagreemnents along the way and we'll see what we'll see on Monday. I'm not going<br />
to start answering hypothetical questions. Obviously everybody knows that a<br />
referendum is a real distinct possibility. Of course it is I mean it has been talked<br />
about by everybody. It's been talked about by a number of people in the Government,<br />
it's been talked about by some of the State Premiers, it's been called for by Mr Beazley<br />
and Senator Kernot...<br />
JOURNALIST: But you haven't said anything until tonight...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh yes I have, I just haven't quite gone as far as people have wanted me to go in<br />
committing myself to it. I'm not committing myself to it tonight. I'm not committing<br />
myself to anything tonight other than to continue between now and Monday to use all<br />
of my efforts and any influence I have to bring about tough uniform national gun laws<br />
and that's what I'll continue to do. I'll continue to talk to the Premiers of the States<br />
about it and I appreciate very much the co-operation that's already been given by the<br />
Premiers of all States. They've been very very helpful and generous and very<br />
supportive of the Commonwealth position. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Were you disappointed it has taken so long and that there isn't a final resolution<br />
tonight? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, no, because these things take a bit of time. I mean, it is very easy when you are on<br />
the outside and you are looking at eight governments and saying ' fellows get it fixed<br />
up' straight away. I mean, we are a co-operative federation and you've got to work<br />
through these things and I think we've come an enormous distance but we are nearing<br />
the point, you know, the moment of final truth and that will be next Monday. And<br />
everybody knows where everybody stands and there's no misunderstandings and our<br />
position was enunciated last week. I rang each of the Premiers and the Chief Ministers<br />
and told them our position. We discussed it again today. We did have the additional<br />
injection on our part... I mean, we worked out this exemption in relation to the<br />
Olympics, and also the Commonwealth indicated a willingness to be you know, our<br />
characteristically generous self in relation to the financial side of it. Now, we had a<br />
discussion and we await the resolution of their respective positions by the three<br />
jurisdictions I've mentioned. Now, I think that is fair, proper, that is how the<br />
federation works in this country, and you always achieve results if you work through<br />
the system in the correct fashion.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
