<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4511</transcript-id>
    <title>OFFICIAL VISIT BY THEIR ROYAL HIGHNESSES CROWN PRINCE HASSAN AND PRINCESS SARVATH OF JORDAN, 4 OCTOBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/10/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004511.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MR CARMODY<br />
EM6B. A00R GO:<br />
pnm<br />
PRiME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 4 OCTOBER 1977<br />
OFFICIAL VISIT BY THEIR ROYAL HIGHNESSES<br />
CROWN PRINCE HASSAN AND PRINCESS SARVATH OF JORDAN<br />
Details of the programme for the Official Visit to Australia of<br />
Their Royal Highnesses Crown Prince Hassan and Princess Sarvath<br />
of the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan have now been finalised.<br />
Their Royal Highnesses will visit Canberra from 11-13 October,<br />
Mt Isa 13-14 October, Cairns 14-16 October, Melbourne 16-18 October,<br />
Adelaide 18-19 October and Sydney 19-22 October.<br />
The programme includes discussions in Canberra, the laying of a<br />
wreath at the Australian War Memorial, a dinner party at<br />
Government House and a luncheon given by the Commonwealth Government.<br />
His Royal Highness the Crown Prince will visit the CSIRO<br />
Headquarters and speak at the National Press Club.<br />
The programme in Queensland, Victoria, South Australia and<br />
New South Wales includes visits to Mt Isa Mines,, and parts of<br />
the Great Barrier Reef, the CSIRO Divisions of Mechanical<br />
Engineering and Building Research, the Bureau of Meteorology,<br />
an animal research institute, an agricultural college, the<br />
Nicholson Museum of Antiquitics at the University of Sydney,<br />
Sydney Opera House, and Taronga Park Zoo, and the CSIRO<br />
Division of Fisheries and Oceanography.<br />
Her Royal Highness Princess Sarvath will also visit a centre for<br />
physically handicapped children, schools and a children's hospital. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
