<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4411</transcript-id>
    <title>GOVERNMENT POLICY ON NUCLEAR SAFEGUARDS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/05/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004411_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 24 MAY 1977<br />
GOVERNMENT POLICY ON NUCLEAR SAFEGUARDS<br />
The future course of world nuclear developnent and the regime<br />
of international controls which should apply to such development<br />
are currently subjects of great international interest. In the<br />
past few w eeks for example, there has been an important statement<br />
by-President Carter on nuclear energy in which he emphasised<br />
the need to restrain the spread of nuclear weapons or explosive<br />
capabilities without foregoing the tangible benefits of nuclear<br />
power. Again, at their recent Su1mmit meeting, the H-eads of<br />
Government of the United States, the United Kingdom, Canada,<br />
West; Germany, France, Japan and Italy committed themselves<br />
to increasing nuclear energy to help meet the world's energy<br />
requirements while reducing the -risks of nuclear proliferation*.<br />
They launched an urgent study'to determine how best to fulifil these<br />
objectives. At the conclusion of the recent Salzburg Conference,<br />
the most important international conference held in recent years<br />
on all aspects of nuclear power, the Director General of the<br />
International Atomic Energy Agency referred to the agreement<br />
of the meeting that nuclear power was a necessary and irreplaceable<br />
source of the future energy supply to mankind for both the short<br />
and the longer term.<br />
It is clear th at there is widespread international concern to<br />
establish a framework of control within which the benefits<br />
which many countries see in the peaceful use of<br />
nuclear energy can be safely realised. These are issues of<br />
major inteornational importance i n their own right, but they / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
have an added significance for Australia because of our<br />
potential as a supplier of uranium. They are issues on<br />
which I have already written to President Carter and Prime<br />
Minister Trudeau and on which the Deputy Prime Minister<br />
and Australian officials have held detailed consultations<br />
with the United States, Canada and other countries. They<br />
are issues which have been under the closest and most<br />
careful consideration from the moment -the Government took<br />
office. In the present period of international reappraisal<br />
of these issues the Government is determined that Australia<br />
should play an active role with other countries in the<br />
search for, and achievement of, joint solutions.<br />
A proliferation of nuclear faL'ilities without adequate<br />
protection against diversion of material to nuclear weapons<br />
production or nuclear explosives would pose serious threats<br />
to international stability and peace, obviously inimical to<br />
Australia's interests and to global and regional security.<br />
It was for this reason that in his address to the United<br />
Nations General Assembly last September, the Foreign Minister<br />
described the strengthening of measures to prevent<br />
proliferation of nuclear weapons as a central and fundamental<br />
area in which Australia looks and hopes for early progress.<br />
This will remain the case whether or not Australia is<br />
ultimately to become a major exporter of uranium. The<br />
safeguards policy which we will follow is, in our view,<br />
appropriate for any country to follow whether it be a uranium<br />
supplier or consumer. I make clear from the outset that the<br />
term safeguards is used here to denote the whole range of<br />
measures used to provide assurance that nuclear material supplied<br />
for peaceful purposes is not mis-used for non-peaceful or </p>
<p>-3-<br />
explosive purposes.<br />
the Government fully accepts that if it were in<br />
future to permit new uranium expqrt from Australia, this<br />
would carry with it added responsibilities. Against the<br />
background of these international responsibilities the<br />
Government accepts that uranium is a special commodity,<br />
the export of which would involve important considerations<br />
of a kind not involved in the export of other commodities.<br />
This implies a requirement for selectivity in the choice<br />
of customer countries and the closest attention to ensuring<br />
adequate safeguards. It is not the Government' s view that<br />
safeguards should be regarded as something to be balanced<br />
against commercial considerations. We view adequate<br />
safeguards as a fundamental pre-requisite of any uranium<br />
export which we would also expect responsible customer<br />
countries for Australian uranium readily to accept.<br />
It will be recalled that, following the release of<br />
the First Report of the Ranger Uranium Environmental Inquiry,<br />
the Government announced in the House on 11 November 1976<br />
that it supported the Inquiry'Is view on the need f or the<br />
fullest and most effective safeguards on uranium exports.<br />
The Government also stated that it was carrying forward<br />
more detailed consideration of safeguards in order to<br />
further develop a national policy on this subject. </p>
<p>-4<br />
The announcement of a policy at this stage, of<br />
course, in no way preempts a decision on the question whether<br />
any such new contracts for the export of uranium will be<br />
permitted. As the Government has repeatedly emphasised, this<br />
remains a matter for consideration following receipt of the<br />
final report of the Ranger Uranium Environmental Inquiry.<br />
However, as the Foreign Minister said in the Government's<br />
foreign policy statement in the Parliament on 15 March 1977 the<br />
Government would be remiss if it did not address itself to<br />
safeguards questions in the meantime. That the Government has<br />
taken certain decisions on safeguards policy at this stage<br />
reflects its determination to ensure that an established framework<br />
of policy exists so that any new uranium exports take place<br />
under the most carefully considered and responsible conditions<br />
possible. The Government wishes to avoid a situation in which<br />
decisions may be required on new uranium marketing at some poInt<br />
in the future without the benefit of a clear policy on the ground<br />
rules to apply so far as safeguards are concerned.<br />
The Government has long recognised the desirability<br />
of defining a comprehensive policy on safeguards. It would<br />
not be desirable for safeguards requirements to be left to ad<br />
hoc decision as this would not afford the strong and clear<br />
support for international efforts to strengthen controls against<br />
nuclear weapons proliferation to which the Government attaches<br />
major importance. Australia is a potentially significant<br />
supplier of uranium, but if we are to play the part which this<br />
potential gives us the opportunity to play of contributing<br />
effectively to international efforts to strengthen the nonproliferation<br />
regime, it is desirable that uranium importing<br />
countries and other nuclear supplier countries alike know<br />
where Australia stands on the matter of safeguards. </p>
<p>the r~ safe,. guar-12 are sys~ tems cof<br />
nuclear-material. 0 an'-facilities de6igned to verify that.<br />
di. ver.;. cn d-O'ES oo . ake plac-e from pea~ ceful to ncn-peacefijI<br />
or exp~ 1;--Le p~ o~~ The majcr SyStEMS; Of inLz: rnaticna1.<br />
safeg-oarols a-E. . adrini-Ler( e. d by thez international Atomic<br />
Energy Agency. Ir. a bioader : sense, S~ afeguards fo.-r future<br />
Australian Urani.; um exports ; kould comprise, a~ s wellI as the<br />
appli.-c--ti;. ir,. ter-ati., E:. al. safeg-oard2 4 this strict sense,<br />
the 5-aecAririg from impor-t2-ng oc(' i. tries cfadequate assjr-ances,<br />
regardi-hg t-lew--se nAc*--trol of . upplied ruclear material<br />
and the ccer-: 1ulico,-r of bind. ing arran gemenc3 to give effect tosuch<br />
asaceI-n ' beth ser. es -as mpechanisms for verification<br />
and as aactc-r. 6j ofldzti. 0m1n3 fo r rnuc: lear eaxports safeguards<br />
arranerrent:; arc-EV-01N. Ing ~ t: t~ continually being<br />
strenz sher~ ed,'~ f e ac-, d imp-c-v-.<br />
A~ nLthis ~ cg'" i I wouald li. ke to anrnounce the<br />
following specifi-c , Eietthsoe comprehensive safegiaards<br />
polic-. y ~ hcitj' G r. me f s adopted. Th-e~ e cover:<br />
the ureeri keEp poli;-Lde review;<br />
C carefA: 1 s : eeic. n cf ' lgbeC'Ustfoomr e-Ursra nium;<br />
. p ~ Wie fh eft-' ec. Ltive lnattrnat. I. onal Atomic<br />
Energy Agency saleguardTh!;<br />
o bilete-ral agreeme-nrs with custotmer countries;<br />
fallback ;;, afeguards;<br />
prinr Aij. ralian: Guvernmerit consent in relation to<br />
re-expir--t:, enrichment reprccessing;<br />
physl. cal sc. urity;<br />
0 safeguards prcovi ioins In ccrntracts; E.. nd<br />
knternational and m,,. ILilat-eral efforts to strengthen<br />
saf fguard s. </p>
<p>-First, it will be a basic feature of our approach to<br />
recognise that the process of strengthening and improving<br />
international safeguards arrangements is an ongoing one. Our<br />
policy and safeguards arrangements must be kept closely under<br />
review to take account of the future evolution of international<br />
thinking on safeguards. In this regard the Government is<br />
pleased that, as recently announced, Mr. Justice Fox has agreed<br />
to become an adviser to me on policy matters relating to nuclear<br />
non-proliferation and safeguards.<br />
Second, should the Government approve further development<br />
of the Australian uranium industry it will retain the<br />
right to be selective in the countries to whom uranium export<br />
will be permitted. The following minimum criteria for eligibility<br />
to receive Australian uranium will apply. The Government<br />
emphasises that these represent minimum conditions for countries<br />
to be eligible to receive Australian uranium. The Government<br />
makes clear that wider foreign policy considerations may also*<br />
be taken into account, ' and that it reserves the right to<br />
refrain from permitting export should this be appropriate in. the<br />
light of such considerations. It does not, therefore, follow<br />
that the Government would necessarily permit export to a<br />
country meeting these minimum safeguards criteria.<br />
In the case of non-nuclear weapon states that -is<br />
to say all countries other than the five existing nuclear<br />
weapons powers recognised by the Non-Proliferation Treaty sales<br />
will be made only to countries which are parties to the Non-<br />
Proliferation Treaty.<br />
Because of these countries' safeguards obligations<br />
under the Non-Proliferation Treaty this policy will ensure that<br />
/ 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
the entire civil nuclear industry in such customer countries<br />
is subject to effective safeguards to verify that nuclear<br />
material, whether of Australian or any other origin, is not<br />
diverted from peaceful uses. The Government is aware that<br />
work has recently been underway within the International<br />
Atomic Energy Agency on a new system of equally stringent<br />
safeguards to cover the entire nuclear industry in non-.<br />
nuclear weapon states which are not parties to-the Non-<br />
Proliferation Treaty. It will be following progress on this<br />
matter and the implications which it may have for our policy.<br />
Regarding existing nuclear weapon states, they<br />
are not obliged under the Non-Proliferation Treaty to<br />
renounce nuclear weapons or accept international safeguards.<br />
They retain the right to use nuclear material for weapons<br />
as well as peaceful purposes. Even so, Australia would<br />
want to have assurance that nuclear material we may supply<br />
for peaceful purposes is not diverted to military or<br />
explosive purposes. We will therefore export only to nuclear<br />
weapon states which give Australia this assurance and accept<br />
that the uranium we supply be covered by International Atomic<br />
Energy Agency safeguards. In this respect the Government's<br />
policy introduces a requirement additional to those<br />
recommended by the Ranger Uranium Environmental Inquiry in<br />
its First Report. / 8 </p>
<p>8-<br />
G iomr.~ ensure that if a<br />
deci ! icn ist-k2t*:--Lr ' i1*.-' IPLi. m export, Ifeli ce<br />
will be. fovered by Inter!' at-icrnal At..-; ric Enoergy Agency safegLards<br />
fro-m the.-time, it. lea-ve3 AM. st. ralian ownErship. Aci<br />
matter: 3 stand, wh. ile safeguardD applied' urder the Non-<br />
Pro li~ fert Treaty require ncotificator. of transfers of<br />
yellcwcake, the full irt~ nsiity-of such safegGards -only commence,,<br />
to apply latEr in the ftlel cycle. Accordingly, it w. Ill be<br />
the Gormrtspolicy Chat any f-LL. re s2alEs3 ar. ngements<br />
for cixprts A A straJ Lar_ jrariLLum Tcidbe :? uch that. the<br />
uranium~ wil 1. in~ a D-ip. v+ hi 2h attr-at.-s full Inlrtzrnratio ral<br />
Atomi. L Energy Agency si~ aEguarcds by tte Lime it leaves<br />
Australian cuwersh. F'y~~ h~ Autt. r'Ui. st will rc-qUre the prior conclusion<br />
of b : Iaera1lATr bet-w( r. Llrme Ati:, tralian Government arnd<br />
ccuntri c s wsI tcJmp.-. rL Aus r. il1an urarlum unciLer any futr._ e<br />
contra, ts. These bilateral. agreeme-t~ nt will pro.-. vide a framewo--k<br />
for dir--ect and bIr~ d7. ng a~ r: esby importing countries to<br />
the Au_-trallnn 7e2: mL-ift Lfi reLati. D-to the e an~ d Control<br />
of uraxiL-_ m. sulppl-ied by Ac. i. ralia o~ r n~ l&amp;' m-. erial derived<br />
frcmit3' I~ e Th f~~ mer. La u~ err. akin~ gs the Governmert wll<br />
wish tc it-tair-Eromurm tpt~ gco-, ntries in such bilateral<br />
agreements are OIL rir: J~ lear nute-r-al 3upplled by -Austra. ia for<br />
peaceful pirpcises -r nwiclear material derived frcm its. uSc will<br />
not be diverted Lo militar-y or exploI. sive piirposes arid that'<br />
Internat-iomal3 At-ori: Energy Agenc,: y safeguardsc will apply to<br />
verify compliace~ with this im,. dertaking. Au3tralia would<br />
seek to arra~ qze w. h iurimpoxtirng co-antries regular<br />
expert-level cor. ultat-: onc_-LC, Fatisf~ y ourselves of thes:: 6000/ 9 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
implementation of the provisions of bilaterial agreements. In<br />
line with the positions taken by the United States and Canada<br />
Australia would retain the right to. cease supply of uranium to<br />
any country which breached safeguards undertakings.<br />
Fifth, the Government takes the view that nuclear<br />
material supplied by Australia or nuclear material derived from<br />
its use should remain under safeguards for the full life of<br />
the material in question or until it is legitmately removed<br />
from safeguards. In line with this basic principle the Government has<br />
decided that bilateral agreements with non-nuclear weapon states<br />
should make provision for so-called fallback safeguards. I have<br />
already made clear that Australia would not be prepared to export<br />
uranium to such countries in the absence of International Atomic<br />
Energy Agency safeguards applied under the Non-Proliferation<br />
Treaty. However, the question arises of ensuring the continued<br />
safeguarding of material already present in an importing country<br />
should safeguards under the Non-Proliferation Treaty at some<br />
stage cease to apply in that country. There should be provision<br />
under the bilateral agreements for the continued application of<br />
international safeguards in such circumstances. Further, the<br />
bilateral agreements should provide for Australia to make<br />
alternative arrangements for the safeguarding of nuclear material<br />
supplied by us in the event of international safeguards as such<br />
ceasing to operate.<br />
Moreover, the Government feels it is reasonable to ask<br />
importing countries who will already accept International Atomic<br />
Energy Agency safeguards of comprehensive scope under the Non-<br />
Proliferation Treaty, to accept that, at the first fallback level<br />
also, international safeguards should apply to all nuclear material,<br />
not just that portion supplied by Australia. </p>
<p>Sixth9 t' -:: Gy-ernnE. n.*-c&amp; on-: ider that it wc-uld he<br />
an ur1, saLi~ fa,-t.') ry s1A. t-: ation ftr 1 : ppl ty Ausiria1La<br />
to one ~ cr o r-. ciiear material de-ved from it-: us-: e, E~<br />
be able to be x -' t-Kcrttd a third '. lUrLtl'y without the<br />
opportunity ft-, r Autralia to satisfy itself that adequate<br />
coctrCls w(' t, 1d apply ti-e Ltansfetred ma'e-rial arid thit.<br />
the na3 i&amp;-21i. t~ ni acceptable to us For this<br />
rei. zor' tbc Gu:. irrtment L as dECideA that. bilateral agreemrnLS<br />
wiihu~ rrm.~ prnc rcin * cxmtn Jiobcld wakKeC y trans3fer-of<br />
suppli ed mater Lal. to a. third p. arty cortinge;-nt co. the prior<br />
coni3er~ t f the Au-. itra'liax G' vwrnmnlEt This jTVlsion will<br />
give Aulstratia. the ec-qs-i ng that our safeguards<br />
rc-qui:-mert-. a e rre.. .* vr t-r~ n,--ffer. c-f the<br />
uranium we : ri or :~: ermater Lal dcri-ied frc-m it.<br />
wcr, Ald e that Australian uranium<br />
supplied to cth, r c'stc: r. r pe.-cref. Ll us~ es ner. t be enrjched<br />
bey-.-nd 20% iu&gt; 3 u-i. hm) ut, P-rx rr A~~ aPr 0 Th ic<br />
provisic. n I~ n iir..! A the adrpted b~ y other ruc1ear<br />
supplier TI-e fig-i! r ef. 20% . e-n chosen as<br />
reptE* Et2 a . g enl-tcr. 1-hrrentL belzow the praz ticai<br />
rLeqL,. ir( I. rrfln-, ! or at i.. lear -xpl.? ive, while being above the<br />
er~ rizrn1n -2-el req' 3ired for most peaceful uss, excepting,<br />
for example, somE rcearch an-d radic-Lsotope producztion<br />
reacto-) rz-, for hi. h. prL. 9 to En----zh to the ne.: essary<br />
level -w-ould reeCl r~ co be rbtained. In res; pect of this requirement<br />
alsq, th -pos. ext;--ds beyc.. nd-the<br />
recommendatica:-jz maje by th) e Rarge. r Ur-anium Enrxironner. tal<br />
Inquiry i-r it. E-F-Lrst Raport, </p>
<p>11<br />
__~ jjh the Gov. errmeit is aware of the iThterest of<br />
some co-antr-^ E3 1. i ter-p:.-rg'fpel. rw1. 2 to<br />
meet their anticipated future fuel requirEments, and to<br />
facilitate the ma. nagement of r. uclea-r material Eollrwirg its<br />
u!, e inI ;. uclear reactor!,, At. thE present time the need for<br />
rEprccessing and the cLtils cf an effective cont'rol regime<br />
for this area o7f t. hE 2cla fuel cycle are the subject cf<br />
close sturdy internationally. This is an area in which there<br />
a-re E. nujmb-er-new ide&amp;. and irnitlatives0 The Un~ ited States<br />
has propo~ sed an International Nuclear Fuel Cycle Evaluation<br />
Prograim to( 7' sc, varic~ us; rujclea-r fuel cycle,. in terms of<br />
thei~ r iMpliC., 5. ti_._ IrfLS f&amp; r prc'liferaLl., n co:. trol. There are also<br />
such ideas as vari, us" schee for mjltinatimnal. control cf<br />
reprocessing fac:. I'lities and for the management of spent fuel.<br />
and plutoium., Th. e Governmi nt " E. ccme,,: these s'tudies and<br />
COT-' ltainc. a-. c1 will. ik ttoo c'or-ribute actively and<br />
cons truct. ve ly t5 relevant aspect(_-n of them such ae f-uel<br />
supply srce andA waio. ta management.<br />
The Ccmt. sview is thl-at,, prior to a clearer<br />
routcome eme-1gL2. g from K.' is za_ rent irtternatio-nal activity9<br />
it would be p~~~~ fcr Ai~ stral2ia to Adopt a unilateral<br />
position on ths detailed Lni-d. iteor~ ~ w hich we might be<br />
prepared to agreetct reproceC3Esing, it anyv of nuclear material<br />
suppii-ed by Australia. Ia order Lo effectively reserve<br />
Australia's p( wsl-* ti. n on '-his mattrer -Eor the time being we would<br />
wish to make prov2Kio,,. In bilateral agreemzn. nts with countries<br />
importing Australian bran.: umn that any reprocezsing of nuclear<br />
material 5-pplied by, Australi. a may z.-ilv take plaze-c with the<br />
prior consent of the Australian Gov,; ernment0 This requirement<br />
is add it~ imal 01h) e -reommEn~ ied by the R nger Uranium<br />
o. o./ 12 </p>
<p>12<br />
Env~ Qm~~. 1 rqiiv F2. r'. t Rcpo-rt and1 reflIect-s<br />
sim~ rlar e' t xp c. yih . qf\ñ l<br />
relation to reproce:. iriz0<br />
Nin~ th, tha Gc--etrnent would reqiuire ill ftur. e bilatexal<br />
agrecments t-eaise fr; mn -Lr-ci'L., fl IMp) crulg countriEs th-at;<br />
adeq-Oate hrIl s-curi-* ty W4 Jl 1. e riabntaived c--n their n-,.. clear<br />
industries. In addit-Ln, wiF believE, tire agreerrents should<br />
specify ccmp1.-~ ine with E-tar-t-ards of phyDLoal seCU. City ') aced,<br />
at a minim-fJ, P T ~ i Inte-rational At; mi-' t,-Eriergy Agen,-zy rocmmendatio-<br />
ris as Pre -tent-l dt3. f1irn U arJ -s pdatell from time t. o tim-re0<br />
They sh,. uld : A. sc, mdke pc' fr ; r rxpert levc-1. : nitat icn<br />
as necessa-iy p1.! 7?-ical1 L. se-: urity artrangement&amp;'. These requ-irements<br />
also t.-5an slate Thto cn rete polj.-y measuices concerns<br />
expresS EAd hy the Ranger Uranilum Environmental1 Inquiry.<br />
The in pir-t~' f r. hL: E pcvE o. in th e Gove-r--<br />
ment' s safeguaids pclicy. re,. E! Ects ,, ux corice-rn that total rnuc*; Ea~ r<br />
control shuild en~ ompa; s~ not jus3t oafeguards to ,-erLfy that<br />
nuclea', material is nct ilzlydiverted from peaceful uce'r<br />
by nat.-;.: nalGern..; m: rti. l uhriizb also; to<br />
prote-cct rrr, n---t. EL E: al fr~: m illegsal u-2e by groups5 rr<br />
individual s.<br />
TF~ nth, the . abi~ rei of effective arrangements<br />
f or safegu3rd-i e: rtial a matte--for Governmentsc an-d<br />
for inter-Gcveir.. merital agr~ eent:, either bilateral or multLilar-eral.<br />
Neverthele.! r 9 it is imp: r-tant to ern7-ure that the actual parties<br />
to c:-mmerz,-al coAnrraz: t. F, whiich may be private erg ani satins<br />
are also awari the : fg: rsohligat. ionr. to which their<br />
transaction is subject, For thi.; -rea3on., alth:-ugh the Ranger<br />
Uranium Envirl-me-nta1 1. nqairy tAin First Report did nri(; t m-3ke<br />
a 0/ 1 </p>
<p>-13-<br />
a recommendation on this matter, the Government has decided<br />
that it is desirable that, as a standard practice, a clause<br />
should be included in any future contracts for the export of<br />
uranium from Australia noting that the transaction is subject<br />
to safeguards as agreed betweenthe importing country and the<br />
Australian Government.<br />
Finally, as an important complement to the measures<br />
I have outlined so far, the Government recognises the importance<br />
of Australia contributing to constructive multilateral efforts<br />
to strengthen safeguards. There is a need for what President<br />
Carter has described as systematic and thorough consultations<br />
in this area. We too consider that it is highly desirable<br />
that there should be the widest possible consensus amongst both<br />
nuclear supplier countries and nuclear importing countries on<br />
the controls to apply to the world nuclear-industry. The<br />
wider the consensus, the more effective these controls will be<br />
as a barrier to nuclear proliferation. The more uniform the<br />
views of the countries concerned, the easier it will be to<br />
implement a properly effective regime of controls. It will be<br />
an integral part of Australia's approach to safeguards to seek<br />
to promote such a consensus.<br />
In particular, we will seek to co-ordinate policy on<br />
safeguards with other like-minded countries. As I noted at<br />
the outset, I have already initiated an exchange of<br />
correspondence with the President of the United States and<br />
the Prime Minister of Canada expressing this wish, and extremely<br />
valuable consultations have already taken place. The policy<br />
I am now announcing incorporates the Government's consideration<br />
of these consultations and represents a very similar approach to<br />
safeguards to that adopted by the United States and Canada. More<br />
generally, nuclear supplier countries have a special role<br />
and responsibility in the ongoing development of safeguards / 14 </p>
<p>14<br />
and ACL.-: ali'a wLlI be ppzedto paf LI-Cpate with them i~ n<br />
We will alcsr: conttirut-actach irnajr importance to<br />
the e-' Fec-tiv,. e applicaticn of safegu~ ards by the International<br />
AtcoIx'c Energy Agency, Via v. 11 S t , L. gate if t~ here are<br />
specific. a-lreas in which Au; trali. cculd usefully assist the<br />
Agency's ca~ pacity to apply -Increacingly effez-tive safeguards.<br />
At. the prEeert ti-m the Guvert.-mernt sees a mlt-ilateral<br />
apprac. h t oward-13 safegua-rd. s qu-estionis being espeacially<br />
desirable fn one spE! cific area as well the Interrational N,-: clear<br />
Fuel. Cycle Evaluation Program already menationEd; we would<br />
wish to lend suipport to the development. of an international<br />
convention on 01-e physical protection of nuclear material in<br />
interrational transit. Als. o,, we wo-ald wish to explore with<br />
other coLtnfrr-cs a. common. approa:. h Lac santjcns in the event<br />
of a breach of supply coerditian.-O<br />
The o~ f ~ tiTlnredptt olicy I have cutli-fned<br />
are ca: E-(;. rUi . lct~ of cu-Lomir ti. appl-iration e.'<br />
interrati.-jra! ofegi&amp; q-Lds t. veri-fv that matEr. i. al supplied for<br />
pca-efll--pjtrrpc. s; s i: 3 nc-L tr.--om the etTihrn of add-itional<br />
safeit~ h. r ~ h hI~ tralagre. menr. s, and an active involvement<br />
by Au 3LtaLP-a in internatiional efforts to upgrade safeguardF.<br />
The poli.. v J-the re'sult of full. careful and devuailed<br />
consideration of sa, f, e gi-uards by the Government. It builds on<br />
the prelimiria-v klt-hink~ ng of th-e Government described in<br />
testinc; ny to L-. e Rang er Uranium En' irunmer.' Ital Inquiry<br />
year, as welul a&amp; 2-the reccrrmendaticx-s of the Fir~ t. Report,-of<br />
the Inq," iry itself. The policy has been the subject of<br />
detailed cxrlangec of vLew-, with ,) ther countries both utrani-um<br />
o0a0/ 15 </p>
<p>impo-t. rs and major r-u. clear expotfer and relevant intermat1:&gt;<br />
rta1 i'gali-a'-. ions ludIng the 0 Inte: z-nair1n Atoic<br />
Energy Ager. ;, y0<br />
As a result the Gbvernment is satisfied that the<br />
poli, y it has; decide4 upon represents a practical, reasonable<br />
and effecLx'; F package of safeguards measures to seek from<br />
counLr'ee wishing to r. mpo--t Lir. nium from Australia under any<br />
future co-, itracts. It i fully in -rep with current internation.<br />
I. Z-fo-rts to crrergthen safeguards. The policy goes<br />
beyond a mere acceptance Aa!: tralia of our international<br />
obligati'n:. as -a party to the Nc:. n-ProiPrferation Treaty and<br />
constithuule3 a poli, ; y as stringent as that adopted to date by<br />
any nuclear supplier country. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
