<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11608</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA-NEW ZEALAND BILATERAL ECONOMIC RELATIONS         Report to the Hon John Howard MP, Prime Minister of Australia         and the Rt Hon Helen Clark MP, Prime Minister of New Zealand         by the Australian Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade         and the New Zealand Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Trade</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/08/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Introduction</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard of Australia and Prime Minister Jenny Shipley</p>
<p> of New Zealand met in New Zealand in February 1999 for annual discussions</p>
<p> on a range of bilateral, regional and multilateral issues.</p>
<p>As a consequence of those discussions and of a mutual desire further</p>
<p> to develop the bilateral economic partnership, Prime Ministers agreed</p>
<p> to establish a Joint Task Force on Bilateral Economic Relations under</p>
<p> the direction of their Departments of Prime Minister and Cabinet. The</p>
<p> Task Force was to address a small number of specific bilateral issues</p>
<p> and to examine ways of building on the already strong economic foundations</p>
<p> of CER. Prime Ministers agreed that the specific bilateral issues would</p>
<p> include:</p>
<p> . barriers and costs to trans-Tasman investment;</p>
<p> . conclusion of negotiations on a bilateral child support</p>
<p> arrangement; and</p>
<p> . revision of the bilateral Social Security Agreement.</p>
<p>On 4 August 1999, after receiving the report of the Task Force, Prime</p>
<p> Ministers Howard and Shipley issued a Joint Communique announcing the</p>
<p> results of the Task Force's work and an agreed program of future action.</p>
<p> In order to ensure the efficient implementation of the work program, Australia's</p>
<p> Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade (DFAT) and New Zealand's Ministry</p>
<p> of Foreign Affairs and Trade (MFAT), in consultation with the two Departments</p>
<p> of Prime Minister and Cabinet, were to provide Prime Ministers with a</p>
<p> joint progress report before their next bilateral meeting.</p>
<p>This report is intended to meet that requirement. Its structure mirrors</p>
<p> the structure of the communique. Extracts from the communique appear in</p>
<p> bold italics and are followed by comments</p>
<p> on progress in implementing the measures agreed by Prime Ministers.</p>
<p>Closer Economic Relations (CER)</p>
<p>"The main focus of both our nations' trade policies is currently</p>
<p> on securing further trade liberalisation through a new WTO round and we</p>
<p> are working cooperatively to promote its launch at the WTO Ministerial</p>
<p> meeting to be held in November in Seattle.</p>
<p>"New Zealand and Australia are willing to consider free trade arrangements</p>
<p> with other significant individual economies or regional groupings, where</p>
<p> they would deliver faster and deeper liberalisation than the multilateral</p>
<p> process, with the objective of gaining better market access for our exporters,</p>
<p> faster economic growth and stronger employment growth. Such arrangements</p>
<p> would need to reflect the principles underpinning CER, including WTO consistency."</p>
<p>Global trade liberalisation</p>
<p>Australia and New Zealand have continued to work very closely in various</p>
<p> international fora, including the WTO, APEC and the Cairns Group, to secure</p>
<p> our shared trade liberalisation objectives, particularly in the area of</p>
<p> agriculture. Australian and New Zealand delegations consulted closely</p>
<p> in the lead up to, and at the WTO Ministerial Meeting in Seattle from</p>
<p> 30 November to 3 December 1999. Following the failure at Seattle to launch</p>
<p> a new round of WTO trade negotiations, Ministers and officials are continuing</p>
<p> to consult closely on the best way to move forward on the earliest possible</p>
<p> launch of a round and on other shared objectives such as progress on the</p>
<p> mandated negotiations in agriculture and services.</p>
<p>Notwithstanding the priority we give to the launch of a new multilateral</p>
<p> round of trade negotiations, both countries remain open to the possibility</p>
<p> of concluding free trade agreements with other countries or regional groupings</p>
<p> where these could be expected to deliver substantial economic gains which</p>
<p> could not be achieved elsewhere within a similar timeframe.</p>
<p>Both governments will seek, through negotiations in the WTO, to multilateralise</p>
<p> progress made in regional trade liberalisation. Australia and New Zealand</p>
<p> will take this up in the forthcoming mandated negotiations on agriculture</p>
<p> and services notwithstanding the lack of agreement in Seattle to a new</p>
<p> round of trade negotiations.</p>
<p>AFTA/CER Task Force</p>
<p>In Singapore on 1 October 1999, CER and ASEAN trade and economic ministers</p>
<p> agreed to establish an ASEAN Free Trade Area (AFTA) / CER High Level Task</p>
<p> Force to explore the feasibility of an AFTA-CER free trade area by 2010.</p>
<p> The Task Force has been asked to submit a set of recommendations, including</p>
<p> on the scope and coverage of a possible FTA and to outline the requirements</p>
<p> an FTA would have to meet if it was to be consistent with Article XXIV</p>
<p> of the GATT and Article V of the GATS.</p>
<p>The Rt Hon Sir William Birch GNZM and the Hon Tim Fischer MP have been</p>
<p> appointed to represent New Zealand and Australia respectively. The Task</p>
<p> Force members met in Jakarta on 8-9 February. The second Task Force meeting</p>
<p> will be in New Zealand on 27-28 April and a third meeting is planned for</p>
<p> September. There were useful discussions between Task Force members in</p>
<p> Jakarta in February and positive progress was made. The feasibility study</p>
<p> will be completed in time to be considered at the next meeting of ASEAN</p>
<p> economic and CER trade ministers in Thailand in October 2000.</p>
<p>Pacific Regional Trade Agreement (PARTA)</p>
<p>Australia and New Zealand are also consulting closely with the Forum</p>
<p> island countries regarding the establishment of a Pacific Regional Trade</p>
<p> Agreement following the decision by leaders at the South Pacific Forum</p>
<p> meeting in Palau on 5 October 1999 to negotiate a free trade agreement</p>
<p> between Forum Member countries. The manner in which Australia and New Zealand</p>
<p> are to be included in the Agreement is under discussion and will be resolved</p>
<p> through the negotiation process. Australia and New Zealand met in Wellington</p>
<p> in January 2000 to discuss a joint approach to PARTA negotiations, and</p>
<p> will participate in a pre-negotiations workshop in Suva on 29-30 March.</p>
<p>New Zealand work on free trade agreement (FTA) prospects</p>
<p>New Zealand has begun negotiation of a bilateral FTA with Singapore,</p>
<p> started work on a Republic of Korea/New Zealand Study and is giving consideration</p>
<p> to work in 2000 on an agreed study of an FTA among Singapore, Chile and</p>
<p> New Zealand. New Zealand is keeping Australia closely informed of progress</p>
<p> and the option is open for Australia to associate itself with this work,</p>
<p> which proceeds in the context of our shared commitment to multilateral</p>
<p> trade liberalisation.</p>
<p>Investment</p>
<p>"Australia has reviewed its foreign investment requirements in line</p>
<p> with its APEC Individual Action Plan and will liberalise its foreign investment</p>
<p> regime. The changes will lower compliance costs for all foreign investors</p>
<p> and provide benefits for New Zealand.</p>
<p>"Australia will:</p>
<p>. increase its existing foreign investment business acquisition threshold</p>
<p> from $A5 million ($A3 million for rural) to $A50 million on a multilateral</p>
<p> basis;</p>
<p>. remove foreign investment approval requirements for New Zealanders</p>
<p> who hold or are entitled to hold a special category visa and invest</p>
<p> in Australian residential real estate through Australian registered</p>
<p> companies and trusts; and</p>
<p>. provide simplified processing arrangements for proposals to invest</p>
<p> in businesses, valued at less than $A100 million, on a multilateral</p>
<p> basis."</p>
<p>Amendments to the Australian Foreign Acquisitions and Takeovers Regulations</p>
<p> 1989, giving effect to the first two measures (above), entered</p>
<p> into force on 10 September 1999. The third measure was implemented by</p>
<p> changes to administrative arrangements on the same day. These three measures</p>
<p> together provide a simpler and more efficient framework for New Zealanders</p>
<p> wishing to invest in Australia.</p>
<p>Additional Australian measures</p>
<p>Consistent with this approach, the Australian Government has also made</p>
<p> the following changes to foreign investment policy:</p>
<p> . The voluntary notification threshold for the Australian</p>
<p> assets of an offshore company to be acquired by another offshore company</p>
<p> has been increased from $20 million to $50 million.</p>
<p>. Acquisitions of residential real estate by Australian permanent</p>
<p> resident visa holders, not ordinarily resident in Australia, purchasing</p>
<p> through Australian companies or trusts has been exempted from notification</p>
<p> requirements;</p>
<p> . Australian citizens and their foreign spouses purchasing</p>
<p> as joint tenants are no longer required to seek approval for purchases</p>
<p> of residential property in Australia.</p>
<p> . The acquisition of house and land packages, where construction</p>
<p> has not commenced, is no longer limited to fifty per cent of the project's</p>
<p> sales. Approval is conditional on continuous construction of the relevant</p>
<p> dwelling commencing within twelve months.</p>
<p> . Where properties are not subject to heritage listing, the</p>
<p> notification threshold applying to the acquisition of developed non-residential</p>
<p> commercial properties has been raised from $5 million to $50 million.</p>
<p> . Acquisitions of developed non-residential commercial properties,</p>
<p> valued between the notification threshold and $100 million, are no</p>
<p> longer subject to detailed examination, unless the facts of the proposal</p>
<p> raise issues pertaining to the national interest.</p>
<p> . The policy of designating Integrated Tourism Resorts (ITRs),</p>
<p> within which foreign persons are permitted to acquire residential</p>
<p> property without restriction, now applies only to developed residential</p>
<p> property which is leased back to the resort operator, to be available</p>
<p> for tourist accommodation when not occupied by the owner. Owners of</p>
<p> residential property in existing ITRs have retained their entitlements.</p>
<p> . An exemption is now obtainable for the acquisition by foreign</p>
<p> interests of strata-titled hotel rooms in designated hotels where</p>
<p> each room is subject to a long-term (10 years or more) hotel management</p>
<p> arrangement.</p>
<p> . An exemption now exists for the acquisition of interests</p>
<p> in Australian urban land by foreign-owned responsible entities acting</p>
<p> on behalf of managed unit trusts and other managed public investment</p>
<p> schemes registered under Chapter 5C of the Australian Corporations</p>
<p> Law, where they are investing for the benefit of fund investors</p>
<p> or unit holders ordinarily resident in Australia. This is consistent</p>
<p> with rules applying to foreign-owned life insurers and superannuation</p>
<p> funds.</p>
<p>"For its part, New Zealand will raise the threshold at which consent</p>
<p> for non-land foreign investment is required from $NZ10 million to $NZ50</p>
<p> million, on a multilateral basis. The criteria for land-related foreign</p>
<p> investment will remain unchanged."</p>
<p>In New Zealand, regulations entered into force on 9 December 1999 which</p>
<p> raised the threshold at which consent for non-land foreign investment</p>
<p> is required from NZ$10 million to NZ$50 million.</p>
<p>"Australia and New Zealand will consult each other on our respective</p>
<p> foreign investment policies in the context of any specific review of those</p>
<p> policies under our international obligations."</p>
<p>Since the communique was issued, there has been no review of Australian</p>
<p> or New Zealand foreign investment policies under our international obligations.</p>
<p> No such review is currently scheduled.</p>
<p>Should either party undertake such a review, it will consult the other</p>
<p> party as required by the communique.</p>
<p>Social security</p>
<p>"New Zealand and Australia both want more stable and durable social</p>
<p> security arrangements that will provide a better strategic fit for our</p>
<p> wider CER relationship, both now and as it develops in future years. As</p>
<p> part of this, Australia and New Zealand:</p>
<p>. will undertake a full review of social security arrangements, with</p>
<p> a view to developing a sustainable long-term solution to current problems.</p>
<p> We expect that terms of reference will be settled before our next</p>
<p> meeting, in February 2000. We further expect to start putting in place</p>
<p> the changes in arrangements stemming from the review before the Prime</p>
<p> Ministerial meeting in February 2001; and</p>
<p>. will implement an interim arrangement for 2 years that will markedly</p>
<p> simplify the current complex and overly cumbersome administrative</p>
<p> arrangements by simply agreeing the reimbursement track in advance,</p>
<p> and provide for a higher level of reimbursement of the social security</p>
<p> costs incurred by Australia over that period than that provided for</p>
<p> under the current Agreement. Specifically, we have agreed that New</p>
<p> Zealand will reimburse Australia $A125m for the year 1999/2000 and</p>
<p> $A135m for the year 2000/2001 for the costs of providing social security</p>
<p> to New Zealand citizens in Australia. This interim agreement, including</p>
<p> increased reimbursement, will continue until it can be replaced by</p>
<p> a new Social Security Agreement."</p>
<p>Review of social security arrangements</p>
<p>Officials from New Zealand and Australia met in Wellington on 17-18 February</p>
<p> to finalise the terms of reference for the review of social security arrangements</p>
<p> and discuss arrangements for conducting the review. It was agreed that</p>
<p> the review was to be completed with a final report to be presented to</p>
<p> Governments by 30 June 2000, with a view to both countries agreeing on</p>
<p> and starting to implement the changes in arrangements stemming from the</p>
<p> review before the prime ministerial meeting in 2001. The terms of reference</p>
<p> for the review are attached to this report.</p>
<p>Interim arrangements</p>
<p>An exchange of notes implementing the interim reimbursement arrangements</p>
<p> agreed by Prime Ministers was completed and came into force on 25</p>
<p> October 1999. The interim arrangement operates with effect from 1 July</p>
<p> 1999 and will remain in force until the entry into force of a revised</p>
<p> bilateral Social Security Agreement. The reimbursement amounts agreed</p>
<p> by Prime Ministers will be applied for the years 1999/2000 and 2000/2001.</p>
<p> If the interim arrangements remain in force after 30 June 2001, the reimbursement</p>
<p> paid by New Zealand to Australia will be derived in accordance with the</p>
<p> terms of the communique. A forecasting model which will underpin determination</p>
<p> of the reimbursement amount is currently under discussion.</p>
<p>Child Support</p>
<p>"Australia and New Zealand have been developing a draft Child Support</p>
<p> Agreement (CSA) to promote more equitable payment arrangements for New</p>
<p> Zealand and Australian parents. We have agreed that the CSA should be</p>
<p> implemented at the earliest opportunity, with operation commencing from</p>
<p> 1 July 2000."</p>
<p>The proposed bilateral child support arrangements comprise two agreements,</p>
<p> a principal Child Support Agreement (CSA) and a service arrangement. The</p>
<p> principal agreement provides for the establishment and enforcement of</p>
<p> child and spousal maintenance liabilities by each country. The final text</p>
<p> of the Agreement was agreed between Australian and New Zealand Child Support</p>
<p> Agencies during February 2000 and is due to be signed in March 2000. Discussions</p>
<p> on the Service Arrangement are still proceeding and it is envisaged that</p>
<p> these will be completed and the Arrangement signed in April/May 2000.</p>
<p>Implementing the CSA in Australia</p>
<p>The agreements will come into force in Australia following amendments</p>
<p> to the Child Support (Registration and Collection) Act 1988, the</p>
<p> Child Support (Assessment) Act 1989 and the Family Law Act 1975.</p>
<p> The agreements are also subject to the Commonwealth's treaty review process,</p>
<p> including scrutiny by the Parliamentary Joint Standing Committee on Treaties</p>
<p> (JSCOT). Subject always to Parliamentary and JSCOT approval, Australia's</p>
<p> procedural arrangements for the entry into force of the Child Support</p>
<p> Agreement by 1 July 2000 are on track.</p>
<p>Implementing the CSA in New Zealand</p>
<p>The Agreement is to be given effect in New Zealand by Order in Council.</p>
<p> It will enter into force 30 days after New Zealand and Australia have</p>
<p> notified each other that respective domestic implementation processes</p>
<p> are complete. Therefore, domestic processes in New Zealand (and Australia)</p>
<p> will have to be concluded before 1 June.</p>
<p>Business law</p>
<p>"We have agreed to explore the scope for further regulatory coordination</p>
<p> of our respective regimes and have agreed that any further reform would</p>
<p> need to take account not just of CER but also of the broader regional</p>
<p> and global environments, including the emergence of global standards.</p>
<p>"A study has been commissioned by New Zealand on possible approaches</p>
<p> to further trans-Tasman business law reform, having regard to our objective</p>
<p> of positioning Australian and New Zealand business on the world stage.</p>
<p> Officials will hold discussions on the study in August, with a view to</p>
<p> identifying possible areas for further regulatory coordination.</p>
<p>"As part of this process, New Zealand and Australia will give specific</p>
<p> consideration to:</p>
<p>. cross-recognising trans-Tasman companies through a simplified registration</p>
<p> mechanism;</p>
<p>. issues related to the regulation of overseas financial products</p>
<p> markets which are adequately supervised; and</p>
<p>. cross-border insolvency, in particular, the adoption of the UNCITRAL</p>
<p> Model Law</p>
<p>"Australia recently announced that it would reform its disclosure</p>
<p> requirements for financial products (other than securities). These reforms</p>
<p> are similar in approach to New Zealand's existing regime. In implementing</p>
<p> the reforms, Australia will harmonise its requirements with New Zealand's,</p>
<p> to the greatest extent possible consistent with its policy framework,</p>
<p> to reduce compliance costs and help facilitate the offering of common</p>
<p> products in both countries."</p>
<p>Officials from the New Zealand Ministry of Commerce and the Australian</p>
<p> Treasury met in New Zealand in August 1999 with a view to identifying</p>
<p> possible areas for further regulatory coordination and to consider implementation</p>
<p> of other business law aspects of the communique programme.</p>
<p>Memorandum of Understanding</p>
<p>Officials have agreed to review and modernise the 1988 Memorandum of</p>
<p> Understanding (MOU) on the Harmonisation of Business Laws, and are working</p>
<p> to produce a new MOU for signature by Ministers by early 2000. The MOU</p>
<p> will reflect the desire of both countries to reduce business compliance</p>
<p> costs, increase trans-Tasman competition and reflect the increasing importance</p>
<p> of a global approach to business laws. It will recognise that business</p>
<p> law harmonisation will not necessarily develop identical laws but should</p>
<p> work towards complementary systems which are capable of resolving any</p>
<p> differences which may act as barriers to trade and investment.</p>
<p>Cross-recognition</p>
<p>Substantial work has already been done on the issue of cross-recognition</p>
<p> of trans-Tasman companies. New Zealand officials are preparing a review</p>
<p> paper which will discuss options for taking the issue forward. A specific</p>
<p> proposal for cross-recognition will be considered by officials in the</p>
<p> first half of 2000, with a view to decision by respective Ministers in</p>
<p> the second half of 2000.</p>
<p>Recognition of overseas financial products markets</p>
<p>Australia is developing the necessary statutory framework to support</p>
<p> recognition of overseas markets which are subject to comparable regulation</p>
<p> as part of its proposed Financial Services and Markets legislation being</p>
<p> developed under the Corporate Law Economic Reform Program. Both countries</p>
<p> are also undertaking further work on comparing their respective disclosure</p>
<p> regimes for financial products, so as to be in a position to assess the</p>
<p> scope for achieving a mutual recognition of disclosure regimes by. As</p>
<p> part of this work, New Zealand has prepared a paper on the New Zealand</p>
<p> disclosure regime for financial products, which is currently being considered</p>
<p> by Australian officials.</p>
<p>Cross-border insolvency</p>
<p>Officials have considered cross-border insolvency issues with a view</p>
<p> to adoption of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law</p>
<p> (UNCITRAL) Model Law on cross-border insolvency. While it may be possible</p>
<p> to go further than the Model Law in relation to trans-Tasman cooperation</p>
<p> on cross-border insolvency matters a number of differences in the way</p>
<p> insolvency administrations are conducted in each country (eg. licensing</p>
<p> of liquidators) still need to be addressed. Officials will ensure that</p>
<p> trans-Tasman harmonisation is considered in the context of future policy</p>
<p> development, with a view to developing a harmonised cross-border insolvency</p>
<p> regime for consideration by respective governments.</p>
<p>Customs</p>
<p>"Our respective Customs agencies have been addressing harmonisation</p>
<p> and simplification issues within CER for some time, and have made considerable</p>
<p> progress. This work will be accelerated, with the objective of: improving</p>
<p> facilitation of trans-Tasman trade by streamlining customs regulatory</p>
<p> procedures; reducing customs compliance costs for trans-Tasman business;</p>
<p> and introducing 'one-stop shop' on-line customs clearance procedures for</p>
<p> agreed trans-Tasman exporters. Officials will implement an agreed work</p>
<p> programme which includes specific milestones for the next year.</p>
<p>Australian and New Zealand customs agencies will also look closely at</p>
<p> the information presently required from importers and exporters, with</p>
<p> a view to investigating ways of appropriately reducing business compliance</p>
<p> costs."</p>
<p>Australian and New Zealand customs services, in consultation with relevant</p>
<p> national agencies, have continued to cooperate on the development of measures</p>
<p> to further harmonise customs procedures and reduce compliance costs for</p>
<p> business, consistent with the pre-existing 25 May 1999 "Trans-Tasman</p>
<p> Cargo Management Statement of Intent". This work has been accelerated</p>
<p> as follows:</p>
<p>Compliance costs</p>
<p>Business compliance costs will be reduced as a consequence of Australia's</p>
<p> cargo management re-engineering program, likely to be completed by mid-2001.</p>
<p> The program aims to reduce by at least 30 per cent the amount of information</p>
<p> required for export/import transactions and will provide the necessary</p>
<p> basis for a trans-Tasman internet-based system for customs reporting.</p>
<p>"One-stop shop"</p>
<p>Australia and New Zealand are evaluating possibilities for establishing</p>
<p> partnerships with strategic industry partners involving periodic Customs</p>
<p> entries and deferred payment of duty. Using methodology developed by Australian</p>
<p> Customs, New Zealand had initiated a trial of partnerships for exports</p>
<p> in August 1998, prior to the Prime Ministers' 1999 meeting. Draft business</p>
<p> rules for accredited clients and an independent audit framework are now</p>
<p> being developed by Australia with a view to an Australian program commencing</p>
<p> by end 2000. The objective in the medium term is to include Australian</p>
<p> and New Zealand traders in this program to facilitate development of a</p>
<p> system of "cross recognition" for each other's audit and compliance</p>
<p> regimes to facilitate cargo clearance. Information on respective compliance</p>
<p> regimes has been exchanged by the two customs services.</p>
<p>Streamlining procedures</p>
<p>A preliminary examination of each country's data requirements has been</p>
<p> undertaken and an analysis of the potential for harmonising our respective</p>
<p> data collection systems is underway. Much will depend on similar work</p>
<p> underway within the G7. This G7 work will be presented to Heads of State</p>
<p> at the next G7 Summit in June 2000 and was analysed by trans-Tasman customs</p>
<p> services in consultation with other relevant agencies. A draft comparison</p>
<p> of Australian and New Zealand Customs import and export data was passed</p>
<p> to New Zealand by Australian Customs in August 1999 and the subsequent</p>
<p> New Zealand analysis is now under consideration by Australian Customs.</p>
<p> This consideration will be completed by 29 February 2000. The customs</p>
<p> agencies propose to publish their analysis by the end of August 2000.</p>
<p>A revised tariff concept paper, which examines the potential for amalgamating</p>
<p> the two countries' tariff functions, was sent by New Zealand Customs to</p>
<p> Australian Customs on 2 September 1999 and is now the subject of</p>
<p> an extensive work program involving several Australian agencies. As a</p>
<p> first step Australian and New Zealand Customs have identified over 500</p>
<p> differences in their respective tariffs. As the next stage in this process</p>
<p> Australian Customs is now identifying goods and classes of goods where</p>
<p> these differences occur. It is expected that this information will be</p>
<p> sent to New Zealand Customs by the end of March 2000. New Zealand is examining</p>
<p> the possibility of adopting Australia's Tariff and Precedent Information</p>
<p> Network (TAPIN) tariff database system, which examination is due to be</p>
<p> completed by 29 February 2000.</p>
<p>A New Zealand proposal to adopt a shared threshold for customs duty on</p>
<p> imports is also being considered by Australia in the context of new tax</p>
<p> system which will be implemented on 1 July 2000.</p>
<p>Oceans management</p>
<p>"New Zealand and Australia will conclude an agreement on the delimitation</p>
<p> of the Australian and New Zealand maritime zones by no later than 2003</p>
<p>  one to three years ahead of our respective deadlines for submissions</p>
<p> on the limits of our continental shelves to the United Nations.</p>
<p>"New Zealand and Australia will continue to work cooperatively in</p>
<p> the development of the Trans-Tasman Understanding on Oceans Policy to</p>
<p> ensure it results in mutual and complementary approaches to the protection</p>
<p> and development or our marine resources.</p>
<p>"Australia will also involve New Zealand in the development of a</p>
<p> Regional Marine Plan for the South-eastern region of Australia's Exclusive</p>
<p> Economic Zone (EEZ) in relation to issues of joint interest."</p>
<p>Maritime delimitation</p>
<p>Both sides plan for substantive bilateral discussions on maritime delimitation</p>
<p> to begin by October 2000, as the first stage of a programme designed to</p>
<p> enable formal bilateral agreement by 2003 as agreed.</p>
<p>Oceans policies</p>
<p>The Australian Government released Australia's Oceans Policy in</p>
<p> December 1998. In October 1999, the New Zealand Government announced that</p>
<p> it will develop an integrated Oceans Policy. New Zealand officials have</p>
<p> begun early work on this, welcoming the useful material contained in the</p>
<p> Australian policy document, and will continue discussions with Australian</p>
<p> counterparts during the development of the policy.</p>
<p>As the New Zealand Oceans Policy is developed, the Trans-Tasman Understanding</p>
<p> on Oceans Planning and Management will, correspondingly, be progressively</p>
<p> developed to ensure complementary approaches to oceans management. The</p>
<p> Understanding will be developed through the Australian and New Zealand</p>
<p> Environment and Conservation Council (ANZECC). Officials from both countries</p>
<p> will continue to work cooperatively during bilateral meetings and in the</p>
<p> margins of multilateral fora to progress the development of the Trans-Tasman</p>
<p> Understanding.</p>
<p>Regional marine plan</p>
<p>Preparations for the development of a regional marine plan for the south-eastern</p>
<p> region of Australia's Exclusive Economic Zone are underway as part of</p>
<p> the three-year A$50 million Oceans Policy programme announced in December</p>
<p> 1998, under the auspices of Australia's National Oceans Ministerial Board</p>
<p> (NOMB). The newly-established National Oceans Office will continue to</p>
<p> develop this plan under direction from the NOMB. New Zealand will be invited</p>
<p> to contribute to the development of the plan through ANZECC and also through</p>
<p> a steering committee to be established by the NOMB.</p>
<p>Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Canberra</p>
<p>Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Wellington</p>
<p>In their Joint Communique of 4 August 1999 the Prime</p>
<p> Ministers of Australia and New Zealand announced that a full review would</p>
<p> be undertaken of bilateral social security arrangements. The following</p>
<p> terms of reference have been agreed prior to the Prime Ministers'</p>
<p> planned March 2000 meeting, in accordance with the terms of the Communique.</p>
<p>Purpose</p>
<p>New Zealand and Australia will seek more stable, durable</p>
<p> and equitable social security arrangements that will provide a better</p>
<p> strategic fit for our wider CER relationship, both now and as it develops</p>
<p> in future years.</p>
<p>To this end New Zealand and Australia will undertake</p>
<p> a full review of social security arrangements between the two countries</p>
<p> with a view to developing a sustainable long-term solution to current</p>
<p> problems.</p>
<p>The review will cover the terms on which each country</p>
<p> will provide access to social security for migrants from the other country</p>
<p> and provide, or contribute to the cost of, social security for migrants</p>
<p> to the other country.</p>
<p>Scope</p>
<p>Australia and New Ze</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
