<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10780</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP                  INTERVIEW WITH MATT PEACOCK,                  AM PROGRAMME, ABC RADIO</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, good news for the Party Room this morning?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There's always good news for our Party Room Matt.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>I understand there's a deal on Wik imminent, is there?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Senator Harradine and I are still in discussion. I'll</p>
<p>   be seeing him again this morning and I've got nothing further</p>
<p>   to say at this time.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But you have made considerable progress. You've been working</p>
<p>   hard in the last week, meeting him...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I've certainly met him a lot, and we've had a lot of</p>
<p>   discussions but I don't have anything to announce at present.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Well there have been consistent arguments by yourself and by the</p>
<p>   Government that Aboriginals shouldn't have greater rights to</p>
<p>   negotiate with miners than say the pastoralists.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Our position has always been that all Australians should be treated</p>
<p>   equally, and that it was a denial of that to have a right to negotiate</p>
<p>   for one section of the community that was denied to others. And</p>
<p>   that's always been our position. As to the details of the discussions</p>
<p>   I don't have anything further to say about it....</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But the boot should be on...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Matt, Matt I have given you my answer, you really are wasting valuable</p>
<p>   seconds by asking me the same question. I'm not going to say</p>
<p>   anything more on this programme.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But just as a matter of principle if pastoralists have the power</p>
<p>   of veto over a mine on their homestead or on their graveyard, for</p>
<p>   example, should Aboriginal people have the same to their equivalent</p>
<p>   sites on that pastoral lease.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Matt.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>No comment at all.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What's the next question?</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Okay, you've said you won't make any concessions, but</p>
<p>   the sunset clause is perhaps negotiable?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Matt, I'm not going to make any further statement on this</p>
<p>   issue. You really are wasting your time and that of the listeners.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, today's news - the polls show a substantial</p>
<p>   fall in support for the Government and One Nation continuing to</p>
<p>   climb. Is National Party Senator Ron Boswell right in saying that</p>
<p>   people don't realise just how extreme this group is?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the poll is entirely predictable. You had an absolute blanket</p>
<p>   of coverage in the news media since the Queensland election about</p>
<p>   One Nation to the exclusion of any dissection of Government policy</p>
<p>   or of the real choice between Labor and the Coalition, and I'm</p>
<p>   not the least bit surprised at this morning's polls, and while</p>
<p>   ever there is a - how shall one put it- a novelty preoccupation</p>
<p>   with One Nation, then everything is seen through the prism of One</p>
<p>   Nation. That will take time to dissipate. Once One Nation is seen</p>
<p>   for what it is, another political party, which has a lack of policy,</p>
<p>   which has differences of opinion on various issues and within its</p>
<p>   own ranks. I believe much of that dissipate. Our task as a Coalition,</p>
<p>   because most of the people who are expressing through the opinion</p>
<p>   polls in the Queensland election support for One Nation, are people</p>
<p>   who would normally vote for the Coalition. Our task of course is</p>
<p>   to regain the confidence of those people, but at the same time to</p>
<p>   point out what they may not be aware of and that is the true impact</p>
<p>   of the policies of One Nation and some of the dangers in those policies,</p>
<p>   particularly the disposition to define people according to their</p>
<p>   racial background which is very damaging, and equally some of the</p>
<p>   very foolish policies that the One Nation Party supports. And I</p>
<p>   think the other thing that we've got to do as a Coalition is</p>
<p>   where the supporters of One Nation have legitimate concerns, we</p>
<p>   ought to point out where we have already addressed those concerns.</p>
<p>   I mean, for example, many of One Nation supporters are concerned</p>
<p>   about such things as work-for-the-dole, now, we've introduced</p>
<p>   that. They are concerned about small business. We've introduced</p>
<p>   laws now blocked in the Senate to reform the unfair, unreasonable,</p>
<p>   Unfair Dismissal laws, which incidentally Mrs Hanson herself did</p>
<p>   not support when it was before the parliament. I think we have a</p>
<p>   task on a number of fronts and we are about doing that.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>All of which takes time. Not a good time to have an election. You</p>
<p>   need surely a couple of months?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The other thing that could be said about the polls in the present</p>
<p>   environment is that they are very volatile. It is in fact six weeks</p>
<p>   ago today that the very same poll that you are asking me about showed</p>
<p>   the Coalition in almost exactly the position it had been in on the</p>
<p>   third of March 1996 when it won a majority of 44 seats. You inevitably</p>
<p>   get a lot of volatility in opinion polls when some atypical event</p>
<p>   such as the arrival of One Nation on the political scene occurs,</p>
<p>   and until people get a proper fix on it, until many of those people</p>
<p>   who might have a transient attraction to One Nation, realise that</p>
<p>   a vote for One Nation could install a Labor Government which is</p>
<p>   not something they want. I think when all of those things are bedded</p>
<p>   down and settled down, people will get a much clearer picture. </p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>So how do you as a politician get a fix on it. You've been</p>
<p>   around this place for a long time. I mean, in some of these seats,</p>
<p>   very safe seats for the Government, for example, it is said they</p>
<p>   are now vulnerable?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, one way you get a fix on it is you don't take fright</p>
<p>   at one or two polls. You understand that these sorts of things have</p>
<p>   happened in slightly different ways, but nonetheless essentially</p>
<p>   before, and if you focus on what I said a moment ago is that where</p>
<p>   One Nation supporters have legitimate concerns you point out where</p>
<p>   the Government has already acted. I mean, for example, the question</p>
<p>   of the English language for migrants - we have already provided</p>
<p>   an extra weighting for people who can speak English but we wouldn't</p>
<p>   go so far as One Nation in saying everybody who comes to this country</p>
<p>   has got to have a knowledge of English before they come, otherwise</p>
<p>   we would deny ourselves some wonderful people. For example, we would</p>
<p>   never have had a man like Arvi Parbo, who ended up becoming Chairman</p>
<p>   of BHP, the big Australian' - he couldn't speak</p>
<p>   a word of English when he came to Australia in the late 1940s. The</p>
<p>   late Victor Chang I understand was born in Shanghai. He came to</p>
<p>   Australia as a small boy. I wonder if he could speak English when</p>
<p>   he arrived in Australia. So if you have that kind of rigid, I think</p>
<p>   quite unfair policy, you are denying Australia people who can make</p>
<p>   a contribution. On the other hand, there is a legitimate need to</p>
<p>   give some kind of margin to people who can speak English and we</p>
<p>   have already done that so this is an area where we have acted on</p>
<p>   the concern of people in the community without going to absurd lengths</p>
<p>   that would actually damage Australia.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you chided Pauline Hanson yesterday in the Parliament</p>
<p>   yesterday for making personal attacks but virtually in the same</p>
<p>   breath you made what appeared to be a personal attack on Helen Sham</p>
<p>   Ho saying that her quitting the Party was an act of sour grapes.</p>
<p>   How do you justify that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I was responding to her criticism of me. I mean she had made</p>
<p>   a very pointed criticism of me and I mean let's just calmly</p>
<p>   recite the facts. Last Friday she said in the New South Wales Parliament</p>
<p>   that she had absolutely no intention of resigning from the Liberal</p>
<p>   Party. That very evening the New South Wales executive of the Liberal</p>
<p>   Party unanimously decided to put One Nation last on every Liberal</p>
<p>   Party how-to-vote card in the forthcoming Federal election. I ask</p>
<p>   what had happened between those two events and yesterday to justify</p>
<p>   her change of mind.....</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Well she said some backbenchers spoke to her and said that the</p>
<p>   mood had changed.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I mean, I will rely on the words of others including members of</p>
<p>   the New South Wales Liberal Party who say that really it was a sense</p>
<p>   of disappointment of not being chosen as the Liberal Party nominee</p>
<p>   for the vacancy in the presidency. I think Mrs Chadwick who was</p>
<p>   chosen is a person of obvious ability. I am rather sorry that Helen</p>
<p>   Sham Ho has left the Liberal Party because the Liberal Party has</p>
<p>   been very good to her. Anybody who is a member of Parliament through</p>
<p>   the sponsorship, as it were, of the political party is in a privileged</p>
<p>   position and I don't think she has repaid the kindness that</p>
<p>   the Liberal Party has displayed towards her.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Do you think she is right in saying that the mood in the Party</p>
<p>   has changed since the Queensland poll?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't. Her claim, I mean just speaking for the Federal</p>
<p>   Parliamentary Party, her claim that in some way she was disadvantaged</p>
<p>   because she is of Asian decent, I don't believe that, I really</p>
<p>   don't. I think that is an unfair thing to say of her former</p>
<p>   colleagues. It's easy to make that sort of remark when you</p>
<p>   are personally disappointed but I really don't believe that</p>
<p>   there is any substance in that and I think given the fact that she</p>
<p>   almost immediately sought and obtained Labor Party support for the</p>
<p>   presidency, that does really diminish the credibility of her attack</p>
<p>   on the Liberal Party and her references to me.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>She has also threatened that she might exhort the Chinese people</p>
<p>   in Australia not to vote for the Coalition. Does that concern you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think what does concern me is the assumption that people</p>
<p>   make that some how or other the so-called ethnic vote is there to</p>
<p>   be commandeered in one or other direction. That's rather patronising</p>
<p>   to Australians of Chinese decent. There are three or four hundred</p>
<p>   thousand Australians of Chinese decent. They are all individual</p>
<p>   men and women. They are not told how to vote by people who appoint</p>
<p>   themselves as leaders of their community, they are individuals.</p>
<p>   I know many of them, I have many of them in my own electorate and</p>
<p>   I can assure you that they are fiercely independent Australians</p>
<p>   like you and I. And the idea that their vote can be directed to</p>
<p>   one or other party by some person who holds himself or herself out</p>
<p>   as being a leader of the community I think is rather patronising</p>
<p>   towards them.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>To go back to Pauline Hanson, didn't she have a point yesterday</p>
<p>   when she said that Aboriginal people get cheap loans in order to</p>
<p>   get their businesses going. Why shouldn't she offer cheap loans?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there are a lot of rural people who under existing policies</p>
<p>   can, in certain circumstances, get subsidised loans. The point I</p>
<p>   was making was that the offer she had made in the Queensland election</p>
<p>   was for a much wider thing and Mr David Etteridge, who is obviously</p>
<p>   a person who exerts enormous influence on her, had acknowledged</p>
<p>   that by saying: well you'd need a lot of money and if you wanted</p>
<p>   a bit more money you'd print it. So it is an entirely different</p>
<p>   situation.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Your Treasurer has been quoted by the Opposition as saying some</p>
<p>   things in politics come before.....or principle comes before politics</p>
<p>   on these issues of, for example, preferences. Do you feel under</p>
<p>   any threat there by Peter Costello's comments?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>In what way?</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>In the sense that he is widely tipped as the heir apparent to your</p>
<p>   job?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>And you think that Mr Costello's stance is okay? I mean, you</p>
<p>   did express irritation when he spoke about the issue of preferences.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you said I did. As far as Mr Costello's position is concerned</p>
<p>   he, like I, recognise that ultimately this matter will be determined</p>
<p>   by the Liberal Party organisation in each State, and so far we have</p>
<p>   had four out of six States. I mean why this preoccupation with the</p>
<p>   time at which each individual State division of the Liberal Party</p>
<p>   makes a decision on preference. I mean four out of the six States</p>
<p>   have already decided to put One Nation last. In the last Queensland</p>
<p>   election the Labor Party directed preferences in 12 seats to the</p>
<p>   Australia First Party whose policies on immigration and so forth</p>
<p>   are exactly the same as One Nation, yet there were no questions</p>
<p>   asked of Mr Beattie or Mr Beazley about that. There seems to be</p>
<p>   a preoccupation with the position of the Liberal Party on this issue.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, one final question. Both you and the Treasurer have</p>
<p>   been analysing the figures on the turbulence in the economy in our</p>
<p>   region. If it comes September and the Parliament is still running,</p>
<p>   how do you think this Government will hold up in terms of its track</p>
<p>   record of economic management if interest rates do go up as a result</p>
<p>   of the Asian crisis?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am not going to talk about interest rates but I am going</p>
<p>   to point out that if we had not got rid of Mr Beazley's $10.5</p>
<p>   billion deficit, if we had not set about getting rid of Mr Beazley's</p>
<p>   legacy of very high debt then this country would now be weaker,</p>
<p>   there would be a lot more economic pain being felt by Australians</p>
<p>   and we'd be far more vulnerable in the eyes of the world. The</p>
<p>   policies that we have undertaken over the last two-and-a-quarter</p>
<p>   years have given this country a level of stability and protection</p>
<p>   that would not have been there if Mr Keating had won the last election.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But could you survive an election.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am not going to start talking about elections. Like any</p>
<p>   other Prime Minister before me I'll have the election at the</p>
<p>   right time for Australia and I am certainly not going to speculate</p>
<p>   about it. But whenever it comes the main issue will be the competence</p>
<p>   of the two opposing sides to manage the Australian economy and Mr</p>
<p>   Beazley and Mr Evans will be asking the Australian people to make</p>
<p>   them respectively Prime Minister and Treasurer. Mr Beazley left</p>
<p>   us the $10.5 billion deficit. Mr Evans has demonstrated a, you know</p>
<p>   to put it at most charitable, a monumental lack of understanding</p>
<p>   of the basics of the Australian economy. I think that will make</p>
<p>   a very, very interesting contrast.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, thanks for joining us.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Pleasure.</p>
<p>[ENDS]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
