<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24577</transcript-id>
    <title>Address to the 58th Federal Council of the Liberal Party of Australia, Melbourne</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/06/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE……………………….……………………………………………………………</p>
<p>Our Party went to the last election with a plan to build a strong, prosperous economy and a safe, secure Australia.</p>
<p>Today, my job is to report to you on our progress and to set out our next steps in achieving this goal.</p>
<p>Our plan means backing hard working Australians to get ahead and to fulfil their dreams.</p>
<p>Our plan is not about us; it’s about you.</p>
<p>It’s about you having more control over your pay packet, more control over your bills and more choice over child care, health care and planning for your own retirement.</p>
<p>It’s about keeping you safe: because that’s more important than anything.</p>
<p>From ‘Menzies’ forgotten people’, to the ‘Howard battlers’ and ‘Tony’s tradies’ – we have always been the party that ‘turned on the lights’; that stood ‘for all of us’; and that seeks ‘hope, reward and opportunity’ for everyone.</p>
<p>Today, I can report to you that our plan is working.</p>
<p>Our plan to grow the economy with lower tax, less red tape, more trade, better infrastructure and stronger borders is working.</p>
<p>Since you elected this government, almost 290,000 new jobs have been created.</p>
<p>Economic growth is now stronger than in most developed nations – and stronger than during the last year of the Rudd Gillard Government.</p>
<p>Company registrations are at record highs because people are ready to have a go when they know that government is on their side.</p>
<p>Export volumes are up, as is residential housing construction and retail sales.</p>
<p>And business confidence continues to strengthen.</p>
<p>Our economy and our country are stronger – despite economic headwinds from the end of the mining investment boom and the low iron ore price.</p>
<p>People might have been a little bit uncertain about us; they always are about new governments – but now they know that we are serious: that our country really is under new management and that Australia really is open for business.</p>
<p>The carbon tax is gone – and everyone is benefiting from lower power prices.</p>
<p>The mining tax is gone – and Australia is once again seen as a good place to invest.</p>
<p>New projects worth over a trillion dollars have received environmental approval – and there is no longer a green veto on development.</p>
<p>50,000 pages of regulation have been scrapped – saving businesses and individuals over $2 billion a year – with much more to come in the months ahead.</p>
<p>Free Trade Agreements with China, Japan and Korea are already creating opportunities for tens of thousands of Australian businesses – and new markets mean new jobs.</p>
<p>Projected long-term debt and deficits have been halved because of the difficult, but necessary decisions we made in Joe Hockey’s first Budget.</p>
<p>The largest Commonwealth-funded infrastructure programme in Australian history is now underway. </p>
<p>We are delivering WestConnex, the Pacific Highway duplication, the Bruce Highway upgrade, the North-South spine in Adelaide, the Midland Highway in Tasmania and major roads throughout Western Australia.</p>
<p>Here in Victoria, there is $3 billion in a locked box waiting for a state government that wants to build the East West Link.</p>
<p>The NBN has passed one million premises and Malcolm Turnbull is turning, another Labor disaster into an asset for Australia.</p>
<p>Most importantly, the Budget is finally on a credible path back to surplus – with the deficit projected to fall by half a per cent of GDP every year. </p>
<p>Already, we have made over $50 billion in savings to help repair the Budget – and the last sitting fortnight has been the most productive since the election.</p>
<p>The parliament has passed legislation to make the age pension more sustainable – with more assistance to 170,000 pensioners with modest assets.</p>
<p>The parliament has passed the instant asset write-off for small business.</p>
<p>The parliament has passed changes to renewable energy to make power more affordable and investment more secure.</p>
<p>The parliament has passed changes to fuel excise and the parliament has passed changes to the PBS.</p>
<p>We’re making the hard decisions so we can make the necessary investments in our country’s future.</p>
<p>For the first time, Northern Australia has a plan for its economic development – including for new dams – because we can't make the most of Australia unless we make the most of our Great North. </p>
<p>We aren’t just improving Australia’s economic security – we are improving our national security as well because a nation’s economic security and its national security go hand in hand. </p>
<p>This government has steadfastly met the challenges of the past 22 months.</p>
<p>We’ve been resolute, determined and have kept the faith.</p>
<p>We’ve stopped the boats – a task that Labor said couldn’t be done – and secured our borders for the first time since the Howard Government. </p>
<p>When 39 Australians were shot out of the sky over Ukraine, our police and armed forces brought our dead home from a war zone. </p>
<p>Our people were superb – and I couldn’t be more proud. </p>
<p>Today, I single out one – my deputy and Foreign Minister, Julie Bishop who criss-crossed the world in the name of justice.</p>
<p>Overnight, we saw again horrors in France, Tunisia and Kuwait.</p>
<p>We are meeting the challenge of the Daesh death cult and the Australians it brainwashes. </p>
<p>Abroad, Australian armed forces are working with a worldwide coalition against a group as evil as any in human history.</p>
<p>At home, we have provided more resources and more powers to our security and intelligence agencies – because they need whatever it takes to keep you safe.</p>
<p>This week, we sent a clear message to those Australians who think they can fight overseas with impunity. <br />
Think again.</p>
<p>We will strip Australian citizenship from terrorists who are dual nationals – because terrorists shouldn’t be walking our streets looking to make our citizens their trophies</p>
<p>Our country is confronting the evil of terrorism – and we are also facing up to the evil of domestic violence. <br />
If there is any place that should be a safe haven – it’s the family home.</p>
<p>There are no excuses for domestic violence. </p>
<p>Former Police Commissioner Ken Lay, and Rosie Batty, are heading up our advisory panel and you’ll soon hear more about how we’ll tackle this national scourge.</p>
<p>Let’s start by making domestic violence orders national, so violent men can’t chase their families across the country.</p>
<p>And let’s expect the perpetrators – and not the victims – to be the ones to leave home.  </p>
<p>Ken Lay is also helping us to beat the scourge of ice – the most dangerous drug of addiction yet seen.<br />
No one should be lost in a world of fear and fantasy in the best country on earth.</p>
<p>In just a few days’ time, Australia will have completed 24 consecutive years of economic growth – only the Netherlands has had a longer run of economic growth.</p>
<p>But we cannot be a country that lives off yesterday’s achievements; we can’t take growth for granted.</p>
<p>The foundation of the next quarter century of prosperity won’t be bigger government, higher taxes or more debt and deficits.</p>
<p>It will be unleashing the entrepreneurs of our country, particularly our small businesses to have a go.</p>
<p>Since the days of the early settlers, through the gold rushes, the wars and successive waves of immigration, Australians have always been willing to work hard, lend a hand to neighbours, make sacrifices for children and look over the horizon to a better future. </p>
<p>That’s the Australian way and they’re the Australians that we want to back.</p>
<p>Every day we are making further progress.</p>
<p>We are working to re-establish a tough cop on the beat in the construction industry to deliver billions of dollars in productivity benefits.</p>
<p>We’ll soon release the Agriculture White Paper and – again – there’ll be more money for dams because you can’t grow things without water.</p>
<p>We’ll soon respond to the Harper Competition Review and the Murray Review into the Financial System – because we want all parts of our economy growing strongly.</p>
<p>By the end of the year, we’ll release Australia’s first ever 15 year plan for infrastructure to get more bulldozers on the ground and cranes in the sky.</p>
<p>Work is underway eliminating thousands of mobile phone black spots in regional areas.</p>
<p>Thousands of young people have already been in the Green Army in hundreds of projects to clean up our lands and waterways – and there’ll be tens of thousands more.</p>
<p>We want to support hard working Australians – especially parents who want work or who want more work.</p>
<p>Our Budget childcare measures should encourage more than 240,000 families to earn more, including almost 38,000 jobless families. </p>
<p>Low and middle income families using childcare will be $1,500 a year better off even before they earn more.<br />
I have said what we will do – let me also tell you what we won’t do.</p>
<p>We won’t increase taxes on superannuation or increase the restrictions on superannuation because your retirement savings belong to you and not the government.</p>
<p>We won’t change the rules on negative gearing because Australians have made decisions based on the rules as they stand – and the last time a government fiddled with negative gearing it caused a crisis in the rental market.</p>
<p>And we won’t be putting a tax on electricity because there are smarter ways of reducing emissions than whacking everyone with a new carbon tax.<br />
For over seventy years, the Liberal Party has built modern Australia – not on ideology, but on backing hard working Australians – people prepared to have a go.</p>
<p>If you’re a young Australian looking for a good job and working for a deposit on your first home – we’re for you.</p>
<p>If you’re a small business person who wants to employ people – we’re for you.</p>
<p>If you’re a young parent trying to balance work and family – we’re for you.</p>
<p>If you’re a migrant who came the right way to build a better life for your children – we’re for you.</p>
<p>If you want to spend less time stuck in traffic to get to work or to pick up your kids – we’re for you.</p>
<p>If you’re working more to get ahead and to provide the best opportunities for your children – we’re for you.</p>
<p>If you believe superannuation is your money and want certainty in retirement – we’re for you.</p>
<p>If you’re on the land despite the ravages of drought – we’re for you.</p>
<p>I should ask: who’s Labor for these days?</p>
<p>I guess the ‘Killing Season’ answered that: they’re for themselves.</p>
<p>They’re the party that promised to be like John Howard, but weren’t.</p>
<p>They’re the party that promised us they wouldn’t restart the boats, but did.</p>
<p>They’re the party that promised surpluses, but delivered record debt and deficits.</p>
<p>They’re the party that said no carbon tax, but gave us one anyway.</p>
<p>The guilty party has not changed.</p>
<p>Almost two years into this term, they still want a carbon tax; they still have no policies to stop the boats and they’re still addicted to taxes and spending.</p>
<p>The choice is clear.</p>
<p>They’re for boats, we’re for none.</p>
<p>They’re for a carbon tax, we’re for lower tax.</p>
<p>They’re for taxes, we’re for jobs.</p>
<p>They do union bidding.</p>
<p>We stand for all of us.</p>
<p>Now I have to confess, I did sneak a peak at that ABC series The Killing Season. </p>
<p>The one thing that Kevin Rudd and Julia Gillard could agree on was: you can’t trust Bill Shorten.</p>
<p>If Julia Gillard and Kevin Rudd don’t trust Bill Shorten, why should you?</p>
<p>If the workers of the AWU couldn’t trust Bill Shorten, why should you?</p>
<p>Only the Liberal party and our National Party colleagues can be trusted to build a strong, prosperous economy and a safe, secure Australia.</p>
<p>It’s built by people who believe in our country and who believe that our best days are ahead of us.</p>
<p>When the history books are written, they will recognise my friend, and our Deputy Prime Minister, Warren<br />
Truss as one of the great leaders of this government.</p>
<p>I can report to you that our Coalition is strong. I can report to you that our party organisation, so well led by President Richard Alston is strong.</p>
<p>Our secretariat, led by Brian Loughnane and supported by our state directors, is the most professional political organisation in the country.</p>
<p>But our greatest strength is not our leadership, it’s our membership.</p>
<p>Our party has been built by hundreds of thousands of men and women from all walks of life, from every nook and cranny under the Southern Cross.</p>
<p>We believe in family, in community and that our nation’s greatest achievements come when our people are encouraged to have a go.</p>
<p>We reflect the length and breadth of Australian life: young and old, rich and poor, farmer and suburbanite, indigenous and immigrant, tradies and nurses.</p>
<p>Our party does not demand blind obedience.  We respect differences – because discussing them is how we come closer to wisdom.</p>
<p>We are a party that honours our history – it’s the foundation we build on.  It’s why we are proud to be the heirs of Menzies, Holt, Gorton, McMahon, Fraser and Howard. </p>
<p>In honouring our history, we remember the good government that Malcolm Fraser led. </p>
<p>He turned on the lights and we’re grateful.</p>
<p>But, today we’re focused on the future.</p>
<p>We’re making our country safer and more prosperous for everyone.</p>
<p>We’re the optimists of Australian life.</p>
<p>We’re yearning and striving to build a better Australia, leaving our children more than we ever hoped for.</p>
<p>That’s our task; that’s our mission and, for our country’s sake, we will succeed.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
