<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4146</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE MINISTER FOR HEALTH - MEDIBANK (PRIVATE INSURANCE)</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004146.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Io<br />
F76/ 11S5t<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 8 JUNE 1976<br />
JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE<br />
MINISTER FOR HEALTH--MEDIBANK ( PRIVATE INSURANCE)<br />
The Prime Minister and the Minister for Health today<br />
, announced the Cabinet decision that Medibank will now<br />
be permitted to offer intermediate and private ward cover<br />
for those people who wish to take out total cover with<br />
Medibank. This means that in the intermediate and private ward area<br />
Medibank will be able to compete on equal terms with<br />
private funds.<br />
The Prime Minister and the Minister for Health forecast<br />
several days ago that Medibank could enter the private<br />
health insurance field to give every Australia a positive<br />
choice of remaining in Medibank either for standard,<br />
intermediate or private ward accommodation.<br />
The Government has decided to give authority to Medibank<br />
so that it can operate as a private insurer in fair<br />
competition with other registered organisations.<br />
Medibank ( Private Insurance) operations will be managed<br />
on a financially viable and separate basis from its<br />
other operaiecins.<br />
While it is planned that Medibank ( Private Insurance) will<br />
make use of existing administrative facilities these will<br />
be costed and appropriate means will be established to<br />
separate these costs. Separate accounts under statutory<br />
requirements, will be kept for these operations of<br />
Medibank. Medibank ( Private Insurance) will be required to comply fully<br />
with the provisions of a National Health Act including<br />
details of registration.<br />
' The Government is : determined to ensure that Medibank remains<br />
available to every Australian. This will enable full-and<br />
open competition between Medibank and the private funds.<br />
That competition will do much to cut down the total cost<br />
of health care. / 2 </p>
<p>The Government by this measure, is giving the widest<br />
possible area of choice and nobody is being forced<br />
out of Medibank.<br />
As a registered organisation, Medibank ( Private<br />
Insurance) will operate basic medical and hospital<br />
benefit tables. These tables will provide private<br />
and intermediate ward cover in public and private<br />
. hospitals and will exempt people from the 2 levy payment. 0 0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
