<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9919</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP MURRAY-DARLING BASIN</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009919.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
MURRAY-DARLING BASIN<br />
Mr Howard's claim to ownership of the sustainable<br />
agriculture/ landcare/ Murray-Darling Basin agenda is a sure sign that once<br />
again, the Coalition is struggling to put together anything credible in a key<br />
policy area.<br />
If you can't develop a decent policy of your own, just claim that someone who<br />
can has stotlen yours.<br />
Mr Howard must have been hoping that everyone else h ad been asleep just<br />
like him until late 1995 when he first discovered the Murray-Darling Basin or<br />
that no one had kept any records.<br />
Unfortunately, the rest of us have been aware of the Murray Darling and<br />
land degradation and the potential of food exports to Asia for quite some<br />
time and actually doing something about it as the attached records shows.<br />
Unlike Mr Howard, Labor has an unparalleled record of achievements on<br />
Landcare, and the Murray -Darling. We don't need to go scratching around in<br />
the empty Coalition policy cupboard for a good idea.<br />
The record speaks for itself.<br />
CANBERRA January 1996 6/ 96 </p>
<p>Some Key Dates<br />
1788-1983: Years of neglect.<br />
1983 Labor Government establishes a Commonwealth/ State<br />
taskforce for drought management. The results included the<br />
removal of fodder subsidies which exacerbate land degradation<br />
by encouraging overstocking during drought.<br />
1983 Removal of tax incentives for land clearing by Treasurer<br />
Keating<br />
1983 Establishment of the National Soil Conservation Program<br />
( NSCP)<br />
1988 Establishment of the Murray Darling Basin Commission and<br />
Ministerial Council.<br />
1988 Commonwealth and States develop and endorse the National<br />
Soil Conservation Strategy.<br />
1988 Establishment of the Community Landcare component of the<br />
NSCP.<br />
1989 The launch of the Decade of Landcare with funding of $ 320<br />
million over ten years<br />
1990 Establishment of the Land and Water Research and<br />
Development Corporation<br />
1990 National Drought Policy which for the first time ensured that<br />
drought assistance took proper regard for environmental<br />
factors.<br />
July 1992<br />
Aug 1992<br />
Dec 1992 Establishment of the Agri-Food Council with its goal to increase<br />
high value-added food exports to more than $ 7 billion per year<br />
by the end of the decade.<br />
Establishment of the Agriculture and Resource Management<br />
Council of Australia and New Zealand ( ARMCANZ) with the<br />
objective of developing integrated and sustainable and natural<br />
resource management policies and practices.<br />
Prime Ministers Environment Statement incorporating a<br />
substantial increases in funding for native vegetation, inland<br />
rivers and land and water management. </p>
<p>1993-1995<br />
June 1994<br />
Nov 1994<br />
June 1995<br />
Sept 1995 Prime Minister has numerous visits to regional Australia to<br />
discuss the drought and the state of our natural resources.<br />
Prime Minister's Science and Engineering Council discusses its<br />
report " Food into Asia: The Next Steps"<br />
Establishment of the Prime Minister's Land Management<br />
Taskforce Prime Minister's Science and Engineering Council discusses its<br />
report " Sustaining the Agricultural Resource Base."<br />
Prime Minister during a visit to Orange announces an inquiry<br />
into " Removing Impediments to the Export of Perishable<br />
Produce."<br />
Oct 1995 Prime Minister meets with Industry Leaders in Canberra to<br />
discuss agriculture and our food industries.<br />
Oct 1995 Prime Minister receives the report of the Land Management<br />
. Taskforce during a visit to Eyre Peninsula.<br />
John Howard's Record<br />
1974-1994<br />
Jan 1995 Years of neglect.<br />
Ian McLachlan's pamphlet " A Clean Australia" is released with<br />
unfunded commitments of between $ 5 billion and $ 15 billion.<br />
Key elements are quickly disowned by the Leader of the<br />
National Party, other coalition members, the NFF and others in<br />
industry.<br />
Oct 1995 John Howard expresses general support, but with no details, for<br />
the rehabilitation of the Murray Darling system.<br />
Jan 1996The nation continues to await details of John Howard's support<br />
for the environment and agriculture. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
