<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10781</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP                 DOORSTOP INTERVIEW &amp;#150; JONDARYAN, OAKEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/05/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.........................................................................................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think some political commentators ought to take a reality check.</p>
<p> There's only one choice. You either have Rob Borbidge as Premier</p>
<p> of Queensland or Peter Beattie. And it is very easy when you have</p>
<p> no hope of winning to sort of make all sorts of promises, and offer</p>
<p> all sorts of inducements and I would say to the people of Queensland,</p>
<p> the choice is between Rob Borbidge and Peter Beattie and between no</p>
<p> other two people and that is what should, in my view, determine how</p>
<p> people vote.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you surprised they're polling so well?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Election campaigns are about communicating messages between the public</p>
<p> and political leaders and the message that I address to people who</p>
<p> might be thinking of voting for a minority party is that it is very</p>
<p> easy when you have no hope of winning to promise the earth and offer</p>
<p> simplistic solutions, and that the real choice is between a Borbidge</p>
<p> led Coalition Government or a Government led by Mr Beattie of the</p>
<p> Labor Party. And that's the message that I communicate and the</p>
<p> message that I respectfully put to the people of Queensland.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: (inaudible)</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, look I didn't hear either of those questions. I dare say</p>
<p> that one of you will cede to the other.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You said a while ago Pauline Hanson was simply a transitory phenomena,</p>
<p> and by the next election people will have seen through her and she'll</p>
<p> disappear. That hasn't happened has it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There'll be a poll on the thirteen of June and, as always in</p>
<p> these things, the public will decide and not the noise of commentators</p>
<p> or the noise of anybody else.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What's your expectation Mr Howard?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>My expectation is that Mr Borbidge will be the Premier of Queensland</p>
<p> and he will have my total support and he deserves to be the Premier</p>
<p> of Queensland. I've found in my own dealings with him that he's</p>
<p> a great fighter for Queensland, and on the Native Title legislation</p>
<p> for example, Mr Borbidge has stood up for the interests of Queensland,</p>
<p> Mr Beattie has sold out the interests of Queensland by opposing a</p>
<p> resolution of the Native Title issue.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>And what will it mean for Queensland if One Nation does hold the balance</p>
<p> of power?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't believe that the result will be other than a National</p>
<p> Party win, but like all election campaigns you've got to work</p>
<p> hard, you've got to talk to people, you don't scream abuse</p>
<p> at electors, you talk to people, you explain the advantages of returning</p>
<p> a Coalition Government and you point out the simplistic solutions</p>
<p> of minority parties. It is very easy for minority parties, if I may</p>
<p> finish, it is very easy for minority parties to offer simplistic solutions,</p>
<p> when they have no realistic prospect of implementing their solutions.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If that situation eventuated though, it would be bad for Queensland,</p>
<p> wouldn't it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it would be very bad for Queensland if Mr Borbidge is not the</p>
<p> Premier after the thirteenth of June, very bad indeed. Thank you.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, is Ian Macfarlane Ministerial material?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Mr Macfarlane is a very fine candidate and I'm very proud to</p>
<p> have him as the Liberal candidate for Groom.</p>
<p>ENDS</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
