<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5801</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH TO THE &#039;LIBERALISE NEW SOUTH WALES&#039; LUNCHEON</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/04/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005801.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AS DELIVERED<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 23 APRIL 1982<br />
SPEECH TO THE " LIBERALISE NEW SOUTH WALES" LUNCHEON'<br />
In times of world uncertainty and economic challenge, people<br />
want to know what a party stands for, the faith it lives by,<br />
and the-direction of its policies. People want dedication<br />
and effectiveness from Government. I don't want glossy<br />
facades, or running away from facts. This makes the campaign<br />
to !' Liberalise New South Wales" all the more important, all the = rre<br />
relevant and it is certainly very timely indeed, for it will carry the<br />
message of what we are doing and where we are going.<br />
our task as the Liberal Party is to keep building a great and<br />
prosperous Australia, to encourage pride in Australia and<br />
confidence among Australians, to increase opportunities so<br />
people can create the way of life they want. for themselves. When we look<br />
at Australia's present position and prospects, there are<br />
two things that stand out, the strengths of our economy, ' and the<br />
damage that sect~ ions or groups sometimes do to Australia. Whi we uniderstand the<br />
real strengths of theAustralian economy, our initiative and<br />
enterprise, our abundant resources, our capacity to find<br />
export markets for our products, our investment, the growth in this<br />
economy, it is impossible to understand how th unbalanced<br />
stories of total gloom that we have read in recent weeks or months ever<br />
get written, ever found their way into any part of the media.<br />
Our greatest strength of. all, the one which underpins all the<br />
rest, is the capacity of Auseralians to keep building<br />
Australia up, and the capacity of Liberal Governments to provide<br />
the conditions in which they can do so. Building Australia<br />
up has always come high indeed on the Liberal Party's agenda,<br />
and it always will. over three-decades of Liberal government<br />
the living standards of Australian families have more than doubled.<br />
and the lifestyle of the average Australian family today bears<br />
no comparison with that of 30 or 40 years ago. It is not<br />
governments Ithat have done this, it is the capacity, the energies<br />
of Australians in every part of this country, but it is Liberalgovernments<br />
for the most part that have established the policies<br />
that have made it possible and that have unleashed the energies<br />
and imaginations of Australians. None of this<br />
of course happens by chance, it has happened because we have<br />
given people room to strive for their desi~ res, room to use<br />
their initiative. It has happened because' we have encouraged<br />
achievement and excellence. As a result people throughout<br />
this nation hEive energy and ability to keep building Australia<br />
and that is the real key to all our strengths.<br />
Through the initiative and enterprise of Australian people,<br />
we have built a strong manufacturing base; we have efficient<br />
primary industry; we have developed the resources; including L # 4 1<br />
/ 2 A </p>
<p>ed -2-<br />
the abundant energy resources, that we have had the good fortune<br />
to be given, ' ardwe have developed the export markets that<br />
are so important to our continuing growth and prosperity.<br />
Through the policies we have applied -for the last six years we h.' ave<br />
created Igrowth substantially in excess of the average<br />
among our majorc trading partners. Would there be anyone here<br />
who would trad2 the policies of this Government and the<br />
achievements of Australia over the last six years for the<br />
policies or the achievements of any other advanced industrial<br />
country anywhere in the world? Private enterprise<br />
under our policies has created hundreds of new jobs<br />
when in some other countries, in the United Kingdom, in<br />
Germany and in France employment has actually declined. You<br />
would have seen the reports in at least one of the journals<br />
this morning, indicating a very significant down turn in the<br />
United States economy.<br />
Above all, we ihave business investment which last year grew<br />
Sat its strongest rate for 30 years, and which is continuing<br />
V strongly this year, not only in the mining industry b * ut throughout<br />
the Australian ecxxonmy. The absurd talk of recent days about the<br />
investment upsuarge petering out totally overlooks the fact that<br />
new investment in this country continues at a high level, while<br />
it is stagnant or declining in other countries. Ongoing<br />
investment is -the lifeblood of Australia's future prosperity.<br />
It is keeping -as growing, if more slowly -than we -would have liked,<br />
and it has* provided 1 he new plant, the new factories, the<br />
mines, the smelters that we need to take full advantage of 4ny<br />
recovery in world trade. When there is an upturn, . as one day,<br />
one month there, must be in the United States and in Europe,<br />
Australia as a result of the investment that has taken place<br />
will be better placed than any other country around the<br />
world to take advantage of that upturn.<br />
While investment is strong as it is, there is underlying<br />
strength in the economy, there is confidence in the future<br />
and a basis forc ongoing growth and improvements in the living<br />
U standards of Australian families. It is economic growth.<br />
The real income increases that growth makes possible, that do<br />
far more to raise general living standards than any tax cut<br />
or public spending program can ever do and I hope no journalist<br />
turns that around into a headline that says Fraser says never<br />
a tax cut ever again. Well it would be quite possible and<br />
not necessarily much worse than some of the things that have<br />
happened. While investmenat is strong, as it is there is<br />
underlying strength in the economy; there is confidence in<br />
the future; there is a basis for ongoing growth. And it is<br />
economic growath, and real income increases that it makes<br />
possible, : that do far more to raise general living standards<br />
than any tax cut or public spending program can ever do.<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
But while our continuing investment, our continuing growth,<br />
indeed all of our strengths, are a source of satisfaction and confidence<br />
Australians have also exhibited a remarkable capacity to do<br />
damage to ' Australia, to Australian prospects and Australian prosperity.<br />
Through strikes, needless disputes, and unrealistic wage<br />
demands, through bad planning and mismanagement, through<br />
faihures to realistically assess Australia's situation,<br />
and through the attitudes brought to so many aspect * s of<br />
. our activities, many people undermine the advantages we have, not<br />
intentionally, and maybe unwittingly, but nevertheless it happens.<br />
Domestic wage anid price pressures, industrial disruption, andthe<br />
sheer mismanagement of some state governments, constitute<br />
a serious threat: to our competitiveness and our growth. The<br />
worst of it is that the effects of these domestic factors<br />
will not simply fade-away with the passage of time. For our<br />
costs and prices are being pushed up at the very time costs<br />
and prices are * Ealling among our trade competitors,<br />
and albeit falling because there is very severe recession<br />
and because of much higher unemployment than there is here,<br />
working people in the United States and in some places in<br />
Europe have been accepting real reductions in their wages.<br />
They would sooner that in-the hope that they could keep jobs<br />
and sell American and European goods. And, at the same<br />
as the world overseas is becoming more competitive,<br />
our reputation as a reliable suppliersto overseas<br />
* markets is being undermined by supply constraints and industrial<br />
disputes. The case of coal exports from New South Wales provides a<br />
particularly disturbing. example. . This great industry has been<br />
plagued by strikes and stoppages. One strike by the miners led<br />
Mr Wran to concede a $ 63 per week wage rise, which has obviously<br />
flowed through the whole industry, about $ 120 a week with<br />
overtime and other benefits that are built in, added on<br />
and that adds up to about $ 4 a tonne to production costs.<br />
H -ow hard our exporters-have to fight sometimes to negotiate<br />
Wa price increase from purchasers overseas of an equivalent.<br />
In present world circumstances it is not easy<br />
to achieve that. IThis comes on top of a chaotic<br />
situation in the ports where most ships have experienced great<br />
delays, 36 days has been normal in Newcastle, and 90 days is not<br />
unknown, partly due to strikes and partly due to poor planning<br />
of port facilities.<br />
The chronic shortage of coal loading capacity in New South Wales'<br />
ports arises directly from mismanagement of the Government, for<br />
it has delayed a decision whether to construct a new loader<br />
in Botany Bay, eventually decided to expand capacity at Port<br />
Kembla instead and to upgrade the Balmain loader as a transitional<br />
arrangement, but fell two years behind in meeting that commitment,<br />
hardly an example of good management. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
As a result, companies which had made contractual arrangements in<br />
the expectation that capacity would be in place, find themselves<br />
with delays and congestion, unable to deliver. This has led to<br />
the absurd situa-: ion of self-imposed quotas on our ' own exports of<br />
coal. We grumble enough when we get quotas against our products<br />
into markets in Europe, Japan or the United St'ates, but this is<br />
a quota placed on our export as a result of bungle and mismanagement<br />
and should never have occurred. There is not the slightest excuse<br />
for it, in any sense at all. The cost of the delays to ships<br />
in New South Wales was estimated at $ 60 million last year, and<br />
export shortfalls have occurred worth nearly $ 200 million in exportearnings.<br />
Quite plainly, when people contract to deliver coal<br />
to a power authority in January and it does not get delivered<br />
until April, Aus-zralia' s reputation is severely damaged. That<br />
reputation is no-: just restricted to coal, it tends to flow<br />
through to other aspects of Australian life.<br />
It is worth I th.* Lnk, making a comparison of what has happened in<br />
Sthe same industry in Queensland, because there ships rarely have<br />
Wto wait, more than 3 days. Queensland has co-ordinated<br />
effectively the expansion of its port capacity with its export<br />
needs. But while this is obviously a dramatic example of what<br />
has happened in New South Wales. It captures the essence of<br />
problems that are encountered to a differing degree throughout<br />
other aspects of the Australian economy.<br />
While some unions are reasonable in their wage expectations<br />
and demands, how often are we confronted with unions who want to<br />
grab the benef its of growth before that growth has even occurred,<br />
and how demand higher incomes, shorter horus and less work at a<br />
time when in other parts of the world employees are offering to<br />
work harder for less, because they know that is the only way they<br />
are going to have any work at-all and in recognition of the<br />
realities of difficult economic ( circumstances. Nothing<br />
government can do can offer to people benefits nearly as large as<br />
they can obtain from sustained soundly based growth and<br />
expanding employment opportunities, because it is upon that<br />
the living standards of Australian families depends, it is upon<br />
Wthat that governments themselves get the resources to provide<br />
other needs, and other services that people expect of us in<br />
Government. Nothing will des-troy the prospects oll a better life more surely<br />
than demands for wages greater the economy has the capacity to<br />
provide, especially in current world circumstances.<br />
While some companiies and senior. executives, and indeed, I believe<br />
a growing number, attempt to develop good relations with their<br />
employees, how often are we confronted with costly strikes that<br />
would really seem to be unnecessary, and with employers who take<br />
the view that it is up to governments to sort out the industrial<br />
relations problems. How often have I, or I suppose John Howard<br />
or others of us a-ere , been tackled and asked what is the Government<br />
going to do about it? We can provide a framework of institutions<br />
and awards that ' hopefully can facilitate good industrial relations </p>
<p>and legislation now before the Parliament I believe will help<br />
very significantly in that regard providing the legislation<br />
is used once it is in place. Whether it is used or not will<br />
to a significant extent depend upon management courage in<br />
its use. The Government cannot conduct industrial relations on<br />
behalf of firms, for in the end industrial relations are<br />
relations between people in their own working environment.<br />
While some firms firmly face up to wage demands that they know<br />
they don't have the capacity to meet, how many others find<br />
it difficult to do that, Hlow many others maybe give in and hope<br />
that the Government will ultimately give in too because that<br />
might seem to be the easiest way out and expand the money<br />
supply and in~ crease protection to accommodate the resulting<br />
increased costs and prices. But while firm money supply<br />
control can be painful, it is the weapon we have to use against<br />
the sorts of pressures that can otherwise lead to<br />
economic ruin if they were left unchedked. While some firms<br />
are prepared to invest, to restructure, to go out and look<br />
aggressively look for markets, even in the most difficult of<br />
circumstances,, how many other others may look for higher<br />
protection to see them through' more difficult times.<br />
We all know t~ hat higher protection is not the way to improve<br />
productivity, to improve profitability. The record does show<br />
that higher p rotection is the path that leads to a more<br />
permanent dependence on government assistance of one kind<br />
or another and to a loss of real income by society as a whole.<br />
In the end it: all comes down to the attitudes that we all<br />
have, our obligations to Australia and what we want to do<br />
about it.<br />
In many ways I think-sometimes we are our own worst enemies.<br />
Too often people fail to assess what is happening realistically<br />
and sensibl. y. People are influenced in this perhaps by<br />
frequent extremism in reporting. Last year we were told<br />
very often that the sky is the limit, there is a resources<br />
boom and I am not trying to suggest that the Government was<br />
not saying that things were good through that good, of<br />
course we we were, but the headline places an extremist<br />
view on it. Then one or two unfavourable indicators coming<br />
through the summer months and suddenly all was gloom. The<br />
future had completely disappeared and the truth of course<br />
was never that.<br />
I don't think any government, any country would ever be in<br />
a time when there are not some economic problems that have<br />
to be grappled with because there are always wants, always<br />
unfilled needs and decisions, often difficult ones, have to<br />
be made. Quite certainly, the optimism of some reporting<br />
last year, the extremism of reporting in the first few months<br />
of this year, the suggestion that inflation was quite out of<br />
control as a result of one dip in the figures last December<br />
are of course doing no good to this economy and confidence<br />
in this economy at all. / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
I hope the figure that came out yesterday of a very good<br />
CPI result will jerk people back to a sense of reality that<br />
there are basic strengths in Australia that we need to<br />
understand arid they don't just disappear because you get one<br />
or two indicators that seem to be unfavourable.<br />
This sort of thing does not only happen in economic reporting,<br />
it happens in political reporting. What with the doom and<br />
disaster for me and the Federal Government as a result of<br />
an 8% swing in Lowe and a swing double that in Drummoyne<br />
and people try to suggest that it has not happened. Well<br />
Drummoyne was as big as Bass and Lowe was half of Bass and<br />
so Mr Wran should take note of that.<br />
Lack of balance, which gets presented to us so often, and<br />
often daily must disturb people quite significantly. It does<br />
have an unwarranted, but real impact on people's expectations<br />
upon their outlooks, upon their hopes for the future, on<br />
their belief in what is possible and in that way makes ~ It<br />
harder for people in businesses to make sound judgements on<br />
some important decisions.<br />
There are of course, significant difficulties ahead, none of<br />
us have tried to hide that, some of which Australians have<br />
tended to create, or make worse themselves and some of which<br />
are created by very difficult conditions in the rest of the<br />
world, but ini a very important sense indeed our own future<br />
is in our own hands. Given the capacity, the resources and<br />
the strengths that Australia has, if we take a realistic<br />
view of our circumstances, we tailor our demands and our<br />
expectations for the realities that we face, if we continue<br />
to apply broadly the policies that we have and that are right<br />
for Australia, then the prospects and the possibilities for<br />
this country are I believe very great indeed, and I would not<br />
change those prospects for the prospects and futures of any<br />
other advanced industrial country anywhere around the world.<br />
It is against this background that the campaign that John<br />
Valder is leading to put things right and to help. with the<br />
rest of the division and parliamentarians to put things<br />
right in the State of NSW is so vastly important because<br />
to Liberalise this state with its industrial strength, with<br />
its great primary industries, with the energies and initiatives<br />
of the people, it cannot afford any more of the bungling.<br />
mismanagement and whatever. Whatever words one wants to use<br />
about recent events in this State, this State cannot afford<br />
these things any more. The administration needs cleaning<br />
up, the policies need putting right and efficiency needs<br />
bringing to bear on government in this State. Because there<br />
has just been an election, it is a long and it is a hard<br />
road ahead and the division realises that and John Valder<br />
realises that but it is going to need the support of all of<br />
you and the.: support of some thousands of other places right<br />
across the State to open the doors whenever the next election<br />
is held. It maybe if some things develop that election might<br />
be forced around earlier than would otherwise be because<br />
things are sick at the heart of this administration in NSW.<br />
Thank you John Valder for what you are seeking to do for the<br />
Liberal Party and for the State of NSW.<br />
oO </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
