<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7849</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER NATIONAL PRESS CLUB CANBERRA - 7 DECEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/12/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007849.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINT DELIVERY EMAGOED UNTIL. DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
NATIONAL PRESS CLUB<br />
CANBERRA 7 DECEMBER 1989<br />
A 60th birthday is not the occasion for a policy<br />
statement from me.<br />
But like turning 21, or 40, turning 60 is a landmark at<br />
which it is permissible to engage in some personal<br />
reflection. And when half of those 60 years have been<br />
spent in public life it is natural that such reflections<br />
should traverse public matters including, to put it<br />
quite frankly, my hopes for my children and my<br />
grandchildren not just as family but as citizens of the<br />
Australia of the future.<br />
It is of this future that I wish predominantly to speak.<br />
But we are, each one of us, the product of our history.<br />
And therefore if I am to speak meaningfully of my vision<br />
of the future and how my Government has been laying the<br />
path to that future I must, briefly, allude to the<br />
history of my own time and experience.<br />
Let me take four precisely divided points in my own life<br />
to indicate how my outlook has been shaped.<br />
19i29, the year I was born, was the mid-point between the<br />
two great wars of this century. It was the eve of the<br />
Great Depression. Mankind was dramatically, tragically,<br />
demonstrating its incapacity to handle economic and<br />
political relationships within nations and between<br />
nations. ' The war to end wars' was coming to be seen to have<br />
taught us nothing. An increasing economic autarky was<br />
inexorably laying the grounds for the devastation of 1939<br />
and the next five years.<br />
The great paradox of the twentieth century was beginning<br />
to emerge the enormous gulf between the human genius<br />
for scientific and technological advancement and our<br />
backwardness as social and political engineers. </p>
<p>This paradox was reflected at the end of the Pacific war<br />
in the classic dilemma of harnessing and controlling the<br />
power of the atom, a dilemma which has haunted us for the<br />
rest of the century.<br />
1949 was a seminal point in Australian history. Australia<br />
turned back to the conservatives after Labor's leadership<br />
in the war and in post-war reconstruction. There followed<br />
the generation of lost opportunities the opportunity to<br />
restructure and make more competitive the Australian<br />
economy, the opportunity within a commitment to the<br />
Western Alliance to forge a position of independent<br />
relevance in the international arena in general and our<br />
region in particular.<br />
And frankly, the Labor Party must accept some<br />
responsibility for this generation of lost opportunity.<br />
Our preoccupations with our internecine conflicts<br />
understandably led the electorate to conclude that if we<br />
could not govern ourselves we were not ready to govern<br />
the nation.<br />
1969 was a significant year for me, being elected<br />
President of the ACTU. We were still in the mire of<br />
Vietnam where a conservative Government reflected abroad<br />
the lack of understanding of historical realities and the<br />
confrontationism it exhibited at home.<br />
It was to be the decade of the successive oil price<br />
shocks which, together with other factors, changed the<br />
world economic environment.<br />
It was for me a decade in which I was given a unique<br />
opportunity to understand the Australian economy the<br />
trade union movement, the business sector, and a range of<br />
community organisations. I learned about its domestic and<br />
international dimensions in a thoroughly practical way. I<br />
learned the art of conciliation and industrial dispute<br />
resolution. This led me to say in my 1975 Presidential Address to the<br />
ACTU Congress, in the context of pointing to a<br />
significant shift from profits to wages:<br />
" The indisputable facts are that a continuation of<br />
recent trends in the division of national income<br />
would mean that Australian workers would have less<br />
opportunities to obtain employment and would pay<br />
very much more for those things with which to<br />
sustain themselves and their families. It is<br />
essential that the self-interest of particular<br />
groups be balanced against the interests of workers<br />
as a whole. </p>
<p>So that was 1929, 1949 and 1969. And here we are at the<br />
end of 1989 on the threshold of the last decade of this<br />
twentieth century. This Australia, this region, this<br />
world are almost unrecognisably different from that<br />
Australia, that region, that world into which I was born.<br />
It is the convictions born of my experience in this<br />
period of the most dynamic change in human history that<br />
have shaped my approach to government and my aspirations<br />
for Australia.<br />
And as we approach the next century what I want to see is<br />
the evolution of an Australia attuned to and conscious of<br />
this tremendous change an Australia with several<br />
distinctive, deeply interrelated characteristics.<br />
First, I want to see us become a modern, growing<br />
Australian economy, shaken out of the old complacent<br />
dependence on commodity exports, re-equipped and<br />
restructured in its attitudes, institutions and<br />
technology to be fully competitive in the world.<br />
Second, I want an Australia self confidently and<br />
vigorously engaged with the world economy, and in.<br />
particular enmeshed with the dynamism of Asia and the<br />
Pacific an outward looking country capable of<br />
contributing to and drawing enduring prosperity from the<br />
region a country which others wish to have as a partner<br />
because they see that we have got our own act together<br />
and are able to contribute.<br />
Third, I want an Australia committed to maintaining and<br />
enhancing the quality of life, not merely the quantity of<br />
our economic output. We must not be panicked into a<br />
strategy of industrialisation at any cost. We must<br />
enlarge our commitment to social justice; to the<br />
preservation of our natural environment; to the creation<br />
of a tolerant, multicultural, egalitarian society a<br />
society immensely vigorous because of its diversity yet<br />
uniquely harmonious because of the deep and genuine<br />
mutual respect each component group holds for all others.<br />
And fourth I want a self-reliant Australia, drawing<br />
strength from its traditional attachments to other<br />
countries but attuned to and pursuing in a hard headed<br />
way its own interests in a changing World; speaking with<br />
an independent voice; not merely fitting in with the<br />
world as we find it but helping shape it.<br />
There is no final destination to this journey no point<br />
at which we will be able to say, " There, we have done<br />
it". It is a national commitment to a fundamental and<br />
continuing prrag of modernisation guided by these four<br />
goals that I seek.<br />
I am perfectly open to debate about the pace of the<br />
change but I shall fiercely resist developments that<br />
would take the vital process backwards. </p>
<p>That is why when the Opposition would scrap the capital<br />
gains tax, far more is at stake than some esoteric<br />
question about tax policy. It is an attack upon the<br />
social equity and economic efficiency which are essential<br />
components of the modern Labor vision for Australia.<br />
It is why when the Pilots' Federation gave us a practical<br />
demonstration of the Opposition's recipe for industrial<br />
relations far more was at stake than just an excessive<br />
wage claim in one industry. It was an attack on the very<br />
economic competitiveness which is at the heart of the<br />
sort of Australia we wish to see.<br />
It is why when the Opposition proposes pulling back the<br />
helping hand to the sick, the elderly, the Aboriginal<br />
people, the newly arrived migrant, we are not just<br />
dealing with some peripheral re-ordering of Government<br />
spending priorities, but symptoms of an ideology utterly<br />
hostile to our Australian vision.<br />
It is why differences over the environment are more tha n<br />
differences over forests and streams; they are<br />
differences over the very values we wish to prevail in<br />
the country which future generations will inherit.<br />
It is why when John Elliott proposes that Australia<br />
become part of the European Community or when others in<br />
the Opposition attack Asian immigration, this is not some<br />
sort of sad joke or minor aberration but a literally<br />
dangerous failure to understand our place in the 1990s<br />
and beyond.<br />
It is why when the Opposition is so sluggish in<br />
recognising change in the Soviet Union and Eastern<br />
Europe, when it childishly plays around with the concept<br />
of an Asia-Pacific trading bloc, when it promises to<br />
abrogate the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone Treaty, when<br />
it pulls back from sanctions against apartheid, we are<br />
not just talking about some slight immaturity in foreign<br />
policy but a deep-seated inability to come to grips with<br />
Australia's future in the world.<br />
In summary, it is why when the Opposition puts short-term<br />
political point scoring ahead of long-term national<br />
interests or when it reveals its utter confusion about<br />
where those interests really lie we are seeing a<br />
debauching of the political debate about the future of<br />
our country. Labor the united Labor movement has<br />
modernised and acquired a maturity and competence in the<br />
pursuit of national goals. The conservatives divided<br />
and immature remain locked in the mindset of the past. </p>
<p>So as Australia enters the 1990s we do not have in this<br />
country two parties of the centre algreed on ends and<br />
locked only in a constructive debate over means. We are<br />
engaged in a sharply drawn contest against a party<br />
ideologically driven by the right. It is no mere<br />
academic debate but a battle with far reaching<br />
implications for the daily lives of every Australian.<br />
It would not be Andrew Peacock who would run a Coalition<br />
Cabinet, certainly not on economic, social or<br />
environmental issues. It would be the much harder men of<br />
the right. Whatever sugar coating is put on the<br />
Coalition's policies in its attempt to get into<br />
government, who could really believe that Andrew Peacock<br />
would have the fortitude, the sheer weight, to take on<br />
the John Stones and the doctrines they represent when the<br />
immediate electoral restraints were off? Andrew Peacock<br />
is a genial disproof of Art Buchwald's lament " I always<br />
wanted to get into politics but I was never light enough<br />
to make the team."<br />
So I do not for a moment deny that our opponents<br />
represent change. Certainly they do but not change-for<br />
the better change dreadfully for the worse.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Let me take head on the questions so much in the<br />
forefront of discussion, and certainly concern, in the<br />
electorate the balance of payments, debt and interest<br />
rates. These are, without question, totally proper and<br />
understandable areas of concern. Indeed as a nation we<br />
ignore them at our peril.<br />
But first we must be clear about this: there is no one<br />
single yardstick of how we as individuals, as families or<br />
as a nation are progressing along the path to future<br />
prosperity in a restructured, more competitive, more<br />
cooperative and more compassionate Australia.<br />
The Accord has been, under this Government, the crucial<br />
instrument of economic and social policy.<br />
There is a fundamental point to be made about the impact<br />
of the Accord. The trade union movement has been<br />
prepared to accept lower money wage increases in exchange<br />
for significant improvements in that broad range of<br />
benefits encompassed under the heading of the social<br />
wage. I accept that current interest rates hurt that the<br />
decline in real wages has hurt. But that is to tell only<br />
part of the story.<br />
For the following things not only do not hurt but in fact<br />
positively add to the welfare of Australian families<br />
and equally importantly they are the building blocks for<br />
our better future: </p>
<p>a record number of new jobs have been created;<br />
our children are staying on in the school<br />
system, and massively increased numbers of<br />
tertiary education places and Job training<br />
opportunities are being provided; Medicare is<br />
guaranteeing decent and fair health cover for<br />
all Australians; superannuation is being<br />
opened up to the great majority of the<br />
Australian workforce; childcare places have<br />
been trebled; pensions have been boosted in<br />
real terms.<br />
This list is not exhaustive. But it illustrates the<br />
basic point: real wage restraint, accompanied by such<br />
massive improvement in the social wage the restraint<br />
with equity that I sought and that has been so<br />
magnificently provided by the Australian community has<br />
set the course for growth sustainable prosperity,<br />
genuinely earned and fairly shared.<br />
This sort of wage restraint has been the starting point<br />
of a positive, dynamic process now under way throughout<br />
the Australian economy.<br />
The equation is crystal clear: wage restraint has meant<br />
higher profits; that has lead to record investment; that<br />
has sustained record employment growth.<br />
Of course the investment surge is sucking in imports at a<br />
level we cannot currently sustain by our own exports.<br />
These imports constitute an essential part of the reequipping<br />
and re-structuring for the future Australia.<br />
But the present Australia cannot, precisely because of<br />
current external pressures, maintain this level of<br />
imports. The problem of high interest rates is the very<br />
product of our success together in encouraging jobcreating<br />
investment so vital to this country's future.<br />
So tight monetary policy -supplementing already tight<br />
fiscal and wages policy -must be used to dampen economic<br />
activity, so that we can have a sustainable level of<br />
imports.<br />
The test of an active economic policy is not that there<br />
be new decisions and new announcements every week or<br />
every month. Our policies are not passive. They are<br />
actively working on the economy day by day to achieve the<br />
results we need.<br />
Signs are emerging that this policy the policy for<br />
Australians present and future is working.<br />
As soon as it is consistent with my responsibility as<br />
Prime Minister which is a responsibility not to secure<br />
immediate electoral acclaim but to protect the future of<br />
this country interest rates will be able to come down. </p>
<p>But I repeat there is no single yardstick not the<br />
balance of payments, not foreign debt levels, not<br />
interest rates that can adequately measure the health<br />
of the economy, the wellbeing of Australians and their<br />
families and our prospects for the future.<br />
And finally on this point, I say that a realistic<br />
awareness of present problems and constructive concern to<br />
tackle them is one thing; self-fulfilling gloom about<br />
the nation's future talking the country down<br />
permitting some artificial crisis of confidence to erode<br />
our immense strengths ignoring what is being done<br />
these things are quite another.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
As I said at the beginning, today is not the time for the<br />
policy speech. We can talk about that next year.<br />
But it is right today that I bring together the essential<br />
elements on which that policy speech will certainly be<br />
based the guiding principles for leading us towards our<br />
four goals for the 1990s principles we have already<br />
firmly established in practice.<br />
* Fundamental to everything that follows is<br />
d~ i~ pined Acnomin policy not the pork barrel, not<br />
gimmicks, not posturing.<br />
That means there will be more of the already countless<br />
hours in the Expenditure Review Committee, holding down<br />
Government spending painstaking evaluation of programs,<br />
not the indiscriminate wielding of a meat cleaver. It<br />
means unyielding defence of a fair and efficient taxation<br />
system. The commitment to an unrelenting drive for world<br />
beRt standards in induntrv-infrastrunture-p and Rarvice<br />
q~ Zotr must continue it must not be botched in the<br />
welter of tough talk, ill-considered action,<br />
confrontation and favouritism that is our opponents'<br />
stock in trade.<br />
Reconstruction has been a continuing and accelerating<br />
process marked by significant achievements unparalleled<br />
in Australian peace-time history. I again challenge our<br />
conservative opponents, and any political or economic<br />
commentator, to examine the document on micro-economic<br />
reform I have released today, and point to any period of<br />
conservative rule which has come within a bull's roar of<br />
this pace and size of change.<br />
Industrial rplationn nped gtability not a wing and<br />
a prayer. </p>
<p>We have proven that distinctively Australian institutions<br />
work well when they are applied properly. The centralised<br />
system has shown it can deliver the goods in testing<br />
economic times responsible wage outcomes, reduction in<br />
industrial disputes, award restructuring and record rates<br />
of job creation.<br />
Without these fundamentals of economic management no<br />
facet of the vision I have for Australia economic or<br />
social, domestic or international will, in the final<br />
analysis, be possible. And I fear for that vision when I<br />
see the Opposition embrace fiscal, monetary and wages<br />
policies the combined effect of which must be higher<br />
interest rates, industrial turmoil,. perversion of the tax<br />
system and ultimately recession. They would in practice<br />
destroy the formidable growth in Australia's productive<br />
capacity that has been achieved by the Australian people<br />
since 1983.<br />
* Enduring financial constraints will mean that ancial<br />
ipning musat continue to hP finely and fairly targeted<br />
not debased by false, crude divisions of the Australian<br />
community into " bludgers" and " workers".<br />
My Government has proved decisively that we can have,<br />
simultaneously, both greater social justice and fiscal<br />
responsibility we can have both compassion and realism.<br />
Critical to the challenge of social justice is the<br />
crato through education and training, of<br />
oppotunities forl young Au~ tralfans to lead fulfilling<br />
and productive lives rather than being forced onto dole<br />
queues as a blunt instrument of economic policy.<br />
An Australia which prizes learning will be an Australia<br />
where the life of individuals, and of our society as a<br />
whole, is enriched. But, beyond that, an Australia<br />
operating at the very peak of its intellectual capability<br />
and skills in management, business, the professions,<br />
the trades, science and technology is an Australia<br />
capable of holding and improving its place in a<br />
competitive world.<br />
We must be committed not merely to the principle of<br />
op~ pao rtunity, but to its achievement in everyday<br />
life through legislation, affirmative action and<br />
institutional changes.<br />
It is precisely because we aspire to enduring social and<br />
economic change that we have adopted National Agendas in<br />
such areas as multiculturalism and the role of women.<br />
And that is precisely the reason we are restructuring the<br />
very institutional framework for Aboriginal Affairs and<br />
expanding access and opportunity for Australians living<br />
outside the major cities. </p>
<p>Where our opponents would backtrack on Annial<br />
lugtinA, we shall look ahead to new issues and seek out<br />
new solutions.<br />
We are developing new initiatives for the 1990s in our<br />
social justice program. This takes us beyond the<br />
pre-occupation absolutely essential in the 1980s with<br />
providing basic income support to disadvantaged<br />
Australians. Our attention must now turn to the<br />
inadequacy of basic services in local communities,<br />
especially those in rapidly expanding outer urban areas<br />
and in provincial areas. And we are working with ACOSS<br />
to tackle these issues.<br />
Protection of our natural environment must be ranked<br />
alongside economic development, not as our opponents<br />
would have it, a poor second cousin. The environmental<br />
cause is no passing fad. It is a profound obligation<br />
born of new knowledge and changing values an obligation<br />
to our children. I shall be speaking more about this to<br />
the Australian Conservation Foundation next week.<br />
In a time of the most profound and remarkable<br />
international change in post-war history, we must be able<br />
to anticipate change, adjust to change, be ahead of<br />
change not shuffle along behind like our opponents.<br />
The change is of course most spectacular in Eastern<br />
Europe, but it is most immediately relevant, most<br />
powerfully felt, in our region.<br />
When I started years ago pressing what I termed<br />
Australia's " enmeshment" with Asia and the Pacific it was<br />
not only to establish a fundamental tenet of a modern<br />
Australian economic and foreign policy it was to<br />
encourage Australians to revise their thinking on where<br />
our future as a country lies. Thus there is a broader<br />
context for such foreign policy achievements as the APEC<br />
initiative and the Timor Gap agreement, and for our<br />
commissioning of Ross Garnaut's report. I want such<br />
steps to be consciously seen by the Australian people as<br />
decisive indications of this country's long term<br />
orientation. We must recognise that there is now the most intimate<br />
connection between the future character of Australia<br />
itself, on the one hand, and the world in which Australia<br />
must function on the other. In this sense foreign policy<br />
has become a key part of domestic policy, and vice versa;<br />
and we must not rend that seamless web.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Ours is a great country its potential is greater still. </p>
<p>When Australians lift their gaze to look ahead they can,<br />
with every justification, see a future rich in hope and<br />
promise. We have the human and natural resources to<br />
bring it about.<br />
So my reflections on turning 60 come to this that if<br />
the kids of Australia grow up in a country like this if<br />
they inherit a country more economically dynamic; more at<br />
home in its region; more caring, diverse and tolerant;<br />
more protective of the natural environment; more<br />
educated; more able to adjust to a changing world then<br />
they will have the best chance we can give them of lives<br />
which are individually fulfilling and rewarding. They<br />
will, moreover, live in a nation even more justly proud<br />
of its achievements, a country where they, the next<br />
generation of Australians, can look with confidence to a<br />
place in the sun as we move into the 21st century. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
