<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2839</transcript-id>
    <title>RIVER MURRAY COMMISSION</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002839.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT NO.<br />
2 March 1973<br />
RIVER MURRAY COMMISSION<br />
The Prime Minister announced today that at the request<br />
of the Premier of South Australia a meeting had been held<br />
between the Premiers of New South Wales, Victoria and South<br />
Australia and himself concerning the River Murray, the existing<br />
powers of the River Murray Commission and the problems which had<br />
arisen in ensuring water quality in the River Murray. The meeting<br />
was also attended by the Hon. Moss Cass, Australian Minister<br />
for the Environment and Conservation, the Hon. G. F. Freudenste'n,<br />
the New South Wales Minister for Conservation, the ilono<br />
Roberts Dunstan, the Victorian Minister of Water Supply,<br />
the Hlon. J. D. Corcoran, the South Australian Ministej w-.<br />
Works. The Prime Minister said that the original River Murray<br />
Waters Agreement had been signed in 1914 and at that time : hce<br />
major factor in interstate disputes had been navigation and<br />
quantitites of water shared between the States. Although quite<br />
a number of amendments had been made to the Agreement since that<br />
cime it had become apparent that a 1973 model was now necessary<br />
because of the vast changes in circumstances which had occurred<br />
since the original Agreement was signed.<br />
Increased use of the River's available water resources<br />
has led to more complex problems involving not only the<br />
availability of water but the quality of water in the river.<br />
Problems include increasing salinity, pollution by pesticides.<br />
weedicides and fertilizers; also the need to prevent pollu-cio...<br />
from new and growing urban areas Albury/ Wodonga and Mon
The meeting agreed to establish a working party of senio.<br />
officials of the Australian and State Governments concerned witLthe<br />
following terms of reference </p>
<p>1. Examine and recommend in an initial report<br />
urgent interim measures which might be<br />
implemented in the short term to deal with<br />
the salinity problems of the River Murray<br />
waters and the means by which those measures<br />
might be financed and operated.,<br />
2. Examine and recommend types of measures which<br />
need to be taken to protect and where<br />
necessary improve the quality of the River<br />
Murray waters in respect of long term<br />
salinity control, and other forms of<br />
water pollution.<br />
3. Examine and recommend changes which would be<br />
required in the River Murray Waters Agreement<br />
to enable the River Murray Commission to<br />
undertake the measures referred to in 2.<br />
4. Enquire into and report on other matters<br />
referred to it by the Steering Committee.<br />
Membership of the Working Party shall comprise<br />
one official each from the Australian Government<br />
and the State Governments. The Australian<br />
Government will provide the Secretariat.<br />
6. The Working Party is empowered to create<br />
sub-Committees and to co-opt as necessary<br />
to fulfill the above Terms of Reference.<br />
7. An initial report is to be made by the Working<br />
Party to the Steering Committee within six<br />
months. The Steering Committee shall comprise the following<br />
Ministers: The Australian Minister for the Environment<br />
and Conservation,<br />
The New South Wales Minister for Conservation,<br />
The Victorian Minister of Water Supply,<br />
The South Australian Minister of Works.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
