<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4674</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/04/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004674.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I THALZJ_ EMsBARGO: 7.00 p. m.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 9 APRIL 1978<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The Government has shown a concern and a commitment to help<br />
those Australians who cannot find jobs. Latest official figures<br />
show that although unemployment is now starting to fall, it is<br />
still unacceptably high. The needs of the unemployed are<br />
of singular concern to us. While we have been setting the conditions<br />
for a return to full economic health, we have responded to this<br />
need in a sensitive way.<br />
The Government has significantly expanded and iffproved Commonwealth<br />
training and employment schemes with emphasis on the problems<br />
faced by young people. The special training programmes are<br />
working well. However, I do not believe the effects of these<br />
initiatives are fully appreciated throughout the community.<br />
Almost 200,000 people mainly young Australians have already<br />
benefitted from these programmes. Given our pledge that finance<br />
will not be a limiting factor, we expect they will continue to help<br />
more Australians.<br />
The National Employment and Training Scheme has been particularly<br />
effective in training and retraining to meet the changing demands<br />
of the labour market. More than 94,000 Australians have<br />
benefitted from this scheme over the last two years. An<br />
important part of NEAT is the Special Youth Employment Training<br />
Programme which has helped more than 40,000 young Australians<br />
since its inception 18 months ago. The Community Youth Support<br />
Scheme which seeks to encourage communities to provide programmes<br />
and services to the young unemployed has assisted 45,000 young men<br />
and women.<br />
In apprenticeship, the Commonwealth rebate for apprenticeship<br />
full-time training the CRAFT Scheme has gone a long way to<br />
lifting apprentice intake. Last year the intake was 42,000 an<br />
increase of 8.5 percent on the previous year..<br />
These employment and training programmes however are not designed<br />
to help young people who have low motivation and self esteem.<br />
Many children leave school with a low level of literacy. This lack<br />
of success is often followed up by failure to find or hold work<br />
and the outcome of frequently a negative attitude towards work or<br />
self improvement. The education programme for unemployed youth<br />
initiated by this Government was conceived specifically to break </p>
<p>this vicious circle and meet the very special needs of such<br />
young unemployed people.<br />
It is the first time any Australian Government has tackled this<br />
very real problem. This programme has enjoyed remarkable success.<br />
originally set up to help people under 21 years, it has now<br />
been extended to the 21 to 24 age group and is now an on-going<br />
programme in all States. During the pilot stage, which<br />
ended last December, 57 courses were completed at 30 colleges<br />
and institutions catering for some 800 students.<br />
In this current six months, 109 courses are planned, 54<br />
institutions will be involved, and 2,000 students are expected to<br />
be enrolled. More than $ 1 million is likely to be spent on this<br />
programme in the current period. All S1ttes are en-ui-asti<br />
about the programme, particularly as some of the young people who<br />
complete the course are returning to formal education on<br />
either a full-time or part-time basis. This is an exciting<br />
development in education as it offers new hope and promise for<br />
many young Australians. ItC deserves wholehearted community support.<br />
While all of these programmes are designed to meet an immediate<br />
social need, they are not a substitute for sound economic policies.<br />
We seek complete economic recovery with satisfying and lasting<br />
employment opportunities for all. our economic policies are<br />
pulling Australia out of the economic ruin we faced at the end of<br />
1975.<br />
Inflation is falling, interest rates are falling, taxes have been<br />
dramatically cut, investment is increasing, and confidence is<br />
returning throughout the community. These are the pre-conditions<br />
to any sustained and lasting reduction in the levels of<br />
unemployment and not irresponsible government spending.<br />
The Government will continue to demonstrate our concern for the<br />
unemployed through the imaginative development of our training<br />
schemes and through firm economic policy. But in looking at<br />
unemployment, it needs to be clearly understood that Australia<br />
has still not recovered from the wage policies of the Labor years.<br />
We are still paying the price and counting the cost of the wages<br />
explosion of 1974.<br />
Business and industry are reluctant to pay excessively high wages<br />
when they can invest their money in labour savinq machines and<br />
equipment. Business has shown it has the ccnfidenoe to invest<br />
but it will not invest in new jobs that it cannot afford.<br />
For this reason the Government will continue to preach wage<br />
restraint wherever it can and argue strongly before the<br />
Arbitration Commission for less than full wage indexation.<br />
If we do not, we would not be fulfilling our obligation to every<br />
Australian. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
