<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5919</transcript-id>
    <title>ST BASIL&#039;S DINNER, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005919.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
POR MEDIA SUNDAY, 26 SEPTEMBER 1982<br />
ST BASIL'S DINNER, SYDNEY<br />
It really is a very real honour for Tarnie and imyself to have<br />
been asked to share with you this 25th anniversary of St Basil's<br />
Homes for the aged. Those who conceived of the idea and through<br />
the years who have worked for the homes made an enormous<br />
contribution to the elderly and the frail aged within the<br />
Greek community of AustrAlia and to Australia itself. I know<br />
there had been government assistance from time to time<br />
from the State and -prom. the Commonwealth, but what is really<br />
important is the sense of community and the indIviduals who are<br />
prepared to qet out and to make this kind of contribution<br />
possible. It would be a very sad day if we ever came to the<br />
circumstance where people said that governments had to do<br />
it all, whether it is a state governmenlt, a local government or<br />
a Commonweal1th Government. One of the great things about the<br />
Greek community in Australia and one of the great things about<br />
Australia as a whole is the way in which people move out to<br />
improve their own communities and make a better place than<br />
would otherwise be.<br />
This provides the kind of care and concern that can never<br />
really come from governments no matter how much those<br />
governments might care and might be concerned because a<br />
government necessarily has to work through a siynficant army<br />
of public servants and departments and it cannot have the initimate<br />
knowledge of the immediate needs of indiViduals, of families or<br />
of elderly people as other people in that community can have,.<br />
So governments I suppose from their size are necessarily to an<br />
extent temote when people from within their own community take<br />
charge of these affairs and do it well, then that is something<br />
of very real value indeed. I would like to thank and congratulate<br />
who have done so much over 25 years in working for St Basil's<br />
Homes* They have made the later years of many people much<br />
happier than it might otherwise have been.<br />
There are biundreds of thousands of Australians of Greek origin<br />
and Greek e'xtraction committed to this country. The overwhelming<br />
preponderance of those who were born in Greece have become<br />
Australian citizens in-;' its fullest sense and you have all<br />
provided enormous energy, skill, initiative and enterprise for<br />
the role that has been played in Australia, helping us to build<br />
a much better and more vigorous nation than this might otherwise<br />
have been. There are industries that would have been established<br />
that would not have been established were it not for the Greek.<br />
association with Australia. There has been an enrichment in our </p>
<p>ST BlASIL'Swhole society because of the intermingling of Greek and cultures<br />
of other lands and of Australia itself. Australians of Greek<br />
origin have taken opportunities, they have set an example to<br />
many other people and have won respect throughout the whole<br />
community. We often talk about a multicultural society and I<br />
think that some aignificant strides have been made in the<br />
achievement of that society over the last five to ten years.<br />
Some of these things have been mentioned tonight.'<br />
There is one aspect of that which may not be adequately understood.<br />
One of the reasons for our support, for my support, for<br />
Government support for a multicultural society and all of those<br />
things which go to make up that society is because we are<br />
committed' . to a fair society. We might not always achieve it in<br />
the fullest measure, but we are committed to a society and to<br />
Government policies that are fair as between all Australians,<br />
no matter where they may come from, no matter what their origins<br />
may be.<br />
I think we have achieved a great deal from the years in which<br />
I was a very young child before the last World War when this<br />
would have been a somewhat narrow, inward looking introspective<br />
anglo-saxon community. There would have been peoplein the<br />
1930s or darlier who said that to be a good Australian, if you<br />
did not come from England or Wales, or Scotland or Ireland<br />
I suppose, they would say,, forget where you came from. We<br />
know that that was a narrow view and a false and that old<br />
narrow anglo-saxon view of Australia is very much a thing of<br />
the-. past because overwhelmingly Australians recognise that<br />
we are strengthened by diversity, we are strengthened by. the<br />
coming together of people from many, many different countries.<br />
We are strengthened enormously by people who have come to this<br />
country through the decades from many countries around the<br />
world from every continent in the world. We have learnt so much<br />
from each others' cultures, we have learnt a greater tolerance<br />
and understanding. of what we are all about and f.' the origins<br />
of the people who make up Australia.<br />
I can reirerTher the arguments about multicultural television in the<br />
early days within the wider community and to some extent within<br />
my own Party. What was all this for people were saying. it<br />
was going to be ' a divisive thing. Why do you want to introduce<br />
it into Australia. The people that took F that view did not<br />
understand any part of. what a multicultural Australia was all<br />
about because multicultural television was never meant to provide<br />
services one hour for Greeks, another hour for Italians and<br />
another hour for people from some other country and whatever.<br />
It was meant to provide programs which would help to unify<br />
Australia because all Australians would want to watch the programs<br />
because they were intrinsically good programs and by so watching<br />
them, all Australians would understand something more of the<br />
origins, of the background of the history in culture of all<br />
the people that go to make up this nation. Multicultural<br />
television was nevery divisive in Its inspiration. It was<br />
unifying, strengthening, leading to a greater understanding<br />
amongst all Australians of other. Australians. ./ 3<br />
2 </p>
<p>ST BASIL'S-3<br />
I have got to say many of those early critics of multicultural<br />
television have come to understand now having seen the programs<br />
and watched its development, have come to understand that the<br />
original concept was a good one and should have been supported<br />
as it is now supported and of course we know that the programs<br />
are going to be extended to a significant number of other<br />
centres and cities around Australia over the next three years.<br />
We began several years ago a review of the post-arrival service<br />
for migrants and this is something which in retrospect should<br />
have been done about 1955 or 1960 or 1965 at the very latest.<br />
It was not done. It was begun about 1976 and led to the Galbally<br />
Report. It led. to the total acceptance of the originial<br />
recommendations of that Report and as suggested in the original<br />
Report, that led to a review of the programs and of virtually<br />
total acceptance of the review only a few weeks ago. This has<br />
led of course to many things, many new and. I think far-sighted<br />
programs which are designed to assist people who first come to<br />
this country. The pity of it is that we did, not, have the<br />
wisdom -to do it so much earlier. The point now is that it has<br />
been done. This must make the early arrival in Australia of<br />
people a good deal ' 6asier than it would Otherwise be. It does<br />
more than that. It does not just try and provide the services<br />
and the circumstance to make it easier for somebody from another<br />
land and who may not spleak English too well in the initial<br />
stages, to understand what Australia is all about, what services<br />
are available, what opportunities there are to be siezed. The<br />
programs are also designed to encourage the -survival and the<br />
passing on of the language, the culture the history and<br />
traditions of your community, the Greek community as part of<br />
Australia and of all the other communities that make up this<br />
country. What we need to understand, and-I think overwhelmingly<br />
Australians * are coming to understand, is that Greek history, your<br />
origins are just as much part of Australia as a Scots history,<br />
or English history or Welsh history or Irish history, I suppose<br />
the countries from which most original settlers came and that<br />
it it is important for these things to be -cherished and passed<br />
on from one generation to another. That can lead to things<br />
that might be small in themselves, but can be signifitcant in<br />
terms of the expression and the understanding that they seek<br />
to unfold and the support for community schools. which will teach<br />
the language and the history of peoples in a way which Australian<br />
Government schools or private ~ schools -might not -otherwise do<br />
is one of the attempts and efforts of government to make the<br />
passing on of cultures and of languages and of history easier<br />
than it might otherwise have been.<br />
Now there is a very widespread commitment to multiculturalism<br />
right throughout Australia. I believe it-is much better<br />
understood than it has ever been. I also believe that we lead<br />
the world in what: we have done over the'.. lakt ten years in these<br />
areas. ./ 4<br />
3 </p>
<p>ST BASIL'S<br />
I would like * to turn if I could to one or two things, that are<br />
obviously important to all of us because for those who want<br />
to look after their own families, who want decent jobs for their<br />
children, who want to build up their standard of living, a strong<br />
economy, a strong Australia is obviously very important. I think<br />
we all know that we live in a world where there are some<br />
difficulties. we know there are problems in Eur6pe, in the<br />
United States, in North America, that the price Australia gets<br />
for export commodities are a good deal less than they were<br />
two or three years ago. M~ ost of usrounderstand that the depths<br />
of the world recession in spite of the problems we may have,<br />
haS_ effected Australia much less than it has effected most<br />
other countries. I believe, with the energy, with the capacities<br />
to work of most Australians* that we won't experience problemrs<br />
anything like as great as many of the countries of Europe<br />
where unemployment levels for example might be 10, 12 or in<br />
Britain 14%. Here it is too high. it is something like half<br />
thatk' but the fact that it is something like half that says<br />
something I believe about the kinds of policies Australia has<br />
pursued as opposed to the kinds of policies that some other<br />
countries have pursued.<br />
we still have recognised the world recession has effected families<br />
it has effected bu~ inesses and in our last Budget we tried to<br />
do,. some things that would help. There are many changes in the<br />
social security area that Fred Chaney looks after and changes<br />
that were designed to assist aged people in the community. The<br />
is going to be a much greater rate of building of homes for the<br />
aged and the frail aged over the next year or two. I don't<br />
know how many of you have applications for-. the faster rate of<br />
spending, but I understand that Senator Chaney i~ s making*<br />
the decisions fairly shortly, but there will be a greater rate<br />
of building and that is one kind of response.<br />
There have b~ een son changes in other social security arrangements,<br />
again designed to assist individuals or families thatmight be<br />
in greatest difficult-y. Family allowances have been increased<br />
very significantly. People trying to pay off their own homes<br />
are being assisted by a housing rebate because we know interest<br />
rates are far, far higher than anyone wants. As a farmer I know<br />
very much how interest rates effect people and small businesses<br />
and individuals with their homes and all the rest. Here we<br />
have been very much effected by what-has happened overseas.<br />
The moves over bhe last week or two in which interest rates<br />
have started to come down,--are in~ deed encburaging and give us<br />
somne reason to hope that that move will be reinforced. I think<br />
it is worth noting that it was sometimes said that the Budget<br />
was not going to help in that area, well I believe it has helped<br />
because it is not only as a result of overseas changes, but<br />
also as a result of our Budget that interest%. rates have started<br />
to move down. I am not going to make predictions, because<br />
I made predictions once before and [-it took me about three<br />
years after that to try'. and persuade people that the prediction<br />
had fin fact been all right, but that circumstances had changed<br />
and I-am not going to give Lionel Bowen the opportunity to make<br />
that kind of argument against me again. I think we must all<br />
hope that rates will start to move down in a way which does<br />
effect families beneficially. -4 </p>
<p>-ST BASIL'S<br />
Also if this last Budget which we introduced can be remembered<br />
for anything, I hope it can be remembered as one which<br />
encourages the situation in which it makes it easier for Australians<br />
to work together and help by wo~ rking together to overcome<br />
whatever problemis that we might have. Let me explain that<br />
by one example. if you had a family on a single income of<br />
say $ 300 a week, a wife and two dependent children paying<br />
off a housing loan of about $ 25,000 which by some of today's<br />
standards would be a relatively modest loant then that particular<br />
family would be $ 18 a week better off as;. a result. of the Budget.-<br />
Now if that person had to be as much'better off by getting<br />
the money from an employer on which tax would have to be<br />
paid, you would have to get about an extra $ 25 or $ 30 a week<br />
and in some circumstances that could be enough to make it<br />
very difficult indeed for the employer and very difficult for<br />
him to continue to sell whatever his product was. Therefore,<br />
those changes I believe make it reasonable to argue fo-r restraint<br />
in things such as wages and reasonable to say that by so<br />
doing that family living standards are not going to fall<br />
because of other countervailing measures in the Budget.<br />
I think this is an example of-the way in which governments<br />
can try and create the situation in which different sections,<br />
different groups within the Australian community can recognise.<br />
that there are problems and if we are all prepared to make<br />
some kind of contribution tothe overcoming of those problems,<br />
then it will happen so much more easily, so much quickly than<br />
would otherwise be the case.<br />
There have been some difficult arguments in the last few weeks<br />
and very briefly I would like to try and explain the Governmeftt's<br />
point of vriew. I said that much of our attitude towards<br />
multi cul turali sm and many of the policies that we have. introduced<br />
have been introduced because we believe in a fair society and<br />
because we believe that governments must govern for all Australians<br />
no matter where they are, where they have come from or what<br />
they are doing, equally and reasonably. This is one of the<br />
things that we have had very much in mind over a somewhat<br />
contentious and difficult tax legislation which some of you<br />
might have heard of over the last three weeks, because a horrible<br />
word retrospectivity has come into the argument. I don't think<br />
anyone likes retrospective legislation, but I would like to say<br />
very briefly what we are in fact doing with legislation that<br />
John Howard introduced last Thursday night.<br />
That legislation is only seeking to collect from a certain very<br />
narrow group within the Australian community, tax that should<br />
have been Oaid, but was not paid because of a device. that was<br />
patently wrong and always was wrong and that at'some point always<br />
had to involve in relation to some of the peor-14 that patticipated<br />
in it, an illegality. It involved a device in which there was<br />
significant income in the course of a year in relation say to<br />
a company and no tax whatever was paid in ielation to that<br />
income. 0. 0 / 6<br />
5 </p>
<p>ST BASIL'S<br />
It would be wonderful if all of us having our individual income<br />
could think up some legal and proper way in which we did not<br />
have to pay any tax, but if the whole community did that we<br />
would know quite well that the community just would not work.<br />
The schools-, the multicultural programs, the whole fabric.<br />
of government and society would fall apart. There is no<br />
reason in my view why people with access to sophisticated.' i<br />
legal and accountancy advice should evade their obligations<br />
to the wider Australian community. The kind of device;-that<br />
we have been talking about was in fact outlawed in 1980, but<br />
there was a very large amount of. tax that should have been<br />
paid and was not.<br />
The legialation that John Howard is introducing is not criminal<br />
legislation as somebody said why did it have to be. Itt is not,<br />
it is tax legislation and it is designed to collect the tax<br />
from those who benefited from the particular device known as<br />
the bottom of the harbour scheme. it became known as a bottom<br />
of the harbour schene because the company was sold, people<br />
converted the income into a capital gain and ultimately the<br />
papers got dropped in the harbour-I don't know whether it<br />
was Sydney harbour or the port of Melbourne, one or the other<br />
or it might even have been Fremantle Habour in Perth. That is<br />
what happened. Without going into the intricacy of it, it is<br />
the only device which this legislation is related to. We have<br />
had to balance our dislike of any kind of retrospective legislation<br />
against our concept aLnd our idea of fairness for all Australians.<br />
We have quite plainly as a Government given greater weight<br />
tio the concept, to ~ the idea of fairness in this particular<br />
instance, because if thbere are people who are not paying taxes<br />
and who ought to be, thnen other people have to pay higher taxes<br />
and that is not fair and it is not reasonable.<br />
other people say that this has never happened at all, I could<br />
but I won't point to Learned opinions in the United Kingdom<br />
going back to 1941 or' 4-2 or ' 43 in which the Lord Chancellor,<br />
in our terms, our Chief Justice has confirmed retrospective<br />
legislation in B~ ritain for very much the same reason as we have0<br />
introduced it in Australia. So it is not a novel step within<br />
English speaking societies. It was done there because some<br />
people were acting very unfairly in relation to the rest of<br />
the British community. There is an interesting phrase because<br />
one of those giving the judgement said that from the nature of<br />
the contest, that is people not wanting to pay tax and people<br />
having to collect tax when those who are-trying to do much<br />
not to pay tax go too far, they should understand the rigour<br />
of the contest and know the consequences. We believc that<br />
some people in Australia, and it is a very few, went too far<br />
and they ought to understand the rigour of the context and<br />
there is the question of fairness to all Australians. That<br />
I believe is perhaps the most important principle of all by<br />
which governments must judge their own decisions.<br />
It is a while ago, but not very long ago, since President visited<br />
Australia and I was honoured to be his host while he was here.<br />
I was not able to be in Sydney while he was in Sydney, but in<br />
./ 7<br />
6 </p>
<p>ST BASIL'S-7<br />
Canberra and in Melbourne. One of the most exciting things I think<br />
I ever was part of was the occasion in which there were 60,000<br />
Australians, I would believe overwhelmingly of Greek origin<br />
around the War Memorial in Melbourne on an occasion to welcome<br />
and to honour President laramanlis. It was a great and exciting<br />
occasion. I think it did much for the relationship between<br />
Greece and Australia and between our two peoples. I am very<br />
glad indeed that the President's visit is going to be honoured<br />
for all -time by the Australian-Greek Presidential Awards,<br />
which over the, last two or three days those who have won<br />
the awards for the first time are first being announced that<br />
will be taken up early in the new year.<br />
We have in the past had Churchhill Fellowships, Queen Elizabeth 11<br />
Trust Fellowships and the Menzies Trust. The Australian-Greek<br />
Presidential Awards in honour of President Karamanlis' visit<br />
to Australia is the first time in the history of Australia that<br />
such awards have been offered I believe to honour one of<br />
Australia's great ethnic communities and to do so in a permanent<br />
way because down through the years, each year young Australians<br />
I suppose mostly of Greek origin, but not necessarily of Greek<br />
origin, will be chosen to study in Greece to learn more of a<br />
very important part of the history anrd culture and experience<br />
of'a people who have done so much to help build up this Australia<br />
which we all love. Some awards have been announced in Melbourne,<br />
others are to be announced tomorrow morning in this city. I am<br />
very glad indeed that these awards have been established because<br />
they will be a perpetual reminder of the living vitality of the<br />
relationship between Greece and Australia and to the contribution<br />
that Australians of Greek origin have made to building this<br />
nation. Australia is not made up of governments of any kind. Australia<br />
is made up of people and the nature of this country the kind<br />
of society it is, is dependent upon the actions of something<br />
a little more than 15 million Australians in every day as they<br />
go about their lives. You are leaders of your corniunity. You<br />
come mostly from Sydney but not entirely from Sydney from other<br />
places as well as we have been told, but all of you in this<br />
room have contributed enormously not only to the Greek community<br />
in Australia, but you have contributed enormously to building<br />
the kind of Australia that we all want to see for the future and<br />
I want to thank you all for that. 7 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
