<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18116</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of doorstop interview, Auckland</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
If I can just say a few words and then I'm happy to take a few questions.</p>
<p>I've just arrived in Auckland. I'm here for the Pacific Islands Forum.</p>
<p>This is the 40th year of the Forum. We've always been a strong supporter and the Forum continues to have a contemporary meaning and relevance.</p>
<p>I'm looking forward to the discussions over the next few days. There will be a range of issues raised, but I will be particularly focussing on four areas.</p>
<p>First, on the question of economic growth and jobs and education, as I say in Australia when I'm back home, having a decent life starts with the opportunity to get a great education and to get a job. The same is true in our region, so I will be particularly focussed on education and skills, on labour mobility, on trade and the power of trade to improve job opportunities, and on the question of remittances: the ability of people who are working in another country to send money back home in a cost-effective way.</p>
<p>Second, I will be focussed on the questions of development aid. A quarter of Australia's aid goes to the Pacific region, and around half of the aid of most of the region flows from Australia. We have the Cairns Compact, and we will continue to work on that because we want to strengthen the effectiveness of our aid in the region.</p>
<p>Third, I'm intending to focus on climate change. This is a meeting that brings together some nations that are most at risk from climate change: they are small, they are low-lying, and most at risk from rising sea levels.</p>
<p>Fourth and finally, I will be talking to the nations participating in this forum so that I can reflect their voice when I go to the G20 and to other meetings around the world.</p>
<p>So, they are my objectives for the Pacific Islands Forum.</p>
<p>Can I say, too, I'm very pleased to be back here in New Zealand, and I'm looking forward to seeing Prime Minister John Key, and to his chairing and leadership of this important event.</p>
<p>This has been a year in which Australia and New Zealand have been brought and bonded incredibly closely together. We are always family for each other, but that family relationship has clearly been shown this year as we have stood by each other in times of trouble - for us, our summer of natural disasters with floods and cyclone; for our friends in New Zealand the shock of Christchurch.</p>
<p>This is my third visit to New Zealand this year, which I think shows the strength of the bond that is always between us, but has been particularly on display during the course of this year.</p>
<p>I'm happy to take any questions.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:Prime Minister, do you plan to speak to the Nauruan president about us building an asylum seeker there, and asylum seeker centre there?</p>
<p>PM:I'm here for the Pacific Islands Forum and I've just outlined my objectives in relation to that Forum. I'm not intending to raise the issue of people-smuggling. Obviously, if leaders want to raise the issue with me, then I will discuss it with them, but it is premature for me to be pursuing that agenda here at this Forum, given the High Court case of last week and that the Government is still preparing its response.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, are you disappointed that today's poll shows that less than a quarter of Australians are happy with the job you're doing as Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I don't do this job as Prime Minister because I want to see it reflected in opinion polls. I do this job as Prime Minister because I want to do what's right for the nation's future: that's a focus on jobs, a focus on opportunity, and a focus on making sure that no-one gets left behind. That's what's driving me and I'll continue to do it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: But you can't keep ignoring the polls, can you, Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PM:Well, democracy isn't about looking at fortnightly opinion polls - it's about making the decisions that give people opportunities and prosperity today: things like getting a job or getting an apprenticeship, and the benefits of opportunity and prosperity tomorrow and making sure that we are organising our nation so we aren't seeing people and regions left behind.</p>
<p>And I do, as Prime Minister, particularly understand at this phase of our economic growth and development, that there are many Australians who feel that they are at risk of being left behind, or the industry that they work in is at risk of being left behind, or their region is at risk of being left behind.</p>
<p>Managing our economy so we see growth and opportunity and jobs right around the nation is what I'm pursuing and what I'm focussed on.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Can you admit that you're a little bit disappointed, or are you happy with the way you're polling?</p>
<p>PM:What I judge myself by is making sure that we are achieving the vision for our nation's future that I aspire to. People will judge that at the 2013 election. That's their democratic right, and they'll go in to polling places then and cast their votes.</p>
<p>For the time in between I will be continuing to strive to realise that vision of the nation's future. I came into politics driven by a vision of opportunity for all. It starts with a great education; it must include having the ability to get a job. That's what's driving me.</p>
<p>Thank you very much. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
