<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4838</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY INTO HOUSING COSTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/09/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004838.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 28 SEPTEMBER 1978<br />
COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY INTO HOUSING COSTS<br />
The Prime Minister has written to the State Premiers regarding<br />
the Report of the Committee of Inquiry into Housing Costs, which<br />
was tabled in Federal Parliament on 19 September.<br />
He has indicated to the Premiers that the Commonwealth regarded<br />
the Report as a most comprehensive document and would be subjecting<br />
its findings to close study over the coming months.<br />
Given the important role which State arnd Local Governments play<br />
in the housing process, he has encouraged the States also to<br />
examine the Report closely. It will only be throu-t a concerted<br />
effort by all levels of government, in cooperation with industry,<br />
that a telling impact will be made on the growth of housing costs.<br />
The Prime Minister would like to see a widespread debate on the<br />
Report and to this end the Government has arranged for the<br />
three Committee members, Mr Ernest Eyers,<br />
Mr Keith Campbell., and Mr Ken Taeuber, to be available<br />
to discuss their findings with Government and industry over the<br />
next few months.<br />
The Commonwealth Government will consider what action might<br />
be taken within its areas of responsibility after it has<br />
thoroughly examined the Report and received public comments.<br />
The Commonwealth role in follow-up to the Report will fall under<br />
the responsibility of the Minister for Environment, Housing and<br />
Community Developruent. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
