<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8470</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINSITER, THE HON P J MP,  PRIME MINISTER MINISTERIAL WOMEN AND SPORTS AWARDS THE REGENT MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008470.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMAICOED UNTIL DELIVERY ( 8.30 PM, 19 MARCH 1992)<br />
ADDRESS BY Tffl PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
PRIME MINISTERIAL WOMEN AND SPORTS AWARDS<br />
THE REGENT MELBOURNE<br />
Thank you very much. It's my great pleasure to be here.<br />
You will have probably heard me say on the odd occasion that<br />
I want to see Australia become more competitive in the<br />
world. It has been one of my ruling passions for the past decade.<br />
More recently you may have heard me utter the words " One<br />
Nation" this is -set to become a ruling passion for the<br />
next decade.<br />
Competitiveness is an essential part of the concept behind<br />
One Nation.<br />
Early in the statement you can read the following.<br />
" The Keating government's goal is an internationally<br />
competitive economy that continually strives for world best<br />
performance and provides equal opportunities for all Its<br />
citizens one nation, co-operating at home and winning<br />
abroad". Read in one context, you might take this to mean that I am<br />
about to give you another one of those boring economic<br />
speeches. And shudder. Or yawn.<br />
. aut I-ask you-to read those words in the context of this<br />
gathering tonig.; ht.'<br />
The values we are honouring tonight are those of<br />
competition. rhey, are also the values of participation and<br />
equity. Tonight we are paying tribute to people whose personal<br />
ambition and personal effort lifts the national ambition and<br />
the national efEfort.<br />
~ JT7JLR1l( O </p>
<p>These awards are a measure of the value of the competitive<br />
spirit. But the value of participation is equally reflected.<br />
For the achievements we honour here tonight, it has to be<br />
said, have bee~ n made against the odds.<br />
Take the Olympics.<br />
The Olympic hockey competition which the Australian women's<br />
team won in Seoul was only the second to be held.<br />
The women's marathon was not introduced until 1984. The<br />
men's was first run in 490 BC1<br />
Unfortunately we can't blame it all on the International<br />
Olympic Committee.<br />
Of the 76 national sporting organisations in Australia, only<br />
14 have women in the top administrative position.<br />
Of the 6.5 million members of sporting organisations in<br />
Australia only a quarter are women.<br />
It has to be said, therefore, that to some extent our women<br />
athletes have -cone it against the odds.<br />
Their achievements, of course, are outstanding.<br />
For a very long time Australian women athletes have been at<br />
the absolute pinnacle of international sport.<br />
Their successes are measures of ourselves of our<br />
confidence, of our' values. They are cultural measures.<br />
Sport is one area where women can be numbered among the<br />
Australian lege~ nds I mean the likes of MarJorie Jackson,<br />
Heather McKay, Dawn Fraser, Betty Cuthbert, Evonne<br />
Goolagong, Shane Gould. These names mean more than sporting<br />
success: each of them stands for character for something<br />
which we identify as Australian.<br />
The list, of course, is much longer than that.<br />
And it should be said that any list of Australian sporting<br />
greats would have to include the hockey team, who recently<br />
-beat . the Geirmans, the cricket -team who beat the English, and<br />
the netball team wh~ o beat New Zealand in one of the great<br />
sports highlights of last year.<br />
Now a government cannot make people competitive we cannot<br />
insist that our athletes become the best in the world, any<br />
more than we can insist that Australian companies become the<br />
best in the world.<br />
But we can do a lot to create the conditions which will give<br />
us the best chance. </p>
<p>3<br />
That's what wet're doing with the economy and the industrial<br />
culture. That's what we want to do with sport.<br />
We want to broaden the base of the pyramid.<br />
That means giving every Australian, regardless of gender,<br />
every opportunity to participate in sporting activities.<br />
There is no better way to increase the numbers who reach the<br />
top no better way to increase the chances for women to<br />
realise their highest ambitions.<br />
But it will be Just as important for those women and men<br />
whose sporting ambitions are more modest.<br />
I mean those who want to play sport at anW level of<br />
expertise or exertion and I am not merely thinking of my<br />
own tennis those who want to play sport for its social and<br />
recreational value.<br />
Beyond all this, of course, lie the physical, communal and<br />
spiritual values which every nation needs and which sport is<br />
uniquely capable of supplying.<br />
We should remember that, when we exclude women in any way at<br />
all from sport, we exclude them from sharing in the<br />
expression of -those values and, what is more important,<br />
from shaping them.<br />
The idea of One Nation is the idea of inclusion.<br />
The idea of closing gaps between places and people. Of<br />
building partnerships. Of making the most of all our<br />
resources and Australian women surely number among the<br />
greatest of thom.<br />
In sport, as in every other aspect of our national life, it<br />
is our intention to lower the drawbridge and let all<br />
Australians in.,<br />
There is more 1to do there nearly always is but in a<br />
number of ways, from broad social and economic reforms, to<br />
specific programs like the Women's Sport in Media project,<br />
the Gender Equity Guidelines and the Active Girls campaign,<br />
mo~ nrore women are finding the! r -aif ntth e niaional<br />
life, including the sporting life of Australia.<br />
In this the efforts of my colleagues, Roe Kelly and Wendy<br />
Fatin, should riot go unacknowledged. Both have been and will<br />
continue to be great contributors, great encouragers great<br />
at creating opportunities and openings.<br />
By recognising those individuals and corporations who<br />
encourage women in sport, and who create the opportunities,<br />
these awards play their part in the goals of excellence and </p>
<p>4<br />
participation which is in essence the goal of national<br />
growth. I said that we want to see partnerships: tonight we see them<br />
between government and corporate sponsors, between<br />
community, medlia and sporting organisations, between men and<br />
women. I want to thanxk and congratulate all those who have played<br />
such constructive parts in women's sport, and take this<br />
opportunity to express the hope that these awards will<br />
rapidly come to play their part in advancing the cause.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
