<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9708</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN, A CURRENT AFFAIR, AUSTRALIA REMEMBERS, 15 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009708.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1 -tv"<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN, A CURRENT AFFAIR, AUSTRALIA<br />
REMEMBERS, 15 AUGUST 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
RM: Prime Minister, thanks for your time.<br />
PM: Good Ray.<br />
RM: Were children, Australian children a deliberate target of this Australia<br />
Remembers campaign?<br />
PM: I think the whole nation was, but we had hoped that young Australians<br />
most appreciated it too because while we now look at the diggers on<br />
Anzac Day or today and we see people 60 or 70 years of age, there is<br />
always the impression of thinking about them. But, it was them as<br />
young people. It was them in their teens and their twenties. And so,<br />
the young Australians of today are, in some respects, entitled to<br />
picture themselves in that picture. So, if we can't make the linkage to<br />
them, in a sense we are failing in the remembrance.<br />
RM: Yes. Some of them said to us today when they saw the veterans<br />
marching today that they felt like crying and some cried. Have you felt<br />
like crying?<br />
PM: Yes, absolutely. But, I was most touched at Kokoda, as I was saying<br />
earlier today, that there is a little green square at Kokoda where the<br />
mists were, the morning tropical mists and as it rose young Australians<br />
of 18 years of age in shorts and singlets fought the best crack troops<br />
that the Japanese Imperial Army could throw at them and there the<br />
defence of Australia began in the hands of 18 year olds. These are<br />
the images, I think, which do bring you to tears.<br />
RM: The vets have said to me over the last couple of days when we have<br />
talked to them that the image that they recall most, that they have<br />
loved the most, has been children waving to them on the train with<br />
balloons. </p>
<p>PM: Yes because it was about, you had to have this view of Australia, your<br />
belief in Australia to fight the fight. It had to be about your family and<br />
the children and so the sentiments for which they fought and died are<br />
the very same things which are ringing a bell with them now. I mean,<br />
seeing young people interested in it and thanking them for it is very<br />
sentimental for them.<br />
RM: Yes, but I would have thought there was a generation gap especially<br />
with the younger people who are 10 or 12 or 14, but clearly there<br />
hasn't. This has brought them together.<br />
PM: Yes, I hope that the whole series of remembrances and ceremonies<br />
has brought into sharp focus what it means and we need to make the<br />
point because our troubles all started in this century in 1914 in<br />
Sarajevo and here we are in 1995 in Sarajevo.<br />
RM: It is a terrible irony isn't it?<br />
PM: And it means that we can never be sanguine about liberty or<br />
democracy and that we always need to guard it and value it and<br />
understand how it has been protected.<br />
RM: A very quick question, have the Japanese now apologised, do you<br />
accept the Prime Minister's statement as an apology?<br />
PM: I think it is a very comprehensive apology and the most pleasing<br />
element to it is his sentiment that he wishes to tell the younger<br />
generation of Japanese people about the mistake in policies of the<br />
past and to go the international way of peace and freedom and not<br />
misplaced nationalism. These are sentiments I have not heard from a<br />
Japanese head of government before.<br />
RM: Strong enough for you?<br />
PM: Yes, some will say in Australia, well it should have come from the Diet<br />
or somewhere else, but Mr Murayama is the Prime Minister of Japan<br />
and he speaks for the nation of Japan. It is a very comprehensive<br />
statement.<br />
RM: Thanks for your time, have a good night.<br />
PM: Thank you Ray.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
