<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8452</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP ALP BUSINESS LUNCHEON, GREAT HALL NATIONAL GALLERY MELBOURNE 12.30 PM, WEDNESDAY 11 MARCH 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008452.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
ALP BUSINESS LUNCHEON, GREAT HALL NATIONAL GALLERY MELBOURNE<br />
12.3OPM, WEDNESDAY 11 MARCH 1992<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Your experience over the years has probably led you to<br />
expect today the familiar post-Budget urge. The old gee-up<br />
speech, in which I tell you what the Budget means and why<br />
it's good for you, and urge you to get out there and do what<br />
you do best.<br />
This time is different.<br />
Today I want to thank you. I want to thank you for your<br />
contribution to the Government's Economic Statement the<br />
commitment to this country that you displayed, your<br />
willingness to offer constructive ideas.<br />
It was a much better Statement for it.<br />
And I want to thank you for your endorsement of it because<br />
the general response from business has been terrific.<br />
That's very important for everyone' s confidence.<br />
I think there is a general opinion now that there is only<br />
one way to go and that is towards growth and recovery.<br />
There is most certainly a . general conviction that we have to<br />
create jobs.<br />
And we have to start doing that now.<br />
Of course the Economic Statement was not a Budget speech<br />
it was much bigger than a Budget. </p>
<p>It ranged very widely across the Australian economy and<br />
society. But its target was very specifically Recovery.<br />
We called it: One Nation with that in mind.<br />
When, after all the discussions, we looked at the measures<br />
we'd come up with the measures we decided would do most to<br />
bring on recovery, we realised that there was a very strong<br />
theme running through them.<br />
And the more we thought about it the more we realised it was<br />
no accident.<br />
We realised that almost every significant measure was<br />
calculated to give us greater strength by harnessing more<br />
efficiently our human and material resources.<br />
I<br />
One Nation aims to close the gaps on a vast continent<br />
where population centres and markets are separated by<br />
great distances<br />
where our political evolution has frequently been out<br />
of tune with our economic development and potential<br />
where, at least until very recently, our industrial<br />
culture has contained its own great distances<br />
and where, if we are to emerge from this recession<br />
stronger than ever and make the great leap into the twenty<br />
first century, at this moment in our history we need all the<br />
social and economic cohesion we can muster.<br />
We called it One Nation because its aim is to forge<br />
partnerships, create efficient cooperative workplaces,<br />
involve more people in the life of the nation and include<br />
them in the : recovery, educate more people and link our<br />
cities and hinterland and ports by the greatest one-off<br />
overhaul of infrastructure for generations.<br />
I believe it is the combination of elements which makes the<br />
Statement strong it is not just an economic package, it<br />
has a certain chemistry to it.<br />
It calls up the resources of our people as well as our<br />
economic. resources. It addresses our weaknesses and calls<br />
up our strengths and one of those strengths, I believe, is<br />
our passion for this country. </p>
<p>In tough times, in historic times as these are, that belief<br />
in our country is very important. A sense of purpose is<br />
very important.<br />
That's why Dr Hewson is so wrong about what he describes as<br />
the nationalist diversion.<br />
He is wrong to think I intend it as a diversion.<br />
He is wrong to think that it could only be a diversion.<br />
He is certainly wrong to think that calling on Australians<br />
to take whole-hearted pride in themselves and their country<br />
is the action of a scoundrel.<br />
Dr Hewson's problem is that he can only follow the textbook,<br />
only obey the ideological reflexes there is no heartbeat<br />
in either of them.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
One Nation is a four year strategy designed to get things<br />
moving. To produce jobs and reduce unemployment.<br />
And to do so in a manner that contributes to a stronger,<br />
more productive economy for the 1990s.<br />
It stimulates business investment and provides a more<br />
efficient and reliable transport system.<br />
It encourages large projects and small business enterprise<br />
alike. It further opens the economy to competition, while providing<br />
enterprises with the ability to respond to the challenges of<br />
competition by encouraging improved work practices.<br />
It improves skills and career prospects, while providing<br />
greater incentives for individuals to take on added<br />
responsibility. And it does this while reinforcing a low inflation culture.<br />
While producing a fairer Australia.<br />
In total, One Nation is a comprehensive and integrated<br />
strategy that will provide the platform for a stronger<br />
Australia, an Australia better able to grow in an<br />
increasingly competitive world. </p>
<p>RECOVERY Our first task is to generate growth.<br />
The high level of unemployment is bringing great hardship to<br />
many families.<br />
We have to bring it down.<br />
And we can bring it down.<br />
Australia is much better placed now than it has been coming<br />
out of earlier recessions.<br />
Inflation is low, profits are high for this stage of the<br />
cycle, and the benefits of past structural reforms are<br />
coming through.<br />
In addition, our, sound underlying Budget position allows us<br />
to provide a fiscal boost now.<br />
We have not stood back and left the economy solely to market<br />
forces as the Opposition would have us do.<br />
Their prescription to get us out of this recession is to<br />
wait and hope.<br />
Instead we have a sensible program of spending and tax<br />
incentives amounting to 1/ 2 per cent of GDP over the next<br />
year to get us moving again.<br />
Coming on top of the stimulus of lower interest rates, the<br />
cyclical unwinding of the budget surplus, and a turnaround<br />
in farm product,, this should see GDP grow by around 4 3/ 4<br />
per cent in : L992-93.<br />
A MORE PRODUCTIVE ECONOMY<br />
Lifting employment and restoring confidence is the immediate<br />
priority. The strength of One Nation is that it does this at the same<br />
time as providing the foundations for a sustained lift in<br />
Australia's productive capacity.<br />
Such a lift in capacity will only be achieved with a private<br />
sector able to respond to today's challenges.<br />
The Government can and will help.<br />
We will provide appropriate incentives, skills and the<br />
infrastructure to support enterprise. </p>
<p>We will not prop up inefficiencies, but we will help<br />
adjustments and direct our limited resources to the areas<br />
where they can be of most use.<br />
Equally, we will not be relying on the hope that market<br />
forces alone will deliver the goods.<br />
It is the Opposition's policy to withdraw from the problem.<br />
Ours is to engage it.<br />
The boost from the Budget will help the recovery get<br />
underway, but as the private sector picks up, we will wind<br />
the Budget back and bring it into surplus by 1995-96.<br />
We will not give away the sound underlying structure of the<br />
Budget we have worked so hard to achieve.<br />
Nor will we let the gains on inflation slip.<br />
Our agreement with the union movement will keep wages<br />
growth, on average, at a rate consistent with keeping our<br />
inflation rate comparable to that of our major trading<br />
partners. This is the key to achieving a low inflation culture.<br />
To making the 1990s a low inflation decade.<br />
Economic recovery, a sensible fiscal policy, and low<br />
inflation will provide the basic environment for renewed<br />
private sector enterprise.<br />
One Nation does this and much more.<br />
I<br />
It will improve the structural or micro elements of the<br />
economy that are so important to private sector decisionmaking.<br />
We need: workplaces that are responsive to change;<br />
a skilled and motivated labour force;<br />
a reliable and efficient infrastructure;<br />
an appropriate tax regime; and<br />
a competitive environment where the best are<br />
rewarded.<br />
One Nation addresses each of these factors. </p>
<p>WORKPLACE REFORM<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
We all know that inflexible workplaces have harmed<br />
performance in the past.<br />
To deliver lasting change in industrial relations we need<br />
employers, unions and government working together.<br />
In this we have made quite remarkable progress. A<br />
centrepiece of Labor's strategy is working.<br />
The Opposition claims that Industrial Relations reform is<br />
also a centrepiece of their strategy.<br />
Yet curiously they devote just three quarters of a page to<br />
it in Fightback.<br />
And what they say there is ill-defined and potentially very<br />
damaging. Predictably it is about confrontation, strengthening the<br />
Trade Practices Act and providing no support for the weak.<br />
It is all very familiar to those who remember the early<br />
1980s.<br />
Confrontation and inflation.<br />
For on top of the GST slug, the Opposition industrial<br />
relations policy will be very inflationary.<br />
What we need a wages policy that will entrench a ' Low<br />
inflation culture and reform the workplace is increasingly<br />
what we have.<br />
More than 40 enterprise agreements have been ratified by the<br />
Industrial Relations Commission since the implementation of<br />
the enterprise bargaining principle last October.<br />
This process will accelerate and we will help it by amending<br />
the certified agreements provisions of the 1988 Industrial<br />
Relations Act to make them more conducive for parties to<br />
negotiate at the~ workplace.<br />
ASKILLED WORKFORCEFlexible<br />
workplaces with a skilled workforce will make the<br />
1990s a more prosperous decade.<br />
We have already done a lot in this regard. </p>
<p>School retention rates have almost doubled since 1983.<br />
The number of Commonwealth funded places at universities<br />
will have increased by 50 per cent by 1994.<br />
These dramatic changes will now be matched in technical and<br />
vocational training.<br />
With an extra $ 720 million of Commonwealth money over the<br />
next three years, and by working with the States, we will<br />
create thousands more places and lift the quality of<br />
vocational education.<br />
One Nation also directs more resources to improving<br />
training, both for those entering the workforce for the<br />
first time and for those currently unemployed:<br />
* we have substantially raised the incentives for emplo<br />
yers to take on apprentices and trainees.<br />
we have increased funds for JOBSTART and JOBSKILL, two<br />
programs that are well targetted to assist long-term<br />
unemployed back into employment.<br />
I NFRASTRUCTURE<br />
For business to compete effectively in Australia and the<br />
world, we need reliable and efficient transport.<br />
We have built up the National Highway System in recent<br />
years, and now, with One Nation we will set aside $ 600<br />
million to upgrade roads over the next two years.<br />
We will thus create jobs quickly, and create a better system<br />
in our cities and on the long hauls between Adelaide,<br />
Melbourne, Sydney and Brisbane.<br />
Strategic investments to straighten rail lines and<br />
strengthen br7idges, and to provide more passing loops, will<br />
see rail transit times reduced and made more reliable 12<br />
hours, reliably, between Melbourne and Sydney by 1994.<br />
We will final~ ly have a standard gauge line connecting our<br />
capital citiE&amp; s from Brisbane to Perth.<br />
Here in Melbourne we will put $ 20 million into upgrading the<br />
terminal at South Dynon and a further $ 5 million connecting<br />
South.. Dynon to. Swanston and Appleton Docks.<br />
The end result will be a rail system able to compete with<br />
road, and a rLetwork of competitive capital city ports. </p>
<p>We are very much aware that upgrading the infrastructure in.<br />
rail will only produce the necessary improvements with<br />
better work practices.<br />
Accordingly, our spending is conditional on commitments by<br />
unions to a Greenfields enterprise agreement with the<br />
National Rai~ l Corporation.<br />
A COMPETITIVE ENVIRONMENT<br />
For the money spent on public investment projects to yield<br />
the maximum benefits, not only are flexible workplaces<br />
required, bu~ t a competitive environment.<br />
Management must perform; the best will be well rewarded.<br />
Labor's reforms over the past 9 years have opened Australia<br />
up to greater competition.<br />
For example, our exporters of manufactured goods have made<br />
remarkable inroads into overseas markets, with manufactured<br />
exports increasing at an annual rate of 10.5 per cent since<br />
1982-83.<br />
They have increased by over 20 per cent in the past two<br />
years. We will continue to integrate the economy into the<br />
international economy with phased reductions in tariffs.<br />
We have exposed other sectors, such as telecommunications<br />
and banking, to competition at home.<br />
One Nation takes this process further.<br />
It introduces revolutionary change to aviation, and the<br />
transmission of electricity.<br />
Among other measures to make the banking sector more<br />
responsive to change, additional foreign bank licenses will<br />
be permitted, subject to prudential standards.<br />
SMALL BUSINESS<br />
This government places a very high value on the small<br />
business sector.'<br />
Small-businesses employ, more.. than 2 million Australians, or<br />
nearly half of the workforce in the private sector.<br />
They are a powerful source of employment, of innovation, and<br />
of rising living standards. </p>
<p>Small business is often the way in which Australians can<br />
improve their lives, and improve their country at the same<br />
time. In our One Nation program, we have taken concrete steps to<br />
strengthen small business not with handouts, but with real<br />
incentives to grow, to innovate, to export and to create<br />
jobs.<br />
We have: substantially increased the capital gains tax relief<br />
for small and growing businesses, to increase capital<br />
mobility and flexibility in the sector.<br />
granted. a three month extension for 1991/ 92 company tax<br />
payments for small business.<br />
tripled the funding to $ 12 million for helping small<br />
businesses ' into export markets through our " Export<br />
Access" program.<br />
provided for the establishment of Pooled Development<br />
Funds which will be able to channel equity capital into<br />
businesses with assets of less than $ 30 million.<br />
In addition, small business, like all business, will benefit<br />
from the other measures in One Nation such as a more skilled<br />
workforce and the new depreciation rules.<br />
All these measures will help small business perform.<br />
We are about helping business succeed, not adding burdens as<br />
the Opposition proposes.<br />
Dr Hewson's new tax will create more than 800,000 tax<br />
collection points.<br />
Business people can forget their Sunday afternoons with his<br />
consumption tax-Sundays will be spent doing the books.<br />
It is a small business nightmare, but an accountant's dream.<br />
No wonder six large accountancy firms are funding Mr<br />
Hewson's GST planning and co-ordination office in Sydney!<br />
A FAIRER AUSTRALIA<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, a healthy efficient economy is a means<br />
to an end that end is a good society.<br />
One Nation builds on our very proud record on social<br />
justice. </p>
<p>Fundamental to making Australia a fairer society is to<br />
create jobs and reduce unemployment.<br />
We did this in 1983 and we will do it again.<br />
Despite the recent declines in employment, we have created<br />
an additional 1 1/ 2 million jobs since 1983.<br />
This has allowed many new entrants, especially women, to<br />
establish themselves in the workforce.<br />
Indeed, female employment has risen by more than 900,000<br />
over this period.<br />
The measures: introduced in One Nation will see strong<br />
employment growth restored.<br />
Over 800,000 new jobs will be created over the next 4 years.<br />
One Nation also will help many of those jobs go to the longterm<br />
unemployed who currently are facing particular<br />
hardship. The successes we had in the ' 80s in lifting employment and<br />
investment and bringing down inflation were achieved in<br />
large part through restraint by the bulk of full-time wage<br />
and salary earners.<br />
Their wage increases were responsible while many of the<br />
benefits flowing from tax cuts were largely directed at<br />
lower incomes.<br />
As a result, many workers are now facing undesirably high<br />
tax rates on. their additional earnings.<br />
One Nation will ensure that the great bulk of workers will<br />
face a maximum marginal rate of 30 per cent.<br />
Those on incomes below $ 20,700 face a marginal tax rate of<br />
cents in the dollar, a rate that was 30 cents when we<br />
came to office.<br />
In addition, for many on low incomes, Government support is<br />
very important.<br />
Labor has targetted social security and welfare spending<br />
effectively so that those in genuine need are now receiving<br />
much more substantial support.<br />
One Nation will preserve these gains and in some areas<br />
extend them.<br />
i </p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen<br />
I could conclude by saying a great many things about Dr<br />
Hewson's Fightback package, but today I shall mention just<br />
one curious and salutary point.<br />
In it he says that he will privatise Australia's ports.<br />
This is very curious.<br />
The Commonwealth of Australia does not own any ports<br />
except ports in the Antarctic, the jetty on Cocos Island,<br />
the port on Christmas Island and the defence jetty at Jervis<br />
Bay. Is this the one he means? Will he also privatise the navy?<br />
Will all shipping on Lake Burley Griffin be sold to<br />
privateers? I mention this because it is an example of our opponents'<br />
ideological blinkers, the obsessive and rigid nature of<br />
their thinking.<br />
Nothing not even facts or common sense will get in Dr<br />
Hewson's way.<br />
You will find significant differences in One Nation. Not<br />
just significant policy differences.<br />
*-like we will upgrade infrastructure but they think<br />
that' s irresponsible.<br />
-we will expand TAFE but they think that's irresponsible<br />
too. Etcetera etcetera., whatever does not fit with<br />
Fightback is per se irresponsible.<br />
But you will see more than these differences. You will see<br />
a fundamental philosophical difference.<br />
One addresses social and business reality, the other<br />
addresses an. ideology.<br />
One is a living and breathing program for Australia, the<br />
other says cur future can be best determined by a sterile<br />
exercise in accountancy.<br />
One recognises people as significant factors in recovery, as<br />
significant.. f actors in an-economy.-the other does not.<br />
One does not want a Recovery.<br />
We do.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
