<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4367</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/04/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004367.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PROME MIMSTER<br />
FOR PRESS 17 APRIL 1977<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
In an historic move, the Federal Government and every state<br />
government, has agreed to work together to break the wage<br />
and price merry go round -one of the central causes of<br />
inflation. Premiers from every state -both Labor and non-Labor<br />
and the Federal Government, unanimously agreed to put t'. aeir<br />
weight behind the call for a three month pause in price rises<br />
and wage increases.<br />
We have called for manufacturers, wholesalers, retailers, professional<br />
bodies and business firms to voluntarily hold prices at<br />
existing levels.<br />
Already, a reference has been made to the Prices Justification<br />
Tribunal a body that can help contain prices.<br />
The PJT is a body of considerable influence and its influence<br />
will be used.<br />
There has not yet been one company that has gone outside its<br />
general recommendations. Some firms have reduced prices and<br />
charges as a result of the PJT's recommendations.<br />
So clearly it will continue to carry great weight in the move to<br />
keep prices down. It will survey the prices htfl. and-report<br />
on its findings.<br />
We have also called on employees to agree to a voluntary wage<br />
pause at the same time.<br />
In these endeavours, we are seeking the closest co-operation of<br />
employer organisations and trade unions and already the signs<br />
of co= operation are most encouraging.<br />
our call to all Australians is a call to put aside sectional<br />
interests for the good of the nation. We have not sought to<br />
coerce or force any group into any course of action. Wie have<br />
simply appealed to the good sense of men and women running<br />
business and to the men and women heading trade unions. Our </p>
<p>-2<br />
our message is plain. Hold off increases in prices and wages<br />
for three months. Hold off seeking personal gain at the expense<br />
of someone else. Give it a fair go, and put Australia first.<br />
There is no doubt that if Austr alians give this a fair chance<br />
to work, then we can break the back of inflation. I want Australians<br />
to understand clearly that this is a wonderful opportunity to break<br />
the link in the ever-revolving and vicious wage/ price spiral.<br />
It is a wonderful opportunity to consolidate on the good start<br />
we have already made in beating inflation.<br />
I think we are all now too well aware that excessive wage increases<br />
and its consequences have been the central cause of our high<br />
inflation over the last few years.<br />
We know that higher wages lead to higher prices. This in turn<br />
leads to our products pricing themselves out of the market here<br />
and overseas. The inevitable result has been increased unemployment<br />
It is for this very reason that the Government has been arguing<br />
strongly for wage restraint ever since we were elected.<br />
This call for a wage and price pause comes at an opportune time.<br />
Australians have just received a wage increase from the last<br />
Arbitration Commission hearing. Additionally, from July 1, wage<br />
earners will benefit again from tax indexation which will put<br />
about $ 4.50 a week extra into the pay packet of an average family<br />
of four on average earnings.<br />
I am absolutely certain that trade unionists see the benefits in a<br />
voluntary wage and price patise. Wives of unionists know too the<br />
exasperating experience of receiving extra cash, only to see it<br />
evaporate because of monotonously increasing prices at the<br />
supermarket.<br />
I want to make the point that businessmen do have a special<br />
responsibility in this call for a voluntary pause in prices and<br />
wages. If they do not conscientiously keep prices at present levels, then<br />
the call will have been of little avail.<br />
It is precisely because of its voluntary nature that I expect every<br />
businessman in Australia from the largest manufacturer to the<br />
smallest corner store to keep faith.<br />
If a business says it must pass on cost increases already in the<br />
pipeline, he has perhaps misunderstood, or misinterpreted the<br />
proposal. / Of </p>
<p>-3<br />
Of course, wages are a major component of cost and the 5.70<br />
increase from the last wage case will be concerning some<br />
businesses. However, with a commitment from business to<br />
hold prices, then a significant benefit will flow through to them.<br />
This is because it will be infinitely easier to command wide<br />
support for the wage pause in the next three months. That would<br />
mean a halt to increases in major costs of businesses.<br />
The Government is pleased at the response to the wage and price<br />
halt.<br />
Many comapnies, many employer organisations, have indicated firm<br />
agreement with the plan.<br />
The Prices Justification Tribunal was immediately asked to monitor<br />
and report on price movements and to defer decisions on -price<br />
applications before it.<br />
Some companies have agreed not to implement price increases already<br />
approved by the PJT before last Thursday.<br />
All this means that recent wage increases will be absorbed by<br />
companies at this time and not passed on in the form of higher<br />
prices. In addition, the Government now proposes that in the event of<br />
broad agreement from the union movement on the wage/ price halt,<br />
a special group comprising representatives of employers, unions,<br />
and the PJT, will be formed to advise Government on the overall<br />
progress of the wage/ price halt.<br />
Such a group would also be able to advise whether or not further<br />
amendments to the Prices Justification Tribunal Act should be<br />
introduced to lend support to the implementation of the wage/ price<br />
halt. Such a body could also act in a general advisory way to the Government<br />
in implementing the wage/ price halt.<br />
With all these developments what happens within the Arbitration<br />
Commission and the response of the union movement will of course<br />
be critical.<br />
With the pause in wages and gices, at the end of three months we<br />
would be better off as a nation. Better off because inflation could<br />
be lower and still coming down, and better off because t~ he repetitive<br />
wage/ price spiral will have been broken.<br />
Business would know that wages -their major cost would not be<br />
going up for three months. That is a great incentive. Wage earners<br />
and trade unionists would get the relief from price increases. / Everyone </p>
<p>4<br />
Everyone business and trade union, employers and employees<br />
have a clear obligation to play the game.<br />
Clearly, however, no single decision of the Prices Justification<br />
Tribunal or the Arbitration Commission will ensure the success of<br />
this call.<br />
For success there must be a total commitment from all organisations<br />
and all people to make it work to put Australia first.<br />
Australia now has a unique opportunity to demonstrate just how<br />
much we really want to beat inflation.<br />
The opportunity is in our hands. I am confident that Australians<br />
will want to get behind their Governments and make it work. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
