<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3180</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S VISIT TO SOUTH EAST ASIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/03/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003180_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
,7<br />
NQ DATE<br />
M4/ 36 7 March 1974<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S VISIT TO SOUTH EAST ASIA<br />
The following is the text of a statement in<br />
the House of Representatives by the Prime Minister,<br />
The Hon. E. G. Whitlam, M4. P., Thursday 7 March 1974:-<br />
Mr Speaker-In this, the first week of the new session of<br />
Parliament, I wish to report to the House and to the Australian<br />
people on my recent visit to South East Asia. I believe that<br />
visit advanced Auistralia's national interests in a region of<br />
c ontinuing and increasing importance to this country.<br />
No one in this House would deny that Australia and the<br />
countries of South East Asia share profolind and lasting common<br />
interests. No one in this House would deny that the maintenance<br />
of close relationships with these countries is one of several<br />
important challenges facing Austra~ lian foreign policy. The<br />
confluence of our history and geography our mainly European<br />
origins and our location on the edge. of South East Asia<br />
affords us a unique opportunity to demonstrate that countries<br />
with different cultural, ethnic, social and religious backgrounds<br />
can evolve intimate and lasting relationships. The Government<br />
is determined to seize that opportunity and to ensure that<br />
Australia is accepted as a good neighbour and a co-operative<br />
and helpful. member of the Asian and Pacific region.<br />
I visited lialaysia from 28 to 31 January, Thailand from<br />
31 January to 4 February, Laos on 4 February, Burma from<br />
4 to 6 February, Singapore from 6 to 9 February and the<br />
Philippines from 10 to 13 February. I also paid a brief visit<br />
to the Malaysian Air Force Base at Butterworth where our Mirage<br />
squadrons are stationed and a brief private visit to<br />
Kota Kinabalu at the invitation of an old friend, the former<br />
Malaysian High Commissioner to Australia and Dean of the<br />
Diplomatic Corps and present Governor of Sabah, Tan Sri Stephens.<br />
-1 </p>
<p>I have now visited, in the 15 months since the<br />
Government came into office, virtually all the major countries<br />
in the Asian and Pacific region. No former Prime Minister has<br />
done more. Visits by the Prime Minister and other ministers<br />
symbolise the importance that the Australian Government attaches<br />
to the countries visited. But there is more to it than that;<br />
the results which will flow from my visit will, I believe,<br />
advance our interests and involvement in this region to a new<br />
level. I had four main objectives in undertaking this visit,<br />
I believe I succeeded in fulfilling them.<br />
My first and perhaps my principal objective was to<br />
emphasise to leaders in South East Asia the continuing and<br />
undiminished importance which my Government attaches to its<br />
relations with the countries of South East Asia. I wanted to<br />
explain to them that wha~ t had changed was not the degree of<br />
Australian involvement in the region but the nature and<br />
direction of that involvement. I wanted to make clear that<br />
our emphasis had shifted from an involvement based mainly on<br />
ideological considerations and military alliances to one based<br />
c _, snore enduring ties such as trade, aid programs, regional<br />
co-operation, ecornomic co-operation, and the development of a<br />
network of cultural contacts and agreements.<br />
My second objective was to establish or reinforce<br />
personal contacts with South East Asian Heads of Government.<br />
I was able to have very frank and detail ed talks with them,<br />
My third objective was to outline to Government leaders<br />
in the region the positive character of the Australian<br />
Government's foreign policy and to dispel any misunderstandings<br />
about it. My fourth objective was to seek practical and enduring<br />
ways in which co-operation between Australia and the countries<br />
of the region can be strengthened.<br />
In all the countries I visited Australia has, and always<br />
will have, an important influence. While our foreign policy<br />
interests have been diversified and our horizons are now wider </p>
<p>than the United States, the United Kingdom and South East Asiavie<br />
no longer ignore, for example, the existence of Communist<br />
Asia, including China with its 800,000,000 people the fact<br />
remains that it is in our own immediate neighbourhood that we<br />
are most likely to find an effective role for Australia. I<br />
found that the new friendships which we have developed with<br />
countries like China and North Viet-Nlam have in no way diminished<br />
our traditional friendships with the countries I visited. If<br />
anything, they have enhanced our standing in them and increased<br />
their interest in us.<br />
Foreign policy cannot be created in a vacuum. It must<br />
grow out of national aspirations and patterns of events in our<br />
environment. We need to take account of the evolving Great<br />
Power relaticnships. In the sixties the main thrust of<br />
United States policy in this area was the containment of China<br />
by military involvement in Viet-Nam. But the United States has<br />
itself opened up new opportunities by abandoning these policies;<br />
itv no longer looks to Australia to provide a mere supporting<br />
echo of policies which it has itself progressively abandoned.<br />
As Dr Kissing-er, the most realistic and pragmatic<br />
necotiator to fill the office of Secretary of State, has shown,<br />
initiatives in foreign affairs open up new possibilities for<br />
progress and understanding. Such initiatives will not always<br />
produce predictable or entirely desirable results, but log-jams<br />
are broken, stale habits of mind are abandoned, and movement is<br />
often pre ferable to a dogged perseverance with an outmoded<br />
status quo. Like most of the leaders I met, I believe that detente<br />
between the Great Powers must be made to work. The journey down<br />
this road has begun. It wil~ l not be smooth. Peace and security<br />
do not come simply because we wish them to come. But diplomacy<br />
must be based on realistic hopes rather than on resignation and<br />
despair. It was in this spirit that I went to South East Asia.<br />
And it was this spirit which evoked such a warm response. I<br />
recall, in particular, the remarks by the Prime Minister of<br />
Singapore at a dinner he gave for my delegation. I shall seek<br />
leave to table the text of that speech, and all other p~ incipal<br />
speeches during my visit, later this evening. </p>
<p>TRADE AND ECONOMIC LINKS<br />
I turn now to trade. I believe that increasingly our<br />
foreign policy in South East Asia will be related to our efforts<br />
to develop mutually advantageous trade. In each country I<br />
visited I expected, and found, keen interest in closer trading<br />
and economic links with Australia.<br />
Australia has long established and valued trading ties<br />
with all the countries I visited0 Last year we had a favourable<br />
trade balance of $ 225 million with these countries and we<br />
expect this favourable balance to increase in the short term.<br />
Our exports last year to these countries totalled $ 318 million,<br />
of which over 40% were manufacturers; our imports from them<br />
were $ 93 million. It can be seen that this situation, while<br />
advantageous to us now, could generate friction if neglected.<br />
So in each country I made a point of explaining the 25% tariff<br />
cut made by the Government in July last year and the greatly<br />
expanded scheme of tariff preferences for developing countries<br />
which came into force on 1 January. I told them of the special<br />
s ervice which has been established in the Department of Overseas<br />
Trade to help developing countries in market research and<br />
-om-inercial contacts. I arranged for experts from Australia.<br />
to visit all the countries on my itinerary, as well as Indorñ-sit,<br />
in March and April. This will ensure that new preferences and<br />
trading opportunities are understood and that the countries<br />
concerned can take full advantage of them. These experts will<br />
also visit a number of other developing countries later in the<br />
year. I elaborated on the statement on Australian investment<br />
policy which the Government issued on 22 January** I emphasised<br />
that, for the first time, an Australian Government had adopted.<br />
a co-operative and creative role in encouraging Australian<br />
investment overseas, particularly in South East Asia. I made<br />
it clear that such investment must accord with the social and<br />
economic objectives of the host country and be consistent with<br />
progressive labour relations and local environmental policies.<br />
I was also able to point to the expansion of the EPIC<br />
investment insurance facilities and the creation of two<br />
separate funds, one of $ 250,000 a year and one of $ 100,000<br />
a year, to promote respectively, investment feasibility studies </p>
<p>overseas by. Australian manufacturers and investment awareness<br />
wi* thin Australia. All these policies and initiatives were warmly welcomed.<br />
I believe the ground is now laid for increased Australian<br />
investment in South East Asia. The obvious link between trade<br />
and investment and the general acceptance of Australia as a<br />
source of investment was widely recognised.<br />
We have reached understandings that our trade agreements<br />
with Malaysia and the Philippines will be updated and that new<br />
Trade Agreements with Thailand and Laos will be negotiated0<br />
A feature of such agreements will be the establishment of mixed<br />
commissions of Australian businessmen and officialsp who will<br />
meet their counterparts -in the other countries on a regular<br />
basis to examine the practical problems of two-way trade and to<br />
seek their prompt resolution.<br />
I also took the opportunity to stress the desirability,<br />
wherever practicable, of securing access to markets over a<br />
long term for the products of Australia's rural industries.<br />
Since my visit, the parties directly concerned have met to<br />
explore the possibility of long term contracts for the export<br />
~ fsubstantially increased quantities of wheat and sugar to<br />
Malaysia. An inquiry for 500,000 tons of coal from Thailand<br />
is under consideraticn and export approval has been given by<br />
the Australian Government for 1509000 tons of coal to Burma.<br />
A number of countries I visited inquired about products essential<br />
to their economic development, including nitrogenous fertilisers,<br />
steel and engineering products. These are being dealt with as<br />
a matter of urgency. An Australian investment of over $ 4 million<br />
in the forging industry in the Philippines was approved within a<br />
few days of my raising this question with President Marcos. In<br />
Thailand our offer tc assist with the establishment and training<br />
of their Trade Cominissicner Service . was accepted and the initial<br />
moves are already under way. We are also examining, as a matter<br />
of urgency, requests received during my visit for extensions to<br />
our scheme of tariff preference for developing countries.<br />
All of this provides a practical illustration of our<br />
present objective of securing a thriving and well-rounded </p>
<p>6.<br />
commercial relationship with the countries of South East As ia.<br />
The* Government's decision last October to respond positively<br />
and constructively to interest in the ASEAN countries in<br />
Australian co-operation with agreed ASEAN projects was also<br />
well received in the ASEAN capitals I visited. In fact, all<br />
our policies and initiatives in trade were accepted as evidence<br />
of our strong continuing involvement in South East Asia and<br />
our willingness to assist our Asian neighbours in genuinely<br />
constructive ways.<br />
DEFENCE During my visit I stressed on a number of occasions<br />
that although the emphasis of our policy is-changing we still<br />
retain important defence interests in South East Asia.<br />
We no longer look on the countries of South East Asia as<br />
buffer states or as some northern military line where a possible<br />
future enemy should be held. Rather, we look upon them as<br />
countries having a conmon Interest with Australia and New Zealand<br />
in consolidating the security and stability of the region as a<br />
whole. I made it clear to representatives of the L~ ao Patriotic<br />
Forces in Vientiane that Australia was concerned that all foreign<br />
countries withdraw their forces from L~ aos. I also expressed the<br />
hope that the Great Powers would cease supplying arms to North<br />
and South Viet-Nam. I said so i~ n the firm belief, which I have<br />
expressed before, that the dpportunities which were lost after<br />
the signing of the Geneva Accords of 1954 should not be lost<br />
again. The pr6spects for reconciliation and for the-formation<br />
of genuinely national governments in the countries of Indo-China<br />
would be greatly enhanced if external interference of all kinds<br />
could cease. We have pledged that the terms of the Five Power<br />
Arrangements will be honQured in full until a more enduring<br />
settlement is reached in establ~ ishing the peace, freedom and<br />
neutrality of the region. Our defence co-operation programs with<br />
countries like Malaysia, Singapore and Indonesia will be<br />
maintained. I also indicated that Australia's Mirage squadrons<br />
would remain at Butterworth as long as they are relevant to </p>
<p>7,<br />
the needs of both our nations and the realities of the region<br />
and that, as previously announced, this question would be<br />
reviewed, as appropriate by the two Governments.<br />
It has been suggested that because I believe our<br />
interest in this region have in the past been seen-excessively<br />
in terms of Defence, Australia is in some way drifting towards<br />
isolationism. I repeat categorically what I said several time s<br />
in South East Asia: Isolationism is not a policy option for<br />
Australia. It is precisely because I thought that we were<br />
isolating ourselves from a quarter of the world's population in<br />
China, and to some extent, from Black Africa and Europe east of<br />
the Elbe, that I have stressed since December 1972, the<br />
Government's wish to diversify its foreign policy interests.<br />
In fact, in both action and philosophy, I believe that my<br />
Government is the most genuinely internationalist government<br />
Australia has had.<br />
RACE, CUTUTRE AITD . IMIGRAT ION<br />
The Government's attempts to rid Australia of any<br />
lingering racist image are very warmly welcomed in South East<br />
Asia. They are especially welcomed in Singapore and the<br />
Prillippines. Race is a transcending international and moral issue.<br />
I am not prepared to allow the bridges that have been built to<br />
the countries of Asia, and which are currently being widened and<br />
strengthened by the Government's policies, to be undermined by<br />
stigma of racism. The Minister for Immigration and his Department<br />
are working -to ensure that there are no gaps between our<br />
enunciated principles and our administrative practices. As I<br />
said in Manila, we want no double standards in this matter.<br />
I was particularly concerned in Manila to explain to<br />
President Marcos the Government's uncompromising opposition to<br />
racism in all its forms and to assure him that our immigration<br />
policy is non-discriminatory. I was able to announce that the<br />
Government had given its agreement in principle to the entry of<br />
Philippine skilled workers for the L~ eyland Factory in Sydney.<br />
A team is to go to Manila next week to help select the<br />
immigrants who will come to Australia. U, </p>
<p>.1 .7. XZU-. iZ.. 4~ z. L L. flL.. C.. L4A..-J<br />
8.<br />
The Government's wish to negotiate cultural agreements with<br />
M~ alaysia, Thailand, Singapore and the Philippines evoked a warm<br />
response. As a result of my visit we have undertaken to double the<br />
number of cultural agreements we now have. We already have such an<br />
agreement with Indonesia. The new agreements will mean that we<br />
shall have cultural agreements with all members of ASEAN. This is<br />
a manifestation of the importance the Government attaches to<br />
promoting a distinctively Australian culture and excellence in<br />
the arts generally. It acknowledges that we have much to gain<br />
from the rich and ancient cultures of our Asian neighbours.<br />
CONTACTS WITH YOUTH<br />
During my visit I sought, with members of my party, to<br />
establish contacts with student and youth leaders. I visited the<br />
University of Singapore, Nanyang University and the University of<br />
the Philippines, at which I delivered a major speech. In Thailand<br />
a senior Foreign Affairs official accompanying me and two members<br />
of jny personal staff spent fLive hours in discussions with Thai<br />
student leaders, These contacts, unprecedented in a visit of this<br />
kind, were of value to both sides.<br />
DISCUSSIONS The discussions I had were, of course, confidential and<br />
lasted many hours, It would be impossible to summnarise them all<br />
in detail. The roles of the great Powers The United States,<br />
the Soviet Union, China and Japan in the Asian region were<br />
discussed in each capital. I discussed my own visits to China and<br />
Japan and economic problems in the region, including the effect of<br />
the oil shortage and the energy crisis.<br />
I discussed the situation in Indo-China and general questions<br />
of security and stability in South East Asia. I found these<br />
discussions in total educative, valuable and of great interest.<br />
In Mvalaysia, Thailand, Singapore and the Philippines there was an<br />
acknowledgement that the normalisation cf relations between China<br />
and the countries of South East Asia is inevitable. Burma and Laos<br />
already have diplomatic relations with China. In the other countries<br />
the issue is not one of principle but of timing. </p>
<p>9.<br />
Another common theme was regional co-operation. The<br />
ASEAN countries naturally attach priority to the consolidation of<br />
ASEAN, an organisation which Australia does not seek to join but<br />
which has our wholehearted support. I was encouraged, however, to<br />
find a widespread interest in the idea of a future wider regional<br />
association in which the countries of Asia and the Pacific could<br />
meet at a high level for informal discussions, much in the manner<br />
in which Commonwealth Heads of Government meet. The Philippines,<br />
in particular, fully agrees with this concept and President Marcos<br />
has advanced almost identical proposals.<br />
STUDENTS I had the opportunity during the visit to discuss with a<br />
number of countries in the region their concern over students.<br />
The countries I visited in particular Malaysia, Thailand and<br />
Singapore continue to place importance on the opportunities<br />
for their studernts to study JIn Australia. The sponsored student<br />
programs, that is, the Colombo Plan and other official programs<br />
in the main run smoothly and successfully. There are no<br />
difficulties in this area. There have been some difficulties,<br />
hi_,-ever, with private students in Thailand over the English test,<br />
whichn is a pre-requisite to entry for study, and the level of entry<br />
for their students. I have agreed to look into these problems and<br />
the Departments concerned are at present conducting a review of<br />
policy with a view to resolving them. The Ministers for Education<br />
and Immigration have also had discussions with the Thai authorities<br />
on this matter.,<br />
In Singapore there were discussions on the return of private<br />
students and the so-called brain drain. Under our non-discriminatory<br />
immigration policy, private students enter Australia on the<br />
understanding that they will return home. However, if they can<br />
meet migration criteria they are allowed to remain in Australia.<br />
The Singapore Government was perturbed about this and have now<br />
decided to sponsor officially all private students coming to<br />
Australia. Sponsored students have always been required to return<br />
to their home country on completion of their studies and this has<br />
been at the express insistence of their home governments. </p>
<p>I want to make it clear that if any student from Singapore is to<br />
be sent home, it will be as the result off his sponsorship by the<br />
Singapore Government and not as the result of a decision taken on<br />
its own account by the Australian Government. Mr Lee also raised<br />
the question of students already in Australia and I have agreed to<br />
look into this.<br />
AID I did not see my visit as an occasion for new aid commitments.<br />
I believe that visits by the Prime Minister and Ministers to<br />
neighbouring South East Asian countries should be seen as part of<br />
a regular pattern of visits and not necessarily as occasions for<br />
important new aid agreements.<br />
Naturally, however, bilateral aid programs were discussed in<br />
each capital. In Kuala Lumpur I undertook to study Malaysian<br />
requests for assistance in preparing a feas6ibility study on the<br />
development of the Trengganu River Basin and on the development<br />
of the proposed Kuantan industrial area. In Vientiane I undertook<br />
* that the Government would consider assisting that city in its<br />
proposed expansion of its city water supply. I stressed to the<br />
Prime Minister of Laos and the leaders of the Lao Patriotic Forces<br />
that Australia would do all it could to help in the postwar<br />
* rehabilitation of Laos. In Bangkok I announced that Australia<br />
* would support the Pioneer Medical Volunteers Program of the<br />
Princess Mother. We will provide ambulances and radio transceivers<br />
fo r the pilot project. In the Philippines I was glad to announce<br />
that the Australian Government had agreed to enter a joint aid<br />
project with the Philippines Government for the construction of<br />
roads and related irrigation and agricultural development in<br />
Zamboanga Del Suir. This is a large project which will cost the<br />
Australian Government approximately S2 million a year for each of<br />
the next five years.<br />
I take this opportunity of informing the House that the<br />
Australian Government has decided to contribute $ 18,150,000 to the<br />
Asian Development Fund. This decision, following as it does on<br />
our decision to join the Ministerial Conference for the Economic<br />
Development of South East Asia and the South East Asian Ministers cof<br />
Education Organisation, and our decision to help finance a greed ASE.---<br />
projects, is a further manifestation of the Government's growing<br />
interest in the well-being of the South East Asian region. </p>
<p>S-a -2rlxAw a. it 11.<br />
I mentioned during my visit the possibility of sending<br />
Australian staff and other forms of assistance to Asian educational I<br />
institutions. This would ease the demand for places in Australian<br />
universities. I expect it to become a more significant part of oix-r<br />
aid programs. It would not, however, mean that we would be<br />
unwilling to continue to assist in training the students and<br />
officials who come to us under the Colombo Plan and other aid<br />
schemes. The presence of overseas students in our educational<br />
institutions and in our whole society is a valuable means of<br />
furthering understanding between Australia and Asia. This view<br />
was also put to me by the Prime Minister of Singapore and the<br />
Prime Minister of Thailand.<br />
I believe that during my visit I was able to affirm<br />
Australia's genuine, continuing and growing interest in South East<br />
Asia. I was gratified that the leaders with whom I spoke and their<br />
statements were reflected in the press of the countries I visited<br />
saw fit to praise Australia and the Government's policies in terms<br />
that went beyond the normal requirements of courtesy to a visiting<br />
Head of Government. I believe Australia walks taller and stands in<br />
higher regard in South East Asia than ever before. Our policies<br />
are understood. Our continuing and growing interest in the regio"<br />
is accepted and appreciated. As one leading South East Asian<br />
statesman said to me, our present policies are " approved and<br />
applauded". I believe we are rightly regarded in South East Asia<br />
as a genuine and trusted friend.<br />
( I seek leave to table the six main speeches I made during<br />
the visit and the main speeches made by the six heads of Government<br />
of the countries visited).' </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
