<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11725</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            AT THE LUNCHEON HELD TO RECOGNISE            THOSE AUSTRALIANS WHO SERVED IN EAST TIMOR            PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/03/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE .............................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much John Moore. To the Leader of the Opposition, Kim</p>
<p> Beazley; the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Alexander Downer; my other</p>
<p> parliamentary and cabinet colleagues; to Admiral Chris Barrie, the Chief</p>
<p> of the Defence Force; Major General Peter Cosgrove, the INTERFET Commander</p>
<p> and the personnel of the Australian Defence Force and the Australian Federal</p>
<p> Police, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>Today is an opportunity in a comprehensive bipartisan way for the people</p>
<p> of Australia through their elected representatives to express their immense</p>
<p> gratitude to the Defence Force personnel, to the Australian Federal Police</p>
<p> and to all the other groups and all the other organisations that played</p>
<p> a role in achieving an outcome in East Timor which has been immensely</p>
<p> to the credit and the reputation of the people of Australia. When I moved</p>
<p> a resolution in the Parliament in September supporting the commitment</p>
<p> and wishing our men and women well and a safe return home to their families.</p>
<p>I said that they did not go in the name of the Government, rather they</p>
<p> went in the name of Australia. And when men and women are asked to risk</p>
<p> their lives abroad in pursuit of a cause, they are entitled to know that</p>
<p> they go in the name of their country who gives them undivided support</p>
<p> in pursuit of their obligations and their responsibilities. And I'm</p>
<p> very proud to be able to say as Prime Minster that that proved to be the</p>
<p> case in relation to our deployment in East Timor.</p>
<p>I am delighted with today's gathering which brings together not</p>
<p> only representatives of INTERFET and the Australian Federal Police, but</p>
<p> also representatives of the Service Spouse Organisations, the families</p>
<p> of the men and women who went to East Timor, the various non-government</p>
<p> organisations that played such a critical role in the days and weeks and</p>
<p> months before the United Nations mandate which provided the legal authorisation</p>
<p> for the INTERFET deployment. Because the weeks and months leading up to</p>
<p> the deployment were in their own way as challenging and as tense as the</p>
<p> weeks and months that followed the deployment.</p>
<p>It is an experience that those of us involved in different levels will</p>
<p> never forget. I will never forget the experience involved as Prime Minister</p>
<p> and I shan't forget the sagacious advice and support of my senior</p>
<p> Cabinet colleagues in which I particularly number Alexander Downer and</p>
<p> John Moore. And the advice and counsel of the Department of Foreign Affairs</p>
<p> and my own Department and my own personal National Security Adviser, Michael</p>
<p> Thawley who's the new Australian Ambassador in the United States.</p>
<p>As we look back now on the an event that was deemed to be highly successful</p>
<p> and an outcome for which we are immensely grateful, it is important to</p>
<p> remind ourselves that the risks that were involved. And for me on behalf</p>
<p> of a grateful nation to pay tribute to those men and women who assumed</p>
<p> the greatest risk of all, and that is the risk to their lives. And if</p>
<p> we keep in mind the tense moments and weeks and months that would have</p>
<p> been the lot of their families.</p>
<p>We thank God that casualties were kept to such an absolute minimum. You</p>
<p> never have any way of knowing that at the beginning. And I shall never</p>
<p> forget the experience of visiting along with the Leader of the Opposition</p>
<p> and the Leader of the Australian Democrats, many of the troops before</p>
<p> they departed and the moments my wife and I spent with many of the personnel</p>
<p> in Townsville and the Lavarack Barracks after having met so many of them.</p>
<p> And seeing the groups of soldiers with their NCOs in the dusk of that</p>
<p> very warm North Queensland evening. And trying in some way to share the</p>
<p> apprehension and contemplation that they must have been feeling. It bought</p>
<p> home to me the immense responsibility and risk that they were assuming</p>
<p> on behalf of our nation and in the cause to which we as a group of people</p>
<p> were so very strongly committed.</p>
<p>May I say to you Major General Cosgrove that you have won the respect,</p>
<p> affection and the admiration of the entire Australian nation. Your qualities</p>
<p> of firm direct leadership, your capacity to articulate in a no-nonsense</p>
<p> fashion, the extent and the amplitude of your mandate and the inspiration</p>
<p> that I know that you have provided to the men and women who served under</p>
<p> you. It is something that makes all of us as Australians feel immensely</p>
<p> proud.</p>
<p>I am delighted that you have a representative group of the men and women</p>
<p> who served under you. I am also delighted that the Australian Federal</p>
<p> Police contingent is so well represented here today.</p>
<p>On the table with us is Alan Mills, now retired from the Federal Police,</p>
<p> but who served there before the INTERFET deployment. Served there immediately</p>
<p> around the time when the ballot took place and I shan't likely forget</p>
<p> the telephone conversation I had with him before the 10th of</p>
<p> September, well before the deployment. When quite literally the Australian</p>
<p> consulate staff in Dili was spending a great deal of time on the floor</p>
<p> to avoid the bullets that were flying around at the particular time and</p>
<p> in his very direct and laid back and very reassuring way when I asked</p>
<p> him how it was and he said it was a bit hairy and I thought that was a</p>
<p> beautiful understatement. But we should never for a moment forget the</p>
<p> risk that was assumed by the members of the Australian Federal Police</p>
<p> and I wanted recorded that the nation is immensely proud and grateful</p>
<p> of the contribution that the men and women of the Australian Federal Police</p>
<p> have afforded and I am very pleased to note the presence of so many of</p>
<p> them here today.</p>
<p>As you know ladies and gentlemen this deployment was the largest by Australia</p>
<p> since the Vietnam war. It was the first occasion on which Australian commanded</p>
<p> an international force and quite rightly significant praise and credit</p>
<p> from around the world has come the way of the men and women of the Australian</p>
<p> Defence Force. But I do not forget the fact, nor should anyone forget</p>
<p> the fact that they operated under the mandate of the security council</p>
<p> of the United Nations. They were never going to go in without the authority</p>
<p> and sanctions and legal commissions of the United Nations and the level</p>
<p> of co-operation that existed between my government and the secretary general</p>
<p> of the United Nations made the deployment possible. The speed with which</p>
<p> the mandate was achieved and the breadth and simplicity of that mandate</p>
<p> that made Internet's task that much easier to achieve was all the</p>
<p> result of the authority given by the United Nations. Nor do I forget for</p>
<p> a moment that we went there as partners with many other nations. And I</p>
<p> am pleased to acknowledge the presence of the High Commissioners and Ambassadors</p>
<p> of so many of the countries that sent troops and personnel to East Timor</p>
<p> to serve with the Australian Defence personnel.</p>
<p>It was a partnership, it was a regional operation, it was also an operation</p>
<p> that included contributions from countries with which Australia has participated</p>
<p> in military conflicts for the whole of this century.</p>
<p>And finally might I say this that we gather here today not in any sense</p>
<p> of triumphalism. We gather here today to express our simple gratitude</p>
<p> to men and women who served their country. They served their country well,</p>
<p> they put their lives on the line for a just cause. They stood up for what</p>
<p> was right and proper and in the process, they made us all feel immensely</p>
<p> proud. We thank god that they have come back to us. We wish all of them</p>
<p> well, we remember their families and we are glad that they can share some</p>
<p> of this occasion. Ladies and gentlemen, simply on behalf of the entire</p>
<p> nation, may I say thank you to general Cosgrove and his men and women</p>
<p> and to the men and women of the Australian Federal Police and I am delighted</p>
<p> to invite the leader of the opposition, Mr Kim Beazley to second my remarks.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
