<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7538</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE 22 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007538.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE<br />
22 MARCH 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Well I am sorry it's late but I thought as a matter of<br />
courtesy I would come and just make a brief statement. AS<br />
you know Mr Willis will be available in a more detailed<br />
press conference tomorrow. Cabinet has spent now a very<br />
considerable period of time considering this matter. It<br />
goes without saying there were a number of complex<br />
considerations that have had to be taken into account.<br />
There were many of us in the Cabinet, and I include myself<br />
in this, who started with the presumption that it would make<br />
more economic sense to not proceed with a third runway at<br />
Kingsford-Smith but to proceed immediately to fast-tracking.<br />
of Badgery's Creek. I must say that the more this matter<br />
was examined the more one became persuaded that that would<br />
not be the appropriate economic decision or the correct<br />
decision in terms of aviation principles. It is the fact,<br />
and I don't disguise it, that this has been a difficult<br />
decision to take in political terms because there is the<br />
assertion made that the decision that we've taken which we<br />
perceive to be in the interests of the country as a whole,<br />
Sydney in general, may cost us some seats adjacent to the<br />
Kingsford-Smith airport. And that was not something that<br />
could be lightly dismissed. But nevertheless, in the<br />
balance the majority of the Cabinet believed that this was<br />
the correct decision to be taken. Let me say that the<br />
interests of the people in the immediate vicinity were not<br />
however overlooked by Cabinet in our deliberations. Indeed,<br />
they formed a significant part of our consideration. on the<br />
information, the best information available to us there will<br />
in fact be a decline in the numbers of people seriously<br />
affected, severely affected by aircraft noise from 56,200 at<br />
present to about 35,500. That's a decline of about 37%.<br />
That decline will occur as a result of a combination of the<br />
new generation of quieter aircraft and the greatly reduced<br />
usage of the east-west runway. So we were in the position<br />
where a combination of economics, a combination of sensible<br />
aviation principles and a consideration of a reduction of<br />
noise levels in general in the area led to the decisions<br />
that were taken. I repeat that hours and hours of<br />
consideration have gone into this, it was a hard and tough<br />
decision to take and one which I'm convinced and the<br />
majority of my colleagues are convinced on all the evidence<br />
is in the best interests of the nation, of Sydney, and of<br />
the aviation and tourist industry in this country. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you believe that Caucus will accept this<br />
decision of Cabinet?<br />
PM: Yes, I don't think it will be unanimous but I believe<br />
the majority will.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think Mr Punch should stay in the<br />
Aviation portfolio?<br />
PM: Let me say this about Mr Punch. You've raised him and<br />
I'm not going to go on for a long series of questions, it's<br />
too late for that, but it's a legitimate question. No-one<br />
could have argued the contra case more eloquently and from<br />
his point of view more effectively I think than did Mr<br />
Punch. This is before he got into the Cabinet and the whole<br />
of the Cabinet proceedings. He had a firm conviction as to<br />
the alternative point of view. He argued that case<br />
strenuously and I can say I believe from his point of view I<br />
don't think he could've argued that case more effectively.<br />
He wants to consider the position as to whether from his<br />
point of view it's most appropriate to stay on in that<br />
particular portfolio. I think it's reasonable that he<br />
should consider that position and I'll have a further<br />
discussion with him when he's ready to have that discussion.<br />
JOURNALIST: Inaudible<br />
PM: Well he should think about it and then he'll talk with<br />
me. JOURNALIST: Would it be reasonable to move him off? Would<br />
that make more sense in the circumstances<br />
PM: It's a combination of circumstances. I think the first<br />
thing to do is what I've said. I've had a brief discussion<br />
with him and he understands that. He wants to think about<br />
the position and talk to me further and I think that's a<br />
perfectly reasonable thing to do.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you say this decision was taken, when you<br />
say the majority of your colleagues agreed with you, is this<br />
to imply that the agreement, the decision was taken without<br />
consensus? PM: It's not only to imply, it's a matter of logic that<br />
that conclusion must follow. But in the end this is not a<br />
Cabinet which takes formal votes. It's clear that the<br />
majority, and a clear majority favoured the position and<br />
when that was clear that that was the position it didn't<br />
take a vote, there were no hands up and that sort of thing.<br />
JOURNALIST: Should it have taken as long as it did? </p>
<p>PM: -Yes of course it should. It's a matter which by any<br />
criterion is one of the more important that Cabinet's had to<br />
deal with. And it was one in which, let me say for the<br />
first time any government had in fact built up a relevant<br />
information base. Let me remind-you that the people who<br />
were in before us had seven years in which they could've<br />
dealt with this matter they didn't. We'd already taken a<br />
first step in dealing with the longer term problem by making<br />
a decision to acquire land at Badgery's. And as we came to<br />
the point now of having to make as it were a final decision<br />
in this matter a great deal of information had to be built<br />
up which involved a lot of assumptions about rates of growth<br />
of international traffic, of domestic traffic, assumptions<br />
about possible improvements in runway productivity, possible<br />
improvements in productivity which flow from other<br />
management and traffic flow decisions, judgements that you<br />
have to make about the diversion of some types of traffic or<br />
portions of it like general aviation traffic away from<br />
Kingsford-Smith. Now in their nature all of these issues<br />
are extremely complex and many of them by definition can't<br />
lend themselves to dogmatic assertions as to what the actual<br />
factual position will be. Therefore there is room for<br />
differences of interpretation. Now those things you simply<br />
don't rush. You can if you want to but I think that what I<br />
said earlier is indicative of the way in which we've gone<br />
about this. I was one who started off with a fairly clear<br />
presumption as to what I thought the best economics and<br />
aviation principles would be. I became persuaded as more<br />
information became available, as we asked more questions, as<br />
more figures were put in front of us in response to those<br />
questions, that initial presumption that I had changed.<br />
JOURNALIST: Inaudible<br />
PM: No need to be so assertive, I can hear.<br />
JOURNALIST: In the end what was it that turned the argument<br />
for you?<br />
PM: It was a combination of information which together went<br />
to the point as to when would be the most likely date at<br />
which you would need the new facility. On the information<br />
that one had had earlier and the assumptions one made it<br />
looked as though what you would doing would be if you built<br />
a third runway would be to go through all the exercise of<br />
building it and almost as soon as you'd built that it<br />
would've reached saturation point. That was a sort of<br />
presumption that I and others had made on the sort of<br />
preliminary assumptions and estimates that were available to<br />
us. The more one looked at the evidence and got additional<br />
information in response to questions, the more it appeared<br />
to be the case on which we've acted that there would be a<br />
quite significant period of time between the completion of<br />
the third runway and when that additional facility would<br />
reach saturation point. So when you then looked at those<br />
considerations therefore in terms of what outlays would be </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PM ( cont): necessary now to have an accelerated<br />
construction at Badgery's Creek and you looked at that in<br />
discounted terms, as you have to do to make the proper<br />
economic assessment, it became clear that you would in fact<br />
be expending more money and considerably more money on the<br />
immediate Badgery's alternative. That was the essence of<br />
the change in our position. Now<br />
JOURNALIST: So when will Badgery's Creek open and when will<br />
the third runway open?<br />
PM: Well, taking the third runway first, there will be an<br />
Environmental Impact Statement and one can't be sure how<br />
long that will take but the assessment is that taking the<br />
period of the Environmental Impact Statement and the<br />
construction period into account, you're looking at a period<br />
of the order of five years for the third runway. There's no<br />
question about that, that that could be the order of it. I<br />
mean if your EIS was considerably shorter, then that period<br />
of five years may be correspondingly shorter. But that<br />
could take that sort of period of time. In other words, I<br />
think one of the misapprehensions through a lot of this<br />
discussion has been the assumption that as soon as Cabinet<br />
made a decision about a third runway, hey-presto, you've got<br />
it. You haven't, it's that sort of period of time. Now we<br />
will be, as you will see from the decision or the press<br />
statement that's been distributed, we will be moving to<br />
accelerate the acquisition of land at Badgery's and we'll be<br />
moving to the construction of a general aviation facility<br />
there that will not take a long period of time. Then we're<br />
also making the decision that the second stage of Badgery's<br />
will be one which will involve a domestic and international<br />
capacity and we want immediate work to be done on the<br />
preparation of plans for that with the actual timing of that<br />
second stage being one that you will make in the light of<br />
the additional information that comes available to you as to<br />
the way capacity is moving. Now, I'm not going to go on any<br />
longer now, the further detailed questions you can address<br />
to Mr Willis tomorrow morning or later this morning.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
