<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10174</transcript-id>
    <title>REMARKS BY THE PRESIDENT, PRIME MINISTER JOHN HOWARD AND OPPOSITION LEADER KIM BEAZLEY THE GREAT HALL THE PARLIAMENT HOUSE CANBERRA, AUSTRALIA 1:25 P.M (L)</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010174.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from: MORE 28/ 11/ 96 17: 82 P97<br />
THE WHITE HOUSE<br />
Office of the Press Secretary<br />
( Canberra, Australia)<br />
For Immediate Release November 20,-19-96<br />
REMARKS BY THE PRESIDENT,<br />
PRIME MXIISTIR JOHN HOWARD<br />
AND OPPOSITION LEADER KIM BSAZLEY<br />
IN TOAST REMARKS<br />
The Great Hall<br />
The Parliament House<br />
Canberra, Australia<br />
1: 25 P. M. ( L PRIME MINISTER HOWARD: Mr. President; Mrs. Clinton;<br />
Your Excellencies; the Leader of the opposition, Mr. Beasley, my<br />
parliamentary colleagues; state premiers; ladies and gentlemen:<br />
This Is, by any measure, a special occasion, we welcome the<br />
President of the United States, a person recently reelected to<br />
lead the most powerful nation in the world. we also welcome him<br />
as the leader of a nation with which we have so much in common.<br />
our relationship is a very deep and rich one. it's<br />
a relationship that is forged on the basis of many common values,<br />
many common elements of our history, our common service on the<br />
battlefields of the world in defense of liberty and in defense of<br />
freedom. We welcome him as a friend. He comes hero as the<br />
leader of a nation with which we have shared so much in the past,<br />
but with which we share so much in the future. one of the, I<br />
think, great elements of the relationship between the United<br />
states and Australia is that we are in the process of<br />
transforming a relationship that was forged in early and more<br />
difficult circumstances Into a new partnership in the Asia<br />
Pacific region. We welcome both of you, Mr. President, as friends of<br />
this country. We hope that you will enjoy your stay here. The<br />
President of the United states is always welcome in Australia.<br />
( Applause.) But as Dr. Johnson reminded us, we should always<br />
keep our relationships in good repair and we should never take<br />
close relationships for granted. We should always work on them,<br />
nurture them and water them. And that is what today's visit and<br />
today's events are all about.<br />
We hope you have a delightful time. we hope you<br />
have some time off, as well as some time for work. You are very,<br />
very welcome, Mr. President and Mrs. Clinton. ( Applause.)<br />
I would now invite the leader of the opposition, Mr.<br />
Kim Beazley to support my remarks. ( Applause.)<br />
MR. EEAZLEY: Thank you very much, Mr. Prime<br />
Minister. Hr. President, Mrs. Clinton, Excellencies,<br />
parliamentary colleagues, ladies and gentlemen: This is a<br />
delightful occasion for all us here in this hall. I don't think<br />
I've set it decked out better. And I think you'll find the<br />
entertainment very much to your taste and I think you'll find<br />
your time here in Australia about as enjoyable as you can fit<br />
into four days, which is lunaticly short. ( Laughter.) I've got </p>
<p>rax t ram 281/ 6178 g<br />
to tell you that. But we'll do the very best for you we can<br />
while you're here, all of us.<br />
I am delighted, too, to see Mrs. Clinton hero, as<br />
wall, after the enormous dedication and energy that she's shown<br />
in assisting your administration and in the course of the last<br />
election. ( Applause.) And I want to congratulate you on that election<br />
victory. I always like to see a fellow win an election. It's a<br />
it's a delight for those of us in opposition to think that<br />
these things can occur from time to time. ( Laughter.) It was a<br />
historic one, indeed.<br />
Looking back, you are the only southern Democrat<br />
since Appomattox to win a second term. Woodrow Wilson doesn't<br />
count he won it from New Jersey. So you're the only southern<br />
Democrat since Appomattox to win a second term as a President of<br />
the United States. And I don't mention Appomattox in a<br />
gratuitous fashion here at all. it was a defining moment for the<br />
modern American nation the event which underwrote America's<br />
role in the 20th century. That you reunited after that, that you<br />
emerged with your morality intact meant that America could<br />
exercise leadership of the democratic nations this century.<br />
And America has been the bastion of democracy this<br />
century, as you visited at the end of it. If you'd been visiting<br />
us here in the middle, of course, you'd have been a bastion<br />
looking around you seeing democracy in retreat everywhere. The<br />
stand that the United States took for the entirety of this<br />
century means that you visit here now and you look at democracy<br />
as the norm as the system governing the nations around the<br />
globe. And in those fights and struggles that you've had over<br />
the years this century to preserve that, to keep decency alive in<br />
international politics, it's been a matter of some pride for us<br />
here in this nation that we have been there with you as well.<br />
There's another reason why I want to mention<br />
Appomattox and note and your status as the most successful<br />
southern Democratic candidate for President since that period of<br />
time. The way in which you reached out to all Americans of all<br />
ethnic, racial, cultural and religious backgrounds, and included<br />
them in your vision of the United States is an inspiration to all<br />
of us. ( Applause.) In the days when I was Defense Minister, it was<br />
fashionable to say that the United States was in decline, What<br />
an extraordinary change over the course of the last decade. The<br />
way in which the global economy works from this point on, the<br />
needs and security of the nations of the economy mean, if<br />
anything, America's role has got larger over the last decade and<br />
the opportunity greater.<br />
AS the new international economy emerges, based on,<br />
essentially, information technology and telecommunications, once<br />
again there's United States companies, United states initiatives<br />
leading the way. And I don't think there's been any President of<br />
the United States who comprehends that better than you.<br />
So I'm looking forward to learning a great deal from<br />
you during the course of this visit. I think that you've got<br />
quite a story to tell in this country. But don't tell it for tkoo<br />
long. Get out on the beaches. Get out on the golf courses. Get<br />
out snorkeling and have a terrific time here. ( Applause.)<br />
PRIME MINISTER HOWARD: Thank you, Mr. 8eazley. I<br />
now invite the President to respond. ( Applause.)<br />
THE PRBSIPSNT: Thank you very much. Prime minister<br />
and Mrs. Howard, Hr. speaker and Mrs. Halverson, Madame<br />
President, nr. Reid, Mr. Beazley, Mts. Annus, Ambassador McCarthy:<br />
Let me say that Hillary and I and all of us in our delegation<br />
MORE 20/ 11/ 96 17: 02 Pg: a </p>
<p>Fax from 281/ 9 782P<br />
have very much looked forward to coming here. so far, our<br />
experiences have even exceeded our bopes. WA have loved every<br />
minute of it. I love the crowds welcoming us in last night. I<br />
think I like Mr. Beazley reminding me that I'm the first southern<br />
Democrat since Appomattox to be elected twice. But I'll have to<br />
wait until I get home to see how that plays at home. ( Laughter.)<br />
We're grateful to be here in Canberra, where there<br />
is clearly a touch of America in the planning of Walter Burley<br />
Griffin, who came from Hillary's home state of Illinois. we feel<br />
very much that we are at home and among friends.<br />
This morning I had a good meeting with the Prime<br />
Minister. I was honored to meet your Cabinet. I was honored to<br />
reaffirm our remarkable security relationship, to review our<br />
common efforts to reduce the danger of weapons of mass<br />
destruction, an effort in which Australian leadership has been so<br />
vital. We're working to provide peace and stability in the<br />
Asia Pacific region together. And together we're going to make a<br />
big difference in building the prosperity of tomorrow, increasing<br />
the ties of trade and investment not only between our two<br />
nations, but throughout the area.<br />
The scope and depth of our cooperation for a long<br />
time now is truly extraordinary, but not surprising. it is the<br />
hallmark of a relationship between two democracies that has grown<br />
through struggles of five wars and a whole century's hard labors<br />
of peace. Half a world of oceans separates us, but the currents<br />
of friendship and commerce and culture flow constantly between<br />
our shores and they are more binding than the land bridges that<br />
connected the continents eons ago.<br />
we have always looked to Australia with groat hope,<br />
with great trust, with great admiration. we see those<br />
expectations from what may be the very first official United<br />
States act dealing with Australia. In 1179, Benjamin Franklin<br />
issued an unusual passport for Captain Cook who was then<br />
returning from one of his explorations here in the South Pacific.<br />
That was, of course,-during our war of independence. And<br />
Franklin sent special orders to the commanders of all American<br />
ships not to attack the ships of the British captain, but to<br />
treat him and his crew with all civility and kindness. He wrote<br />
that Cook's explorations would facilitate communication between<br />
distant nations to the benefit of mankind in general.<br />
Franklin was a prophet. From our common struggle in<br />
five wars, to the trade we have created, to our shared efforts to<br />
reduce the nuclear threat, the bonds between our distant nations<br />
have indeed been an immense benefit not only to ourselves, but to<br />
mankind in general. The United States is profoundly grateful for<br />
thin relationship, for the affection and the warmth that has<br />
grown between our citizens.<br />
For many reasons our ties have grown. One of the<br />
most important is that we see in each other qualities that we<br />
prize and hops for in ourselves. We admire in each other the<br />
pioneering spirit that our forbears brought to the tasks of<br />
pushing back the frontiers and building nations.<br />
AS We Move into a new century, we face new and very<br />
different frontiers. we are called upon not to homestead In the<br />
wilderness, but to build for the security and the prosperity of a<br />
new era, to deal with the challenges of this new explosion in the<br />
global economy and information technology in the diversity within<br />
all of our own societies. But we still need that frontier<br />
spirit, we still need to believe that with courage and vision<br />
and daring and a firm adherence to our shared and unshakable<br />
values, we can make the future better than the present and leave<br />
a world worthy of our children and our heritage.<br />
MORE 20/ 11/ 96 17: 02 Pg: 9 </p>
<p>Fax from : 28/ 11/ 96 17: 82 Pg: 18<br />
I want all of you to know how very much we Americans<br />
like and admire and value Australia and her people. We want the<br />
21st century to be a large partnership between ourselves for the<br />
betterment of all of humankind. I believe that we are entering<br />
the era of greatest possibility in human history. I believe<br />
there will be more people able to live out their dreams than any<br />
time in all of human existence if the values, the record, the<br />
partnership we have established can chart the way to the future<br />
we long to build. And I promise you that we, in the United States,<br />
will do our best to be worthy of our friendship and that kind of<br />
future. Thank you very much. ( Laughter.)<br />
END 1: 39 P. M. ( L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
