<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10096</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON.JOHN HOWARD MP DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, NSW GENERAL MEETING OF STATE COUNCIL - ST MARY&#039;S BAND CLUB</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/09/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010096.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from 07/ 09/ 96 18: 39 Pg: 18<br />
7 SEPTEMBER 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, NSW GENERAL MEETING OF<br />
STATE COUNCIL ST MARY'S BAND CLUB<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr B3eazley intends to oppose measures in the Budget. What is your response to that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
If you really believe in lower interest rates you will let the Budget go through<br />
unscathed. There's a direct link over time between the size of the Budget deficit and<br />
the level of housing interest rates. I can't think of anything that's more likely to slow<br />
down further interest rate reductions over time, than people mucking around with the<br />
Budget. JOURNALIST: How far will you be pushed, Mr Howard, before it becomes a possibility of a double<br />
dissolution? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh look I'm not contemplating a double dissolution. It's not in my range of<br />
contemplation. JOURNALIST: How much trouble will you have to have with the Telstra sale, before that becomes an<br />
option? </p>
<p>Fax from PRIME MNISTER:<br />
Well I'm not considering a double dissolution, I'm continuing to advocate getting the<br />
Telstra legislation through, advocate the cause of that through the minor parties in the<br />
Senate and I hope that we can be successful, but I don't take anything for granted. I'll<br />
continue to talk to them and deal with them and listen to their questions and respond<br />
to their concerns, and I'm hopeul but I don't take anything for granted. But as far as<br />
a double dissolution is concerned, I'm not interested in a double dissolution, I'm eager<br />
to have three years and I think the Australian public is eager that we have three years<br />
and probably some more after that as well, but that'll be a matter for them to decide in<br />
three years' time or two and a half years' time.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will Senator Colston's defction make it easier for you to get your package through?<br />
Have you speaking to him over the last few days?<br />
PRIME MINISTER;<br />
I haven't spoken to him, no. Some of my colleagues I think have spoken to him, I<br />
don't know how many. I'm not going to publicly speculate about how any individual<br />
is going to vote or how the Democrats are going to vote, the only person who can say<br />
how Senator Colston is going to vote, is Senator Colston. The only person who can<br />
speak for Senator Harradiae, is Senator Harradine, and the only people who can speak<br />
for the Australian Democrats are the Australian Democrats. And I want to make it<br />
clear I am not going to get into the business of publicly ruminating about or<br />
speculating as to how any of these people are going to vote. If you want to know how<br />
they're going to vote, you should address your questions to them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the appointment, of a Labor Minister to head of SOCOG, how do you<br />
feel about that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't want to make any comment about it at this stage beyond saying again that to<br />
me, total co-operation between the Labor Government of New South Wales and the<br />
Liberal National Party Govenment federally is important, to Australia having and<br />
Sydney having a successful Olympic Games in the year 2000. The Australian public<br />
Wants a bi-partisan apolitical approach on both sides, on both sides, to the Olympic<br />
Games and I will talk to some people on the SOCOG Board, I'll talk to the Premier,<br />
I'll naturally talk to Mr Coates the head of the Australian Olympic Committee, I'll do<br />
everything I can to make sure that the Olympic Games of 2000 in Sydney are a<br />
uniting experience for the Australian people and an opportunity to showcase the<br />
wonders of Australia and the beauty of Sydney to the rest of the world. 2.<br />
07/ 09/ 96 18: 39 PS: 11 </p>
<p>Fax from JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, will you rule out meeting, or having Mr Downer meeting the Dalai<br />
Lama? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't have anything to add to what I've said before in relation to that. I place a very<br />
high store on human rights and naturally I meet people according to my assessment of<br />
what is in the best interests of Australia.<br />
JOURNALIST: How do you feel at the moment about the possibility of a by-election?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh there's a possibility of a by-election, because the defeated Labor member who was<br />
thrown out with a swing of more than 12 per cent, by Jackie Kelly who's with me thik<br />
morning, has gone to the Court of Disputed Returns and the Judge has reserved his<br />
judgemernt. And if a by-election is ordered, because of a technicality, then we'll fight<br />
very hard to retain the seat. It will be a tough fight, but we've got a geat member in<br />
Jackic Kelly. She's asked more questions of the Government than any other member<br />
of Parliament in the six months that she's been in Parliament and if ever anybody<br />
represents the aspirations of western Sydney, it's Jackie Kelly.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It will be a tough, hard fight. It was a Labor stronghold until Jackie Kelly came in<br />
like a breath of fresh air with the policies of the Coalition in March and we'll be<br />
asking the people of Lindsay, if there is a by-election ordered, to confirm their<br />
decision of March and to vote for the future rather than the failed past<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I didn't hear a word of that I'm sorry.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible) 87/ 09/ 96 18: 39 Pg: 12 </p>
<p>I Fax from PRIME MINISTER:<br />
jcan't every imagine either Donald McDonald or John Valder not getting a say.<br />
Thank you. Faoxm 07/ 89/ 96 18: 39 Pg: 13 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
