<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7859</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPERATION IMMUNE &quot;THANK YOU&quot; CEREMONY RICHMOND RAAF BASE - 15 DECEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/12/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007859.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK RGAINST DELIVERY EIBARED-UNITLInLIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPERATION IMMUNE " THANK YOU" CEREMONY<br />
RICHMOND RAAF BASE 15 DECEMBER 1989<br />
On behalf of the people of Australia, it is my pleasure<br />
today to thank all those pilots, aircrews and support staff<br />
who over the last three and a half months have taken part in<br />
Operation Immune.<br />
Operation Immune has provided the nation with vital air<br />
services at a time when the domestic airline industry had<br />
been crippled by the shortsightedness and greed displayed by<br />
the leadership of the pilots' Federation.<br />
The dimensions of your contribution to the nation during<br />
this damaging period can be simply measured:<br />
You provided some 224,000 seats including, at the height of<br />
operations, 3071 seats on a single day;<br />
You carried 175,000 passengers;<br />
You were, for the first four weeks of Operation Immune,<br />
Australia's major domestic carrier, providing between 30 and<br />
per cent of available seats;<br />
You serviced seventeen locations around Australia and in<br />
particular maintained air links between Tasmania and the<br />
mainland; You flew nearly 2 million nautical miles that's to say,<br />
equal to one thousand trips across Australia, or about<br />
times to the moon and back.<br />
Behind these statistics of course lies something harder to<br />
measure the intangible but all-important Quality of the<br />
service you have provided.<br />
And as you know from the tributes you received directly from<br />
passengers, your service has not just been good, it has been<br />
exceptional. I ~ v </p>
<p>As Vrlim(-n ,3 ' I ve the req u i r pl~ t; i~ oCI ; r i l<br />
RAAF on my of PL1a. tave.). around Ain tVrl. La atid ovc~ ent%<br />
even flown in a Hierr-most recently, to the South<br />
Pacific F'orumf in Kiribati. I've always known that RAAF<br />
flights are synonymous with reliability, good humour and<br />
service. So it did not surprise me at all that when the RAAF was<br />
exposed to many more Australians, the public's response was<br />
overwhelmingly positive.<br />
I do have some questions, however.<br />
Is it true that passengers were told in pre-f light briefilngs<br />
to " sit down until we reach the terminal, or else you wll.<br />
be shot?" They apparently obeyed, anyway. And were<br />
passengers reassured when told that the only time to paniu<br />
was when they saw " the men in green running down the aisle<br />
and jumping out of the rear of the aircraft"?<br />
I want to pass on to you the contents of a letter written to<br />
me by Michael Field, the Premier of Tasmania, expressing the<br />
gratitude of the people of Tasmania for the vital help you<br />
provided. fie said:<br />
My dear Prime Minister<br />
Now that the Defence Forces are winding down -their passenger<br />
air services to Tasmania, I wish to express the profound<br />
gratitude of this State for the vital help provided by our<br />
flying servicemen during a period when air travel to and<br />
from the State has presented many stresses.<br />
The pilots, cabin crew and ground crew of the Defence Force<br />
aircraft have filled a gap which, quite frankly, co'ild not,<br />
have been closed without their presence.<br />
' rhe planes might be somewhat old and noisy and the oii-board<br />
amenities fairly basic, but they have carried thiousoinds of<br />
people from point to point in safety, with little fuss and<br />
in great humour. Everyone I have spoken to has beeni futi of<br />
praise for the Defence Force effort.<br />
The sudden switch to general passenger carrying must have<br />
come as a shock to many of the crew, pilots and stewards<br />
alike, but all responded in the positive manner we have come<br />
to expect from our armed services.<br />
4 1' i~ </p>
<p>To you and to those of your Ministers responsible for the<br />
" air lift", and to all the Defence Force pilots, cabin crew<br />
and ground crew involved, I extend a hearty thank you from<br />
the Government and the people of Tasmania.<br />
Yours very sincerely<br />
Michael Field<br />
PREMI ER<br />
This is an opinion that has been repeated over and over by<br />
the many people who have travelled on Defence Force<br />
aircraft. In expressing that widespread gratitude today, I don't want<br />
to spoil the occasion with undue political partisanship.<br />
But I cannot let pass in silence the amazing hypocrisy of<br />
the Opposition's spokesman on aviation one David Jull, in<br />
attempting to add his voice to the national expression of<br />
thanks to the defence forces.<br />
After spending the last few months doing nothing but support<br />
the Pilots' Federation, including questioning the safety of<br />
RAAF flights which led to a specific repudiation by Air<br />
Vice Marshal Radford Mr Jull yesterday issued a press<br />
release vouching for your " professionalism and dedication".<br />
If you think that's a breathtaking U-turn you're right.<br />
And let me take this opportunity to pass on Hazel's<br />
appreciation for your hard work. As she has told me on a<br />
number of occasions after her Defence Force flights, what<br />
you have been doing over the last couple of months has been<br />
the best possible publicity for Australia's defence forces.<br />
Now, of course, as normal conditions return to the<br />
commercial aviation industry, the need for your services has<br />
dramatically declined. In the week ending 8 December, Air<br />
Force and Navy aircraft accounted for less than 4 per cent<br />
of available seats.<br />
In other words, you've done your job, and you've done it<br />
well. So to all those involved, in Squadrons 32, 33, 36 and 37,<br />
Maintenance Squadrons East Sale and 486 RAAF Richmond, and<br />
to the Royal Australian Navy HC 723 Squadron, let me express<br />
my thanks and the heartfelt thanks of a proud nation. 4 1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
