<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11113</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   DOORSTOP INTERVIEW                   MICHAEL PHOTIOS&amp;#146; CAMPAIGN OFFICE, RYDE, NSW</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/02/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is the heroin trial an option at all...(inaudible)... constructive</p>
<p> alternatives?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, I am looking for constructive alternatives but the views that</p>
<p> I have on a heroin trial have not changed. And those views are based</p>
<p> not on some kind of old-fashioned knee jerk reaction of a heroin trial,</p>
<p> they are based on examining what has happened in relation to those</p>
<p> trials around the world. They are also based on a concern I have that</p>
<p> there's always a danger in our society that when a problem looks</p>
<p> as though it may be extremely difficult to solve then a rather instinctive</p>
<p> reaction of some people is to say, well, let's try this, and</p>
<p> maybe that'll solve it without thinking through the consequences</p>
<p> of trying that alternative. And there are many people who believe</p>
<p> that the conduct of a heroin trial would send a very bad signal, would</p>
<p> say to the community that it represents the first step down towards</p>
<p> a far more liberal approach to the drug activity and to the drug trade.</p>
<p> And they are some of the reasons why I don't support a heroin</p>
<p> trial. Could I also say that I think it's important that the</p>
<p> issue of a heroin trial whether you are for it or against it is not</p>
<p> really the major issue. The major issue is to have an effective strategy</p>
<p> in those three areas. So much of the debate now is either about a</p>
<p> heroin trial or the law enforcement side. Now, the law enforcement</p>
<p> is very important but so is education and so is rehabilitation. And</p>
<p> we have put more resources than any Federal Government of the past,</p>
<p> and I don't say that critically of former federal governments,</p>
<p> I am not interested in pointing the finger at former federal governments</p>
<p> or indeed of any State governments. We have put more resources into</p>
<p> rehabilitation through the programmes I announced progressively through</p>
<p> 1997 and 1998 than any federal government.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What do you think of the comments last night of the New South Wales</p>
<p> [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't agree with him nor I notice does Mr Carr and nor</p>
<p> I notice does the New South Wales Coalition. I don't believe</p>
<p> that the community supports the sort of approach that Mr Cowdery outlined.</p>
<p> I respect his view. I mean, one of the difficulties in this issue</p>
<p> is that everybody who is styled as an expert has a different point</p>
<p> of view. And people say, let's have a meeting of experts. That's</p>
<p> fine, the problem is you won't get a united view out of the experts.</p>
<p> Some people who work in the field have a very different view from</p>
<p> others. I have talked to many parents who have lost children from</p>
<p> drug overdoses and one of the perplexing, difficult tragic things</p>
<p> in those discussions apart from the personal hurt so many of them</p>
<p> feel understandably, and the sense of desolation that they feel, is</p>
<p> that they too have very different views. Some of those parents have</p>
<p> a view that no response can be tough enough. Others have a completely</p>
<p> different view and what that really means is that in the end you have</p>
<p> got to use your best judgement as a human being and you can't</p>
<p> just say....it's not just a medical problem, it's a behavioural</p>
<p> problem. Of course people start substance abuse and drug taking because</p>
<p> of unhappiness and depression and a sense of personal failure and</p>
<p> a lack of self-esteem. There are a whole variety of personal reasons</p>
<p> as to why people start and, of course, it's right when people</p>
<p> say the way you stop it is to attack the causes. But successfully</p>
<p> attacking the causes of itself is not a good enough response to the</p>
<p> community. No community will accept a government that goes soft on</p>
<p> people who are making money out of other people's misery and</p>
<p> death. And any government that even breathes of that is a government</p>
<p> that is failing the community but equally we have a responsibility</p>
<p> to help the victims of drug abuse. And when I talk about zero tolerance</p>
<p> I am talking about zero tolerance on drug traffickers, I am talking</p>
<p> about zero tolerance in schools but I am also talking about having</p>
<p> an understanding of people who have got a problem and helping those</p>
<p> people through rehabilitation programmes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Those proposals that you are taking to the meeting.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look, I am not going to even talk about the detail of them yet</p>
<p> but obviously they'll be proposals that are constructive. And</p>
<p> I am deliberately going to have the meeting....the meeting's</p>
<p> on the 9th of April that's after the New South Wales</p>
<p> election and I think that's the right time to have it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, will there be any diversion [inaudible]....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's an ongoing thing and you need to take...to have</p>
<p> fresh proposals or variations of proposals all the time. But I am</p>
<p> not going to, at this stage, foreshadow what's going to be in</p>
<p> them. I am simply going to say that I'll go to that meeting keen</p>
<p> to discuss the issue with the State Premiers keen to ensure that what</p>
<p> we are already doing collectively is understood by the Australian</p>
<p> community. I am not interested in a polemical debate about, you know,</p>
<p> who is, sort of, keener on tackling drug abuse and whether one person</p>
<p> is more active than the next. I am just interested in working together</p>
<p> and I'll have some new ideas to put on the table. But they certainly</p>
<p> won't in any way derogate from or undermine or be contrary to</p>
<p> what we have already proposed. Because what we have already proposed</p>
<p> is really a very, very strong programme.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do State governments need to increase police numbers?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I don't want to get into...look, I mean, I think one</p>
<p> of the last things that should happen in this debate is that States</p>
<p> should be giving the Federal Government a, sort of, unsolicited generic</p>
<p> advice and that the Federal Government should be giving the States</p>
<p> unsolicited generic advice. I would say to any State Premier of Australia</p>
<p> who is seriously interested in co-operating with me and in co-operating</p>
<p> with the Federal Government, let us sit down first of all in private</p>
<p> and have a serious discussion about it, otherwise it simply becomes</p>
<p> a captive of the normal political exchange that goes on between Premiers</p>
<p> and Prime Ministers. And frankly this is too serious for that sort</p>
<p> of issue. I am not interested in saying who is right or who is wrong</p>
<p> at a State level. I don't care what their politics are but I</p>
<p> am interested in having a serious discussion with the elected Premiers</p>
<p> and Chief Ministers of the States and Territories of Australia on</p>
<p> the 9th of April. But until then I am not going to be found</p>
<p> to be criticising any State Premiers and frankly if they are interested</p>
<p> in working with us they shouldn't be seeking to, sort of, demonstrate</p>
<p> that they are more interested in fighting the problem than somebody</p>
<p> else.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you see that the drugs issue will become a.....issue in the</p>
<p> State election campaign?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is a matter for the parties. Look, it should be talked</p>
<p> about, it should be debated and the policies of the two parties should</p>
<p> be presented and should be decided upon by the people of Australia.</p>
<p> And obviously the people of New South Wales and obviously, I am in</p>
<p> practice you see, obviously people will make a judgement on it. And</p>
<p> I think the priority that has been given to crime prevention generally</p>
<p> is a very, very important priority because crime is an issue that</p>
<p> is of concern to people. But it is tremendously easy for the debate</p>
<p> to get picked up and sensationalised and trivialised and misunderstood</p>
<p> and I really don't want to myself get into a slanging match or</p>
<p> a debating exchange in public in this sort of general pointless way</p>
<p> with State Premiers.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>PM, will the .....take advice from any so called experts?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look, I have got an open mind about...look, you always get a,</p>
<p> I mean, I am getting advice...I get advice every day from experts</p>
<p> on everything and that's, you know, that's part and parcel</p>
<p> of political life. But in the end, the only people who can decide</p>
<p> policy change in this country are the elected leaders of the people.</p>
<p> And in the end, most of these issues involve a judgement by human</p>
<p> beings of goodwill who are trying to reach the right decision for</p>
<p> the benefit of the community. Now, I talk to police about drugs, I</p>
<p> talk to people who are working at the sharp end of the human misery</p>
<p> like Salvation Army officers. I talk to doctors, I talk to psychologists,</p>
<p> I am going to talk to the Director of the FBI on Friday. Now, it's</p>
<p> not for any other reason that I think it's important. He was</p>
<p> always going to see me anyway. But I think it's important that</p>
<p> a man like that you listen to, he'll no doubt give me some run</p>
<p> down on what's happened in the United States that doesn't</p>
<p> necessarily mean I am going to say, well let's do all of that</p>
<p> in Australia. I am never one for slavishly copying what is done in</p>
<p> the United States or indeed anywhere else. But you draw your information</p>
<p> from a whole variety of sources but in the end, you have got to make</p>
<p> the decision. And in the end I accept that once I am unwilling to</p>
<p> take political decisions and be seen by the public as accepting responsibility</p>
<p> for them, that is the time to give politics away and that time has</p>
<p> not arrived.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't use the expression give-away. I think it's</p>
<p> an excellent policy and can I, I'm glad you asked me that question</p>
<p> because it allows me to say something about privatisation. I mean</p>
<p> there's one big difference between the Coalition and the Labor</p>
<p> Party at both the State and the Federal level on privatisation, and</p>
<p> that is that we are up front and honest about our position. We believe</p>
<p> in privatisation. We believe that there are economic benefits for</p>
<p> the nation, and in the case of New South Wales for the State, in privatising</p>
<p> those assets. We believe that people should get a return, a personal</p>
<p> return out of that privatisation which is what is being proposed by</p>
<p> the New South Wales Coalition. Everybody knows that Bob Carr and Michael</p>
<p> Egan were desperate to privatise the New South Wales power authority</p>
<p> and everyone knows they were prevented from doing it by the union</p>
<p> bosses of the Labor Party. And everybody knows that Kim Beazley, when</p>
<p> he was Finance Minister in the Keating and Hawke Governments loved</p>
<p> privatising assets like QANTAS, the Commonwealth Bank and Australian</p>
<p> Airlines. Now he's in Opposition he's hypocritically opposing</p>
<p> it. The unions rolled Carr and Egan and now they're hypocritically</p>
<p> attacking the Coalition. Now I think they just ought to stay out of</p>
<p> that because they have no credibility on it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will you take the shares or cash?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The shares or the cash? Well I haven't considered that yet. And</p>
<p> in fact I've been living in Canberra for the last month.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What's your principal place of residence?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What's my principal place of.....? Well I vote in the electorate</p>
<p> of Bennelong.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you still have a power bill?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I do have a power bill. I still have a power bill for 19 Milner Crescent</p>
<p> Woollstonecraft.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] benchmark for future privatisations? Will the Federal</p>
<p> Government [inaudible] on those kinds of give-aways or privatisations</p>
<p> you're planning to...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think anything necessarily sets or doesn't set a</p>
<p> benchmark. I think it depends entirely on the circumstances. But I</p>
<p> think what Kerry has proposed in New South Wales is sensible, it's</p>
<p> clever, it's innovative, it brings home to people the value for</p>
<p> them of the privatisation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is it a bribe?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No it's not a bribe. How is it as bribe to return the benefit</p>
<p> of something to all of the people and that is what she is doing. She</p>
<p> is returning the benefit of the sale of that asset to all of the people.</p>
<p> I don't think that is a bribe. A bribe is something that you</p>
<p> give in totally different circumstances. I mean, of course the critics</p>
<p> of it are going to call it a bribe. I don't think it is at all.</p>
<p> I think it is a very novel, intelligent way of returning to the people,</p>
<p> and reminding the people of the benefits of privatisation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, is it fair to link university grants to [inaudible]</p>
<p> union fees?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it is very fair for the law to prevent compulsory unionism</p>
<p> in universities as it does in the private workplace or in the public</p>
<p> sector. I find the claim being made by the Vice-Chancellors Organisation</p>
<p> this morning that in some way this is an interference in the autonomy</p>
<p> of universities. I find that quite extraordinary because if a private</p>
<p> company practices discrimination or compulsory unionism, under the</p>
<p> law of Australia they can't do it. Yet apparently the universities</p>
<p> are asserting the right to do it. I think it is entirely fair to ensure</p>
<p> that the law against discrimination is properly enforced.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is it fair to cut grants to universities?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it is fair to take whatever reasonable steps to make certain</p>
<p> that that law is enforced.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You have spoken about the economy today. [inaudible] under threat</p>
<p> from Asia or over....?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think there are good signs that the worst of the Asian economic</p>
<p> downturn has past us, although it will still be some time before the</p>
<p> economies of most of the Asian countries worst effected, that most</p>
<p> of them....it will still be time before they are out of the woods.</p>
<p> I think Australia has come through the Asian economic downturn remarkably</p>
<p> well and that is a credit to the Australian people first and foremost.</p>
<p> It also reflects very well on the policies of the Coalition Government.</p>
<p> The current outlook for the Australian economy remains very strong</p>
<p> and I haven't seen fundamentals in the Australian economy as</p>
<p> strong as they have been now since the late 1960s. You have to go</p>
<p> back to that time to find a period where the Australian economy has</p>
<p> been as strong.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is the worst over Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I never like dealing in absolutes like that because.....is</p>
<p> the worst over in relation to Asia? Look, the signs are that the worst</p>
<p> is probably behind us but I say that with a degree of caution.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
