<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2401</transcript-id>
    <title>FURTHER VIETNAM WITHDRAWALS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/04/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002401.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: PM No. 43/ 1971<br />
FURTHER VIETNAM WITHDRAWALS<br />
Statement ty the Prime Minister, Mr. William McMahon<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. McMahon said in Brisbane this afternoon that<br />
President Nixon's statement at mid-day clearly indicated the growing capacity<br />
of the Republic of Vietnam to provide its own defence.<br />
It was this growing capability and the success of the total Vietnamisation<br />
programme which had enabled President Nixon to announce the continuing<br />
withdrawals of United States' military personnel.<br />
Mr. McMahon said that this same progress by the people, Government and<br />
armed forces of the Republic of Vietnam had made it possible for him to announce<br />
on 30 March, the withdrawal of 1, 000 Australian servicemen from Vietnam<br />
beginning next month.<br />
Mr. McMahon said that the President had sent him advance notice of the<br />
decisions. They would be taken into account by the Australian Government in keeping<br />
continually under review the problem of future arrangements about Australian<br />
forces in Vietnam.<br />
Mr. McMahon said that the people and Government of Vietnam deserved<br />
praise for all they had done to make Mr. Nixon's announcement possible.<br />
But it must be remembered that when Mr. Nixon had taken off ice he had been<br />
under enormous domestic pressure, as he still is, to end United States' involvement<br />
in the War by an immediate withdrawal of United States forces. Instead, President<br />
Nixon had taken the courageous and difficult course of reducing the United States'<br />
commitment only as the increasing capability of the South Vietnamese Government<br />
and forces made ir possible to do so, without conceding to the North Vietnamese<br />
and Viet Gong all that had been so far achieved.<br />
The President recognised that, the War would not necessarily end simply<br />
because United States' forces were being reduced. He had taken the view that the<br />
United States' responsibility extended not only to the citizens of his own country,<br />
but also to the people of the Republic of Vietnam who had suffered so much and who<br />
had called upon the United States for assistance against North Vietnamese aggression.<br />
The Prime Minister warmly endorsed Mr. Nixon's call for an end to the<br />
barbaric use by the enemy of prisoners of war as pawns in negotiation.<br />
CA NBERRA<br />
8 APRIL 1971 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
