<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9619</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP AUSTRALIAN REPUBLIC (EMBARGO: 7.30PM 7 JUNE 1995)</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009619.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 51/ 95<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
AUSTRALIAN REPUBLIC<br />
( embargo: 7.3Opm 7 June 1995)<br />
It is the view of the Government that Australia's head of state should be an Australian<br />
and that Australia should be a republic by the year 2001.<br />
I announced in the Parliament today the Government's approach to achieving the<br />
transition to an Australian republic. The proposals involve minimal change to Australia's<br />
system of government and institutions.<br />
This is the final step to becoming a fully independent nation. It will permit the full and<br />
unambiguous expression of Australia's national identity.<br />
The Government is releasing its proposals as a focus for further public discussion and<br />
debate. All Australians should participate in this important national debate.<br />
The Government's package is outlined in the Attachment. The main features are:<br />
the Commonwealth Parliament would appoint an Australian head of state by a twothirds<br />
majority vote in a joint sitting of the Senate and the House of Representatives a<br />
process designed to ensure that the office of head of state is not politicised;<br />
serving Federal, State and Territory politicians would not be eligible for nomination<br />
until at leat 5 years after their departure from Parliament;<br />
all the powers possessed by the Governor-General would be held by an Australian<br />
head of state, including the so-called " reserve powers"; and<br />
the States should be free to determine their own constitutional arrangements.<br />
However, the Government is confident that the Australian people will decide against<br />
the constitutional anomaly of monarchical States existing within a republican<br />
Commonwealth.<br />
The proposals can only be introduced by referendum. Under the Constitution, the<br />
changes will require the support of a majority of Australian voters and a majority of voters<br />
in a majority of the States. </p>
<p>2<br />
The Government proposes to hold a referendum in 1998 or 1999. If the people agree, the<br />
changes would come into effect no later than the centenary of Australia's Federation in<br />
2001. Our course is simple and, we believe, irresistible as simple and irresistible as the idea of<br />
a Commonwealth of Australia was to the Australians of the 1890s.<br />
Our goal now echoes that founding sentiment of a century ago. It flows from the fact that<br />
we are all Australians. We share a continent. We share a past, present and a future.<br />
And our head of state should be one of us.<br />
CANBERRA 7 June 1995 </p>
<p>ATTACHMENT<br />
AUSTRALIAN REPUBLIC GOVERNMENT PACKAGE<br />
" Commonwealth of Australia" would be retained as the title of an Australian republic, and " President of the<br />
Commonwealth of Australia" would be adopted as the title of an Australian head of state.<br />
The President would be appointed for a non-renewable term of office of five years by a two-thirds majority<br />
vote in a joint sitting of the Commonwealth Parliament. following the nomination of a single individual by the<br />
Prime Minister. The requirement for a two-thirds majority of a joint sifting will mean effectively that there<br />
will need to be prior bi-partisan agreement to the nominee.<br />
The President would be an Australian citizen of voting age and may not hold any other remunerated position<br />
while in office.<br />
Serving Commonwealth, State and Territory parliamentarians would be excluded from nomination as<br />
President, and former Commonwealth, State and Territory parliamentarians would be excluded from<br />
nomination until five years have passed since their departure from parliament.<br />
The Commonwealth Parliament would nominate, by a two-thirds majority vote in a joint sitting, the office<br />
holder( s) entitled to temporarily perform the duties of President should circumstance or need arise.<br />
The Government supports the appointment of State Governors to act as President when needed, with those<br />
eligible being from States no longer using The Queen to appoint their Governors. If no State Governor from<br />
a republican State is available, the President of the Senate should act.<br />
The President would have the right to resign. His or her resignation would be passed to the Speaker of the<br />
House of Representatives, who would convey it to the Parliament. The resignation of a President would be<br />
self-executing, with the Constitution to provide for an acting President to assume office upon the resignation<br />
of the President.<br />
The President would be subject to removal by a two-thirds majority vote in a joint sitting of the<br />
Commonwealth Parliament, with either House to have the right to initiate the joint sitting by passing a<br />
motion supported by a simple majority of its members. However, the President's removal would not be<br />
contingent on a specified set of facts, circumstances or conditions.<br />
The President would perform the ceremonial and representational functions currently performed by the<br />
Queen and Governor-General.<br />
The President would exercise the powers currently exercised by the Governor-General under<br />
Commonwealth legislation, on the advice of the Federal Executive Council.<br />
The President would exercise all the constitutional powers currently vested in the Governor-General and,<br />
except in relation to the reserve powers, be expressly required to act in accordance with Ministerial advice.<br />
The reserve powers currently possessed by the Governor-General would remain with the President, and the<br />
Constitution would provide that the constitutional conventions governing the exercise of these powers would<br />
continue, but the conventions would not be spelt out. The manner of exercise by the President of the<br />
reserve powers would not be open to challenge in the courts.<br />
All references in the Constitution to the Queen, the Crown and the Governor-General would be removed.<br />
The States would be free to decide their own State constitutional arrangements.<br />
Australia would remain a member of the Commonwealth of Nations. Currently, 29 of the 51 member<br />
countries of the Commonwealth are republics.<br />
Copies of the Prime Ministers speech are available from the Prime Ministers Press Office, telephone<br />
( 06) 277 7744. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
