<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3092</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER MR. E.G. WHITLAM, Q.C. M.P., AT THE ENVEILING OF THE EUREKA FLAG, BALLARAT FINE ART GALLERY. BALLARAT, 3 DEECMBER 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/12/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003092.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINIISTER<br />
MR, E. G. WHITLAM, MP.,<br />
AT THE UNVEILING OF THE EUREKA FLAG,<br />
BALLARAT FINE ART GALLERY,<br />
BALLARAT, 3 DECEMBER<br />
1973<br />
NO DOUBT MY OPPONENTS WOULD SAY THAT THE CHIEF LESSON<br />
OF EUREKA IS A SIMPLE ONE: THE GOVERNMENT WAS NO MORE POPULAR<br />
WITH MINING INTERESTS IN THE MID-NINETEENTH CENTURY THAN THE<br />
PRESEN4T GOVERNMENT IS TODAY. NEVERTHELESS, I HAVE ALWAYS THOUGHT<br />
IT AN AUSPICIOUS COINCIDENCE THAT THE ELECTION OF THE FIRST<br />
NATIONAL LABOR GOVERNM4ENT FOR 23 YEARS SHOULD HAVE OCCURRED,<br />
ALMOST TO THE DAY, ON THE ANNIVERSARY OF THE EUREKA STOCKADE.<br />
NOT THAT MY PARTY CLAIMS ANY MONOPOLY OF PATRIOTIC SENTIMENT,<br />
ANY EXCLUSIVE AFFINITY WITH THE SYMBOLS OF AUSTRALIAN HISTORY.,<br />
EUREKA HAD LITTLE OR NOTHING TO DO. WITH THE FORMULATION OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY. IT HAD LITTLE OR NOTHING TO DO WITH<br />
THE GREAT MOVEMENT FOR FEDERATION THE MOVEMENT THAT CAME<br />
TO FRUITION HALF A CENTURY AFTER EUREKA IN THE EMERGENCE OF<br />
AN AUSTRALIAN NATION. YET WE IN THE LABOR PARTY'-WOULD<br />
BE LESS THAN HUMAN IF WE DID NOT SEE IN THE EVENTS OF EUREKA<br />
SAD AND REMOTE AND ISOLATED AS THEY WERE A SYMBOL OF THE PRIDE<br />
THE INDEPENDENCE OF SPIRIT, THE DEMOCRATIC TRADITIONS AND THE<br />
STRONG NATIONALIST ASPIRATIONS FOR WHICH LABOR HAS ALWAYS STOOD,.<br />
AND WITH WHICH THE NEW GOVERNMENT IS ESPECIALLY IDENTIFIED. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
I HOPE YOU WILL FORGIVE ME FOR STRIKING THIS PARTISAN<br />
NOTE, IT IS A TRUISM, PERHAPS, THAT THE IMPORTANCE OF AN<br />
HISTORICAL EVENT LIES NOT IN WHAT HAPPENED BUT IN WHAT<br />
LATER GENERATIONS BELIEVE TO HAVE HAPPENED, ON THAT SCORE,<br />
THERE CAN BE NO DOUBT OF EUREKA'S IMPORTANCE TO THE LABOR<br />
PARTY AND TO AUSTRALIA, HISTORY IS A PROCESS OF COLLECTIVE<br />
REMEMBRANCE; AND BEYOND QUESTION THE EVENTS OF 3 DECEMBER<br />
1854 PERSIST IN THE MEMORY AND CONSCIOUSNESS OF OUR PEOPLE<br />
IN THE WORDS OF ONE WRITER AS " THE PIONEER AND SUPREME<br />
AUSTRALIAN EVENT IN THE SPECTACULAR SENSE," DR, EVATT, A GREAT<br />
STATESMAN AND A PERCEPTIVE HISTORIAN, WENT SO FAR AS TO DECLARE<br />
THAT " AUSTRALIAN DEMOCRACY WAS BORN AT EUREKA", I ACCEPT THAT<br />
JUDGEMENT, AND HERE, IN THE CITY AND BIRTHPLACE OF EUREKA,<br />
I PROCLAIM THE CENTRAL AND ENDURING RELEVANCE OF THOSE EVENTS<br />
TO OUR OWN DAY, TO THE GREAT REFORMS IN OUR NATIONAL LIFE AND<br />
INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS ON WHICH THIS COUNTRY IS EMBARKED, AND<br />
THE CREATION OF THE MORE JUST AND HUMANE SOCIETY TO WHICH MY<br />
GOVERNMENT IS COMMITTED,<br />
YOU'HEAR MUCH THESE DAYS OF THE " NEW NATIONALISM"<br />
OF ALL THE SLOGANS APPLIED TO MY GOVERNMENT, I THINK IT IS THE<br />
ONLY ONE OF WHICH I CANNOT CLAIM THE AUTHORSHIP, LIKE A GREAT<br />
NUMBER OF THINGS, IT WAS INVENTED BY THE PRESS, YET I AM HAPPY<br />
TO ADOPT AND AFFIRM IT, THERE ARE MANY PEOPLE WHO SEE SOMETHING<br />
SINISTER OR THREATENING IN THE IDEA OF A " NEW NATIONALISM" SOME<br />
DISTURBANCE TO OUR WAY OF LIFE, THE OVERTURNING OF RECEIVED IDEAS<br />
AND SETTLED TRADITIONS, THE BREAKING OFF OF OLD FRIENDSHIPS,<br />
THAT IS NOT WHAT WE INTEND THE NEW NATIONALISM TO MEAN, </p>
<p>-3-<br />
RATHER THAN DISCARD OUR AUTHENTIC TRADITIONS, WE WANT<br />
TO RESTORE AND INVIGORATE THEM. RATHER THAN BREAK OFF OLD<br />
FRIENDSHIPS, WE WANT TO FORM NEW. ONES FRIENDSHIPS THAT WILL<br />
ENHANCE OUR NAME AND REPUTATION IN THE WORLD AS A GOOD FRIEND,<br />
A CONCERNED AND HELPFUL PARTNER IN OUR REGION AND BEYOND.<br />
RATHER THAN OVERTURN THE TRUE VALUES OF AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY,<br />
WE WANT TO RESURRECT AND FOSTER THOSE VALUES. THE LABOR PARTY,<br />
THE PRESENT GOVERNMENT, HAS NEVER HAD ANY DOUBT ABOUT WHAT<br />
THOSE VALUES WERE. THEY WERE, IN TRUTH, IDENTIFIED AND PROCLAIMED<br />
AT EUREKA JUSTICE, FREEDOM, INDEPENDENCE,<br />
FRATERNITY, THE INSTINCT FOR FAIR PLAY AND EQUAL OPPORTUNITY<br />
FOR ALL OUR PEOPLE. EGALITARIANISM BY WHATEVER NAME<br />
WE CALL IT IS AT THE HEART OF\ AUSTRALIAN TRADITION.<br />
INTANGIBLE AS THESE VALUES ARE, THEY HAVE A VERY REAL<br />
MEANING FOR THE LABOR PARTY, THEY ARE CLEARLY EXPRESSED IN THE<br />
PLATFORM OF THE PARTY AND IN THE POLICIES OF THE GOVERNMENT.<br />
ANYONE READING THE PLATFORM WILL BE STRUCK BY THE EMPHASIS<br />
ON " AUSTRALIA", THE " AUSTRALIAN NATION", ON NATIONAL GOALS AND<br />
ASPIRATIONS, ALONE AMONG'THE PARTIES WE AFFIRM THE SUPREMACY<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN SOVEREIGNTY OVER THE WHOLE NATION AND ITS<br />
TERRITORIES. ANYONE WHO HAS STUDIED THE RECORD OF THE GOVERNMENT'S<br />
ACHIEVEMENTS SINCE COMING TO OFFICE WILL RECOGNISE THIS NATIONALIST<br />
SENTIMENT AS THE GREAT BINDING THEME OF ALL OUR MAJOR DECISIONS<br />
AND INITIATIVES. I I, </p>
<p>-4<br />
AS A PHILOSOPHY, A MODUS LIVEIADI FOR THE NEW GOVERNMENT,<br />
THE / INEW NATIONALISM If BRINGS TOGETHER A GREAT NUMBER OF DIVERSE<br />
STRANDS AND ATTITUDES AND AMBITIONS. IT MEANS,<br />
THE GREATEST POSSIBLE MEASURE OF AUSTRALIAN CONTROL OVER OUR<br />
INDUSTRIES AND RESOURCES. IT MEANS AN INDEPENDENT FOREIGN<br />
POLICY NOT ONE WITHOUT ALLIES, BUT ONE WITHOUT OBSESSIONS,<br />
WITHOUT DISTORTIONS, WITHOUT SUBJECTION TO THE IDEOLOGIES OR<br />
FOLLIES OF OTHER POWERS. IT MEANS THE CREATION OF A ROBUST AND<br />
THRIVING ECONOMY BY WHICH THE TALENTS AND SKILLS OF ALL AUSTRALIANS<br />
CAN BE FULFILLED. IT MEANS STRENGTHENING AND DEVELOPING<br />
AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRIES, INCLUDING RURAL INDUSTRIES, TO. MAKE.<br />
THEM MORE RESILIENT AND COMPETITIVE IN A CHANGING<br />
WORLD. IT MEANS THE FULLEST PARTICIPATION OF AUSTRALIANS IN<br />
DECISIONS INVOLVING THEIR OWN DESTINY. IT MEANS THE PRESERVATION<br />
OF THE NATIONAL ESTATE OUR HISTORIC BUILDINGS, AND NATURAL<br />
ENVIRONMENT. IT MEANS THE PROTECTION OF ABORIGINAL CULTURE<br />
AND TRADITIONS AS THE ORIGINAL AND MOST AUTHENTIC EXPRESSION OF<br />
AN AUSTRALIAN IDENTITY. IT MEANS THE CULTIVATION OF VITALITY AND<br />
CREATIVENESS IN THE ARTS, IN ORDER TO IMPART To AUSTRALIAN LIFE<br />
A VIGOROUS AND DISTINCTIVE INTELLECTUAL IMPETUS.<br />
THERE IS NOTHING COARSE OR INTOLERANT OR XENOPHOBIC<br />
ABOUT THIS KIND OF NATIONALISM. IT DOES NOT MEAN CLOSING OUR SOCIETY<br />
TO BENEFICIAL IDEAS FROM ABROAD. AN AUTHENTIC AUSTRALIANSIM<br />
CAN READILY ACCOMMODATE FOREIGN INFLUENCES AND FOREIGN CULTURES,<br />
JUST AS WE HAVE PROSPERED FROM THE POST-WAR PROGRAM OF IMMIGRATION.<br />
THEY WERE MIGRANTS, AFTER ALL IRISH, EUROPEAN, AMERICAN WHO<br />
PROVIDED THE BACKBONE OF THE EUREKA RISING, NOR DO I CARE FOR<br />
THE ARGUMENT THAT A " tNEW NATIONALISM' IS OUTMODED OR EVEN DANGEROUS<br />
IN A WORLD THAT HAS SUFFERED TOO MUCH FROM NATIONALISTIC HATREDS<br />
AND PASSIONS AND STRIVES ONLY FOR PEACE AND SECURITY BASED ON </p>
<p>INTERNATIONAL UNDERSTANDING, NO GOVERNMENT IS MORE COMMITTED THAN<br />
MINE TO INTERNATIONALISM IN THIS HIGHEST SENSE, YET IF WE LOOK<br />
AT THE NATIONS, EXCLUDING THE MAJOR POWERS, THAT HAVE ADVANCED<br />
INTERNATIONAL CO-OPERATION THE MOST INDIA, CANADA, THE<br />
SCANDANAVIAN COUNTRIES WE FIND THEY ARE NATIONS WITH A SECURE<br />
AND DISTINCTIVE NATIONAL IDENTITY OF THEIR OWN, ECHOES AND<br />
SHADOWS, SATELLITES AND VASSALS ARE NOT FORCES FOR PEACE AND<br />
CO-OPERATION: THEY ARE MORE LIKELY TO BE THE FIRST VICTIMS<br />
WHEN PEACE AND CO-OPERATION ARE OVERTHROWN,<br />
DURING THE ELECTION CAMPAIGN LAST YEAR, I ANNOUNCED THAT<br />
A LABOR GOVERNMENT WOULD OFFICIALLY PROCLAIM A NEW AUSTRALIAN<br />
NATIONAL ANTHEM, THIS YEAR A COMPETITION WAS HELD TO SEE IF<br />
ANYONE COULD PRODUCE BETTER WORDS AND MUSIC THAN THE SONGS<br />
WE HAVE ALREADY, THE INTERESTING THING ABOUT THAT EXERCISE WAS<br />
NOT THE QUALITY OF THE ENTRIES THERE ARE VERY FEW PEOPLE WHO<br />
CAN COMPOSE GOOD WORDS AND MUSIC BUT THE QUANTITY, THERE WERE<br />
MORE THAN 1300 ANTHEMS, GIVEN THE DIFFICULTIES INVOLVED, THAT<br />
WAS A CONSIDERABLE AND HEARTENING RESPONSE, THERE IS NO DOUBT<br />
IN MY MIND THAT THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE WANT A NATIONAL ANTHEM<br />
OF THEIR OWN AN ANTHEM THAT TRULY REFLECTS THE CHARACTER AND<br />
TRADITIONS OF OUR PEOPLE, NEXT YEAR WE SHALL HAVE SUCH AN ANTHEM,<br />
THERE IS NOTHING EXCESSIVE. OR JINGOISTIC INTHE PROPuSITION THAT<br />
AUSTRALIA SHOULD NO LONGER BE WILLING TO SHARE A NATIONAL ANTHEM<br />
WITH ANOTHER COUNTRY, </p>
<p>6-<br />
I CONGRATULATE THOSE WHO HAVE PRESERVED AND RESTORED<br />
THIS HISTORIC FLAG, IT IS FITTING THAT IT SHOULD REMAIN HERE IN<br />
BALLARAT, IN THIS GALLERY, AS A-' RELIC OF EUREKA. OUR PAST IS<br />
DEFICIENT IN TURBULENT EVENTS, IN THE CIVIL CONVULSIONS AND<br />
UPHEAVALS THAT PROVIDE FOR OLDER CIVILISATIONS A FOCUS FOR<br />
NATIONALISTIC FERVOUR AND POPULAR EMOTION, THOSE SYMBOLS AND<br />
RITUALS WE HAVE, LIKE OUR PARLIAMENTARY AND CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM<br />
ITSELF, DERIVE FROM A QUIESCENT COLONIAL PAST. I AM NOT ONE TO<br />
ARGUE, AS SOME ROMANTICS DO, THAT TRUE NATIONHOOD MUST SPRING<br />
FROM THE AGONY AND SUFFERING ENDURED BY FORMER GENERATIONS.<br />
YET IS IN THE NATURE OF THINGS THAT AN EVENT LIKE EUREKA<br />
WITH ALL ITS ASSOCIATIONS, WITH ALL ITS POTENT SYMBOLISM,, WILL<br />
ACQUIRE AN AURA OF EXCITMENT AND ROMANCE, AND STIR THE IMAGINATION<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE.<br />
DR. JOHNSON REMARKED THAT PATRIOTISM IS THE LAST REFUGE<br />
OF A SCOUNDREL. HE WAS WELL AWARE THAT PATRIOTISM CAN BE CARRIED<br />
TO EXTREMES, AND THAT NATIONALISM CAN BE CARRIED TO EXCESS.<br />
THERE IS NEVERTHELESS A KIND OF NATIONALISM THAT EVERY COUNTRY<br />
NEEDS. IT IS A BENIGN AND CONSTRUCTIVE NATIONALISM. IT HAS TO DO<br />
WITH SELF-CONFIDENCE, WITH MATURITY, WITH ORIGINALITY, WITH<br />
INDEPENDENCE, OF MIND. IF AUSTRALIA IS TO REMAIN IN THE<br />
FOREFRONT OF NATIONS, IF TO RESIST T HE TEMPTATION TO BE<br />
A SECOND-RATE OR IMITATIVE SOCIETY, '-IF . DETERMINED TO BE A<br />
TRUE SOURCE OF POWER AND IDEAS IN THE WORLD,,<br />
AGENEROUS AND TOLERANT AS A itj1J<br />
RESPECTED FOR OUR GENEROSITY AND TOLERANCE, THEN<br />
IBELIEVE THAT SOMETHING LIKE THE " NEW NATIONALISM" MUST PLAY A<br />
PART IN OUR GOVERNMENT AND IN THE LIVES OF US ALL. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
