<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1154</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 70/1965 - FORMER NAVAL CHIEF TO SUPERVISE AUSTRALIAN PARTICIPATION IN CANADIAN EXHIBITION - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/09/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001154.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. 11. No. 70/ 196<br />
FORMER NAVAL CHIEF TO SUPERVISE AUSTRALIAN PARTICIPATION<br />
IN CANADIAN EXHIBITION<br />
Statement by te Prime Minister, Sir Robert Menzies<br />
Vice-Admiral Sir Hastings Harrington, C. B. E,<br />
DS. O. has been appointed as Commissioner-General to represent<br />
Australia in connection with the International Exhibition<br />
El' 67 to be held in Montreal, Canada, betieen April and<br />
October, 1967 as part of the Canadian Government's celebration<br />
of the centenary of Canadian Confederation.<br />
Sir Hastings, who recently retired as Chief of<br />
the Naval Staff will be in charge of the special arrangements<br />
to be made for Australia's participation in the exhibition.<br />
The principal feature of this participation will be an<br />
Australian pavilion. Expo. 67 has been approved as a First Category<br />
Exhibition by the International Bureau of Exhibitions. It<br />
takes as its theme " Man and His World" and will portray human<br />
aqcomplishments in various fields.<br />
As part of the arrangements it is now making, the<br />
Australian Government proposes to appoint a representative<br />
committee which will be able to furnish expert advice and<br />
suggestions to the Commissioner-General on the nature of the<br />
Australian pavilion and other Australian participation. The<br />
Commissioner-General will also draw upon the resources of<br />
Commonwealth Departments and authorities and will be assisted<br />
by a small specialist staff. He will be in consultation with<br />
Government and other bodies as planning proceeds.<br />
The office of the Commissioner-General will be<br />
attached to the Prime Minister's Department and will, for<br />
the time being, be located at Red Cross House, Hobart Place,<br />
Canberra City.<br />
CANBERRA September, 1965. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
