<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3526</transcript-id>
    <title>LIMITATION OF STRATEGIC OFFENSIVE ARMS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003526.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1 . W<br />
NO DATE<br />
M 152 5 December, 1974<br />
LIMITATION OF STRATEGIC OFFENSIVE ARMS<br />
The Prime Minister and Acting Foreign Minister,<br />
Mr Whitlam, said today that he welcomed the joint statement<br />
by President Ford and Mr Brezhnev on the limitation of<br />
strategic offensive arms issued at the conclusion of their<br />
recent talks at Vladivostock. The two leaders had reaffirmed<br />
their intention to conclude a further ten-year agreement on<br />
the limitation of strate-ic offensive arms.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that all governments should agree<br />
with President Ford and Mr Brezhnev that a long-term agreement<br />
on this question would be a sipnific-nt contribution<br />
to improving relations between the United States and the<br />
Soviet Union, to reducing the danger of war, and to the<br />
enhancing of world peace.<br />
The joint statement said that the two leaders<br />
agreed that further negotiations, which would resume in<br />
Geneva next month, would incorporate relevant provisions<br />
of the interim SALT agreement concluded in 1972, and provide<br />
for a new agreement to run from October 1977 to 1985. Both<br />
sides would be entitled to have a certain agreed aggregate<br />
number of land and sea-based missiles equipped with multiple<br />
independently targetted warheads ( MIRVs).<br />
The Prime Minister said this agreement regarding<br />
future negotiations was a significant and heartening<br />
result of the first meeting between President e'ord and<br />
Mr Brezhnev. He welcomed the comment of the US Secretary<br />
of State, Dr Henry Kissinger that the agreement " marks the<br />
breakthrough witl the SALT negotiations that we have sought<br />
to achieve in recent years".<br />
The Frime Minister zecalled that during his own<br />
address to the United Nations General Assembly on<br />
September, he had spoken of the special obligations which<br />
the might of the superpowers imposed upon them, and had<br />
said that other countries were entitled to ask the superpowers<br />
to move forward to a stage of complete detente where<br />
their tremendous power can be used jointly to the betterment<br />
of the whole of civilisation. A </p>
<p>The Prime Minister said all reasonable persons<br />
must realise that there would be very many great problems<br />
to be resolved in the long negotiations which would be<br />
held between the US and the Soviet Union towards the<br />
conclusion of a new ten-year agreement, but that it was<br />
heartening to learn that President Ford and Mr Brezhnev<br />
had concluded that favourable prospects existed for the<br />
completion of the work on the proposed new agreement in<br />
1975. The subjects to be discussed were very complex<br />
and highly technical, and they bore on the vital security<br />
of two super powers and thus, directly or indirectly, on<br />
the security of all othcr countries in the world.<br />
The Prime Minister said he hoped that this<br />
welcome development between the two super powers would be<br />
followed by action by the US and the Soviet Union and by<br />
the other nuclear powers and countries of advanced technology<br />
towards strengthening the NPT, and thus working for<br />
the containment and reduction of nuclear weapons, and to<br />
endeavour to ensure that nuclear energy, with its tremendous<br />
potential, was directed towards peaceful uses. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
