<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6175</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME  MINISTER, THE HON RJ HAWKE AC MP, TO THE BRISBANE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE, 8 AUGUST 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/08/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006175.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J. AUST AAI1 . I. A<br />
PRIME 1/ I NISTER.<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRI E rI'USTER, THE HON, R. J. HAWKE, f. P.<br />
TO THE BRISBANE CHAfNBER OF COMIERCE<br />
8 AUGUST 1983<br />
EMBARGOED AGAJNST DELIVERI CHECK_ GAINST DEIVERY<br />
THE TIMING OF THIS OCCASION MY FIRST VISIT TO<br />
QUEENSLAND SINCE THE ELECTION IS BOTH FORTUNATE AND FORTUITOUS.<br />
FORTUITOUS BECAUSE NOTHING IN THE SCHEDULING OF THIS<br />
VISIT HAD ANYTHING TO DO WITH THE INTERESTING POLITICAL EVENTS<br />
WHICH ARE NOW TAKING PLACE IN QUEENSLAND AND WHICH OBVIOUSLYj<br />
ONE WAY OR ANOTHER, MUST HAVE CONSIDERABLE SIGNIFICANCE FOR THE<br />
FUTURE OF BOTH QUEENSLAND AND AUSTRALIA. AND BEYOND THAT,<br />
I WISH TO MAKE NO COMMENT WHATSOEVER.<br />
BUT FORTUNATE BECAUSE THERE IS NO BETTER PLACE THAN<br />
BRISBANE, AND NO MORE RELEVANT FORUM THAN THIS CHAMBER OF<br />
COMMERCE, FOR ME TO HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO GIVE THE GENERAL<br />
BACKGROUND TO THE MOST IMPORTANT EVENT OF THIS YEAR, APART FROM<br />
THE 5 MARCH ELECTION ITSELF.<br />
AND OF COURSE, I MEAN, BY THAT, THE BACKGROUND TO<br />
THE 1983 BUDGET, I SAY " IEBAKGROUr" ADVISEDLY AND WITH PRECISION.<br />
./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
THAT, OF COURSE, IS AS FAR AS i CAN GO<br />
TO GIVE YOU, AS REPRESENTATIVES OF THE QUEENSLAND AND<br />
AUSTRALIAN BUSINESS COMMUNITY THE BACKGROUND AGAUINST WHICH<br />
WE, AS A GOVERNMENT, HAVE MAD) E THE DECISIONS WHICH WILL BE<br />
ANNOUNCED BY THE TREASURER,.&amp; P KEATING, ON THE 23RD AUGUST.<br />
AND ABOVF ALL I WISH TO CONVEY A MESSAGE, NOT JUST<br />
ABOUT THE BUDGET ITSELF, BUT ABOUT THE PROSPECTS FOR THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY UPON WHICH OUR FIRST BUDGET WILL BE<br />
BASED. AND THAT BASIC MESSAGE WITH ALL THE NECESSARY<br />
QUALIFICATIONS AND RESERVATIONS, THE REASONS FOR WNHICHI<br />
SHALL MAKE QUITE CLEAR IN THE COURSE OF THIS ADDRESS THAT<br />
BASIC MESSAGE IS ONE OF FIRMLY-BASED CONFIDENCE,<br />
LET ME FIRST MAKE SOME GENERAL OBSERVATIONS ABOUT<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY, WITH A FEW PARTICULAR REFERENCES TO<br />
QUEENSLAND. IT SEEMS THAT Ali IMPROVED SALES OUTLOOK IS LEADING<br />
TO REVERSAL OF THE DE-STOCKING THAT EXACERBATED LAST YEAR'S<br />
DECLINE, THE RAINS HAVE SET THE SCENE FOR A YEAR OF STRONG<br />
FARM GROWTH, ALTHOUGH NATURE HAS REMINDED US OF OUR OWN<br />
VULNERABILITY IN THE AUSTRALIAN BUSH BY REPLACING DROUGHT<br />
WITH FLOOD IN PARTS OF OUEENSLAND. </p>
<p>IMPROVED WORLD DEMAND CONDITIONS HAVE INCREASED<br />
PROFITABILITY IN SOME OF OUR MINERALS AND RURAL INDUSTRIES<br />
NOTABLY NON-FERROUS METALS AND SUGAR AMONGST INDUSTRIES<br />
IMPORTANT TO QUEENSLAND,<br />
SOME PROPOSALS FOR LARGE RESOURCE INVESTMENTS ARE<br />
BEING DUSTED AND TAKEN BACK INTO THE BOARDROOMS,<br />
THERE ARE SIGNS OF RETURNING CONSUMER CONFIDENCE.<br />
PRODUCTION AND EMPLOYMENT IN MOST INDUSTRIES HAVE PULLED OUT<br />
OF THE FREE FALL THAT CHARACTERISED THE YEAR BEFORE MY<br />
GOVERNMENT TOOK OFFICE. A FEW KEY INDUSTRIES, INCLUDING<br />
HOUSING AND STEEL, ARE OPERATING AT HIGHER LEVELS.<br />
UNDERPINNING THIS RETURN OF CONFIDENCE HAS BEEN<br />
OUR EXPANSIONARY FISCAL POLICIES, AND A RE-DISCOVERY THAT<br />
AUSTRALIANS ARE CAPABLE OF WORKING TOGETHER FOR COMMON PURPOSES,<br />
IT IS NOT YET A STRONG RECOVERY. AT THIS STAGE WE<br />
PREFER TO CALL IT A LIFT IN ACTIVITY, THE IMPROVEMENT IN<br />
ACTIVITY IS UNEVEN, AS IT IS IN THE LEAD-UP TO ALL RECOVERIES,<br />
SOME TYPES OF ACTIVITY REMAIN DEPRESSED. PRIVATE<br />
FIXED INVESTMENT OUTSIDE HOUSING WILL FALL FURTHER BEFORE IT<br />
STRENGTHENS AWAITING, AS IT MUST, THE REALITY OF<br />
INCREASED DEMAND AT HOME AND ABROAD. / 4<br />
*, jJ </p>
<p>THE SIGNS OF IMPROVEMENT ARE NOT UNIFORM ACROSS<br />
AUSTRALIA. QUEENSLAND BUSINESS LEADERS WILL HAVE NOTED THE<br />
WEAKER GROWTH, RELATIVE TO AUSTRALIA AS A WHOLE, OF SOME<br />
QUEENSLAND DEMAND INDICATORS IN THE MOST RECENT MONTHS,<br />
INCLUDING MOTOR VEHICLE REGISTRATIONS AND RETAIL SALES.<br />
QUEENSLAND DWELLING APPROVALS AND HOUSING LOANS RECENTLY<br />
HAVE NOT LOOKED SO STRONG.<br />
IT IS INCONCEIVABLE THAT NATIONAL ECONOMIC RECOVERY<br />
COULD OCCUR WITHOUT STRONG GROWTH IN QUEENSLAND, WITH<br />
ONE-SIXTH OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE AND MUCH MORE THAN<br />
ONE-SIXTH OF AUSTRALIA'S VALUABLE NATURAL RESOURCES AND<br />
POTENTIAL FOR GROWTH. SO WE MUST ALL WORK TO ENSURE THAT<br />
THIS GREAT STATE PARTICIPATES FULLY IN THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
ECONOMIC RESURGENCE, ALTHOUGH THE LIFT IN ACTIVITY IS UNEVEN, AND<br />
ALTHOUGH IT IS NOT YET STRONG, THERE SEEMS LITTLE DOUBT THAT<br />
OUTPUT THIS FINANCIAL YEAR WILL BE SUBSTANTIALLY HIGHER<br />
THAN LAST YEAR, CLEARLY THE MAIN TASK OF ECONOMIC MANAGEMENT IS<br />
NOW TO WIDEN, STRENGTHEN AND SUSTAIN THE RECOVERY, WHILE<br />
KEEPING INFLATION ON A DOWNWARD PATH.<br />
-4-</p>
<p>LANDMARKJILLQdP1Q1ic POi iC'Y<br />
IT IS NOW JUST FIVE MONTHS SINCE THE PEOPLE OF<br />
AUSTRALIA ELECTED A NEw GOVERNMENT TO REVERSE THE DECLINING<br />
FORTUNES OF THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY,<br />
IN TWO WEEKS TIME, THE TREASURER, PAUL KEATING,<br />
WILL ANNOUNCE MY GOVERNMENT'S FIRST BUDGET.<br />
THE FIVE AND A HALF MONTHS BETWEEN THE ELECTION A1ND<br />
THE BUDGET COULD NOT HAVE BEEN MORE ACTIVE AND PRODUCTIVE<br />
IN ECONOMIC POLICY-MAKING. THAT SHORT PERIOD HAS SEEN<br />
SUCCESSIVELY THE NATIONAL ECONOMIC SUMMIT CONFERENCE, THE<br />
MAY ECONOMI. C STATEMENT, AND THE FIRST PREMIERS' CONFERENCE<br />
SINCE WORLD WAR 11 TO PRODUCE AN AGREED COMMUNIQUE ON<br />
THE MANAGEMENT OF THE NATIONAL ECONOMY,<br />
OUR FIRST BUDGET WILL BE THE CULMINATION OF MUCH<br />
OF OUR WORK ON ECONOMIC POLICY SINCE MARCH. IT MUST BE READ<br />
TOGETHER WITH THE RESULTS OF THE SUMMIT, THE PREMIERS'<br />
CONFERENCE, AND MOST IMPORTANTLY THE MlAY STATEMENT.<br />
THESE FOUR IMPORTANT EVENTS IN ECONOMIC POLICY,<br />
CULMINATING IN THE BUDGET, ESTABLISH A BASE FROM WHICH<br />
NATIONAL ECONOMIC RECOVERY CAN BE LAUNCHED.<br />
WE HAVE HAD TO' ASK THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE-TO ACCEPT<br />
SOME FIRM MEASURES IN THE MAY STATEMENT AND SOON IN THE BUDGET.<br />
WE BELIEVE THAT THE OVERALL EFFECT OF OUR MEASURES IS TO PLACE<br />
THE MAIN BURDEN ON PEOPLE WHO ARE IN A RELATIV/ ELY GOOD<br />
POSITION TO BEAR IT. .1 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
IT HAS NOT BEEN EASY, 1 AND I AM NOT ABLE TO PROMISE<br />
THAT THE BUDGET MARKS THE END OF THE HARD CHOICES AND HARD<br />
DECISIONS, BUT THERE IS NO EASY WAY TO REMOVE DISTORTIONS OF<br />
THE KIND THAT HAVE DRAGGED DOWN AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY AND THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY OVER THE PAST FEW YEARS$<br />
As I SAID IN OPENING THE ELECTION CAMPA[ GN ON<br />
16 FEBRUARY: " WE OFFER NO MIRACLES. WE OFFER NO OVERNIGHT SOLUTI ONS<br />
FOR THE IMMEDIATE PROBLEMS WE FACE OR DEEP-SEATED<br />
PROBLEMS WE MUST FACE TOGETHER.<br />
WHAT WE HAVE TO DO IS BREAK OUT OF THE VICIOUS CIRCLE<br />
OF CONFRONTATION.,. j<br />
THAT WILL INVOLVE SIGNIFICANT NEW EXPENDITURE1..<br />
IT WILL ALSO INVOLVE PUTTING IN PLACE MECHANISMS TO<br />
ENSURE THAT THE NEW GROWTH DOES NOT DISAPPEAR IN A<br />
NEW ROUND OF INFLATION THAT IS WHAT OUR PRICES AND<br />
INCOMES POLICY IS ALL ABOUT",<br />
ISAID THEN THAT THE WHOLE THRUST OF OUR POLICY WAS<br />
TO ATTACK THE TWIN EVILS OF UNEMPLOYMENT AND INFLATION TOGETHER.<br />
THAT WAS OUR FUNDAMENTAL COMMITMENT. WE HAVE COME2<br />
A LONG WAY,, EVEN IF THERE IS STILL A LONG WAY TO GO. 11117 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
TONIGHT I WANT TO TAKE YOU BACK OVER SOME OF THE<br />
POLIC-Y THEMES OF THE SUMMIT, THE MAY STATEMENT AND THE<br />
PREMIERS' CONFERENCE, AND TO FORESHADOW SOME BROAD OUTLINES<br />
OF THE COMING BUDGET, I. WILL THEN CONCLUDE WITH A FEW<br />
OBSERVATIONS ON POLICY ISSUES THAT ARE CRUCIAL TO THE<br />
LONG-TERM IMPROVEMENT OF AUSTRALIAN LIVING STANDARDS,<br />
BEYOND THE RECOVERY THAT IS NOW IN PROSPECT.<br />
FISCAL PolICY-L THIS-YEAR'IS BQDGET<br />
THE 1983-84 BUDGET, EMBODYING THE DECISIONS ANNOUNCED<br />
IN THE MAY STATEMENT AND THE PREMIER'S CONFERENCE, HAS BEEN<br />
EXTREMELY DIFFICULT TO PREPARE.<br />
WE CAME TO OFFICE COMMITTED TO EXPANSIONARY POLICIES<br />
TO ASSIST IN PROMOTING NATIONAL ECONOMIC RECOVERY, DURING THE<br />
ELECTION CAMPAIGN WE OUTLINED A NUMBER OF NEW PROGRAMS THAT<br />
WERE TO PLAY A MAJOR PART IN RECOVERY, INCLUDING A COMMUNITY<br />
EMPLOYMENT PROGRAM AND A PACKAGE TO STIMULATE THE HOUSING<br />
INDUSTRY. THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT AT THAT TIME WAS TELLING<br />
THE AUSTRAL. IAN PEOPLE THAT IT WAS HEADING TOWARDS A BUDGET<br />
DEFICIT OF ABOUT SIX B~ ILLION DOLLARS IN 1983-8' 4. WE JUDGED<br />
THAT OUR PROGRAMS WOULD HAVE ADDED ABOUT ONE AND A HALF BILLION<br />
DOLLARS TO OUR PREDECESSORS'I ANTICIPATED DEFICIT. AT THE<br />
TIME OF THE ELECTION, AN OVERALL DEFICIT OF ABOUT SEVEN AND<br />
A HALF BILLION DOLLARS SEEMED TO US TO PROVIDE AN<br />
APPROPRIATE LEVEL OF STIMULATION) WHILE AVOIDING EXCESSIVE<br />
STRAIN ON FINANCIAL MARKETS. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
THE WHOLE ENVIRONMENT OF FISCAL POLICY-MAKING<br />
CHANGED DRAMATICALLY THE DAY AFTER WE TOOK OFFICE WHEN THE<br />
TRUTH CAME OUT, WE WERE ADVISED THAT THE CONTINUATION OF<br />
POLICIES IN PLACE AT THAT TIME WOULD GENERATE A 1983-84 DEFICIT<br />
OF ABOUT $ 9,6 BILLION.<br />
A $ 1.5 BILLION ADDITION TO A $ 9.6 BILLION DEFICIT<br />
IS OBVIOUSLY VERY DIFFERENT TO A $ 1.5 BILLION ADDITION TO A<br />
$ 6 BILLION DEFICIT, I SAY THE DIFFERENCE IS OBVIOUS THOUGH<br />
IT IS SURPRISING HOW DIFFICULT IT CAN SOMETIMES BE TO GET THE<br />
OBVIOUS ACCEPTED, A LARGER BUDGET DEFICIT CAN, WITHIN WIDE LIMITS,<br />
PROVIDE SOME IMMEDIATE POSITIVE STIMULATION TO ECONOMIC<br />
ACTIVITY, HOWEVER, WITHIN THE NON-INFLATIONARY MONETARY POLICIES<br />
TO WHICH THIS GOVERNMENT IS COMMITTED, BEYOND SOME POINT<br />
THIS WILL EXERT PRESSURES TOWARDS INCREASES IN INTEREST RATES.<br />
IF THESE PRESSURES ARE EFFECTIVE, THEY WILL TEND TO REDUCE<br />
HOUSING AND OTHER INVESTMENT THAT IS SENSITIVE TO INTEREST<br />
RATES. WITH THE INFORMATION AVAILABLE TO IT IN OFFICE, MY<br />
GOVERNMENT FORMED THE VIEW THAT A DEFICIT AROUND $ 8.5 BILLION<br />
WOULD PROVIDE SUBSTANTIAL DIRECT STIMULUS TO ECONOMIC ACTIVITY,<br />
WHILE AVOIDING EXCESSIVE PRESSURES ON FINANCIAL MARKETS.<br />
WE TESTED THIS VIEW BEYOND THE CIRCLES OF OUR<br />
OFFICIAL ADVISERS, INCLUDING AT THE SUMMIT AND, LATER, THE<br />
PREMIERS' CONFERENCE, ,/ 9 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
ESTIMATES OF THE PROSPECTIVE BUDGET DEFICIT ON<br />
UNCHANGED POLICIES HAVE VARIED THROUGH THE YEAR IN THE LIGHT<br />
OF NEW INFORMATION, FOR EXAMPLE ABOUT PRICES AT HOME AND<br />
ABROAD, OR ABOUT RATES OF ECONOMIC GROWTH, SOME CHANGES<br />
HAVE INCREASED WHILE OTHERS HAVE REDUCED THE PROSPECTIVE DEFICIT<br />
ON UNCHANGED POLICIES.<br />
A BETTER OUTLOOK FOR ECONOMIC GROWTH IN 1983-84,<br />
ITSELF PARTLYATTRIBUTABLE TO GREATER CONFIDENCE IN THE ECONOMY<br />
UNDER THE POLICIES OF MY GOVERNMENT, LOWERED THE PROSPECTIVE<br />
DEFICIT SOMEWHAT, IN THE OTHER DIRECTION, AND ALMOST AS LARGE,<br />
REVISED ESTIMATES OF THE COSTS OF FRASER PROGRAMS IN 1983-84<br />
ADDED SUBSTANTIALLY TO THE PROSPECTIVE DEFICIT,<br />
THE MOST RECENT OFFICIAL FIGURING AVAILABLE TO ME SUGGESTS<br />
THAT THE NET EFFECT OF THESE OPPOSING TENDENCIES WAS AT BEST<br />
SLIGHTLY TO REDUCE THE PROSPECTIVE DEFICIT, LEAVING US SEEKING<br />
NET REDUCTIONS IN THE ORDER OF A BILLION DOLLARS THROUGH<br />
DISCRETIONARY CHANGES TO REVENUES OR OUTLAYS.<br />
SOME DEVELOPMENTS SINCE MARCH HAVE MADE THIS DIFFICULT<br />
TASK EVEN HARDER, THE DEFEAT OF OUR TAX RECOUPMENT LEGISLATION<br />
IN THE SENATE WAS A BIG SETBACK.<br />
AT THE PREMIERS' CONFERENCE, WE PROVIDED A ONCE-OFF GRANT<br />
TO ALL STATES, ABOVE LEVELS INDICATED IN THE THREE-YEAR FORMULA<br />
AND WRITTEN INTO THE FORWARD ESTIMATES, WE ALSO RAISED LOAN COUNCIL<br />
BORROWINGS THROUGH THE COMMONWEALTH BUDGET ABOVE THE FORWARD<br />
ESTIMATES, WE DID THIS TO AVOID THE STATES HAVING TO CUT<br />
EXPENDITURE AND INCREASE CHARGES AND TAXES IN AREAS THAT WOULD BE </p>
<p>MORE DAMAGING TO RECOVERY THAN COMMENSURATE ADJUSTMENTS IN<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH BUDGET. QUEENSLAND'S SHARE OF THE ADDITIONAL<br />
$ 155 MILLION REVENUE GRANT WAS $ 31 MILLION, THIS ADDITIONAL<br />
GRANT TOGETHER WITH THE INCR EASED LOAN COUNCIL FUNDING SHOULD<br />
ENABLE THE QUEENSLAND GOVERNMENT TO INTRODUCE A RANGE OF<br />
NEW ACTIVITIES TO PROMOTE RECOVERY WHILE AVOIDING TAXATION<br />
INCREASES IN ITS NEXT BUDGET.<br />
THIS RESPONSE TO THE PREMIERS WAS APPROPRIATE FROM THE<br />
POINT OF VIEW OF THE NATIONAL ECONOMY AS A WHOLE, BUT IT HAD<br />
THE EFFECT OF COMPOUNDING OUR OWN BUDGETARY DIFFICULTIES IN<br />
1983-3L48 THERE IS NO PAINLESS WAY OF REDUCING A PROSPECTIVE<br />
BUDGET DEFICIT BY ONE BILLION DOLLARS, IN THE MAY STATEMENT WE<br />
WERE ABLE TO ANNOUNCE COMMITMENTS TO KEY ELEMENTS OF OUR<br />
RECOVERY PROGRAM, NOTABLY THE PACKAGE OF NEW HOUSING POLICIES AND<br />
THE COMMUNITY EMPLOYMENT PROGRAM, AT THE SAME TIME AS WE REDUCED<br />
SOME OF THE OUTLAYS AND TAX EXPENDITURES WHICH WE HAD INHERITED,<br />
THE NET EFFECT WAS TO REDUCE THE PROSPECTIVE 1983-84 DEFICIT BY<br />
HALF A BILLION DOLLARS. SOME HARD DECISIONS HAD TO BE TAKEN TO<br />
ACHIEVE THIS RESULT, BUT AS WAS AGREED BY ALL SIGNATORIES TO THE<br />
SUMMIT COMMUNIQUE, NATIONAL ECONOMIC RECOVERY REQUIRES A SHARING<br />
OF THE BURDEN OF RESTRAINT BY ALL AUSTRALIANS WHO ARE IN A<br />
POSITION TO ACCEPT IT. </p>
<p>-11-<br />
RESPONSIBLE FISCAL MANAGEMENT HAS REQUIRED A PAINFUL<br />
REASSESSMENT OF PRIORITIES, WE HAVE ENDEAVOURED TO IMPLEMENT<br />
QUICKLY THOSE PARTS OF OUR ELECTION PROGRAM WHICH ARE MOST<br />
IMPORTANT TO ECONOMIC RECOVERY AND TO ASSISTANCE TO AUSTRALIANS<br />
WHO HAVE SUFFERED MOST SEVERELY DURING THE RECESSION.<br />
WE WISH WE HAD INHERITED A POSITION IN WHICH WE COULD<br />
DO MORE. BUT AS I SAID BEFORE, OUR STRONGEST EFFORTS HAVE BEETN<br />
DIRECTED TOWARDS FULFILLING OUR FUNDAMENTAL PLEDGES ON<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT AND INFLATION. WE HAVE HAD TO WORK WITHIN THE<br />
LIMITS OF THE PROBLEMS WE INHERITED, AND WE WOULD HAVE LET<br />
DOWN THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE IF WE HAD RISKED DAMAGING RECOVERY,<br />
BY PRETENDING THAT THE THREE BILLION DOLLARS ADDITION TO THE<br />
PROSPECTIVE DEFICIT MADE NO DIFFERENCE$<br />
IDO NOT COUNT AMONGST MY DISAPPOINTMENTS THE FACT<br />
THAT WE HAVE CONFRONTED SOME LONGSTANDING DISTORT10ONS IN THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN TAXATION SYSTEM. TAX EVASION AND AVOIDANCE IN<br />
RECENT YEARS HAVE REMOVED ANY SEMBLANCE OF EQUITY FROM THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN TAXATION SYSTEM, AND my GOVERNMENT HAS A POWERFUL<br />
MANDATE TO REMOVE THEM.<br />
THE ACHIEVEMENT OF TAX EQUITY WAS ONE IMPORTANT<br />
PURPOSE OF THE REFORMS OF SUPERANNUATION ARRANGEMENTS THAT WE<br />
ANNOUNCED fN MAY. WE WERE SEEKING TO CLOSE A MAJOR TAX LOOPHOLE,<br />
OUR PROPOSAL IMPOSES A VERY MODERATE TAX ON SUCH<br />
LUMP SUM PAYMENTS IN RESPECT ONLY OF FUTURE EMPLOYMENT. WE ARE<br />
REDUCING THE COST TO THE REVENUE OF A TAXATION CONCESSION<br />
THAT HAS ALWAYS BEEN MOST USEFUL TO RELATIVELY WELL-OFF<br />
MEMBERS OF THE WORKFORCE. Il/ 12 </p>
<p>-12-<br />
THE MAY STATEMENT FORESHADOWED CONSULTATIONS WITH<br />
INTERESTED PARTIES ON THE FINAL FORM OF THE PROPOSALS, THE<br />
MODIFICATIONS ANNOUNCED YESTERDAY BY THE TREASURER MEET ALL<br />
REASONABLE POINTS THAT HAVE BEEN MADE IN THE DISCUSSIONS,,<br />
WHILE PRESERVIN4G THE MOST IMPORTANT PRINCIPLES EMBODIED IN<br />
OUR REFORM,<br />
OTHER POLICIES-E. OR RECOVERYX<br />
WHILE FISCAL POLICY IS OBVIOUSLY OF CENTRAL IMPORTANCE<br />
IN ESTABLISHING A BASE FOR ECONOMIC RECOVERY, IT CAN BE EFFECTIVE<br />
ONLY WITHIN APPROPRIATE MONETARY AND WAGES POLICIES, IN THESE<br />
AREAS, WE HAVE GONE A LONG WAY SINCE MARCH IN IMPLEMENTING<br />
POLICIES WHICH WILL SUPPORT RECOVERY WHILE HOLDING INFLATION<br />
ON A DOWNWARD PATH.<br />
WE WILL MAINTAIN SUFFICIENT MONETARY GROWTH TO ALLOW<br />
THE ECONOMY TO REALISE ITS FULL POTENTIAL FOR GROWTH IN OUTrPUT.<br />
THIS RATE OF MONETARY GROWTH MUST ALLOW FOR THE MINIMUM FEASIBLE<br />
RATE OF PRICE INCREASES IN THE ECONOMY, WHICH ITSELF WILL BE<br />
STRONGLY INFLUENCED BY THE WAGE-SETTING SYSTEM, THUS WE WILL<br />
ALLOW SUFFICIENT MONEY GROWTH TO FINANCE THE LIKELY AND<br />
DESIRABLE RATE OF GROWTH IN NOMINAL GROSS DOMESTIC PRODUCT.<br />
THE " FIGHT INFLATION FIRST' STRATEGY OF OUR<br />
PREDECESSORS IM~ PLIED THE TIGHTEST POSSIBLE MONETARY POLICY.<br />
IN PRACTICE, MONETARY POLICY OVER THE PAST SEVEN YEARS WAS<br />
CHARACTERISED MORE BY INCONSISTENCY THAN BY TIGHTNESS,<br />
WI1TH OUR POLICIES SUPPORTED BY THE PRICES AND INCOMES<br />
ACCORD, OUR MO1NETARY OBJECTIVES ARE DIFFERENT. WE AIM TO<br />
IMPLEMENT CONSISTENTj FIRM POLICIES THAT ACCOMMODATE STRONG<br />
GROWTH, BUT NOT INFLATION. </p>
<p>-13-<br />
FIGHTING INFLATION AND UNEMPLOYMENT AT THE SAME<br />
TIME REQUIRES US TO MANAGE THE EXCHANGE RATE WITH AT LEAST<br />
ONE EYE ON THE COMPETITIVENESS OF OUR EXPORT AND IMPORTCOMPETING<br />
INDUSTRIES, AND NOT SOLELY AS AN INSTRUMENT OF<br />
ANTI-INFLATION POLICIES.<br />
WE SHOULD REMEMBER THAT AUSTRALIA WILL BE AFFECTED<br />
BY PRESSURES IN INTERNATIONAL FINANCIAL MARKETS, WHATEVER<br />
HAPPENS AT HOME. AUSTRALIAN REAL INTEREST RATES WILL TEND TO<br />
RISE IF UNITED STATES* REAL INTEREST RATES RISE. ON OUR RECENT<br />
VISIT TO THE UNITED STATES, THE TREASURER AND I HAD EXTENSIVE<br />
DISCUSSIONS ON MONETARY DEVELOPMENTS WITH TREASURY SECRETARY,<br />
DONALD REGAN, THE CHAIRMAN OF THE FEDERAL RESERVE, PAUL VOLCKE?,.<br />
OTHER SENIOR OFFICIALS IN THE UNITED STATES, AND LEADING<br />
PARTICIPA1NTS IN THE NEW YORK FINANCIAL MARKETS. WHILE THESE<br />
LEFT US WITH A GREAT DEAL OF CONFIDENCE IN THE SHORT-TERM STRENGTH<br />
OF THE UNITED STATES RECOVERY, THERE WAS ALSO CAUSE FOR SOME<br />
ANXIETY THAT THE CONTINUATION OF EXTREMELY HIGH BUDGET DEFICITS<br />
COULD LEAD TO UPWARD PRESSURE ON UNITED STATES INTEREST RATES AS<br />
PRIVATE INVESTMENT EXPANDED IN 1984 AND 1985<br />
WHILE WE CANNOT INSULATE OURSELVES CO. MPLETELY FROM4<br />
FINANCIAL DEVELOPMENTS ABROAD, CONDITIONS WITHIN OUR OWN FINANCIAL<br />
MARKETS CAN EXACERBATE OR AMELIORATE THE PRESSURES CONING FROM<br />
OVERSEAS. GIVEN THE CONSIDERABLE PROSPECT THAT INTERNATIONAL<br />
FINANCIAL MARKETS WILL EXERT UPWARD PRESSURE ON AUSTRALIAN<br />
INTEREST RATES IN THE PERIOD AHEAD, WE WILL BE WORKIN G<br />
TO ENSURE THAT DEVELOPMENTS AT HOME DO NOT COMPOUND THE THREAT<br />
TO THE RECOVERY OF PRIVATE INVESTMENT, </p>
<p>-i1l-<br />
ALTHOUGH THERE IS WIDE ACCEPTANCE THAT A DEFICIT<br />
AROUND $ 8.5 BILLION WOULD BE APPROPRIATE IN THE CURRENT<br />
FINANCIAL YEAR, THE COMMONWEALTH WILL NEED TO REDUCE THE<br />
DEMAND IT MAKES ON FINANCIAL MARKETS AS PRIVATE INVESTMENT<br />
INCREASES IN THE PROCESS'OF RECOVERY,<br />
THE LUMP SUM SUPERANNUATION ARRANGEMENTS WERE ONE<br />
OF A NUMBER OF MEASURES IN THE MAY STATEMENT WHICH HAVE<br />
THEIR MAIN EFFECT IN REDUCING THE BUDGET DEFICIT NOT IN<br />
1983-84, BUT IN LATER YEAR~ S. THE CHANGES IN THE SUPERANNUATION4<br />
ARRANGEMENTS ANNOUNCED OVER THE WEEKEND DO NOT SUBSTANTIALLY<br />
ALTER THE MAIN THRUST OF. THE MAY MEASURES, WHICH WAS TO<br />
REDUCE VERY SUBSTANTIALLY THE PROSPECTIVE DEFICIT IN THE<br />
YEARS AHEAD. THE PROCESS OF RECOVERY ITSELF WILL TEND TO REDUCE<br />
FUTURE DEFICITS, BY RAISING REVENUE AND REDUCING RECESSIONRELATED<br />
OUTLAYS, AT THE TIME OF THE SUMMIT, WE ESTIMATED<br />
THAT ABOUT HALF THE HYPOTHETICAL DEFICIT WAS CYCLICALi AND<br />
COULD BE EXPECTED TO FALL AWAY WITHOUT DISCRETIONARY POLICY<br />
ACTION AS THE ECONOMY RETURNED TO A MORE NORMAL LEVEL OF<br />
OPERATION. THE RATES OF GROWTH ENVISAGED IN SNECARio A,<br />
AS PRESENTED TO THE SUMMIT, WOULD REDUCE THE 1984I-85 DEFICIT<br />
BY OVER A BILLION DOLLARS IN 1O'-5FROM THE CURRENT YEAR'S<br />
LEVELS. </p>
<p>IT IS NOT CLEAR AT THIS EARLY STAGE WHETHER<br />
THIS CYCLICAL EFFECT, TOGETHER WITH THE STRUCTURAL EFFECTS OF<br />
THE MAY STATEMENT AND THE B3UDGET, WILL REDUCE NEXT YEAR'S<br />
DEFICIT ENOUGH TO MEET OUR STABILITY OBJECTIVES WITHOUT<br />
FURTHER DISCRETIONARY ACTION. THIS WILL DEPEND VERY MUCH ON<br />
THE COURSE OF PRIVATE INVESTMENT IN THE RECOVERY, AS WELL AS<br />
ON WIDER DEVELOPMENTS IN FINANCIAL MARKETS, BUT IT IS LIKELY<br />
THAT FURTHER REDUCTIONS IN THE STRUCTURAL BUDGET DEFICIT WILL BE<br />
REQUIREC FOR NEXT YEAR,<br />
MIY COLLEAGUES AN~ D I HAD LITTLE MORE THAN THREE MONTHS<br />
WITHIN WHICH TO EXAMINE CRITICALLY THE EXPENDITURE COMMITMENTS<br />
WHICH WE HAD INHERITED FROM THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT, FROM THE<br />
TIME OF THE SUMMIT TO THE COMPLETION OF WORK ON THE EXPENDITURE<br />
SIDE OF THE BUDGET,<br />
THE ACHIEVEMENTS OF THIS BRIEF PERIOD HAVE BEEN<br />
CONSIDERABLE, IN REORDERING PRIORITIES TOWARDS THE REQUIREIMENTS<br />
OF ECONOMIC RECOVERY AND, IN THE WELFARE AREA, OF THE GENUINELY<br />
NEEDY IN OUR SOCIETY. BUT WE CAN GO FURTHER WHEN WE ARE IN<br />
CONTROL OF THE BUDGET-MAKiNG PROCESS NOT ONLY IN THE FINAL<br />
MONTHS, BUT IN THE FULL YEAR LEADING UP TO THE BUDGET, WIT:; A<br />
FULL YEAR TO L lA BUDGET, WE WOULD P. E LOOKING TO INTE-' RATE<br />
FINANCIAL " Di MANPOWER REQUIREMENTS MORE EFFECTIVELY THAN IS<br />
POSSIPL' 2 WITHIN THE ARRANGEMENTS THAT WE HAVE INHERITED,<br />
OUR EXPENDITURE REVIEW PROCF%" WILL BECOME PART OF THE<br />
NORMAL OPERATIONS OF GOVERNMENT, OPERATION'S LIKE THAT OF THE<br />
EXPENDITURE REVIEW COMtITTEE IM RECENT MONTI-S WILL CONTINUE TO<br />
./ 16 </p>
<p>REALLOCATE EXPENDITURE III LINE WITH THE REQUIREMENTS OF EQUITY<br />
AND GROWTH AS WE REDUCE THE STRUCTURAL BUDGET DEFICIT IN THE<br />
COURSE OF ECONOMIC RECOVERY$<br />
OJR EXPANSIONARY FISCAL AND MONETARY POLICIES ARE UNDERPINNED<br />
BY THE PRICES AND INCOMES ACCORD. WHEN THE AUSTRALIAN ECONWY WAS<br />
STRUGGLING INTO RECOVERY IN THE SO-CALLED RESOURCES BOOM IN<br />
1981, A WAGES EXPLOSION HELPED TO TURN A GREAT OPPORTUNITY<br />
INTO A DISASTER, OUR PREDECESSORS AND, SPECIFICALLY; MY OWN<br />
PREDECESSOR, INVITED THE UNIONS TO USE THEIR POWER IN THE<br />
MARKET PLACE, AUSTRALIAN UNIONS ACCEPTED THEIR INVITATION,<br />
THE WAGES EXPLOSION WAS AN INEVITABLE RESULT OF ABANDONING<br />
THE CENTRALISED WAGE-FIXING SYSTEM AT A TIME OF RISING<br />
EMPLOYMENT. WAGES POLIC Y IN ANY COUNTRY MUST BE ATTUNED TO THE<br />
TRADITIONS OF THE LABOUR MARKET, IN AUSTRALIA, STRONG TRADE<br />
UNIONS HAVE SHOWN SOME WILLINGNESS TO ACCEPT A DEGREE OF<br />
RESTRAINT IN THE WIDER INTERESTS OF AUSTRALIAN WORKERS, SO<br />
LONG AS THE OVERALL FRAMEWORK WITHIN WHICH THEY ARE OPERATING<br />
IS SEEN AS BEING EQUITABLE. THE AUSTRALIAN TRADITION ALSO<br />
EMBODIES STRONG COMMITMENT TO RIGID WAGE RELATIVITIES,$ UNDERSTOOD<br />
AS itCOMPARATIVE WAGE JUSTICE" WHICH CAUSE WAGE GAINS BY STRONG<br />
UNIONS TO BE TRANSIMITTED WIDELY THROUGH THE ECONOMY. THE LEGAL<br />
SUPERSTRUCTURE, INCLUDING THE FEDERAL STRUCTURE OF ARBITRATION<br />
AND CONCILIATION, MAKES THESE RIGIDITIES LESS MALLEABLE TO<br />
ECONOMIC PRESSURES THAN THEY OTHERWISE WOULD BE, </p>
<p>-17-<br />
THESE AUSTRALIAN TRADITIONS, WHICH CANNOT BE<br />
ABOLISHED AT THE WHIM OF ANY GOVERNMENT. PROVIDE AT THE SAME<br />
TIME A THREAT TO THE COMING RECOVERY, AND AN OPPORTUNITY TO<br />
BUILD A DURABLE RECOVERY. THE THREAT WOULD HAVE BEEN REALISED<br />
IF WAGES POLICY HAD IGNORED THE TRADITIONS. THE PROMISE CAN<br />
BE REALISED BY THE APPROACH THAT WE ARE ADOPTING 1TO THE PRICES<br />
AND INCOMES ACCORD.<br />
F: OLLOWING THE SUMMIT AND IN OUR SUBMISSION TO THE<br />
CURRENT WAGE CASE,, MY GOVERNMENT INDICATED SUPPORT FOR A<br />
GENERAL WAGE INCREASE IN THE ORDER OF 3 To 4 PER CENT IN THE<br />
SECOND HALF OF THIS YEAR, UNTIL THE GOOD NEWS ASSOCIATED<br />
WITH THE BREAKING OF THE DROUGHT RAISED FOOD PRICES SHARPLY,<br />
IT SEEMED THAT AN INCREASE BASED ON THE INCREASE IN THE C. P-.<br />
IN THE FIRST HALF OF THIS YEAR MIGHT FALL COMFORTABLY WITHIN<br />
THIS RANGE. IN THE NEW CIRCUMSTANCES, WE JUDGED THAT IT WAS<br />
BEST TO ACCEPT A WAGE INCREASE OF 4.3 PER CENT, TO SECURE<br />
WORKERS' FIRM COMMITMENT TO PURSUING WAGE CLAIMS ONLY THROUGH THE<br />
CENTRALISED SYSTEM,<br />
IF THE RECOVERY PROCEEDS STRONGLY IN THE YEAR AHEAD<br />
AND BEYOND, AS IT SHOULD EVEN WITH A WAGE INCREASE SLIGHTLY<br />
HIGHER THAN WE WOULD HAVE PREFERRED IN OTHER CIRCUMSTANCES,,<br />
THIS WAGE ADJUSTMENT WILL BE SEEN AS A GOOD INVESTMENT IN<br />
FUTURE WAGE MODERATION. IN THE FIRST HALF OF NEXT YEAR, THE<br />
INTRODUCTION OF MEDICARE WILL TAKE A FEWq PERCENTAGE POINTS<br />
OFF THE INCREASE IN THE CONSUMER PRICES INDEX, AS A RESULT,<br />
EVEN WITH FULL-WAGE INDEXATION, MONEY WAGE INCREASES IN 1984<br />
SHOULD BE IN LINE WITH THE UNITED STATES AND OTHER MAJOR<br />
ECONOMICES EXPERIENCING STRONG GROWTH WITH RELATIVELY LOW INFLAT1( </p>
<p>-18-<br />
ON THE OTHER HAND, IF AUSTRALIAN RECOVERY IS<br />
DELAYED, OR INSUFFICIE14TLY STRONG TO PROMISE PROGRESS IN<br />
REDUCING UNEMPLOYMENT, THE PRICES AND INCOMES ACCORD PROVIDES<br />
A FRAMEWORK FOR ADJUSTMENT OF POLICY, INCLUDING THE TIMING<br />
OF WAGE INCREASES. OF COURSE, THE ARBITRATION COMMISSION RETAINS ITS<br />
INDEPENDENCE, THE COMM4ISSION WAS THE INSTRUMENT PREFERRED BY<br />
ALL PARTIES AT THE SUMMIT, INCLUDING EMPLOYERS, FOR<br />
ADMINISTERING THE RETURN TO CENTRALISED WAGE FIXATION, THE<br />
GOVERNMENT HAS MADE ITS OWN VIEWS KNOWN. IN THE PRESENT CASE,<br />
AND IN FUTURE, EMPLOYERS AND THE UNlIONS HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY<br />
TO CONVINCE THE COMMISSION THAT IT SHOULD ADOPT A DIFFERENT<br />
COURSE. THE AUSTRALIAN TRADE UNION MOVEMENTS IS NOT A<br />
MONOLITHi SOME-UNIONS FROM TIME TO TIME WILL FEEL THAT<br />
THEIR OWN INTERESTS MIGHT BE SERVED BY PURSUING CLAIMS<br />
OUTSIDE THE CENTRALISED SYSTEM. THE RETURN TO CENTRALISED<br />
WAGE-SETTING WILL NOT DELIVER THE BENEFITS OF ECONOMIC<br />
RECOVERY TO ALL AUSTRALIANS IF WORKERS FEEL FREE TO PURSUE<br />
CLAIMS OUTSIDE THE SYSTEM, IF THAT BECAME WIDESPREAD, WE<br />
WOULD HAVE LOST THE BASIS FOR OUR EXPANSIONARY FISCAL AND<br />
MONETARY POLICIES, IDO NOT BELIEVE THAT AUSTRALIANS WILL'<br />
LIGHTLY LET THIS HAPPEN, IWE ARE REASSURED BY THE STRENGTH<br />
OF THE ACIU's COMMITMENT TO THE SYSTEM, THE ACTU LEADERSHIP<br />
EXPECTS THE COMMISSION TO MAKE COMPLIANCE WITH THE SYSTEM A<br />
CONDITION OF A GENERAL WAGE INCREASE, </p>
<p>-19-<br />
QDImA-POLICI ES FOR, LQIGcTERM-GROWTH<br />
THE FISCAL, MONETARY AND WAGES POLICIES WHICH WE<br />
HAVE PUT INTO PLACE OVER THE PAST FIVE MONTHS ESTABLISH AN<br />
1INTEGRATED B~ ASE FOR STEADY GROWTH IN OUTPUT AND EMPLOYMCNT,<br />
ACCUM'ANIE) BY THE MODERATION OF INF~ LATION.<br />
BUT WHETHER AUSTRALIAN LIVING STANDARDS CONTINUE TO<br />
RISE BEYOND THE LIFE OF THE PRESENT PARLIAMENT AND INTO THE<br />
NEXT, AND BEYOND, DEPENDS ON OUR SUCCESS IN ALLOCATING OUR<br />
RESOURCES TO THEIR MOST PRODUCTIVE USES. PRODUCTIVE USE OF<br />
OUR RESOURCES REQUIRES ACCEPTANCE OF NEW WAYS OF DOING THINGS,,<br />
STRUCTURAL CHANGE IN OUR ECONOMY,, RAPIDLY CHANGING PATTERNS<br />
OF FOREIGN TRADE, AND HIGH LEVELS OF INVESTMENT FROM HOME AIND<br />
ABROAD, AN AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY THAT IS BROADLY UNITED ON THE<br />
GREAT NATIONAL GOALS, THAT IS SEEN BY MOST OF ITS CITIZENS<br />
AS A FAIR SOCIETY, AND WHICH OFFERS ITS PEOPLE SECURITY OF<br />
INCOMES AND EMPLOYMENT, WILL EMBRACE THESE CHANGES, BUT A<br />
DIVIDED AUSTRALIA, A SOCIETY THAT IS SUSPICIOUS OF ITS<br />
GOVERNMENT, WILL CLING TO WHAT IT HAS,<br />
A CONSERVATIVE AUSTRALIA, AN AUSTRALIA THAT IS AFRAID<br />
OF CHANGE, WILL BE CONDEMNED TO DECLINING LIVING STANDARDS<br />
AND AN INCREASINGLY INSECURE PLACE IN A RAPIDLY CHANGING<br />
WORLD. .120 </p>
<p>-23-<br />
LONG-TERM GROWTH IN OUR LIVING STANDARDS IS<br />
FEASIBLE ONLY IF WE MAINTAIN OPEN INVESTMENT AND TRADE<br />
POLICIES, BUT THESE POLICIES WILL BE POLITICALLY FEASIBLE<br />
ONLY IF AUSTRALIANS BELIEVE THAT THE BENEFITS OF PROSPERITY<br />
ARE BEING SHARED EQUITABLY,<br />
WE MUST PREPARE TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF NEW TRADING<br />
OPPORTUNITIES IN NEW INDUSTRIES IN NEW PLACES,, AS THE<br />
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES OF NORTHEAST ASIA AND SOUTHEAST ASIA<br />
OVERTAKE JAPAN AS THE MAIN CENTRES OF STRONG INDUSTRIAL<br />
GROWTH IN OUR REGION AND. INDEED, IN THE WORLD,<br />
WE MUST CREATE NEW OPPORTUNITIES IN THE RESOURCES<br />
AREA BY FINDING NEW MARKETS OUTSIDE OUR OWN REGION.<br />
RATIONALISATION OF FISCAL ARRANGEMENTS I N THE COAL INDUSTRY,*<br />
THROUGH CO-OPERATION BETWEEN THE COMMONWEALTH AND THE STATES,<br />
ALONG THE LINES MY GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN SEEKING, COULD OPEN<br />
A NEW ERA OF EXPANSION OF COAL PRODUCTION AND EXPORT TO<br />
EUROPE. WE WILL CONTINUE TO USE OUR INFLUENCE AS A<br />
GOVERNMENT TO SECURE OUR TRADITIONAL MARKETS. THIS IS CLEAR<br />
FROM THE PRIORITY MY GOVERNMENT H4AS GIVEN TO SECURING OUR<br />
BEEF MARKETS IN THE UNITED STATES, TO BUILDING A NEW<br />
INTERNATIONAL SUGAR AGREEMENT, AND TO PREVENTING BILATERAL<br />
DEALS BETWEEN THE UNITED STATES AND JAPAN DAMAGING OUR OWN<br />
FOOD AND MIINERALS MARKETS IN JAPAN. </p>
<p>IT IS NOT APPROPRIATE TO INTRODUCE NEW PROGRAMMES<br />
TO LIBERALISE IMPORTS AT THE HEIGHT OF RECESSION. BUT ANY<br />
ADDITIONAL ASSISTANCE THAT WE PROVIDE TO LESS COMPETITIVE<br />
INDUSTRIES WILL BE DIRECTED AT ENCOURAGING RATHER THAN<br />
DISCOURAGING PRODUCTIVITY GROWTH, AND TO THE LONG-TERM<br />
VIABILITY WITHOUT PROTECTION OF THE INDUSTRY, THIS HAS<br />
BEEN OUR OBJECTIVE IN NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE STEEL INDUSTRY,<br />
THE OUTCOME OF WHICH WILL BE ANNOUNCED BY SENATOR BUTTON<br />
LATER THIS WEEK. </p>
<p>-21-<br />
PARADOXICALLY, RAPID STRUCTURAL CHANGE AND<br />
PRODUCTIVITY IMPROVEMENT REQUIRE STABILITY OF POLICY,<br />
AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY HAS SUFFERED FROM EXCESSIVELY RAPID<br />
CHANGE IN POLICY IN RECENT YEARS. WHILE WE WILL BE DOING<br />
ALL THAT WE CAN TO PROMOTE ECONOMIC EFFICIEN4CY AND EQUITABLE<br />
INCOME DISTRIBUTION), WE WILL AVOID CHANGE FOR ITS OWN SAKE.<br />
MORE GENERALLY, THE STRONG POLITICAL POSITION OF<br />
my GOVERNMENT PROVIDES A BASIS FOR GREATER POLICY CONTINUITY<br />
THAN AUSTRALIA HAS KNOWN FOR MANY YEARS. AND OUR SEARCH FOR<br />
CO-OPERATIVE SOLUTIONS To AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL PROBLEMS,<br />
SYMBOLISED IN THE PRICES AND INCOMES ACCORD, THE SUMMIT,<br />
AND THE PREMIERS' CONFERENCE, SHOULD REDUCE THE HUGE COSTS<br />
TO LONG-TERM GROWTH OF THE DEBILITATING CONFLICTS IN<br />
INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS AND THE FEDERAL-STATE AND INTER-STATE<br />
RIVALRIES THAT HAVE HELD BACK AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL GROWTH<br />
FOR M'ANY YEARS&amp; IDON' T BE-LIEVE IT'S POSSIBLE TO EXAGGERATE THE<br />
COST OF THE CONFRONTATION AND CONFLICT OF THE KIND WHICH<br />
CHARACTERISED OUR SOCIETY FOR MUCH OF THE PAST DECADE THE<br />
COST, NOT JUST IN MATERIAL TERMS, BUT IN TERMS OF NATIONAL<br />
COHESION AND PURPOSE. I BELIEVE IT WAS THE RECOGNITION OF<br />
THE COSTS OF AVOIDABLE CONFLICT AND I EMPHASISE ~ A AMLE<br />
CONFLICT THAT MOTIVATED THE OVERWHELMING MAJORITY OF THE </p>
<p>-22-<br />
PARTICIPANTS AT THE SUMMIT, AND I STILL BELIEVE THAT THE<br />
ESSENTIAL SPIRIT OF THE SUMMIT CAN BE SUSTAINED AND PUT TO<br />
WORKj IN A THOROUGHLY PRACTICAL WAY.<br />
THE MOST CONCRETE EXAMPLE OF THE CONTINUING-WORK<br />
OF THE SUMMIT is EPAC THE ECONOMIC PLANNING AND ADVISORY<br />
COUNCILS As IT DEVELOP, EPAC'S GENUINE ADVISORY ROLE WILL<br />
REINFORCE, AS PART OF THE NORMAL PROCESS OF ECONOMIC<br />
DECISION-MAKING IN THIS COUNTRY THE TWO ELEMENTS WHICH<br />
WERE THE KEY TO THE SUCCESS OF THE SUM1MIT CONSULTATION AND<br />
KNOWLEDGE-SHARING. EPAC WILL ENSURE THAT THESE PROCESSES<br />
OF CONSULTATION AND INFORMATION-SHARING WILL BE PLACED ON A<br />
CONTINUING BASlSj FOR THE FIRST TIME IN AUSTRALIA'S HISTORY,<br />
AND INDEED, THE ENTIRE EFFORT OVER THE PAST FIVE<br />
MONTHS HAS BEEN DIRECTED TOWARDS CREATING A NEW,, AND<br />
FOR AUSTRALIA, UNIQUE FRAMEWORK FOR ECONOMIC DECISION-MAKING<br />
IN THIS NATION. WE HAVE NOT REGARDED OUR TASK AS BEING MERELY TO<br />
DRAW UP AN ANNUAL BUDGET AND THEN TO PRESENT THAT BUDGET AS<br />
THE BE-ALL AND END-ALL OF ECONOMIC POLICY,<br />
WHAT WE HAVE DONE AND IT IS UNPRECEDENTED IN<br />
AUSTRALIA IS TO ESTABLISH A COMPREHENSIVE AND INTEGRATED<br />
BASIS FOR CONSISTENT, LONG TERM ECONOMIC PLANNING, AND IN </p>
<p>-23-<br />
ESTABLISHING THAT COMPREHENSIVE AND INTEGRATED FRAMEWORK,<br />
WE HAVE SOUGHT TO INVOLVE, ON A CONTINUING BASIS, THE<br />
RELEVANT SECTIONS OF THE COMMUNITY OTHER GOVERNMENTS,<br />
BUSINESS, INCLUDING SMALL BUSINESS., THE UNIONS, THE RURAL<br />
SECTOR, THE COMMUNITY GROUPS WHICH ALL HAVE SUCH A HIGH<br />
STAKE IN THE SUCCESS OF OUR POLICIES, IN BOTH THE SHORT AND<br />
LONGER TERM. FOR WHAT IS AT STAKE IS NOTHING LESS THAN THE<br />
FUTURE PROSPERITY AND WELLBEING OF AUSTRALIA ITSELF. AND<br />
I DO BELIEVE THAT WHEN THE TIME COMES AND THE WORK OF THE PAST<br />
FIVE MONTHS AND I MEAN THE REAL WORK, OUR REAL CONCERNS AS<br />
A GOVERNMENT CAN BE JUDGED IN THE PROPER PERSPECTIVE OF<br />
HISTORY, IT WILL BE ACKNOWLEDGED THAT WHAT HAS BEEN ACHIEVED<br />
NOT JUST BY MY GOVERNMENT, BUT BY ALL THE SECTIONS OF THE<br />
COMMUNITY, LIKE YOURSELVES, WHO HAVE CONTRIBUTED TO THE WORK<br />
IT WILL BE ACKNOWLEDGED THAT WHAT HAS BEEN ACHIEVED HAS BEEN<br />
A TRANSFORMATION -A TRANSFORMATION INATTITUDES, IN THE APPROACH<br />
TO ECONOMIC DECISION-MAKING, AND IN THE MEANS AVAILABLE TO<br />
GOVERNMENT AND THE COMMUNITY FOR BETTER, MORE SOUNDLY-BASED<br />
ECONOMIC DECISION-MAKING THAN WE HAVE EVER HAD BEFORE, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
