<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8468</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP SOUTH AFRICAN REFERNDUM</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008468.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL 30/ 92<br />
STATEMENT 13Y THlE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. MEATING MP<br />
SOUTH AFRICAN REFERENDUM<br />
I welcome the positive outcome of the South African<br />
referendum and hope the result will add fresh momentum to<br />
the process of political reform in that country.<br />
I congratulate President de Klerk on receiving a clear<br />
mandate from the white community for his reform program.<br />
The referendum result is 8 boost for the forces of democracy<br />
and Australia hopes that this will be the last racially<br />
based poll in South Africa. It is important that the<br />
victory won by whites in favour of genuine reform serves as<br />
a catalyst to a ccelerate the development of a non-racial<br />
democratic constitution.<br />
I look forward to further positive developments in<br />
negotiations. Further progress in the Convention for a<br />
Democratic South Africa ( CODESA), the forum created for allparty<br />
negotiations, will enable countries such as Australia<br />
to review remaining sanctions against South Africa.<br />
The level of violence in South Africa during the referendum<br />
campaign is a cause for serious concern and I urge all<br />
parties to redouble their efforts to bring a stop to the<br />
senseless bloodshed.<br />
The referendum result should speed the process of<br />
democratisation, and I call on all parties to accept the<br />
will of the people and move without delay towards the<br />
establishmnet of a truly non-racial constitution in South<br />
Africa. 18 MARCH 1992 T1E8L:. Mar. 92 21: 43 No. 023 P. 01/ 01 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
