<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2596</transcript-id>
    <title>MACQUARIE NETWORK WEEKLY BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP - 17 MAY 1972 - UNEMPLOYMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002596.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO NOT FOR RELFFASE BEFORE, 6.30 pm ( EA. ST)<br />
PRIM AMTAIAISTE<br />
% VACQLTARIE NETWORK~ WEFKLY BROADCAST<br />
BY THE PRIME f1I1-IS-vER, THE RT HON.<br />
WILLINNI 1McMiAHON, CN, MP, 17 MAY 19 72<br />
U N E I P 1 -Y JP N T<br />
Yesterday the Govornment announced thDe A-) ril figurcs for<br />
unemployment i -n ZAustralia. R-ighitly, -,, rious unemrnloyment is a probLDm<br />
we all feel deep~ ly about. Txis-is n view I havc li, 1d av( r r'unck. I have<br />
been in political life. It is a d -nly held conviction of mine that<br />
every Liberal Gov-rnmc~ nt should do evznrything n its power to ons!,-Z1<br />
the fullest employment of our monpower ind r!.-source--s. I w--Tant to rcepeat<br />
that policy to you now. And we; c have , over thi: v~ nars, beccn unbzeli vably<br />
successful with.-thes--prlicics.<br />
We must a--lso remember that over the Cl-ristmas/ New Year neriod<br />
a large number of school lc2avers and those who. finishe; d their tertiary<br />
education, entered the work force for the first time. This year thlere<br />
wiere about 180,0,31. Please ac this in mind.<br />
At the and of January there were about 130,00T) registered<br />
unempl oyed.~ VThese figures wer-a re duced considera'Oly in February, Marchn<br />
and 17nril. For the third month in a row, uncraployrment fell this<br />
t -i-mec to about 93,40,0, a fairly big dron -frcm 1-30,0-, 0 in January.<br />
Just as imnortant and looking to the,-future, healthy trcend<br />
developed in job vacancies in all St,-ates. T. 11 these! facts arr-important<br />
not only becauae of th-e vital fact that many mr -re pennol, have found<br />
jobs, but be: causo2 thf-. se are facts -not cnniolis,; but facts which confirm<br />
predictions my Ministers have bee n makIng of the-: imnroving trend<br />
of the economy and thAe grc, 7ath of businc-ss cnnfidence, T. h-y giv the<br />
lie , dire-ct to the ness; imists in tho Labor Party who have made -gild and<br />
irresponsible foreca3ts of unomployment figura s as high as 200,000.<br />
Back in January, when many.,. ooole, including myself, were very<br />
worried about the level of un-' mploymnnt, the Leader of the Ounnsition<br />
stapped off a plane and immodiately mad--the7-prediction th t and I<br />
quote " There would 1) a another 50,000 unaninloy d witi. 1in three mcriths".<br />
If-Mr Whitlam' s guess had come true, it would haJve brought the? total<br />
of un -rnployed to 173,000. In fact it is now a little~ over 93,000. Once<br />
aaain the facts thems-i v, . s destroy the Labor Party's forecasts. </p>
<p>Five days later, with time for sober reflection, he repeated<br />
exactly the same dangerous forecast. His spokesman on Industrial and<br />
Labour matters, Mr Clyde Cameron, was making the same sort of anguished<br />
cries to any reporter or television interviewer who would listen, that<br />
there would be 200,000 people out of work.<br />
There is only one conclusion to be drawn from these statements.<br />
Both these leaders of the Labor movement treated unemployment as a<br />
political issue. They wanted greater uncertainty and more unemployed.<br />
The more people who were out of work the more votes for them. I think<br />
most Australians will agree with me that people who try to make politics<br />
out of unemployment really do not care about the people themselves. This<br />
c-lies to Mr Hawks of the A. C. T. U. as well. If, and I emphasise if, it<br />
was not a deliberate and premeditated political tactic, then it was<br />
negligent and downright dangerous.<br />
The employment position we are now in is pretty good under the<br />
circumstances. Now let me talk to you about the positive decisions we have<br />
taken to live up to our promise of full employment. We did not hesitate<br />
to take faction to fight unemployment. We will not hesitate in the<br />
future. We do not think unemployment is a nolitical issue. And don't<br />
want it to be.<br />
We believe that all Australians want unemployment to be. t. e. ated<br />
with seriousness and with sincerity and that the Liberal policy of . ll<br />
employment be sustained. I assure you that is what the Government has<br />
done. I assure you that is what we will do. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
