<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8789</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP FAREWELL REMARKS TO AUSTRALIAN CONTINGENT TO SOMALIA TOWNSVILLE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/01/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008789.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 14. Jan. 93 15: 29 No. 010 P. 01<br />
-7<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, MP<br />
FAREWELL REMARKS TO AUSTRALIAN CONTIGENT TO SOMALIA<br />
TOWNSVILLE, THURSDAY 14 JANUARY 1993<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
I am honoured to take part in this ceremony to farewell Australian troops dcploying to<br />
Somalia. Tomorrow you will be in Somalia, joining colleagues who have gone ahead to prepare<br />
for your arrival.<br />
You will be part of an historic international undertaking, involving military personnel<br />
from more than 20 other nations.<br />
Never before has the United Nations sanctioned intervention on such a scale in the<br />
internal affairs of a member state for humanitarian purposes.<br />
The world has bccn appalled by the human disaster in Somalia.<br />
A quarter of a million people havc dicd as a result of famine and clan warfare.<br />
Last year Somalis continued to star,, c while food donated by the international<br />
community was plundered by armed gangs or remained in warehouses because safe<br />
passage could not b; guarantccd.<br />
Operation " Rcstore Hope" is the international response to this terrible situation.<br />
Its objective is to establish as soon as possible a secure environment for humanitarian<br />
relicf operations in Somalia.<br />
Australia's contribution to " Restore Hope" is a further demonstration of our support for<br />
a stronger UN role in pcacekccping and humanitarian intervention.<br />
We have a proud record in peacekceping. </p>
<p>2<br />
Today, Australian personnel are serving in UN-mandaced operations in Cambodia,<br />
Iraq, the Red Sea, Western Sahara, Cyprus, Pakistan and Afghanistan, Israel and Syria,<br />
as well as the multilateral operation in the Sinai.<br />
when you join up with the remainder of the battalion group, you will become part of<br />
Australia's largest contribution to UN operations since tbe Korean War and our largest<br />
overseas deployment of ground forces in more than 20 years.<br />
This deployment is also significant in providing an opportunity for Australia's infantry<br />
to demonstrate the professional skills for which you arc so highly regarded.<br />
I know you are well trained and cquipped for the challenging tasks that await you.<br />
' The risks that you will face are real.<br />
The Government is acutely awarc of what this means for you and your families.<br />
Your assignment is limited to 17 weeks, and this is accepted by Australia's partners in<br />
the operation.<br />
We have no doubt you will be able to make a valuablc contribution to O9eratio<br />
" Restore Hope" in this period.<br />
It is appropriate that you have been assigned duties in the Baidoa area where Care<br />
Australia has maintained a major relief operation in the most difficult circumstances.<br />
You leave these shores with the full support of the nation as affirmed in the joint<br />
resolution passed by both Houses of Parliament on 17 December.<br />
On behalf of all Australians, I should like to express our deepest gratitude for your<br />
service. You go to do what Australians want to see done:-security re-established;<br />
humanitarian relief resumed.<br />
Less suffcring. More hope.<br />
I know that they arc proud of you, and that they wish you God-spccd and a safe return<br />
to Australia.<br />
I should now like to invite the Leader of the Opposition to join me in wishing you<br />
every sucrCess in your important assignment.<br />
CANBERRA 14 January 1993 TEL 14. Jan. 93 15: 29 No. 010 P-02,-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
