<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18209</transcript-id>
    <title>Reception in Honour of Her Majesty, The Queen and His Royal Highness, Prince Philip, Canberra</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/10/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
On an autumn day in Cape Town 64 years ago, a remarkable address was given.</p>
<p>It was the speech of a young woman who knew a life of duty stretched before her.</p>
<p>A life she accepted with courage and with grace.</p>
<p>In that address, Princess Elizabeth pledged that her “whole life whether it be long or short” would be devoted to the service of the British people and the Commonwealth.</p>
<p>Your Majesty, You have kept that pledge with unbroken constancy of purpose.</p>
<p>And the life upon which you were venturing has turned out to be long, eventful and greatly productive.</p>
<p>So it is that we greet you on the sixteenth time you have honoured us with a visit to our shores.</p>
<p>Many heads of state and government are welcomed within these walls.</p>
<p>But in this home of Australian democracy, you are a vital constitutional part, not a guest.</p>
<p>Just as in this nation, you can only ever be welcomed as a beloved and respected friend.</p>
<p>Your Majesty is the longest-lived sovereign in British history.</p>
<p>And surely history's most travelled head of state as well.</p>
<p>You are also the first and only reigning monarch to venture upon these shores.</p>
<p>Not merely to visit  -  but to share and understand the life of this nation.</p>
<p>You have witnessed our evolution from a small agricultural economy to an open, modern trading nation at home in this region and the world.</p>
<p>A vibrant multicultural democracy that has welcomed people from every corner of the globe.</p>
<p>A nation that honours its First Peoples and speaks the truth about its past.</p>
<p>A nation that more fully embraces the rights and aspirations of all its people, women and men alike.</p>
<p>And it is perhaps a sign of our progress that Your Majesty was welcomed at Canberra Airport by a female Governor-General, a female Prime Minister and a female Chief Minister.</p>
<p>These have been remarkable decades indeed.</p>
<p>My eminent predecessor once spoke of a lady passing by.</p>
<p>Far from passing by, you have endured.</p>
<p>You have endured with dignity and abiding strength of spirit.</p>
<p>As heir and monarch, you have walked fully two-thirds of Australia's national journey with us.</p>
<p>Understanding with clarity and sympathy our growing maturity as a nation and as a people.</p>
<p>Visiting every corner of this Commonwealth.</p>
<p>And sharing great national moments like the opening of the Opera House, the Bicentenary and this very Parliament building.</p>
<p>Now you stand at the gate of a truly extraordinary year;</p>
<p>An anniversary experienced by only one other monarch in our long history: because in 14 weeks time, the people of Britain and the Commonwealth will mark your diamond jubilee.</p>
<p>We will celebrate that jubilee with sincere gratitude and joy.</p>
<p>We will honour a wise and gracious sovereign who has spent her life in the cause of duty.</p>
<p>And we will honour the consort who has stood so constantly</p>
<p>at your side, himself a true friend of this country in peace and war; an outstanding supporter of science, innovation, and the education and support of our young people; and man whose robust humour and commonsense have always resonated with the Australian character.</p>
<p>Your Majesty, we do not know where Australia's path of nationhood may lead in the times to come.</p>
<p>We are, as you once so rightly said, “a country on the move and will go on being so”.</p>
<p>But we know this for a certainty: your journey of service will continue all the length of your days.</p>
<p>Keeping faith with the pledge made in Cape Town so many years ago.</p>
<p>And keeping faith with us, the people you have so long served.</p>
<p>And who give you, in return, our lasting affection and our very deep respect. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
