<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7863</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/12/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007863.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M.' S PRE55 OFFICE CRND TEL: 51-052-732923 rj9,01390 14: 50 NO. 002 F. 01<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 22 DECEMBER 1988<br />
The Government has formally nominated about 262,000 hectares<br />
Of South West Tasmania for World Heritage Listing. The<br />
nomination adds to the existing World Heritage site some<br />
per cent of the Lemonthyme and Southern Forests inquiry<br />
area, together with the Walls of Jerusalem National Park and<br />
the Central Plateau Conservation Area.<br />
The co~ nbined area, to be known as the Tasmanian World<br />
Heritage area, will exceed one million hectares. This is<br />
equivalent to one-seventh of the land mass of Tasmania.<br />
The nomination is fully supported by the Tasmanian<br />
Government. Premier Gray has signed a letter with me,<br />
jointly transmitting the nomination to the world Heritage<br />
Committee.<br />
Achieving the agreement of the State Government to joint<br />
nomination provides an additional measure of protection for<br />
the areas.<br />
The new areas nominated c -onta'in large pristine tall1 forest<br />
ecosystems, together with superlative examples of<br />
wilderness, rainforest, alpine ecosystems and glacial<br />
landscapes. They also contain rare and endangered species<br />
and a number of sites of major Aboriginal cultural<br />
significance.<br />
This is a landmark decision in the conservation of<br />
Australia's unique and fragile natural heritage. It follows<br />
my Government's successful nomination to the World Heritage<br />
List of the Wet Tropics of Queensland, the New South Wales<br />
Rainforests, Uluru and stage II of Kakadu National Park.<br />
Australia has done more than any other country for the<br />
conservation of nature through the World Heritage<br />
Convention, as acknowledged recently by the World Heritage<br />
advisory body. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
