<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6853</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW, MAX WALSH ON CARLETON WALSH REPORT, 5 MARCH 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/03/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006853.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Jj,, AUSTHAL1A~<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW, MAX WALSH ON CARLETON WALSH REPORT,<br />
MARCH 1986<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
WALSH: Mr Hawke, congratulations on making your third birthday<br />
as Prime Minister. Have you pondered in the last few days that<br />
if you hadn't have gone to that early election you would have had<br />
an election in the last month or so when you almost certainly<br />
would have been returned with a larger majority facing another<br />
36 months in office.<br />
PM: No, I haven't. We made what we thought was the right<br />
decision at the time to coincide with the half Senate election.<br />
And I know that when we come up at the end of this full term we<br />
will win again.<br />
WALSH: At your address today to the National Press Club you drew<br />
attention to the little shop of horrors you inherited when you<br />
came to office in terms of the economic situation. But you then<br />
went on to say that the conditions we now face are even more<br />
difficult and more complex.<br />
PM: What I said was that the goals, the objectives were very<br />
simple when we came in. I said, I went on, you will recall, to<br />
say that the mechanism, the means to turn the economy around<br />
weren't simple. What I am saying is that the complex situation<br />
now, paradoxically, represents the price we are paying for the<br />
success of our policies. The high levels of economic growth that<br />
we have generated, running at six per cent per annum up to the<br />
last September quarter in non-farm GDP, has occurred in a<br />
situation, as you know, of a current account deficit problem. We<br />
are sucking in very high levels of imports with that level of<br />
growth.-There seems, as you know max, to be a situation that<br />
importers have carried some of those pricing impacts within their<br />
profit margins, so there hasn't been the diminution in the level<br />
of imports that you might have expected as quickly. Therefore,<br />
what we have got to do in that situation is to pursue a policy,<br />
we have been doing by monetary policy, to try and take the top<br />
off the level of demand. What I am saying is that we have got to<br />
walk that very tightrope between the levelling off process to<br />
protect our external position while at the same time, Max, not<br />
taking you back that far that you are going to produce a<br />
situation where we can't maintain a sufficient level of activity<br />
to cope with the unemployment problem.<br />
WALSH: So in the very short term do you see the balance of </p>
<p>payments problems being the major constraint upon your economic<br />
activies? PM: I think that is a fair statement. AS we went towards the<br />
end of 1985 and have come into ' 86 that has been the major<br />
constraint. I believe that is right.<br />
WALSH: You made the point in your speech that Australia can't<br />
afford to keep living on the savings of the outside world. I<br />
have read that as saying that you saw some necessity to cut back<br />
on overseas borrowings both at the public and private level.<br />
PM: IT is the case that we have got to, as far as the public<br />
sector is concerned which we directly control, I think reduce<br />
the public sector borrowing requirement. Now, it is a matter of<br />
logic, as you know, if you have got a gap between what you earn<br />
overseas by your earn overseas and what you import then you have<br />
got to borrow. The borrowing has got to be done.<br />
WALSH: Yes, but you face a very high level of past borrowings at<br />
a time when, would you agree, we are moving into a very difficult<br />
situation in terms of our own terms of trade, major export<br />
commodities. PM: Absolutely. Max, you are quite right there. What<br />
Australia, I think, doesn't appreciate sufficiently, including a<br />
lot of reasonably informed commentators, what a devastating<br />
impact there has been in the change in the terms of trade in the<br />
last 6 months or more.<br />
WALSH: But I am really looking at the coming 6 months, because<br />
it is starting, you see we still haven't seen the impact of the<br />
oil price cut on coal prices, which surely will follow through.<br />
We haven't yet seen the full impact of the American export<br />
enhancement policy on grain prices.<br />
PM: We also haven't seen, I mean I don't dispute those<br />
propositions, but in balance nor have we yet seen Max, the impact<br />
upon the level of economic activity worldwide of the reduction in<br />
oil prices. And that increase in activity, which one would<br />
assume, I think sensibly, can result from lower oil prices,<br />
should mean a better-demand for a number of our products. I<br />
mean, it is not a completely one-sided picture, I think you will<br />
agree.<br />
WALSH: Yes, but the trouble is that our major commodity exports,<br />
our non-ferrous metals and our iron ore etc, there is simply so<br />
much more competition now out there now than there used to be.<br />
PM: But it is also the case, it is a matter of economic logic to<br />
expect that if fuel prices are significantly reduced through this<br />
period then that factor of itself should increase the level of<br />
activity internationally. And to the extent that there is an<br />
increase in the level of activity, that should, other things<br />
being equal, be to our advantage.<br />
WALSH: One of the things which you said today, you said, I even<br />
think you said it was your proudest achievement, that you had<br />
reduced real unit labour costs to the levels of the late sixties,<br />
early seventies. </p>
<p>PM: I didn't say it was my proudest achievement, that was a<br />
reference. But it was part of the achievement..<br />
WALSH: Well, you didn't apologise and later you, you focussed on<br />
this particular point. And while that is perfectly true in<br />
respect of the manufacturing industry and that is what you were<br />
talking about, is that our manufacturing exports are only a very<br />
small proportion of our export situation.<br />
PM: It's true. But what we have got to do as a country is to<br />
increase the competitiveness of our manufacturing sector. And<br />
I think one of the reassuring statistics recently, Max, has been<br />
the evidence of increased investment in manufacturing. You will<br />
recall that looking at the figures for the December quarter and<br />
comparing them with the previous December quarter, there is an<br />
increase of 46.4 per cent in manufacturing fixed capital<br />
investment. That is a very significant investment. And it does<br />
suggest that the judgement is being made, Max, by many people in<br />
our manufacturing sector that they are now better placed than<br />
they have been for anything like recent memory to take advantage<br />
of the conjunction of circumstances to which I have referred.<br />
WALSH: Well, what I really want to get around to saying is do<br />
you expect that this surge in manufacturing investment will be<br />
reflected in both increased manufacturing exports of a<br />
significant degree and significant import replacement?<br />
PM: I hope, well I am glad you went to that second because one<br />
of the problems, talking in technical economic terms, has been<br />
that the assumption that the depreciation would lead to import<br />
replacement, the argument is that in some respects that has not<br />
been possible because of the type of demands within Australian<br />
are not capable of being satisfied, at this stage, by our<br />
structure of manufacturing industry. Therefore we have simply had<br />
to continue to get them from overseas, yes. It is my hope that<br />
part of this longer term pattern that you are rightly directing<br />
the viewers attention to will be an increase in the capacity of<br />
Australian manufacturing industry to provide elements of our<br />
infrastructure which hi. therto they have not been able to display.<br />
The increase in competitiveness will reflect not only in<br />
additional exports of manufactured goods but in additional<br />
capacity to cover import replacement.<br />
WALSH: Mr Hawke, if I could move on to BHP. John MacBean wants<br />
to have the whole question of the Holmes-a-Court takeover bid<br />
referred to the Steel Industry Authority. What's the Government's<br />
attitude to this?<br />
PM: Well, as I said at the National Press Club today, it is<br />
arguable that under section 7 of the Act you could ask the<br />
Authority to have a look at it. But it wasn't really intended for<br />
that sort of purpose. In the end the Government Max, has to<br />
satisfy itself about certain public interest questions and our<br />
judgment is that the best way of satisfying ourselves on that is </p>
<p>4<br />
to look at it directly ourselves. Nevertheless, I think it proper<br />
that we should have some discussions with the Steel Industry<br />
Authiority and in fact therefore what we will be doing is after<br />
having spoken with BHP and having spoken with Mr Holmes a Court<br />
we will, immediately following that, talk with Mr Roberts of the<br />
Steel Industry Authority so that we can give him the benefit of<br />
those discussions and ourselves receive the benefit of any<br />
comments that he has got to make to us.<br />
WALSH: Well, understandably the debate on BHP has to a large<br />
extent focused on the iron and steel division but will your<br />
inquiry into the public interest and your questions with BHP and<br />
Mr Holmes a Court range into the areas of oil exploration,<br />
mining? PM: I believe that we will range more widely than just the steel<br />
industry although I think you can appreciate the pre-eminence of<br />
that concern given the history since we came into government.<br />
When we came in to government the position then was that BHP was<br />
contemplating closing down its steel industry. I said I wouldn't<br />
tolerate that. we brought in the steel industry and we have<br />
transformed the industry. Now we are not going to allow a<br />
situation to occur where the future integrity and viability, the<br />
capacity for expansion of the steel industry is prejudiced. So I<br />
think you will appreciate the pre-eminence of that concern. But,<br />
no, we will be looking at these other issues to which you refer.<br />
WALSH: And one of the incidental debates which has arisen out of<br />
this particular issue of the BHP takeover is the habit of<br />
takeovers where borrowings are used to replace equity capital and<br />
the corporate tax base is eroded. Is this part and parcel of your<br />
inquiry?<br />
PM: Well, there will be questions to the two parties that are<br />
relevant to that but in addition max, we have also asked Paul<br />
Keating, the Treasurer, to bring to Cabinet in the near future a<br />
broader paper on this which goes beyond just this takeover which<br />
has its implications in that area.<br />
WALSH: Just a final question Prime Minister, and nothing<br />
connected with what we.. have been talking about but you must be a<br />
little bit disappointed and disturbed that sort of in your third<br />
birthday week that the appearance of unity in your Cabinet has<br />
been a little shattered by a series of leaks......<br />
PM: I don't accept that. Seriously, I am not just being a<br />
politician being protective of his government. Let me say these<br />
things, firstly, leaks have been a feature of governments of both<br />
political persuasions for a very long period of time. I mean we<br />
haven't had the situation yet where a whole Budget has been<br />
leaked as happened under the Conservatives point one. Point<br />
two, nevertheless I am disappointed that there has been that<br />
leak. But point three, let me make the point, ag I did at the<br />
Press Club today, I respect my Ministers in the welfare and<br />
associated areas wanting to protect the interests that they<br />
represent. I mean if they weren't in there trying to fight for<br />
and protect those interests they shouldn't be in the job. </p>
<p>WALSH: You are referring to the letter you received?<br />
PM: Yes, sure. But going to the issue of the leak of the<br />
document which was in yesterday's Sydney Morning Herald and at<br />
least a discussion about a document which was reflected in<br />
today's Sydney Morning Herald, I would rather, of course, that<br />
that had not occurred and I am annoyed about it. But what I am<br />
saying is that that reflects no split in the Cabinet. The<br />
spending Ministers, if I can go back to that group of seven, in<br />
their letter, the letter is a perfectly respectable letter. They<br />
recognise the relevance of the economic environment. So what we<br />
are seeing is the classic case of a government having to balance<br />
the need for expenditure restraint against the natural instincts<br />
and interests of Ministers who have specific portfolio<br />
responsibilities. As I said at the Press Club and I repeat on<br />
your program, we don't have to be in a position where we say, oh<br />
look please trust us, you know we'll work it out. We have been<br />
here for three years, we have proved the best the economic<br />
managers in the post war period of Australia, we have produced<br />
record growth, we are outstripping the rest of the world. And we<br />
have done that in a process which has involved expenditure<br />
restraint, a balancing of competing priorities. We have done it<br />
three times, we will do it again.<br />
WALSH: OK Prime Minister, thanks very much.<br />
PM: Thanks Max.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
