<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5643</transcript-id>
    <title>WORLD TRADE CENTRE - STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER MR ANTHONY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/08/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005643.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
2c~<br />
FOR MEDIA WEDNESDAY, 26 AUGUST, 1981<br />
WORLD TRADE CENTRE<br />
Statement by the Acting Prime Minister<br />
Mr. Anthony.<br />
The Acting Prime Minister, Mr. Anthony, today announced the<br />
Commonwealth Government's intention to lease office space in the<br />
World Trade Centre, Melbourne.<br />
The World Trade Centre complex is a major undertaking of the<br />
Victorian Government which will provide a comprehensive service<br />
to assist in the development and facilitation of international<br />
trade in Melbourne.<br />
The Commonwealth Government is pleased to be associated with<br />
the project and also pleased that elements of its trade-related<br />
Departments will be able to give support to assisting the Centre<br />
in its role of developing Victoria's exports.<br />
The Commonwealth Departments involved are Trade and Resources,<br />
Business and Consumer Affairs and Primary Industry.-The Trade<br />
and Resources element will provide a comprehensive information<br />
service on international trading matters as well as a market<br />
advisory service for devqloping countries. The customs element<br />
of the Department of Business and Consumer Affairs will be<br />
located in the Centre to provide customs services. These two<br />
Departments will move to the World Trade Centre as soon as<br />
accommodation is available. The Primary Industry element will<br />
move into the Centre when the lease of its current premises<br />
expires in 1984.<br />
The location of all these Departments in the World Trade Centre<br />
and their proximity to the Port of Melbourne, the city centre<br />
and commercial trading organisations will, in the Commonwealthi<br />
Government's view, be of great assistance in the development<br />
of Victoria's international trade. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
