<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5767</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN GREEN PRESIDENTIAL AWARDS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005767.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA WEDNESDAY, 10 MARCH 1982<br />
AUSTRALIAN GREEK PRESIDENTIAL AWARDS<br />
I have announced today the introduction of a program of<br />
Australian Greek Presidential Awards in honour of the visit<br />
of President Karamanlis.<br />
The awards reflect the special links which Australia has<br />
with Greece through our large Greek community, and will<br />
help to naintain and strengthen them.<br />
Awards will be granted each year to eight young Australians<br />
to allow them to study or gain practical experience in Greece.<br />
The awards will cover a wide range of activities that will<br />
foster -the maintenance and development of Greek culture<br />
within A'-stralia's multicultural society. Examples include<br />
opportu-. ities; for young Greek Australians to work or study<br />
in their own fields for 12 months, for migrant education<br />
teachers or ethnic cor.. unity workers to improve their understanding<br />
of Greek customs, and for high school students to<br />
spend tir-e in a Greek school, billeted with a Greek family.<br />
Awards may also be granted to student teachers or teachers<br />
of modern Greek language, and social welfare workers, doctors<br />
and lawyers working with the Greek Australian community.<br />
Participants in the program will be selected by a national<br />
committee that will comprise six representatives of the Greek<br />
cor,.: unity, and representatives of the relevan-t Government<br />
departments and the Australian Institute of Multicultural<br />
Affairs. The Office of Youth Affairs will be responsible for<br />
administration of the Program.<br />
Nominations for awards will be invited from Greek community<br />
organisations throughout Australia, as well as applications froii<br />
individuals, to be lodged with the Office of Youth Affairs by<br />
1 July 1982 for the first round of awards.<br />
Awards will be made to people under 30 years of age, on the<br />
basis of their proposals outlining the activities they wish to<br />
undertake and the expected benefit of the award to the participz: nts<br />
and the wider links between Australian and Greek society.<br />
The awards will cover the return fare to Greece for the<br />
participant and a living allowance. The living allowance and<br />
the period of the award, which can be for 12 months, will vary<br />
depending on the requirements of the individual and the type of<br />
activity for which the award is granted.<br />
-oooOCO coo<br />
PRiE IVHSISTER </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
