<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10980</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 INTERVIEW WITH JEREMY CORDEAUX, RADIO 5DN</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>...The Prime Minister of Australia and we welcome you sir?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning, how are you?</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Are you well?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, I am indeed.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>I'm glad.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Very well indeed.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>We've just got back from a little trip up east and one of the</p>
<p> things that I saw  not much coverage of Australia  but</p>
<p> one thing that I did see was the demonstration in Castlereagh Street,</p>
<p> the Serbs bringing that awful war to our shores in a most unpleasant</p>
<p> way. I suppose this is something you worry about as well.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I certainly worry about the use of violence. And anybody has</p>
<p> the right of peaceful protest in this country but anything that involves</p>
<p> violence, violence in relation to disputes that don't involve</p>
<p> Australia in a direct sense  I mean, we make foreign policy</p>
<p> decisions not based on assessing the totality of domestic opinion</p>
<p> on this or that argument but we make decisions based on what is in</p>
<p> the best interests of Australia and all Australian citizens irrespective</p>
<p> of their ethnic background must accept that that is the way this country</p>
<p> operates. Now, people who have a Serbian background are understandably</p>
<p> emotionally involved in what's happening in their former homeland.</p>
<p> I understand that and that is perfectly human and perfectly natural.</p>
<p> And our argument is not with the Serbian people but with the Milosevic</p>
<p> Government. But they should not use violence. They should not assault</p>
<p> police. They should not endanger lives or property in their behaviour.</p>
<p> And I think all Australians condemn the violence. And I noticed that</p>
<p> the leaders of some of the groups in Australia involved in the demonstrations</p>
<p> have also condemned the violence and I encourage them to continue</p>
<p> to do so because there is no sympathy in this country for violent</p>
<p> demonstrations of any kind regarding political issues.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Do you have any major concerns yourself as to just where this conflict</p>
<p> in Serbia is going to lead us?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's very difficult, Jeremy. The NATO countries were left</p>
<p> with no alternative. There hasn't been a quick submission by</p>
<p> the Milosevic regime. The images on our television screens of the</p>
<p> exodus of refugees are quite appalling. You're looking at one</p>
<p> of the largest movements of humanity, certainly the largest movement</p>
<p> of humanity in Europe since World War II and one of the largest in</p>
<p> the world in the last few decades. The stories coming out about the</p>
<p> atrocities being committed against the Albanians are equally appalling.</p>
<p> So the world can at least see why the NATO countries felt they had</p>
<p> to do something. In a sense you're damned if you do and you're</p>
<p> damned if you don't. If great powers stand by and allow things</p>
<p> to go on, which we all find unacceptable, they are criticised for</p>
<p> doing nothing and that happened in Bosnia. Remember all the criticism</p>
<p> of how long it took for countries like the United States and the NATO</p>
<p> countries to do anything. Now in this instance they have acted far</p>
<p> more quickly and people are beginning to say:- oh well, that hasn't</p>
<p> solved the problem straight away. It is a hugely difficult issue because</p>
<p> we can't close our eyes to what is happening to humanity in other</p>
<p> parts of the world. You can't ignore gross human rights abuses</p>
<p> and breaches. But it is never easy through military action - and that</p>
<p> is all you are left with if diplomacy and patience and talk failS</p>
<p> - it's never easy to get a quick result. On all the evidence</p>
<p> available to me and to the Government the NATO action was a regrettable</p>
<p> necessity.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>I see that Roxby Downs is in the news, not in really the way we would</p>
<p> like it to be. I was talking yesterday about Mr Kevin Buzzacott who</p>
<p> I believe, if he's been quoted correctly here, says that he could</p>
<p> kill, under Aboriginal law, he could kill Western Mining chief, Hugh</p>
<p> Morgan, because of the effects of the mine on his homeland and his</p>
<p> people  he could kill under Aboriginal law. What an extraordinary</p>
<p> thing for a community leader to say.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Of course, it's an extraordinary thing for anybody to say. Now,</p>
<p> I don't want to treat such a comment too seriously except to</p>
<p> say that every Australian, including Aboriginal Australians, would</p>
<p> find that kind of remark absolutely unacceptable.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Yeah, but what about the jobs and the wealth that is created not just</p>
<p> for shareholders but for the entire country of which he is a part?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, of course. This is a whole argument about not only Roxby Downs</p>
<p> but it's the argument about Jabiluka. It is the argument about</p>
<p> so much of the measured development of our mineral deposits. That</p>
<p> development, when it leads to exports, earns billions of dollars for</p>
<p> this country. The Aboriginal people share in that. In some parts of</p>
<p> Australia they share more than anybody else does because there are</p>
<p> special royalty arrangements. And the amazing thing is that the course</p>
<p> of action being advocated in relation to Jabiluka, for example, by</p>
<p> the more widely reported Aboriginal leaders is, in fact, against the</p>
<p> long-term interest of the Aboriginal people in that area. Because</p>
<p> many of the mining developments in Australia over the last 20 years</p>
<p> have been accompanied by special royalty arrangements for indigenous</p>
<p> people and that has meant millions of dollars being available to those</p>
<p> people and over and above the benefits of that mine. And Aboriginal</p>
<p> leaders who attack further mining development are attacking the opportunities</p>
<p> of their fellow Aboriginal people to share in the development of Australia's</p>
<p> mineral resources. I cannot understand that people who constantly</p>
<p> campaign against resource development in Australia, in the name of</p>
<p> respecting Aboriginal rights, really have the interests of those people</p>
<p> at heart because they will benefit more in many cases than the rest</p>
<p> of us because of these special royalty arrangements.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Yes, well if somebody finds something of value under my land it would</p>
<p> just be acquired I take it. I mean, I wouldn't...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, precisely, precisely.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Exactly.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Exactly. Now, we have special arrangements and I don't begrudge</p>
<p> those special arrangements. I'm in favour of them. It's</p>
<p> part of giving greater economic empowerment and independence to the</p>
<p> Aboriginal people. But it has to be said that their fellow Aboriginal</p>
<p> leaders or fellow Aborigines who attack these developments can go</p>
<p> off to UN committees trying to have them stopped are really doing</p>
<p> their fellow Aborigines in the eye in the process.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Yes, Prime Minister, I mentioned that we had a little holiday up east</p>
<p> and a couple of the things that occurred to me - and travel, no doubt</p>
<p> broadens the mind...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>So they say.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>One of the things I saw up there in this incredible port of Singapore</p>
<p> was the way in which that port operates 24 hours a day  three</p>
<p> shifts a day I understand. The busiest or the second busiest port</p>
<p> in the world and such prosperity. They think they're in the middle</p>
<p> of a recession. If that's a recession I think we should have</p>
<p> it here. Where are we with industrial reform at the moment, industrial</p>
<p> relations reform?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we are certainly doing a lot better than we were. And interestingly</p>
<p> enough, the reforms that have occurred over the last three years have</p>
<p> not been accompanied by an increase in industrial disputes. In fact,</p>
<p> industrial disputes now are at an 80-year low. You have to go back,</p>
<p> I think, to the year 1913 to get a lower level of industrial disputes</p>
<p> in Australia. Where are we in relation to the waterfront, after the</p>
<p> enormous dispute last year, what has happened is that in the port</p>
<p> of Melbourne you have significant increases in productivity. Other</p>
<p> ports, the improvements have not been as great because the reforms</p>
<p> there have not been as readily embraced by sections of the Maritime</p>
<p> Union of Australia. But in Melbourne where the unions and the workforce</p>
<p> have responded in a very positive way, not only has the productivity</p>
<p> lifted but also the pay and remuneration of the waterside workers</p>
<p> has also been extremely good. And that has demonstrated the benefit</p>
<p> of reform. The company that drove the reform, Patrick, so far from</p>
<p> going out of business as its union and Labor Party critics predicted,</p>
<p> has in fact done very well. And I think what we've had demonstrated</p>
<p> to us is that if you have the strength of purpose, as the Government</p>
<p> and that company did, to drive a reform  and we're now</p>
<p> getting up to the first anniversary of those reform measures </p>
<p> I believe that you do get results. And I don't think the Australian</p>
<p> waterfront will ever be the same again and we have achieved, particularly</p>
<p> in the port of Melbourne, some significant changes and improvements.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Well, I can't see why we can't be just as productive as</p>
<p> the people in Singapore but I guess that's another story.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Jeremy, to be fair to Australia, we have in fact done very well.</p>
<p> I mean, we are doing economically better than most countries in the</p>
<p> world and the productivity improvement from the Australian workforce</p>
<p> over the last few years has been quite significant.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Let's go back to something you said where basically we can, and</p>
<p> I think you were talking more about in the context of this Baywatch</p>
<p> kafuffle a little while ago, you said that largely Australia's</p>
<p> reached a point where we can choose the level of productivity. We</p>
<p> can choose the level of unemployment that we want. But we must understand</p>
<p> that it is in the palm of our hand to make the hard decisions and</p>
<p> to go the way we choose the go.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it has all ways been that way, and even more so now because we</p>
<p> are living in a global economy and the idea that the rest of the world</p>
<p> is going to bail us out. I mean so many investments now will just</p>
<p> shop around for the most attractive location and if we don't</p>
<p> welcome investments, if we chase it out of our backyard, then it's</p>
<p> going to go some where else. Now we've actually been quite good</p>
<p> over the last few years. We have kept our inflation down, our interest</p>
<p> rates down, we've paid off our debts, we've become more</p>
<p> productive, and we've out performed just about every country</p>
<p> in the industrialised world and most countries in our region. But</p>
<p> we have to keep it up and the point I was making about Baywatch, and</p>
<p> I'd make it again and again, if we choose to maintain in our</p>
<p> system barriers against employment growth well we won't have</p>
<p> employment growth. That is why we argue very strongly you've</p>
<p> got to keep junior wage rates. Why we argue very strongly for small</p>
<p> business you've got to get rid of these absurd unfair dismissal</p>
<p> laws. We've been trying for three years to really clean that</p>
<p> up and the Senate keeps blocking us. But we're going to keep</p>
<p> trying that again and again. I mean I think the Australian public</p>
<p> is getting fed up with the policies of opposition for opposition's</p>
<p> sake. The job of an Opposition is to oppose some times, but it's</p>
<p> also to put forward alternatives. And if an Opposition spends all</p>
<p> its time saying no no no to everything the Government does, in the</p>
<p> end the public will run out of patience. And this is particularly</p>
<p> true in relation to our tax reform plan. It's true in relation</p>
<p> to unfair dismissal and junior wage rates. We took all of those things</p>
<p> to the public last October. We won the election and we are entitled</p>
<p> to ask the Senate to pass those measures.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>There is a feeling apparently that Labor is softening its stance on</p>
<p> the GST. Do you sense that yourself?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I sense that the public is fed up with the politics of opposition</p>
<p> for opposition's sake. I find in the community, even amongst</p>
<p> those people who didn't vote for us, an acceptance that: well</p>
<p> at least you fellas put the plan up before the election. You told</p>
<p> us about it before the election, you didn't mislead us. And you</p>
<p> won the election and even though we don't like it I suppose you're</p>
<p> entitled to have it because the public voted for you. And that is</p>
<p> our argument. I mean you cannot run a democracy, a parliamentary system</p>
<p> properly if a party that lays everything out in absolute detail is</p>
<p> still frustrated. It's a different matter I suppose if you haven't</p>
<p> said anything about it.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Yeah sure.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But we couldn't have been more up front. I mean even to the point</p>
<p> of people saying we were crazy to reveal so much detail. But we did</p>
<p> it, and we are now saying to those in the Senate who are opposing</p>
<p> us: listen to the public. And we're saying to the Labor Party:</p>
<p> you run the risk if incurring the scorn and the wrath of the community</p>
<p> even though some of them may not have supported us and a lot of them</p>
<p> didn't. That's the nature of Australian politics they accept</p>
<p> that we won the election. And this applies not only with tax. It applies</p>
<p> with Telstra; it applies with junior wage rates; it applies with unfair</p>
<p> dismissal laws. All of those policies were put on the table before</p>
<p> the election. I don't know how else you can conduct an election</p>
<p> in a Parliamentary democracy. You go to an election and say: if you</p>
<p> vote for us we'll do the following things. But the public votes</p>
<p> for us and then we're stopped from doing those following things.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Well it must be very frustrating, [inaudible].</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well of course but I am more concerned about the impact it has on</p>
<p> good policy and the Government of the country. We are doing very well</p>
<p> at the moment but we could be doing even better if we could get these</p>
<p> things through. And we have a heaven sent opportunity at the end of</p>
<p> this century to really surge into the next century in an even stronger</p>
<p> economic position. But we need tax reform, we need to get rid of our</p>
<p> Commonwealth government debt, and we need more industrial relations</p>
<p> reform and we are being frustrated at every turn by the Labor Party</p>
<p> and the Democrats in the Senate.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, one thing that is surging is the number of Australians</p>
<p> who say they have used heroin. The number of Australians has doubled</p>
<p> since 1995. Just going back to Singapore as an example of how they</p>
<p> beat their problem. They had a big problem up until 1970 when they</p>
<p> introduced the death penalty, or 1972 I think it was. And I believe</p>
<p> they have hanged 200 drug pushers in that time up until now and I</p>
<p> was talking to the guy that was explaining the sort of status quo</p>
<p> of Singapore and I said: do you have a drug problem now? And he said</p>
<p> of course not, no we don't have a drug problem. Surely there</p>
<p> is an example to follow. I know that you've met with the FBI</p>
<p> and you've talked about what they do in America. But they haven't</p>
<p> beaten the drug problem the way the Singaporeans have beaten the drug</p>
<p> problem.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that is true. On the other hand Singapore is a more authoritarian</p>
<p> country than Australia.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>But you want to beat this....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah I know, but I also treasure the open Australian way of life.</p>
<p> And whilst I admire a lot of what Singapore has done I treasure very</p>
<p> dearly the individual freedoms that Australians have and I don't</p>
<p> think you can automatically transplant the culture of Singapore to</p>
<p> the culture of Australia. Having said that, of course I have a very</p>
<p> strong view about heroin use. You know my attitude towards a heroin</p>
<p> trial. I will be having something more to say about this in the lead</p>
<p> up to the Premiers' Conference. There is more that all governments</p>
<p> can do. We can do more to treat people who want to beat their addiction;</p>
<p> we can do more to educate our young; we can do more to set an example</p>
<p> in the schools. And can I say we've had a recent example in Sydney</p>
<p> of an independent school expelling some girls. Now however difficult</p>
<p> that may be for those girls and their families I applaud the strength</p>
<p> of purpose of the school and I would hope that all schools around</p>
<p> Australia would take the same attitude. It would be a good thing if</p>
<p> government schools took the same attitude as well. One government</p>
<p> school in Sydney tried to do the same thing about 18 months ago and</p>
<p> it was stopped from doing so by the intervention of the education</p>
<p> minister in New South Wales and I think that was highly regrettable.</p>
<p> I think you are entitled to encourage schools to have no tolerance,</p>
<p> to have zero tolerance, whatever expression you want to use, in relation</p>
<p> to drug use in schools. Because if you have a black and white attitude</p>
<p> at that stage I think you are far more likely to yield results. I</p>
<p> mean look at the success we have had in reducing the incidence of</p>
<p> tobacco smoking in our community, remembering that tobacco still causes</p>
<p> more deaths than any other drug as I understand it. Tobacco and alcohol</p>
<p> is still the largest claimants on the lives of Australians as far</p>
<p> as drugs are concerned. We have had a lot of success because we have</p>
<p> made it less and less acceptable in our community to smoke. And I</p>
<p> say as a former smoker myself, I don't have an individualistic...I</p>
<p> didn't have an individually intolerant view of it because it</p>
<p> would be hypocritical of me to do so. But I do think that we've</p>
<p> had a lot of success because we've made it less and less acceptable</p>
<p> and less and less fashionable. Therefore it is possible through a</p>
<p> concentrated government campaign to alter community attitudes. And</p>
<p> those who throw up their arms and say because the incidence of say,</p>
<p> cannabis use is rising we should stop all efforts in future to tackle</p>
<p> the problem and just adopt a more permissive approach. I don't</p>
<p> accept that and I don't believe the majority of the Australian</p>
<p> community does. But we do need to double our efforts and we need a</p>
<p> combined assault. We need the State government and the Federal government</p>
<p> working together across party lines. I've talked about this problem</p>
<p> with both Mr Carr and Mr Kennett, and Mr Olsen, and I'm hopeful</p>
<p> that whatever our differences on one or two peripheral issues might</p>
<p> be we can get a very good result out of the Premiers' Conference.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, one thing that might get up the nose of Australians</p>
<p> when they see the frequent flyer, $22.5 million bill I think it was</p>
<p> this morning for Federal members of Parliament to fly around the world</p>
<p> in luxury. Is that justifiable?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, you could stop it all by having no Federal Parliament. And you</p>
<p> could stop it all by having no State Parliament. I mean you'd</p>
<p> save travel expenses if you had no members of Parliament and you just</p>
<p> handed the administration of the country over to some kind of unelected</p>
<p> bureaucracy and abolished Parliament. That would save money but I</p>
<p> don't know that Australians would want that. I mean this is a</p>
<p> big country. You cannot run a Federal Parliament, wherever it may</p>
<p> be based. I mean Canberra is the most, as far as travel is concerned,</p>
<p> is about the most economic location. You can't run a national</p>
<p> Parliament without people flying from Western Australia, and Queensland,</p>
<p> and Sydney and Melbourne to Canberra. It's just not possible.</p>
<p> So therefore a certain amount of expenditure is absolutely unavoidable.</p>
<p> Now as far as overseas travel is concerned you can always argue as</p>
<p> to whether there's too much of it. But in the end, as you rightly</p>
<p> said, travel does broaden the mind and the idea that in the global</p>
<p> economy in which we exist, our senior government people, or for that</p>
<p> matter, our senior Opposition people, shouldn't occasionally</p>
<p> go overseas I think it unrealistic. Business people do it, sports</p>
<p> people do it. I mean we are living in a global village. We are living</p>
<p> in a world where we're increasingly interdependent. So it's</p>
<p> easy for people to take pot shots at the cost of Parliamentary travel.</p>
<p> And as I say you could abolish the lot of it if you abolish democracy.</p>
<p>CORDEAUX:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, I've just got about 45 seconds left, a lot of</p>
<p> people, some people are screaming for you to ban Lolita. Did you see</p>
<p> t</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
