<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6624</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/04/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006624.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 23 April 1985<br />
I have advised the Council of Procedural Specialists<br />
that the Commonwealth Government will not be represented<br />
at the Council's meeting on Saturday 27 April.<br />
I understand that the Federal Branch of the Australian<br />
Medical Association has also declined to attend the<br />
meeting. The Council should abide by the wishes of the<br />
overwhelming majority of the medical profession and<br />
resume duty in the New South Wales public hospital<br />
system.<br />
Attached is a letter that was today sent to<br />
Dr Bruce Shepherd, President of the Council of<br />
Medical. Procedural Specialists.,. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CANBERRA<br />
2 3 APR 1985<br />
Dear Dr Shepherd<br />
I have received your letter of 19 April 1985 inviting<br />
the Commonwealth Government to be represented at the<br />
meeting of the Council of Medical Procedural Specialists<br />
to be held on Saturday 27 April 1985.<br />
No useful purpose would be served by Commonwealth<br />
representation at the meeting.<br />
The terms of the Commonwealth and New South Wales<br />
Governments' package have been well canvassed. An<br />
overwhelming majority of the medical profession have<br />
indicated their support for the package and their belief<br />
that the Council's industrial action should cease to<br />
allow restoration of full services in the New. South<br />
Wales public hospital system.<br />
In the interests of the medical profession, and public<br />
patients in New South Wales hospitals, I believe that at<br />
its meeting the Council should now . agree to recommend a<br />
return to normal duties.<br />
Yours sincerely<br />
R. J. L. Hawke<br />
Dr Bruce Shepherd<br />
President Council of Medical Procedural Specialists<br />
Suite 4<br />
900 Pacific Highway<br />
GORDON N. S. W. 2072 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
