<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9869</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP AND THE MINISTER FOR INDUSTRY SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY, SENATOR THE HON PETER COOK WORLD CONGRESS CENTRE, MELBOURNE, 6 DECEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009869.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE<br />
HON P J KEATING MP AND THE MINISTER FOR INDUSTRY SCIENCE AND<br />
TECHNOLOGY, SENATOR THE HON PETER COOK<br />
WORLD CONGRESS CENTRE, MELBOURNE, 6 DECEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Well, ladies and gentlemen, you know that I had the opportunity of<br />
delivering on behalf of the Government this statement to the National Trade<br />
and Investment Outlook Conference, which is now a very large forum for<br />
advancing Australia's trade development and trade policies. And we are<br />
getting a very high degree of attendance, larger constituencies from various<br />
countries and business communities around the world and particularly<br />
around the region. And we are very pleased with the progress of it.<br />
So we thought given that much of what we are doing here today is building<br />
on the successful industry policy structure we have put into place, it was<br />
important to put that in the context of where Australia is growing in trade<br />
and investment in the region and to say in which way it is changing and to<br />
take the policy framework further and that we are doing.<br />
Could I say that the principal driver of the process has been my colleague,<br />
Peter Cook, as Minister with industry responsibilities and I think that you<br />
will see by the nature of the package that, as I said in the Conference<br />
today, we are long past the notion of whether we are free trade, or<br />
protection, or those old debates. But rather how we can grow out, further,<br />
product innovation, research and development, applying better ideas and<br />
seeing which way we can help small and medium sized business<br />
communities and this can I say also my colleague, Senator Schacht, has<br />
had a substantial role to play and in doing this, looking into the package as<br />
a way of further developing innovative policy in Australia.<br />
This is part of a package. It is a responsible package. It is, in fact, raising<br />
about $ 350 million more in revenue than we are actually spending over the<br />
next four years. But, I think, it is important to show that money of this<br />
dimension, sensibly spent, can have a big impact in filling out the picture, in<br />
building on what we have now in terms of our trade development, in terms<br />
of the development of Austrade, in terms of our outreach programs and, of<br />
course, in the big context of APEC etc. </p>
<p>It further underlines a central thing too which this Government has always<br />
been committed, which is competition. It is through competition which we<br />
have had by dropping the tariff wall, by micro-economic reform, by opening<br />
up the airline system, in whichever field you wish to focus on that<br />
competitive urge is what is making Australia more efficient, where we have<br />
seen productivity higher, inflation lower and our trade competitiveness in<br />
better shape.<br />
So we need to provide the sort of fine textured detail on how to grow and<br />
prosper in the world and, I think, that this sort of a statement wouldn't have<br />
been possible, it wouldn't have meant anything, in Australia ten years ago.<br />
But, of course, now it fits I think very well the niche we need for it.<br />
It has got a number of elements to it. Perhaps I can just flick over them and<br />
then Peter can round out my remarks. We have always had a very strong<br />
public sector research and development effort. We have a very large<br />
commitment. We spent about $ 3 1/ 2 billion on current public sector<br />
support for R&amp; D. We have now succeeded, I think, in building private<br />
business R&amp; D and you can see that with a lot of Australian specialised<br />
businesses now. What we are seeking to do here is to improve that. Also,<br />
focussing on some major facilities which will advance that effort and then<br />
looking at such things as the extension of the 150%, the Major Facilities<br />
Program, the Cooperative Research Centres, in commercial isation, using<br />
ideas. For instance, in areas such as the specialised manufacturing<br />
technologies of Fraunhofer type institutes, or the Queensland<br />
Manufacturing Institute taking that further, linking Australia to world<br />
leading edge technologies. All these ways of deepening our innovation<br />
and our propensity to use it.<br />
There is also, I think, an important -change here for the support in equity of<br />
small and medium sized enterprises through encouraging banks into the<br />
equity business. It is banks, after all, who have the closest focus on<br />
medium sized firms, who know more about their prospects and their<br />
management then say any funds management institution would. And we<br />
think this will be an important component for the equity support of<br />
businesses which are already up and running and which require that kind of<br />
support.<br />
And then reaching out to the world, we have got the TradeBlazer program<br />
which is, again, looking at not only providing, if you like, on-line advertising<br />
for one's product and the capacity to link to a market abroad. But, also, to<br />
actually do your business on-line and do the customers procedures and all<br />
the payments system being on-line too and this, I think, is a very innovative<br />
program.<br />
We have got the proposal where we are going to use funds with other<br />
commercial enterprises in building up a trading house capacity in Osaka, in<br />
Japan. We have had approaches over the years from the Kansai region.<br />
Set up costs in that part of Japan are lower than in Tokyo and Kansai has a </p>
<p>population almost twice the size of Australia and, therefore, we think this is<br />
a good place to try and advance further the whole notion we have had with<br />
Austrade and start to focus it in, in a practical way, on these things. But not<br />
the Government doing it doing it with private business, but us helping.<br />
In new ways to operate, we have got the leading edge customers,<br />
encouraging suppliers. We have got the response to the Karpin Report. In<br />
industry technology, further developing the whole notion of access with<br />
schools and young people, children, communities and, in content, through<br />
the Creative Nation on-line services developing that further. And in<br />
industry, with the computer bounty, helping firms operate with the<br />
TradeBlazer concept, the Highway Ready Scheme.<br />
As you know, we are rolling out the cable in Australia now very quickly<br />
through Telstra and through Optus. We have got an ambitious regulatory<br />
environment post-I 997 into place. We have already seen prices falling.<br />
There is about a $ 1/ 2 billion benefit, in recent times, to the whole<br />
community from falling telecommunications prices. And so that IT<br />
componentry, the access and content of the industry, the regulatory<br />
environment, all this complements the general thrust of bringing innovation<br />
to Australia.<br />
So I complete on these notes to say that what governments have got to do<br />
now is be alert to the directions in which innovation is heading, in which<br />
ways government might help to spur that process and to know that in all<br />
these international and competitive things like benchmarking and the<br />
focus on leading edge technologies and the dissemination of these ideas<br />
and the linking of small and medium sized businesses into it are the way<br />
in which the trade debate, under this Government, is heading.<br />
And my colleague, Peter Cook, has been the driver of this and I would now<br />
like him to round out my remarks. Thank you, Peter.<br />
PC: Well thanks, Paul, and thank you ladies and gentlemen. Can I just start by<br />
saying this is a fully costed package as Paul has said. It falls easily into<br />
five parts: generating ideas; once you have generated them,<br />
commercialising them; how Australia then links to the world; and new ideas<br />
of business in the workplace; plus accelerating ideas, bringing us all into<br />
convergence with the superhighway.<br />
I would describe this as really the post-debate for the tariff free trade<br />
argument in Australia. We have passed that. We have crossed the<br />
Rubicon. We are looking at Australia in the international open market as a<br />
competitive nation and what this package does is build our scientific<br />
prowess, which is considerable, with our commercial sector.<br />
Commercialising the ideas that we create in Australia to give us a sharper<br />
edge and a more competitive edge in a more open APEC trading<br />
environment. And so it is about Australia winning in APEC and winning in<br />
the world as an outcome for the free trade market that we are creating. </p>
<p>Can I also say that one of the questions I am often most asked is where are<br />
the jobs coming from in the future in the next century. This is a package<br />
that addresses that full on. As Paul said in his speech, we have invested a<br />
huge amount in education, skill and training in this country. This is a<br />
natural out-growth of that significant investment in education because we<br />
are talking here about intellectual industry intellectual industry in the next<br />
century and positioning Australia to be a leading provider of that in this<br />
market. The main elements that I think have been left to me, however, is to say that<br />
this package also involves a major investment by Australia in new science<br />
facilities $ 62.4 million which was funded under the Working Nation<br />
program and which means investment for Australian science in new<br />
infrastructure that will underpin its international leadership position. Now<br />
that goes to the Australian Telescope, upgrading of that, building<br />
interchange links between Australian astronomers and world astronomers.<br />
It goes to renting some time on the Synchrotron Research Program and<br />
expanding our cooperation with the Japanese on Synchrotron research.<br />
That is all a very, very important element for our science community. It<br />
involves, as well, the Genome Research Facility at the cost of $ 10 million,<br />
which we will establish now based in the University of Queensland and the<br />
Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research in the Royal Melbourne<br />
Hospital. million on Airborne Research, which is to do studies including the<br />
ozone layer, water and soil evaluation studies, remote sensing studies,<br />
studies on oceanography and environmental monitoring studies this is an<br />
area where Australia does have a world leadership, this facility will<br />
consolidate that leadership.<br />
The Proteome Analysis Centre at million will study the structure of<br />
protons formed from genes and fit closely into the Genome Facility that we<br />
are funding. And the Plasma Fusion Research Facility at a cost of<br />
$ 8.7 million, which will look at energy fusion options.<br />
All of those will give Australian scientists major facilities enabling them to<br />
continue their leadership role in these sectors of the economy and they will<br />
be facilities in Australia. And, under the arrangements that we have worked<br />
with out with APEC Science Ministers, we will have some of them come and<br />
work with us some of their scientists from this region as well on our<br />
facilities, so that we can build closer links within the region which we can<br />
husband internationally.<br />
So, for me, if I had to describe this in a brief summary call, I would say that<br />
what the Snowy Mountains Scheme did for Australia in the 1950s, this<br />
package is aimed at doing for Australia in intellectual industry in the next<br />
century and putting Australian intellectual infrastructure in place to capture<br />
what will be the new frontiers of industry in this region and the world in five<br />
years to time, for the next millennium. </p>
<p>PM: Well thank you, Peter. I think we are actually happy to take questions.<br />
J: Mr Keating, some would say you are taking more out of research and<br />
development than you are putting in [ inaudible]?<br />
PM: No, not out of research and development. It is taking it out of, some times,<br />
the hands of some of the tax professionals doing that. But it is not taking<br />
out of R&amp; D and the closer focus of the measures means that and also<br />
using money directly into some of the other related programs, other than by<br />
the tax system the overall R&amp; D effort will be more effective.<br />
J: How quickly, Prime Minister, will you expect the changes to withholding tax<br />
on the arrangements of banks to translate into cuts in interest rates and are<br />
you able to quantify that at all?<br />
PM: Well I mean, I think, the changes that take effect on 1 January 1996 we<br />
will still have to legislate the changes but their impact, I think I wouldn't<br />
want to make a judgement about their impact on interest rates at this point.<br />
J: Prime Minister, there is an extra $ 350 million to play with, where would you<br />
like to direct that?<br />
PM: Well the Government will be announcing a series of statements over<br />
ensuing months and, of course, that will be employed on that task.<br />
J: Will part of the money be put into the housing statement?<br />
PM: Well we have got a housing statement coming, which is I think it is going to<br />
be a very large change in policy and it may require some of these funds.<br />
But I am not sure that it will.<br />
J: Prime Minister, in your speech you expressed some scepticism about the<br />
possibility of educating superannuation fund trustees about making money,<br />
equity funds, available for small and medium enterprises. Do you have any<br />
ideas, any carrots, or sticks in mind for helping to educate them in that<br />
area?<br />
PM: No, but I think it is important that I mean a lot of trustees are conscious<br />
of their trustees' obligations and they feel, correctly, the impulse to be<br />
prudent and to be cautious. It is a matter of letting them understand that<br />
within the framework of that prudence that they can do things which are<br />
better for their funds, for their earnings, for their members, and for the<br />
economy. But they need to get their confidence levels up and I think that is<br />
all about education. And then, of course, with it up, they will be more<br />
demanding of the funds management industry and it will commensurately<br />
have to improve its act as time goes on. So I think given the fact that we<br />
are moving now down the road of a Government engendered in<br />
Government sponsored, but privately operated, national savings schemes<br />
through superannuation, we need to get the private participants role in it up<br />
and, I think, this is one of the ways of doing it. </p>
<p>J: Prime Minister, who has been rorting the R&amp; D allowance system and how<br />
have they been getting away with it?<br />
PM: Well the Tax Commissioner could probably give you that advice, I can't<br />
Malcolm. But one thing is certain, that Peter Cook and I and before Peter,<br />
John Button we have taken the view that we want to make a statement<br />
about research and development and the importance of innovation in the<br />
Australian corporate culture. We haven't had the spread of R&amp; D into the<br />
private economy in this country as we have seen in comparable economies.<br />
We have got a very big concentration in the public sector. We wanted to<br />
underwrite, very obviously, investment in research and development and<br />
we have done that by allowing 150% deduction for investment there. But,<br />
like any concession in the system glaring concession as this is, as we<br />
want it to be the tax professionals will be in there trying to work out how<br />
they can use it to shelter income, or avoid income. Some of that, we think,<br />
has been going on and these changes should yield savings to the Budget<br />
which won't diminish the R&amp; D effort in the nation overall. But will certainly<br />
improve the Budget balance and let us have a better bank for the buck in<br />
industry policy terms.<br />
J: Prime Minister, it won't be easy banks to buy equity John Howard<br />
announced it two weeks ago<br />
PM: No, no, let me just correct this. John Howard's idea of policy is to find out<br />
what we might be doing through the bureaucracy and try to announce it<br />
before we actually get the documents down.<br />
J: So are you saying he pinched your idea?<br />
PM: Look he doesn't have any ideas. So must of the stuff that comes from him<br />
is from us. I mean this is a derivative business. He derives much of his<br />
stuff from gossip around the corridors or from the bureaucracy. In this<br />
respect, can I say to you, before John Howard ever made that statement, I<br />
had had long meetings with a couple of the managing directors of the major<br />
banks, going through the tax principles involved, whether they were<br />
accruals taxed, whether there were tax choices between accruals and<br />
realisations on one side, whether we would have in the tax system the tax<br />
treatment of it being either on realisations or an accruals basis,<br />
guaranteeing symmetry of tax treatment on the way through. And in that<br />
long debate, when you are involving private companies as we are with<br />
private banks even for those who have difficulty recognising a policy idea,<br />
there was probably so much of the bits and pieces around the landscape<br />
that Mr Howard has tripped over one. But let me assure you that was all on<br />
weeks and weeks before John Howard ever said a word about it.<br />
J: John Howard has these great contacts, these great sources </p>
<p>PM: Well can I just say, he doesn't have them though, Laurie. You see what he<br />
does is he picks up the threads and the thread he picked up on the growth<br />
numbers, of course, today he exposed himself on AM.<br />
J: He is right on one leg. Why shouldn't he be right about the other one?<br />
PM: Well where did you get that notion from?<br />
J: You claim he got a leak about your policy here. So how can you dismiss...<br />
PM: In other words, a leak about something in industry policy we have been<br />
speaking to a bank about, means that any leaks he gets on anything else<br />
must be right.<br />
J: [ inaudible]<br />
PM: Now, Laurie, even for a champion leaker like you, with Budgets and other<br />
things to your name, even you wouldn't subscribe to those principles. And I<br />
thought John Howard put himself down eloquently today by saying, when<br />
asked by the compere ' you don't really have an idea about this Mr Howard<br />
do you?' And he virtually admitted he didn't.<br />
Can I just say about the growth figures. We are in our seventeenth quarter<br />
of growth, we have been through our seventeenth quarter of growth and we<br />
are in our eighteenth. And certainly the strong contribution which we saw<br />
in the September quarter from the rural sector which has come, of course,<br />
from the breaking of the drought in some areas. It won't be repeated and<br />
stocks may detract from growth, but there is going to be a very strong<br />
contribution there from the public sector and from investment in plant and<br />
equipment which fell last time, but we think we will be stronger through this<br />
quarter. The bottom line is we belie ve we are in our eighteenth quarter of<br />
growth and, I think, most of the private economists agree with us and if you<br />
turn up our famous The Economist magazine forecast, they have got for<br />
Australia in 1996 3.1 per cent, which is of course, very strong growth.<br />
J: One more question Prime Minister, Mr Beazley on Sunday didn't seem<br />
entirely confident about that?<br />
PM: It is your judgement about the degree of confidence. I am entirely confident<br />
that we are in a growth quarter and we have already created the post war<br />
record last quarter. The country has never had 17 consecutive quarters of<br />
growth since the war. It has now had it and we are now in our eighteenth<br />
quarter. Remember this, John Hewson said before the last election that we<br />
were going into a double dip recession and then as he got gloomier, we<br />
were going into a depression. You might remember John Howard echoed<br />
those comments in the lead up to the 1993 election. This is the Howard<br />
version of the Hewson foray into econometrics and economy forecasting.<br />
He is trying to get everyone ready to think that while we have had this huge<br />
growth phase which he formerly described as a double dip recession and a<br />
depression, making them seem complete jokes both of them, he is now </p>
<p>trying to say ' oh, oh, the best days are over'. Remember his five minutes of<br />
sunshine. I don't know how many five minutes there are in 17 quarters.<br />
J: figures for the 18 quarters of economic growth..<br />
PM: I'm not sure when they are published.<br />
J: March<br />
PM: March 20, if you ask me to assure you about the election campaign date, of<br />
course I wouldn't.<br />
J: Prime Minister, I am a reporter from Taiwan's Commercial Times, my<br />
question is in regard to a story published in our newspaper that Australia..<br />
there, Australians have a lot of business because Canberra can not stand<br />
up to China over the issue of Taiwan, I would like to have your comment on<br />
this.<br />
PM: I don't think that has been a major factor in the development of our exports.<br />
Our policy is well known on this issue and during the period when this has<br />
most been debated around the world, Australian exports have gone from 13<br />
per cent of gross domestic product to 22 per cent of gross domestic<br />
product. So, if it is restraining our growth in exports it is not apparent.<br />
J: Prime Minister, one of the innovations here in Victoria causing controversy<br />
is the Citylink project. You have got your reservations about that, but can<br />
you confirm that there will be no changes under Federal law to the tax<br />
treatment of that project even though you disagree with it?<br />
PM: The Federal law in respect of the Melbourne Citylink has never been an<br />
issue. It is a matter for the Victorian Government and they want to avail<br />
themselves of these capacities, the capacity under the tax system to do<br />
things, it is a matter of how they construct packages with private companies<br />
and what they have to do to make them work, If Jeff Kennett wants to make<br />
a sheep run out of the Citylink it is his business. It is like saying to the<br />
Commonwealth ' well, if some company is doing one thing or another<br />
because they are all subject to the Australian taxation system in some way<br />
then the Commonwealth is responsible'. Well, of course, it isn't unless, of<br />
course it is out in the area of tax avoidance or something like that.<br />
J: Mr Keating, how much damage could Mr Howard cause by talking up a<br />
recession at the moment?<br />
PM: Well, it didn't do Dr Hewson much good and, I think, this sort of what I call<br />
studied gloominess Mr Howard now has won't do him any good and, of<br />
course, it is not meant to do the economy any good and that his been their<br />
stock in trade. They have tried to score off the backs of the Australian<br />
people and their progress for their own miserable political ends. I think, Mr<br />
Howard running around talking about negative growth in this quarter is just<br />
like the unbelievability of his five minutes of sunshine line. </p>
<p>J: any interest rate cut that might occur before the next election then has<br />
the gloss taken off it and seen in the context of an economy stalling, just as<br />
he as predicted?<br />
PM: Not at all. The Government has made it very clear, as I have all the years I<br />
have been the Treasurer or Prime Minister, that interest rates are adjusted<br />
when they need to be not in response to the political circumstances. Let<br />
me remind you of the former Governor of the Reserve Bank. He said<br />
' relations with the government have been entirely proper, but only an<br />
insider could know this was not always so.' That is alluding to John<br />
Howard's period as Treasurer and his intervention in interest rate setting<br />
and Dr Hewson's intervention when he worked for Mr Howard forays<br />
which were famous in the corridors of the bank. Now, this never happened<br />
under this Government and it is not happening now. Mr Fraser has made it<br />
very clear that if he sees a need for interest rates to shift and he<br />
approaches the government and the government agrees, the initiative for<br />
that will come in response to the economic circumstances. In other words,<br />
it will be entirely and I think Mr Fraser will take this view, that he may or<br />
may not do things which are seen to advantage the government just the<br />
same as he might do the contrary. In other words, he won't be taking any<br />
notice of the comments of commentators about making shifts in policy in<br />
response to the electoral cycle.<br />
J: ( inaudible)..<br />
PM: I got asked all those silly questions for years and I gave silly answers, but I<br />
have run out of them.<br />
J: Prime Minister, can I ask you John Howard..<br />
PM: Well, I'm just saying and let me just get this clear. This is a policy which we<br />
have developed over, now, quite a long period of time. We have been<br />
thinking about it for well over a year, probably 18 months or so.<br />
J: That being the case Prime Minister, why then did Senator Cook bucket it?<br />
PC: Let me indeed answer that, because if you compared what he said to what<br />
we are doing, my criticism of the broad idea which we were at that stage<br />
refining was that his structure of it, the idea in the broad that he had<br />
pinched would have caused the advantage to drift to the big end of town.<br />
This is a targeted measure which is aimed squarely in the heartland of<br />
where it is needed among small to medium sized companies and what he<br />
missed out on was the policy refinement we brought to this measure.<br />
PM: The real debate about this measure was, apart from the prudential question<br />
of the Reserve Bank, but in the terms of the tax treatment was whether a<br />
bank investing in a company which was experiencing loses could actually<br />
deduct those loses in the year in which the loses, were actually hitting the<br />
balance sheet. In other words, were we going to tax them on an accruals<br />
I Z 7 .7 </p>
<p>basis where as. they got the deduction for loses, they were given it, but<br />
when the company went into profit they were then taxed on an accruals<br />
basis as it went into profit. Now, it won't surprise you to know that some of<br />
the banks wanted accruals deductions for loses, but realisation taxation for<br />
gains. The point I made to them was that we had to have symmetry of tax<br />
treatment, not asymmetry. You couldn't have accrual deductions for loses<br />
on one hand, but not accruals taxations for gains on the other and whether<br />
they weren't better opting for the tax treatment under capital gains where<br />
they're taxed they get the benefit of deferment and they are taxed on a<br />
realisations basis only. In the end, I think, this is what they have chosen as<br />
the best way to go. It is certainly the way the government believes it is<br />
best, but that has involved a number of meetings, no doubt a number of<br />
papers being written in banks and a bit of this stuff has fallen in Mr<br />
Howard's hands. We have seen no policy detail from him, but he is quite<br />
happy to run out and blurt this out knowing full well that the government<br />
had the matter well and truly in hand for a long time.<br />
J how can you say that business finance is targeted guidelines..<br />
PC: No, we have said it is for equity finance between $ 2 million and $ 50 million<br />
and it is in that area that we are proposing to the Reserve Bank for the<br />
guidelines to be reconsidered and that is the area where most Australian<br />
small to medium sized companies operate at.<br />
J: companies access to funds to actually start up emphasise why can't<br />
supervised access..<br />
PM: Well, we have had that in the past with MICs and other instruments, but<br />
what we have found is that the costs of first of all researching out the<br />
companies, seeing what the value of the innovation is, how it might be<br />
applied, how it might be commercialised before one dollar is actually put<br />
into the business. These have got very high background costs and the<br />
dollars that need to be committed for the outcome or output have, whenever<br />
we have seen them, not been there. With the MIC companies what we<br />
found was that were it not for the value of the tax concession we would not<br />
have had the investment. There was no genuine interest in investment by<br />
the funds management business in what they might see as the blue sky of<br />
high growth, innovative companies. We have, I think, discerned the greater<br />
need for those to be who are already up and running, but who are<br />
desperately short of equity or capital and can't get it. Often companies that<br />
have capital, so called, or equity, the equity has been borrowed from<br />
someone else maybe relatives or maybe a financial institution or some<br />
other business yet if they have equity, I think, the attitude of the banks<br />
would be and they can speak for themselves, but if they stay in these<br />
companies for four or five years, build them up and then offer the equity<br />
back to the original owners or anyone else that wants to take a part in the<br />
business. That is, they get them on their feet, put the equity in them and<br />
then move out of them </p>
<p>For banks who are looking at a marginal return on debt at best and 100 per<br />
cent loss at worst, or a large part there of and requiring something like 11<br />
and 12 per cent return on funds, it's going to help them flesh out their return<br />
on funds if they invest in companies that actually grow and produce high<br />
levels of earnings. In other words, for banks that are facing competition<br />
now in the banking system for housing and some of the staples where their<br />
margins are being thinned out, this will be a useful area for them and, I<br />
think, given the fact that banks are closer to most companies, they can get<br />
the specialisation there that a funds management business can't.<br />
So, that is why, I think, it is a real opportunity for the banking system<br />
because we are seeing the whole basis of banking change. Banking is<br />
changing, where once people had the mortgage, that was the foundation<br />
building block of their relationship with the bank. Those mortgages are now<br />
being packaged up and sold into the bond markets. The founding<br />
relationship with the bank now is your credit card, the plastic card and it is<br />
through the plastic card and transaction charges that banks are making<br />
their earnings and, I think, this gives banks another area in which they can<br />
actually lift their profitability and do some good things for companies.<br />
We think those medium range companies, the ones that have got money,<br />
are already going, is where the greater need is rather than us trying to<br />
devote a substantial slab of our own equity to a venture capital business.<br />
PC: Can I also say the premise is a bit wrong. Have a look at the research<br />
commercial isation program which is $ 10 million over four years to help<br />
public sector science products to be commercialised which is, really, at the<br />
very early stages of start up and the Australian technology group which<br />
helps private sector start up companies get their product commercialised<br />
too. This is an area in which there are positive supports for very early first<br />
stage commercial isation.<br />
J: Prime Minister, given your interest in family television, how much input did<br />
you have in this so called ' V chip proposal to cut offensive material off?<br />
PM: This technology is around the world, it is about these days and we are<br />
going to see how it might be applied and, I think, Michael Lee is going to<br />
talk to the broadcasting authorities about how and in which way it might be<br />
used. But obviously, the capacity is there if a family wants to block out<br />
some of this violence in television or particular categories of programs that<br />
seems to me to be a very democratic choice that the technology will offer<br />
them.<br />
J: ( inaudible)..<br />
PM: I don't know, free to air broadcasting is a science all of its own. There are<br />
greater authorities on that in this country than me.<br />
J: Prime Minister, your forecasts are quite specific, how confident are you that<br />
you will actually meet those forecasts and will there be any pressure on the </p>
<p>R&amp; D body like the industry board et cetera to actually ensure that those<br />
targets are met by limiting access to the tax concessions?<br />
PM: Well, there is always pressure in the tax system particularly when the<br />
accountants are in there in a big way in some areas and no doubt we will<br />
get pressure from this, but again, I think, good policy is best achieved by<br />
being clear about what the objectives are and going after them. I cut my<br />
teeth on the Fringe Benefits Tax and the Capital Gains Tax and a few of<br />
those other icons, so this one is very much par for the course.<br />
J: Mr Keating, a question not about the election, but after the election. If the<br />
government is returned..<br />
PM: When the government is returned.<br />
J: It is good to see your confidence. If the government is returned to office<br />
what are the two most important things that you would like to achieve in that<br />
term of office?<br />
PM: This is all election campaign material, you are wanting a peek-a-boo into<br />
the campaign, telescoping into the campaign? Well, I think, the most<br />
important thing we have done in this Parliament is the development of<br />
APEC. From a cold start we have now set up the political infrastructure of<br />
the Asia-Pacific and a trade structure there and the integration of Australia<br />
with Asia, I think, has been one of the things in this Parliament we have<br />
concentrated on all of us I mean, Peter as Trade Minister at the<br />
conclusion of the GATT round and then into industry and his lock in to all<br />
these export markets. That is one thing and the other thing, of course, is<br />
you can't do these things without understanding some of the core elements<br />
of our identity. Of course, the issue which will most focus that in the next<br />
Parliament will be the republic._<br />
J: Mr Howard [ cross media] ( inaudible) Kerry Packer?<br />
PM: Did you notice he slipped this little one out on a Perth radio station late for<br />
the evening news and he had to wait until the Parliament got up before he<br />
said that he thought he would get rid of the cross media rules. To say that<br />
he thinks that television owners can own print in the same city.<br />
J: we are seeing now between Rupert Murdoch and Kerry Packer<br />
increasing links over recent months, there is no such thing as this being the<br />
Packer candidate, I mean a Packer-Murdoch conglomerate.<br />
PM: I think that you should have read closely the fine print of Mr Kitney's story<br />
last week and you would have found that Mr Howard's expressions which I<br />
believe largely came from his end of year drinks party made it very clear<br />
where his loyalties were going to be. He was telling us a couple of years<br />
ago we should junk the foreign investment policy and now he is getting all<br />
very het up about Australian owners of television and media assets. I think </p>
<p>Rupert Murdoch knows it doesn't mean him, so he might be slipping past<br />
one or two of you, but I doubt if he is slipping past Rupert.<br />
J: ( inaudible) [ contribution to the Carmen Lawrence Fund]<br />
PM: I think I probably will, yes.<br />
J: ( inaudible) [ how much?]<br />
PM: Why should I tell you?<br />
J: ( inaudible)..<br />
PM: No, everyone can make their own minds up about these things. This is<br />
some moral issue here as the Coalition who have staged a $ 5 million royal<br />
commission against one person and then when that person seeks<br />
representation before the commission as other people have done, as Nick<br />
Griener has done and Mr Grey in Tasmania has done, she has been<br />
denied the appropriate finance by a very snaky and spiteful opposition. I<br />
would like to see how they feel about that if Mr Court was drawing on the<br />
resources of his boat building business to pay for some of his freight.<br />
J: Mr Keating, if the superannuation education campaign fails to change the<br />
behaviour of fund managers, could you consider other incentives given the<br />
frustations you have expressed about their performance?<br />
PM: We are going through a very interesting time in the building of a pool of<br />
national assets that we know that have been privately funded and privately<br />
managed and we hope can be privately employed in a way that really<br />
benefits the nation and to individual superannuants. I think, that the<br />
debates that we have been having, whatever the occasions of them may<br />
be, are good for this process and, I think, these sorts of things are going to<br />
be good for it to try to encourage trustees to know more about the business<br />
they are in and be more discerning about who manages their funds. To be<br />
picky and choosy about who does it, why, what their objectives are et<br />
cetera. But when we get that diversity in funds management, the market<br />
itself will start picking out the people with the bigger I mean, the<br />
specialisation you see in the US fund markets is there where some fund<br />
managers distinguish themselves by consistently higher levels of earnings.<br />
This will just draw custom to them, so others will fall by the wayside and<br />
that has already been happening. You can see it with the changes of the<br />
AMP Society, the changes in management there.<br />
J: Mr Keating, with the changes in the Reserve Bank guidelines to allow them<br />
to invest in small and medium sized businesses for, the first time, what sort<br />
of safe guards will there be to ensure that the banks don't, in fact, demand<br />
equity in small businesses in return for extending credit.<br />
PM: Some of these issues will need to be worked out between the bank and the<br />
banking system, but I think, there is a big opportunity here being given to </p>
<p>14<br />
the banking system. I notice Mr Mercer in the print today talking about the<br />
future of banking and I think this is one of the innovative things that banks<br />
can do and do well. Given the opportunity, I think, they will make the most<br />
of it with the Reserve Bank.<br />
J: You don't believe ( inaudible)..<br />
PM: Well, let's see how the regime comes out.<br />
J: Can you spell out what limits will apply in the prudential guidelines as to<br />
what sort of companies they can lend to and how much of their issued<br />
capital..<br />
PM: Obviously, we will be more precautionary about it than we would be if this<br />
was obviously a scheme that is up and running. They are all subjects that<br />
we will attend to, I think, in defining that.<br />
J: how much money they might be prepared to put into this venture?<br />
PM: would contribute to the order of $ 300-400 million in the first tranche<br />
which is a sizeable slab of capital given that we are talking about<br />
companies needing somewhere between probably $ 210 million and maybe<br />
$ 215-220 million. It is going to be a healthy addition and certainly to the<br />
stock of companies which any one particular bank has the relationship with.<br />
J: ( inaudible)..<br />
PM: I could, but I don't know whether I should Michelle ( Grattan). I will just say<br />
that I have had strong indications from the banks, in general, that they see<br />
a future for themselves here and, I think, they will take the opportunity up. I<br />
thank you all for coming.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
