<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>897</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 18/1964 - PRIME MINISTER&#039;S LETTER TO SOVIET PREMIER</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/03/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Letter</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000897.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO : NOT TO BE PUBLISHED, BRC_ DCAST OR TELECAST BEFORE<br />
6.30 P. M4. ON SUNDAY, 1ST MARCH, 1964<br />
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 18/ 1264<br />
PRIME~ MINISTERtS LETTER-U0i SOVIET PREMIER<br />
The following letter has been sent to the Soviet<br />
Premier, Mr. N. S. Khrushchaev, by the Prime Minister, Sir Robert<br />
Menzies, in reply to a New Year letter from Mr. Khrushchev:<br />
" Dear Mr. Chairman,<br />
I have given careful and close attention to your<br />
message of 31st December, 1963, -the receipt of which I<br />
acknowledged in my last brief message to you. I should<br />
like to say at the outset that, while I am unable to agree<br />
with some of what you say in the course of expounding your<br />
argument and although you introduce qualificacions which<br />
I could not concede I welccme your clear statement of<br />
belief in the need L renounce the use of force in relation<br />
to disputes between states over territorial claims and<br />
question-o of boundaries. Such disputes are, of course,<br />
only one' category, and, in the way you limit them, a<br />
relatively small category, of the differences whi~ h arise<br />
in international relations: the principle of avoidance<br />
of the use of force, subject to the right of individual<br />
and collective self-defence, is fundamental to the<br />
Australian Government's attitude -towards all international<br />
disputes. Indeed, the general obligation to seek the pacific<br />
settlement of disputes is placed upon all those states which<br />
have subscribed to the Charter of the United Nations. As<br />
members of the United Nations, Australia and the U. S. S. R.<br />
have both accepted this obligation, together with the<br />
obligation stated in Article 2.4 of the % Charter that * all<br />
members shall refrain in their international relations from<br />
the -threat or use of force against the territorial<br />
integrity or political independence of any state.'<br />
I believe, Mr, Chairman, that it is necessary for<br />
us both to strive to live up to these obligations ourselves,<br />
and also to do what we can to secure their universal<br />
acceptance and application by all governments and regimes,<br />
whether or not they are members of the United Nations.<br />
For the Charter provides a code of international conduct<br />
which, if consistently accepted and honoured by all, would<br />
enable problems arising between states, including territorial<br />
disputes, to be settled justly and by peaceful means.<br />
I agree with your observation that methods of<br />
settling disputes peacefully have been improved, and<br />
with particular reference to territorial disputes that<br />
experience shows that peaceful means of settlement are<br />
feasible. The United Nations, despite its imperfections,<br />
has shown itself capable of useful work in this respect;<br />
and I believe that our best course lies in seeking to<br />
make it more effective both in performing its functions of<br />
mediation and conciliahion, and also in its peacekeeping<br />
activities. evo ./ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
" The first necessity is that member Stbates should<br />
fully accept and live up to the principles and obligations<br />
of the Charter. Then, it is essential, if the United Nations<br />
is to carry out its functions, that it should be on a sound<br />
financial footing, which means that all members should<br />
contribute their proper share of its expenses. Also it is<br />
clearly most desirable that meons of peaeeful settlement in<br />
accordance with the Charter shou. d be respected and observed:<br />
that when, for example, procedures of ascertainment of the<br />
wishes of the people of particular territories have taken<br />
place through the United Nations in accordance with the<br />
principle of self-determination, all members of the United<br />
Nations should accept and support the outcome of those<br />
procedures. The problem of territorial disputes is but one aspect<br />
of the wider problem of creating an international comnmunity<br />
that will learn to live in peace and without mutual interference,<br />
whether ideological or physical, and to settle its disputes<br />
by agreed peaceful procedures according to principles that must,<br />
if they are to have any real moaning, bo universally applicable<br />
to all. In this rospcct as I have said I cannot agree with<br />
the various exceptions to the principle of peaceful settlement<br />
that you appear to be stating in parts of your letter in<br />
suggesting that in certain cases the use of force is justified<br />
whilo in others it is not. Nor, incidentally can I accept your<br />
description of certain countries ( the Republics of Viot Nam,<br />
Korea and China) as being ' under foreign occupationt; nor, in<br />
the face of such problems as that of Germany and Berlin, your<br />
reference to the ? postwar settlements' as apparently being<br />
excluded from the realm of unresolved questions in international<br />
affairs. In conclusion, Mr. Chairman, I wish to reaffirm that<br />
the Australian Government accepts and will continue to abide<br />
by the principle of peaceful settlement of all disputes,<br />
including those arising out of territorial or border claims.<br />
I welcome the Soviet Governmentts apparent acceptance of the<br />
same view, and I hope that the Soviet Government will use its<br />
influence in all cases where border troubles are now causing<br />
tension, or may do so in future, towards a peaceful settlement,<br />
in accordance with the principles of the United Nations Charter<br />
and with accepted international procedures.<br />
Yours sincerely,<br />
( Sgd.) R. G. MENZIES<br />
Primo Minister<br />
His Excellency Nikita S. Khrushchev,<br />
Chairman of the Council of Ministers of<br />
the U. S. S. R.,<br />
MOSCOW. CANBERRA,<br />
1st March, 1964. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
