<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11071</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE                   HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   PRESS CONFERENCE                  PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA                                                  SUBJECTS: East Timor, Meeting with Habibie</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.......................................................................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I spoke to the Indonesian President Dr Habibie earlier this afternoon</p>
<p> and it was a very useful and candid discussion. I told him that Australia</p>
<p> respected very much the leadership he had taken earlier this year</p>
<p> in announcing a change of Indonesian Government policy regarding East</p>
<p> Timor, and that I was calling him as a friend and as the leader of</p>
<p> a country that had very close and friendly relations with Indonesia,</p>
<p> and that therefore because we have those friendly relations and against</p>
<p> the backdrop of those relations I could speak to him very openly and</p>
<p> very candidly in conveying the concern of the Australian Government,</p>
<p> and I am sure the concern of the Australian people about developments</p>
<p> in Timor.</p>
<p>I told him that I and the Australian Government were very deeply concerned</p>
<p> about recent developments in East Timor, particularly the recent killings.</p>
<p> I noted that we had called for restraint on all sides but I said that</p>
<p> there was a strong and inescapable impression in Australia that ABRI</p>
<p> had not done enough to discourage the violence and discourage the</p>
<p> killings. That ABRI had primary responsibility for maintaining security</p>
<p> in Indonesia and that quite plainly that responsibility in East Timor</p>
<p> had not been properly discharged.</p>
<p>I told him that the damage that could flow to Indonesia's international</p>
<p> reputation as a consequence of these developments was significant</p>
<p> and that it was important to us as a friend of Indonesia that that</p>
<p> damage not be aggravated.</p>
<p>In response the Indonesian President said that he appreciated my call</p>
<p> and he appreciated the frank way in which I had put the concerns of</p>
<p> the Australian Government. He shared my concern about the development</p>
<p> in Timor that he had taken action today in Jakarta to call upon those</p>
<p> involved to cease their acts of violence. He has given certain instructions</p>
<p> to the Indonesian Security Forces regarding that, and that he would</p>
<p> obviously be discussing the matter with his colleagues at a cabinet</p>
<p> meeting which he was about to join after our discussion had taken</p>
<p> place.</p>
<p>He confirmed the strong determination of the Indonesian Government</p>
<p> to go ahead with the UN sponsored consultation on autonomy for East</p>
<p> Timor and he reiterated that he saw a very important role for Australia</p>
<p> in this.</p>
<p>We both agreed that the direct and immediate discussion between us</p>
<p> in such a frank way has been very useful, and we agreed at my suggestion</p>
<p> that we should meet within the next week if possible - probably in</p>
<p> Bali - to further our discussions regarding this issue and I will</p>
<p> probably be accompanied by Mr Downer and Mr Moore. Mr Downer and the</p>
<p> Indonesian Foreign Minister, Mr Alitas are already beginning to make</p>
<p> arrangements. The meeting will take place as soon as possible. It</p>
<p> probably can't be before the weekend or early next week because</p>
<p> Mr Alitas will be attending a United Nations meeting in New York.</p>
<p> He will be leaving Jakarta to go to New York tomorrow.</p>
<p>The President readily agreed to my suggestion that we should meet</p>
<p> and further our discussion, and it will be an opportunity to emphasise</p>
<p> a number of things. To emphasise the concern that the Australian Government</p>
<p> feels about the situation in East Timor, and I don't want anybody</p>
<p> to be left in doubt, in any doubt we believe that the situation has</p>
<p> deteriorated sharply, and that is why I spoke as I did yesterday,</p>
<p> it is why I spoke to the Indonesian President today, and it is why</p>
<p> I propose that we meet as soon as possible to further discuss the</p>
<p> matter.</p>
<p>It is also an indication of course that the relationship between the</p>
<p> two countries remains , and I stress between the two countries, remains</p>
<p> very close, that there are obvious demands placed on a relationship</p>
<p> when public criticism is offered of the conduct of the armed forces</p>
<p> in one country by the leader of another country. But it is nonetheless</p>
<p> a very strong and durable relationship. We have been a good friend</p>
<p> of Indonesia's over the past year or two. We've supported</p>
<p> them economically, we've argued their case in the face of some</p>
<p> rather peremptory and insensitive responses from some who would have</p>
<p> sought to impose a more severe economic solution. I expressed to the</p>
<p> President today my feeling that Indonesia had been delivered a particularly</p>
<p> unfair and difficult international economic hand, and that Indonesia</p>
<p> had suffered more than she deserved as far as the economic downturn</p>
<p> was concerned.</p>
<p>I think that the opportunity that the meeting between us affords for</p>
<p> a furtherance of our discussion today is very important. Its an opportunity</p>
<p> for me to put very directly our concerns and discuss Indonesian responses,</p>
<p> recognising of course that Indonesia has sovereignty over East Timor,</p>
<p> that there is a commitment from the Indonesian Government that there</p>
<p> will be a proper act of self-determination. I have no doubt that Dr</p>
<p> Habibie remains very strongly committed to allowing that act of self-determination</p>
<p> to take place and he is very strongly committed to the consultation</p>
<p> process. Obviously that can't be achieved whilst the fighting</p>
<p> goes on and obviously the call that he has made today in Indonesia</p>
<p> for people to cease hostilities and to put aside their arms, is from</p>
<p> his point of view and earnest of his good intentions, and he does</p>
<p> intend to involve the International Red Cross in providing relief</p>
<p> work for people who have been caught up in the violence. The violence</p>
<p> has been ugly. There has been a very significant loss of life. They</p>
<p> are distressing developments. It's important that Australia play</p>
<p> a constructive role and as a close friend of Indonesia's, our</p>
<p> role surely is to speak frankly but fairly, to offer our counsel,</p>
<p> to offer our understanding but also as is appropriate in a close relationship</p>
<p> between two countries not to be reluctant to express a strong point</p>
<p> of view if the circumstances require it.</p>
<p>I would expect that we would meet sometime in the next week or ten</p>
<p> days, probably in Bali and that the arrangements would be made by</p>
<p> Mr Downer and Mr Alitas. I will be accompanied on that visit by both</p>
<p> the Foreign Minister and the Defence Minister.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did you specifically ask Dr Habibie about disarming these militias</p>
<p> and if so, did he respond?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>He indicated that he was taking steps to get everybody involved, I</p>
<p> think the best way I can paraphrase his response, to put aside their</p>
<p> arms.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well let me put it this way, there was no serious difference between</p>
<p> us during the discussion.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Given the role of ABRI in this, would you hope or expect that General</p>
<p> Wiranto would also take part in the talks as Defence Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that is a matter for Dr Habibie. It is not for me to say who</p>
<p> should comprise his party in the meeting. But the fact that I will</p>
<p> be taking our Defence Minister probably indicates that the same could</p>
<p> well be the case on the Indonesian side. But I can't say who</p>
<p> is going in the party.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you confident that Dr Habibie has genuine control of the Indonesian</p>
<p> Armed Forces?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Dr Habibie has as the political head of that country has ultimate</p>
<p> responsibility and clearly my remarks of yesterday and today indicate</p>
<p> that I am unhappy, the Government is unhappy, with the behaviour of</p>
<p> ABRI and there's been a clear transmission of our view that ABRI</p>
<p> must accept responsibility for the aggregate security of Indonesia</p>
<p> including of course the security situation in East Timor and Dr Habibie</p>
<p> certainly today made it very plain that he was unhappy with the situation</p>
<p> in East Timor and he recognised and understood our concern.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What inference should we draw from the fact that you are taking the</p>
<p> Defence Minister with you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No inference other than that is entirely appropriate, that on a meeting</p>
<p> like this you have available to you all the relevant ministers who</p>
<p> may be helpful.</p>
<p>JOUNRALIST:</p>
<p>What do you hope to practically achieve at the meeting with Dr Habibie?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The most important thing is an opportunity to underline the concern</p>
<p> we have about what is happening. The fact that we are concerned but</p>
<p> we're also a friend, that this is a very difficult time for Indonesia.</p>
<p> It's a particularly difficult time for the people of East Timor.</p>
<p> This is our part of the world. We are seen by the rest of the world</p>
<p> as having a particular involvement in this part of the world and it</p>
<p> would be very strange indeed in a situation which has clearly deteriorated</p>
<p> if the Prime Minister of Australia and the President of Indonesia,</p>
<p> given the long history of relations between the two countries, were</p>
<p> not to meet and to have a discussion about it. I would hope that I</p>
<p> would be able to drive home to, or put as strongly as possible to,</p>
<p> the Indonesian Government the concerns that we have. I would hope</p>
<p> that out of the meeting there would be an unmistakable and unambiguous</p>
<p> understanding of how we feel, but also we would be transmitting that</p>
<p> feeling against a background of being a friend - not necessarily an</p>
<p> uncritical friend - but a friend of Indonesia's. And it is still</p>
<p> very much in the short, medium and long-term interests of Australia</p>
<p> that we maintain a frank and open and close relationship with Indonesia.</p>
<p> We have been able to achieve that...or preserve that through some</p>
<p> very difficult times over the last few years, and it would be a very</p>
<p> strange Australian government at this difficult time that did not</p>
<p> see it appropriate for the Australian Prime Minister and the Indonesian</p>
<p> President to meet and talk about these things which are of such direct</p>
<p> relevance to both countries and to our region.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Have you been talking to other countries trying to get them to apply</p>
<p> pressure on Indonesia to restrain ABRI?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well let me say this, the only country I've spoken to today has</p>
<p> been Indonesia. I don't rule out some contact with representatives</p>
<p> of other countries either by myself, or more particularly by the Foreign</p>
<p> Minister. But we're not involved in some kind of international</p>
<p> ganging up. We're involved in a process of putting our view as</p>
<p> a close neighbour and a friend and a nation that has developed a particular</p>
<p> and very positive relationship with Indonesia, but also a country</p>
<p> that's very concerned about the deteriorating situation in East</p>
<p> Timor and the damage it is inflicting obviously on the people of East</p>
<p> Timor, the damage it's inflicting on Indonesia's international</p>
<p> reputation. And also, out of a natural concern to make a positive</p>
<p> contribution.</p>
<p>JOUNRALIST:</p>
<p>Did you put directly to Dr Habibie that you believe that ABRI has</p>
<p> been arming the militias within East Timor?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The words I used, as best I can paraphrase them, is that there was</p>
<p> an unmistakable impression in Australia that ABRI was turning a blind</p>
<p> eye. I didn't specifically use the words that you have just used,</p>
<p> but to use the same expression again there was an unmistakable conveying</p>
<p> in my conversation of the concern that I have about the role of ABRI.</p>
<p> I mean I don't think we should sort of get hung up on a semantic</p>
<p> debate about how you describe the role. Clearly the role has not been</p>
<p> satisfactory when you put it that way and the Australian Government</p>
<p> is unhappy with it and that is why I said what I did yesterday and</p>
<p> it's why I spoke to him today, and it's why I proposed to</p>
<p> continue the discussion at our meeting.</p>
<p>JOUNRALIST:</p>
<p>...the Australian and Indonesian defence forces which have been</p>
<p> close, any way that can be used positively in East Timor?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>In a situation like this Dennis I think you would use all contacts</p>
<p> to urge restraint, to urge moderation. You've got to remember</p>
<p> that ABRI is quite a large organisation and there are some signs of</p>
<p> dis-aggregation in the command structure and therefore you can't</p>
<p> always assume that everything that happens in the name of ABRI in</p>
<p> certain parts of Indonesia is necessarily at the direct behest or</p>
<p> the direction of the central authority. Now that is a matter for Indonesia</p>
<p> and that's the responsibility of Indonesia. But we are willing</p>
<p> to use all of the contacts that we have at different levels to convey</p>
<p> our concern and to urge a change. I do want to make the point that</p>
<p> Dr Habibie did show a great deal of leadership in changing Indonesian</p>
<p> policy on Timor. He was not without his critics domestically in his</p>
<p> own country when he changed that policy. He deserves credit, he deserves</p>
<p> a lot of credit for that and he deserves respect for the leadership</p>
<p> that he showed on that issue, and I'm sure that he remains very</p>
<p> sincere about the act of choice, or self-determination, or whatever</p>
<p> you want to call it. The involvement of the United Nations, the involvement</p>
<p> of Australia and other countries in the supervisory process under</p>
<p> the egis of the United Nations. He's very committed to that.</p>
<p> In all of it I think it's important. Although we have a lot of</p>
<p> concern about what has happened over the last 48 hours, it is very</p>
<p> important that we recognise, given the history and the background</p>
<p> of Indonesia's relationship with Timor, just how significant</p>
<p> were his actions earlier this year in changing his Government's</p>
<p> policy.</p>
<p>JOUNRALIST:</p>
<p>Did you get any sense today that the President was unhappy with or</p>
<p> frustrated by the actions of ABRI? You've expressed Australia's</p>
<p> unhappiness. Did we meet that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we spoke for about 20 minutes or so on the phone, 15 or 20 minutes.</p>
<p> I put my concerns, he responded. I've tried to describe his response</p>
<p> and we've agreed to meet. The fact that he has agreed to meet</p>
<p> me indicates that he understands our concern and that he sees it as</p>
<p> something that is very important, I don't know that I ought to</p>
<p> try and parse and analyse the every nuance of his response.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Given your concerns over what is happening with ABRI, would you support</p>
<p> an outside supervisory force moving into East Timor?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, look, Indonesia has sovereignty over East Timor and sovereignty</p>
<p> carries both authority and responsibility. And the point that I emphasise</p>
<p> in these matters is that when you have sovereignty and you have the</p>
<p> authority that goes with sovereignty you also have the responsibility</p>
<p> that goes with sovereigny. I think it's quite counter- productive</p>
<p> to be talking about substitute outside supervisory forces at this</p>
<p> time.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>...pro-integrationist forces can't be disarmed or can't</p>
<p> be brought under control then can Australian afford to sit by and</p>
<p> watch a slaughter.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I, look you know, the worst thing to do in a situation like this</p>
<p> is to respond in a knee-jerk way to every hypothesis. And one thing</p>
<p> at a time. We're going to have a discussion and there are Australian</p>
<p> interests, there are world interests, there are regional interests</p>
<p> and there are bilateral interests in this situation. Naturally the</p>
<p> Australian interest is best met by my putting our view very directly</p>
<p> which I've done, talking to the Indonesian President. I'm</p>
<p> not going to make this country or any of the resources of this country</p>
<p> willy-nilly hostile to a particular outcome. I think it is very important</p>
<p> that countries measure their responses and work out in advance what</p>
<p> their capacity is to influence events if the course of action they're</p>
<p> currently following doesn't work. I don't think it's</p>
<p> a good idea to sort of telegraph in advance on a "what if"</p>
<p> kind of scenario what you may or may not do. Two more questions on</p>
<p> this. Well, I  I'm sorry  I haven't had one</p>
<p> from you, no.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Just to clarify Prime Minister, could you just clarify for us, did</p>
<p> Dr Habibie acknowledge that ABRI was or may have been complicit in</p>
<p> the events of the weekend?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>He did not dissent from the view that I put. I want you to understand</p>
<p> what I'm saying.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>(inaudible) whether he acknowledged....?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, well, I mean, please, it's not appropriate that any words</p>
<p> be put into his mouth or mine on an issue such as this. I put a point</p>
<p> of view and his response essentially was well I appreciate the candour</p>
<p> with which you have expressed your view.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>And he didn't directly give you his view about that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't intend to say any more than that. I don't</p>
<p> think it is appropriate or helpful.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, how soon now do you think that it will be possible</p>
<p> to have civilian UN personnel on the ground in Timor given the deal</p>
<p> that's on the table in New York later this week.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Very difficult given what has happened in the last forty-eight hours</p>
<p> for me to give a helpful response at the moment to that  I don't</p>
<p> know.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What do you think these events have done to the timetable for....?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's too early to make that judgement. They've obviously</p>
<p> not helped the timetable, but can I say again that Dr Habibie was</p>
<p> insistent today about his commitment to the UN involvement and the</p>
<p> process. He really sounded to me very committed to it and a person</p>
<p> who is quite prepared to work very hard and very strenuously to bring</p>
<p> it about.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What did Senator Tierney mean this morning when he said that the Government</p>
<p> was still discussing the tax scale and I think at the end of</p>
<p> the day we're going to end up with a much fairer package'.</p>
<p> Is he saying that the package is going to changed to be much fairer?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the Government hasn't been discussing the scales, it's</p>
<p> a very fair package. The Government's position was made very</p>
<p> plain yesterday on television by me and it's been made very plain</p>
<p> by the Treasurer in an article in a newspaper this morning and our</p>
<p> position remains that the Senate processes  I haven't seen</p>
<p> their latest offering because I've been at other meetings this</p>
<p> afternoon  is it out yet? No. Our position is that no indentation</p>
<p> of consequence has been made in the package through the Senate processes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>(inaudible) saying it could be made much fairer?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's a very fair package and people from time to time express</p>
<p> their point of view in a free party. We're not a gathering of</p>
<p> Stalinists.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, you talked about fine-tuning yesterday. Could you elaborate</p>
<p> in what area or areas you see a possibility of such fine-tuning?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Would compensation be fine-tuning?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Our position is as I've described it and I'm not going to</p>
<p> be further drawn, I'm not going to further speculate. It is a</p>
<p> fair package, I've always said that. We're not going to</p>
<p> alter the essential thrust, we're not taking out food. I've</p>
<p> never ruled out fine-tuning, you're not going to start getting</p>
<p> me speculating, hypothesising, musing, ruminating, or anything else</p>
<p> of that kind in any other way.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
