<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>343</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRLIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION DINNER, SYDNEY - 12TH JULY 1961 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000343_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
theh ~ iis 12" m 1th e R-t. don<br />
SirYou GrcegChief Justioe, Your œ xaellency and laies and<br />
I think this is orbeof thoe. occasions when,, as an ertirely<br />
lofl-oontntiouls person ( Ldaughter-) devoted to nothing more dopl; 3y then<br />
to a quiet life, I ought to make a few points about some of the<br />
people who are sitting at Lho top table* ( I'll say something, about<br />
or,, 4hite later on and I hasten to say entirely In his fa. votxr)<br />
( Laughter) But I do want to tell you ws crts of~ the charnel-house<br />
knowing that tiny won't io a" y Aurther. ( LaughterJ<br />
dhe. I accepted my Invitation to cam ho: e the fish at<br />
last A--4 you know I did so under the f'ir Impression1 that,, like<br />
so mayof you I would wear . a nice soft shirt and black tie and be at<br />
home &amp; nd comfortable. Then Mr, President forzston niaid nio no,<br />
Reialorcad concrete is the order of the day". ( Laughter)' I<br />
protested und my secretary protested and the President ive all the<br />
initation that a man of his typ~ e can of being the injured innocents<br />
" kit xW dear fellow, Sir you kriov, we can't, you know.. 3o .1<br />
devoted, or rather my wil. did, U l1a&amp; theo r this a eraiuoa to<br />
, dotting to o:. cased in ooncrete. Arid when I arived 4areo t~ on-ight and<br />
met Yaorton 1 rapped hiu on z-hu chtilf and&amp; I said 111? y dear bay you<br />
are ieurinj a sami-stifi shirt". ( Laughter,, ajptfalse)<br />
1Ito ofours. delighted I don't need to tell you to<br />
arrive here tonight and see ' Uis 4ruce the Archibishop. kno there<br />
is rjthing that urings sjah balm to he spirit of a man ohto is<br />
occ; Asij! nally In trouable hiias&amp; f ( Lau. ghter) Well I don't need to<br />
finish my : sentence do 11 Therefore i want to ; a~ y to Aj ruce the<br />
. irohisbop " Thank you, 3' 4r thank you fbe hauIin been 30 onfsiderate<br />
to ai mere Presbytei-ian, M. brins the union of the Chirches closer<br />
and closer and closer." W ( Lau ghter) ( Applause)<br />
Mind you Sir this Is not as irrelevunt. as you rway think<br />
beciano after all the ohject of this magnificent associ itI ~ ri Is unity,<br />
bringing us topther. aid I tell you that I ifouldn't be a tit<br />
O sP. raerpsbriybteedr iaanf teCrh urthchis , g ettoti nfg'i ndto atheeth e4rh urchI ' voer nAlon ldaozudb t untod tthtee enormous<br />
advtaU;_ of the ? resbyterian Church. G'-auehter) Juit anyhow we shall<br />
see0 Then, of course, i have a particular pleasure In seeing here<br />
a nan whom I may almost regard by nov asi an old friend -the very<br />
disting~ ished Chief Justice of the Uited 3tates. ( Applause) 11e and<br />
I have you will be surprised to know a certain amount in comn<br />
because some years back we rlew together from Washington to [ allas,<br />
You tier. then, Sir* Joyornor of California, a tremndous dignitary and<br />
you rers oin., to a 3over ors' OCPnfereiiao 4 art t ne~ t ca other<br />
and you vw re :' rightftli kind to me. I was deli.; hted, of ( xtrseq to<br />
aee At that tim you, hav; ing been u lawyor, had tjOMQo a<br />
deplorable politician and I, havine. been. a lavyer had Inecam a<br />
deplorable politician. You havre the advantae of we beaine having<br />
beom* a deplorable politician you rnot long theroaftor revert od to<br />
your leial character ( Laughter) &amp; uid became u distingiisied Oxief<br />
Justice something that thw e aJ profession in : tuzstr&amp;. tAi is<br />
delighted to know Al11 never hiappen to me. (.:. au,; hterJ<br />
fou know I can't InuAine a happier conjunction of the<br />
plansts tian that Chief Justice 4arra should be here In kw 4alia,<br />
not only because there is a great legal ooiiVertian but bec use there<br />
is this 25th birthday party of tie Australian-Arwerican ' ssociz tion.<br />
I have had the great opportunity and pleasure, now,, year by year, of </p>
<p>eating at the expense of the Supreme Court of the United State s<br />
havnA unch iith the Justices, may of them very great and lose<br />
frinii ofmine and if i my say so Chief justice, nobody waud<br />
axwoIfy in h Masell,* more than YOU do, all the qualities that we In<br />
Australia think that w share with the United -ta tes of Amrica.<br />
( Applause) As a matter of fact he oo4d pass ctf an an W~ stwellian.<br />
rook at hsm6 dhat a wonderful leader of the Opposition he vould<br />
make&amp; ( Laughter) Sir, as couldn' t be more delighted taan ' in . re to<br />
see you here. AmV I know that it is the fashion to make speIvas on these<br />
occasions in which all Is sweetness and light. All we fL-Ai t-o do is<br />
to have a jolly gpod dinner* reaffirm our belief that we are exactly<br />
the same as each other and po awy in a slightly mellow ' inse of<br />
sentlmnt. 1 don't tink that is quite true. I huve bermn reminded<br />
b~ V -tz. Yorstcui that I1 have, on quit* a few occusiorks spok. on to the<br />
Anoriokn.. Autrallan ;. 4so01dtiun in Nov Ytork first 01' all imder my<br />
frind ktobinss as Chairmant and then und.. r œ he auspices of that<br />
taciturn friend of ours, Floyd Mli. And the only tim T ever omild<br />
get Wing eff.-ctively was when Danny Weay was kind enaugh to em. w<br />
Fro the mo~ ont I stood up he Interjaoted and -is had a aonfliet in<br />
ihich I was so tolerably suossst-iJ. that he offurad ne a pisos in his<br />
troupe. ( Laughter) B3ut there is a disposition to believe that thie 3ritishq the<br />
Ameriftnsp thte Aastralians, the &amp;' ev4" ~ aandw-s vloever taey may be,<br />
are bound to think the hae wy tweause they, uody speak then same<br />
lan eaap. There are certaink dialectical difleranoes and certain<br />
dl ftoiveces of dialect. Jut at; an rate, yes,, undersatand each<br />
othar; we understand what the other mans is sain&amp;. ier'iaps V~ at Is<br />
one o5 our dangers. It is easier to quaarrel with one -ithor : in a<br />
ooimn~* languaip thun It Is to quarrel through an intarpretaro<br />
( Applause) I know th; at b*,-ause I had an hour a~ nd a quarter with<br />
Khra4shchev lcsz Rovember In Saw York and we ha4 an Interpreter and<br />
we v'! re almost Imater" at the end of the tim. kkat that was because<br />
the Interpreter took the crackle out of It, kJt of course you am<br />
quarrel readily with people in your own langua gi; and of cnirse wie<br />
have differences. The grea test thing that any '. ustraiian--i-~ -rican<br />
Association, or American-. Autralian Assoclation, or Azaglom'werican<br />
Association, has to discover and to preach is that we have masses of<br />
differenoes* Your job * and my job and the job of every other person<br />
of Sood wll and intelligence, is to bridle the difforeaoes, to ake<br />
t'Veu Intelligible on eaOh side*<br />
It is quite foolish for people to saf as 1 have Ieard then<br />
saY " at of course we are bound to be friends becaiuse oa have the<br />
samae system of Jovernment, . e haven't. Oe have utterly different<br />
systems of jovrret. They say we must be friends because we have<br />
the sawe history. Well. up to a point, we had the same history; up<br />
to thew late part of the 18th oentury we had the samte history4 hut It<br />
then becme a little abruptly divided into two streams. it do we<br />
have the system of' Jovornmentt<br />
I rind that I have had an iwense experieonce aov r f these<br />
things around the world, and I also find that so many peopies for<br />
example in Oreat BrItain, don't understayid thut vhat a . oaretary of<br />
in' tatthee mpasyr esasye et oo af tChoen gPrreessssi, o natsl nCootc mtoit tebee tuankdeenr acsr osths-ee xraiinnaal~ tviioenw<br />
of the Governument of the United States. Weg don' t have this kind of<br />
thing. w not suimoned beftre Cmittees. and put on oath d told to<br />
explain to them bow y mind Is working. Dear me,, tha, vouild be a<br />
tasks wouldn't itT That would be to explore the 4nknown with a<br />
venommnee 46 wait, under our system, until im have had discussions<br />
in &amp; bine-t and then we announoe to some appropriate vehicle whiat the<br />
polfi7 is.. But in the United States the whole business -I not<br />
quarrelling about this; this is a system that thwy havre dovised and<br />
that they understand -is to have these things thrashed outp to have<br />
a man ao before a Comittee, to have him unsver, to have his, If you<br />
likes think aloud about it* </p>
<p>Ultimately bF this process, vbhich, frm the point of viev<br />
of ow AMrican friends Is a superlatively ceoratic onat of<br />
thrashing out pol icy, the result emrips and that Is dootrine fr the<br />
United States. And Indods v4hen It amerjes, hov many times it has<br />
beena so wonderful for the world* But under our system things are<br />
done diff) rently. that is why when~ I an in Angland and I meet some<br />
man idhm I know, soas W&amp; mit aed man, 9 he will soy to me * Did<br />
you see what aoamidn utsh o r day In America? to. i kn o<br />
can't trust those, fellovo. Heally that's too ridiculous old boy.<br />
And Ttv to say " jut that is not his finalvword** I havebhad to<br />
explain once or tvice Chief Justice, and I hope you will c, 3nfimu my<br />
recollection on this, that If a 3earetary of State for exa--pl* is up<br />
boebre a CnwItte. and somebody pruts a question and he says ' Wll,<br />
perhapov I thin2k ythat might be the answer to thatst the<br />
gontlemima from Vw Ndcahoma walumderbus' writes that doun and whIps<br />
It outs that's In line vkh his policy. Ten mits later the man<br />
b . fbrci the Comittee may be saying exoa tly the opposite -Is we all<br />
do ewin we are thinking to oursolves and this produces in the other<br />
parts of the &amp; igiish. speaing world u~ sort of confusion bocause we<br />
just don't understa-or most of us don't. that we are dealing with<br />
a differe* nt system of ( Ioverninnto<br />
Now I do beg of all Australians, and of all z; hgl sh-5Man to<br />
understand that the diffrerences in syatms of ; Iovor o : t can sasil<br />
give rise to hostiles. where none ne" edmr at uli. 4ocaiuse of<br />
all this I have had friends in the United : 3tatesq In 1asAIlgtcn wo<br />
having read the remarks judo by a prominent private somber of tVW<br />
House of Commns say OAh, that is what they iire thinking'. Whereas<br />
of course,, if I mziy speak as an export as a~ former Leado.-of the<br />
Opposition, what a member of the Opposition Was isn't vht the people<br />
are ti-inking at all. ( Laughter, applause)<br />
$ up SIr really what I want to smy to you ins let -as<br />
recolpise our &amp; tfI~ erencs iet usovercome our diffe.-anose so that<br />
the restating ste gill be al th grae. Jcauseunes<br />
b,, tien the " Juited States and rho rest of our world, there ine<br />
undarstariding, a knoviedse of differonces, a villingness to overom<br />
them$ a ooncentration upon all the .; roat matters of unity, unless<br />
this happens nobody will be atte. ading the 50th Anniversary of this<br />
A" ssoo ition. Let us make no mistake about it. 4e are In a -mtld in which<br />
all the forces that are hostile to our way of living are on the march,<br />
They will never be not and defeated bF disunited peoplu. Jo. imr was<br />
ever , on by disuni~ ted foroes, it Is our groat moral respxisibllity,,<br />
not to be too clover, but to be unilted, to Ot topther, to say ' We<br />
most ' 11u-e unity we must undorstand our areat urmoe". -And our<br />
peat puarpose, sir, Is not one of ag rndsoment ( Jod kcnows it has<br />
nothing to do with agprandisoemt our groat pirpose is to be<br />
allowied to live as vs now live , as you now live In your country, freely,<br />
happily* or unhappily, but to live ourz own lives. This is t great<br />
Ii* In the wrd. And 1 would abandon proposition afteropasition,<br />
myself I would concede point after point In ai disssion,<br />
so Ion~ as I felt œ hat at the ultimate point we, and the inited<br />
3ta tere# all the L'Oaflishmspoaking free, people around the 4orld, were<br />
at ,~.( Applaue Sir$ the last thinj I want to say is this. This<br />
Ass~ iation was established 25 years a~ p by m~ y Wrend itog a<br />
man of enormous integrity of character and driving ability and<br />
enthusiasm* ( Applause) I an perfeatly certain that when it bopn in<br />
thoe days before the ~ ar, wen the United States didn't irnov so much<br />
about us mid., to tell the truth we didn't know so nuch about the<br />
United States -when it belan in 1936 1 am sure, that -9 hite was<br />
sustained by his enthusiasm rather than by any cocrete -opeo He<br />
has seen It pro-imr, during the war, something that made sich an<br />
enormus difference to our relationships with the United -J1tates<br />
postwar* where we find ourselves almost an favourite, neplawso I thiz* </p>
<p>that is true in the Amerioan ind. And as you look baoN' omr<br />
years of this I am sure that you, liko se, wiii &amp; Lv. immnee credit<br />
to the man whose imagination foundbd it, and whose ability -zid iriwo<br />
urougbt It on into its zatarity. ( A1ppla-Ase)<br />
You are now 1going to here Mr. ",: mbassador !* bald and Ohn you<br />
have liard him tw Is ur man tell vorth listening to, thioni rith his<br />
peraission I ; WtI stand up a second time and ive you the toast of<br />
the Issoci4tion. ( Applause) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
