<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6370</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, NINETEENTH NATIONAL HOUSING CONVENTION, THE SIR PHILLIP LYNCH AWARD FOR OUTSTANDING SERVICE TO THE HOUSING INDUSTRY, ADELAIDE, 14 APRIL 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/04/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006370.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHEC AGANSTDEULNITERIYLE M1B0A RAG. OME. D<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME M4INISTER<br />
NINETEENTH NATIONAL HOUSING CONVENTION<br />
THE SIR PHILLIP LYNCH AWARD FOR<br />
OUTSTANDING SERVICE TO THE HOUS ING INDUSTRY<br />
ADELAIDE 14 APRIL 1984<br />
Mr President, Distinguished Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
Whilst Sir Phillip and I may have somewhat differing<br />
political views, I hold him in high regard and am saddened<br />
that he is so unwell. I deem it both a pleasure and a<br />
privilege to act on his behalf in the presentation of the<br />
Award which bears his name.<br />
This year the Award is to'be presented to a man who has<br />
devoted 34 years of-service to home seekers and to the home<br />
building industry through his work in the building society<br />
movement in New South Wales, and both nationally and<br />
internationally. Today he is Managing Director of one of Australia's largest<br />
Permanent Building Societies. In this capacity, he has been<br />
responsible for many financial innovations that have helped<br />
home seekers to home ownership, and by this means he has<br />
also helped New South Wales builders to build more homes. I<br />
am, of course, referring to Jim Wills, A. M.<br />
Jim pioneered flexibility in lending for housing in New<br />
South Wales.<br />
He developed the Joint Income Scheme; he made tangible<br />
inroads into discrimination against women and lone parents<br />
in the criteria for home lending; he was one of the leaders<br />
who led the way for high ratio loans to assist young couples<br />
to bridge the deposit gap; and he was responsible, more<br />
recently, for the development and introduction of the<br />
Deferred Interest Scheme, to help young couple's cope with<br />
higher interest rates and attain home ownership..<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY </p>
<p>2.<br />
Jim has served the industry in various capacities. He is a<br />
Past President of the Building Societies Institute of New<br />
South Wales; Past President of the Australian Association of<br />
Permanent Building Socities Advisory Committee to the New<br />
South Wales State Government; a member of the Financial<br />
Advisory Committee of the AAPBS; a member of the<br />
International Union of Building Societies and Savings<br />
Associations; and was Chairman of the International School<br />
in Australia in 1979.<br />
I would single out Jim's role in securing the prestigious<br />
International School for Australia in 1979.<br />
That event brought international recognition of the efforts<br />
of the industry in Australia in the field of housing finance<br />
and development. A recognition well deserved!<br />
Jim Wills has been, and still is, a strong and innovative<br />
leader in an industry which is vital to those in need of<br />
housing, and to those who build homes. Many families who<br />
now have homes owe their ability to finance t * hem to his<br />
leadership in pioneering flexible home lending practices.<br />
The effects of this leadership do not remain just with the<br />
families who have been helped. The whole fabric of society<br />
has benefited by such leadership and the economic benefits<br />
to the broader community have been of major significance.<br />
Many industry and government leaders who have witnessed Mr<br />
Wills' tireless efforts over a long period of distinguished<br />
service, believe that he is richly deserving of the 1984<br />
Award. I congratulate him on his many outstanding achievements<br />
within the Housing Industry, and on behalf of Sir Phillip<br />
Lynch I now ask Mr Wills to come forward and accept the<br />
Award. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
