<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>404</transcript-id>
    <title>NO.2 TV RECORDING: - &quot;TALK TO THE NATION&quot; BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES 23RD NOVEMBER, 1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/11/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000404_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
2-TV RECORLDI: ~ LU~ PR~ k~ E 23RD ANOVE1v1BER0 196-1 ñ L~~ E'Z<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I'm going to talk to you for a few minutes about the<br />
development of Australia. I'm sorry if, standing here, I appear<br />
to be rather of a school master about to give you a lecture--I<br />
even have a sort of cane in my hand but there is a map and I<br />
;;! ant to point a few things out to you on tile map.<br />
But bernre I do that I just want to say this: the<br />
business a Commonwealth Government is overwhelmingly to do<br />
what it cal. to develop the country. If there is one thing that<br />
we look back on with some satisfaction over the last ten years,<br />
twelve years, it is the enormous growth of Australia, the<br />
development of its resources. If there is one thing that we<br />
put before you as our policy, it is to continue that<br />
development to the greatest possible degree.<br />
And in order to do that you don't want. to have a<br />
Government that says " let it be done". You must have a<br />
Commonwealth Government that knows that it wants to help to get<br />
certain great things done; you want State Governments willi~ ng<br />
and able to co-operate in the getting of them done and some<br />
enormous work has been done in 0the States and in the thira<br />
place you want to have a proper co-operation with large private<br />
enterprise. I'll point that out to you in a moment on the map<br />
when I refer to the railways project in Wiestern Australia, or<br />
the Mount Isa railway project in Queensland. All three parties<br />
must work together. They must have a co-operative spirit, and<br />
they must have a clear idea in their minds of what it is they<br />
want to do. Now we've been in office, as you know, for 12 ypars,<br />
and in the course of that time tremendous things have been going<br />
on in Australia. I'm going to mention one or two of them to<br />
you by pointing them out or pointing their location out on<br />
the map. And in particular I want to refer to a few of them to<br />
which we have directed attention quite in the last few months.<br />
Now let me just look at the map and point out one or<br />
two things to you. I'm not going to pretend to exhaust the<br />
list because time would not permit that, but there are a few<br />
things here that weren't here a few years ago.<br />
Down here in Victoria for example you see the railway<br />
line running down to Melbourne. The unification of the'railway<br />
line from Wodonga to Melbourne is a work of tremendous<br />
importance: it means that you will have a standard gauge<br />
railway available for great traffic from Sydney to Melbourne.<br />
And of course there is already a standard gauge one that runs<br />
up to Brisbane. Down here in this corner is Tasmania. Tasmania always<br />
had a tremendous problem of shipping, because of course, it<br />
depends on shipping. It has no land transport, obviously, to<br />
the mainland: it needs shipping. And f~ or many years it relied<br />
on a subsidised ship, plus rather uncertain shipping services<br />
from other sources. dJe have, ourselves, in the last few years,<br />
had built and put on to the run to Tasmania the Princess of-<br />
Tasmania, a tremendous boon particularly to the Tasmanian<br />
tourist traffic; the Bass ñ 1rader the roll-on roll-off ship<br />
which greatly facilitates the handling of cargo; and we have<br />
already had, in the last few months, a little to do with<br />
roviding a new cattle ship for King Island. So that the<br />
transport problem of Tasmania has been, in a large measure,<br />
solve a, in the last few years. </p>
<p>Another great problem that confronted us was the<br />
problem of developing our exports, This is vital to Australia.<br />
And we have looked at all these proposals that come up from the<br />
States, largely in the light of whethtr they will develop export<br />
business and improve our international, and therefore our local,<br />
financial position. And so, in the last few months, we have<br />
made arrangements with the Government of New South W4ales under<br />
which we make available substantial financial assistance for<br />
improving the coal ports in Newcastle, Sydney in Balmain in<br />
fact and in Port Kembla; and also an arrangement with the<br />
Government of Queensland in relation to the port of Gladstone.<br />
Now all of these ports, the new facilities that will exist in<br />
them, will give an increasing export trade in coal and how<br />
important that is you will perhaps remember when I tell you, or<br />
remind you, that when we came into office Australia was<br />
importing coal. Today we are exporting it in large and growring<br />
quantities. ) ii search has gone on, of course, and those engaged<br />
in it are optimistic about ultimate results, here, and over in<br />
the dest and around he-. e. And, well all I need say is that we<br />
have some hope on this matter. But a great deal. of work haq<br />
been done, and great financial encouragement has been given by<br />
the Government of the Commonwealth.<br />
Up here in Queenslanud is the major wfork the<br />
reconstruction of the railway line from Mount Isa down to<br />
Townsville arid Collinsville. Now that is a veizy big undertaking.<br />
My Government has agreed by a contract signed only a<br />
few months ago, to find œ C20m. of the initial cost of this line<br />
for the Government of Queensland. The effect of the line will<br />
be to make it possible indeed to make it certain that the<br />
Mount Isa mine will become probably the greatest copper mine in<br />
the world! The Company itself will spend scores of millions of<br />
pounds; and the result will be to add, I believe scores of<br />
millions of pounds to the export income of Australia.<br />
Now I won't take time about Weipa and bauxite because<br />
they go back a few years, although they are now in the process<br />
of development. But up here we have, in the last few months, provided<br />
money for the Government of Queensland to encourage the building<br />
of beef roads, that is to say roads that will enable beef cattle<br />
to come off in better condtion, and thereby add to our export<br />
income. The same is true in the Northern Territory, where, of<br />
course, in addition, as you know, we have these great deposits<br />
of bauxite and the already substantially worked deposits of<br />
uranium in Rum Jungle.<br />
In the '. est up in the north we have found millions<br />
ourselves for the development of the Kimberleys; and quite<br />
recently more money for beef roads to take cattle into Wyndham,<br />
Down here, the great scheme, a scheme that will cost<br />
Governments œ C+ 2m. and the steel company at least as much the<br />
great scheme of unifying the gauge from Kalgoorlie doi-mL<br />
Kwinana, enabling iron ore deposits of great magnitude to be<br />
worked in Koolyanobbing, and a new iron and steel industry in<br />
Western Australia, something that will revolutionise that State.<br />
These things have been discussed, and agreed upon, and put into<br />
motion in the last few months.<br />
In South Australia you may see, perhaps, the line of<br />
the Murray the great problem, I believe, in South Australia is<br />
the problem of water. And although the Snowy Scheme on which un<br />
spend so much every year has, I believe assisted the supply of<br />
water in the Murray, we now have under Aiscussion with New </p>
<p>South ' 4ales, Victoria and South Australia a new dam about here1<br />
at a place called Chowilla. And in relahoh to that which il<br />
it goes on, and I believe it will, will be the biggest water<br />
storage in Australia we, the Commonwealth Government, have<br />
found, or will promise to find, a quarter of the estimated cost<br />
just as we found a quarter of the cost in the case of the<br />
H-ume dam and other works on the Murray.<br />
Now that just gives you a sort of broad conspectus of<br />
it. But there is a vary interesting aspect of it that I want tc<br />
point out to you. My opponent, Mr. Calwell who, I must say has<br />
an admirable faculty for coining a phrase every now and then,<br />
likes to refer to-my Government and I suppose to me as<br />
" tired an'. lazy". d~ ell I think that one is entitled occasionall~ y<br />
to be tireu, but laziness is not something that I am accustomed<br />
to being accused o. L,<br />
Anyhow he says this is a tired and lazy governmlent<br />
and it's t~ me you had a change. And here is the point that<br />
want to make: In the last three months of this Parliament this<br />
" tired and lazy" Govcr~ ment, instad of deferring works so that<br />
it could promise them in a Policy Speech, got vith the job<br />
negotiated with Queensland, negotiated with New South -dales,<br />
negotiated with South Australia, negotiated with -Jestern<br />
Australia. And the result is that in these last few months of<br />
this Parliament we have put in hand, so that they will go<br />
roaring along for the next three years at leas the works on<br />
the coal ports, the Mount Isa Railway scheme the great iron r. nd<br />
steel and railway and iron ore scheme in destern Australia the<br />
dieselisation of certain railway lines in the State of South<br />
Australia, the preliminary discussions on the technical level<br />
for the great new dam at Chowilla, let's see, yes, the beef<br />
roads up here, the beef roads in Queensland. I could, perhaps,<br />
if I had time talk about half a dozen matters which, literally,<br />
have been brought to their final stage of preparation, to the<br />
stage of agreement, to a stage where the financial arrangemen+ s<br />
are made and the work can be put in hand, all in the last three<br />
or four months. I hope you will allow me to say that even a Government<br />
that wasn't " tired and lazy" might be hard put to it to be<br />
brisker than that, or to achieve so much as that in so limited a<br />
time. But the work must go on that's the great point. And I<br />
don't believe, do you, that it can go on unless you have a<br />
feeling of co-operation, a feeling of confidence between the<br />
Commonwealth and State authorities, between the 6ommonwealth and<br />
the local authorities and the great private enterprises which<br />
have so much to contribute to the development of Australia,<br />
It is co-operation, stability of Government,<br />
certainty of purpose, a willingness in a Government to go<br />
straight forward with these jobs these are the thin,. s that<br />
matter, these are the things that will be determined by your<br />
vote on Polling Day.<br />
Therefore having given you this very trifling survey<br />
of some of the thVi ngs that are going on I leave it to you to<br />
instruct the Parliament of the Commonwealth, through us, that<br />
this work is to on and that Australia is to be bigger and<br />
better; in other woras that we shall, as you may see on the<br />
corner of the map, be buildingr for tomorrow. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
